<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 04:14:49 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 04:14:49 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>Addressing Moral Uncertainty using Large Language Models for Ethical Decision-Making</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05724</link>
   <description>We present an ethical decision-making framework that refines a pre-trained reinforcement learning (RL) model using a task-agnostic ethical layer. Following initial training, the RL model undergoes ethical fine-tuning, where human feedback is replaced by feedback generated from a large language model (LLM). The LLM embodies consequentialist, deontological, virtue, social justice, and care ethics as moral principles to assign belief values to recommended actions during ethical decision-making. An ethical layer aggregates belief scores from multiple LLM-derived moral perspectives using Belief Jensen-Shannon Divergence and Dempster-Shafer Theory into probability scores that also serve as the shaping reward, steering the agent toward choices that align with a balanced ethical framework. This integrated learning framework helps the RL agent navigate moral uncertainty in complex environments and enables it to make morally sound decisions across diverse tasks. Our approach, tested across different LLM variants and compared with other belief aggregation techniques, demonstrates improved consistency, adaptability, and reduced reliance on handcrafted ethical rewards. This method is especially effective in dynamic scenarios where ethical challenges arise unexpectedly, making it well-suited for real-world applications.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.05724v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Rohit K. Dubey, Damian Dailisan, Sachit Mahajan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Whose Journey Matters? Investigating Identity Biases in Large Language Models (LLMs) for Travel Planning Assistance</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17333</link>
   <description>As large language models (LLMs) become increasingly integral to the hospitality and tourism industry, concerns about their fairness in serving diverse identity groups persist. Grounded in social identity theory and sociotechnical systems theory, this study examines ethnic and gender biases in travel recommendations generated by LLMs. Using fairness probing, we analyze outputs from three leading open-source LLMs. The results show that test accuracy for both ethnicity and gender classifiers exceed random chance. Analysis of the most influential features reveals the presence of stereotype bias in LLM-generated recommendations. We also found hallucinations among these features, occurring more frequently in recommendations for minority groups. These findings indicate that LLMs exhibit ethnic and gender bias when functioning as travel planning assistants. This study underscores the need for bias mitigation strategies to improve the inclusivity and reliability of generative AI-driven travel planning assistance.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.17333v2</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ruiping Ren, Xing Yao, Shu Cole, Haining Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Neural Collapse-Inspired Multi-Label Federated Learning under Label-Distribution Skew</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12544</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) enables collaborative model training across distributed clients while preserving data privacy. However, the performance of deep learning often deteriorates in FL due to decentralized and heterogeneous data. This challenge is further amplified in multi-label scenarios, where data exhibit complex characteristics such as label co-occurrence, inter-label dependency, and discrepancies between local and global label relationships. While most existing FL research primarily focuses on single-label classification, many real-world applications, particularly in domains such as medical imaging, often involve multi-label settings. In this paper, we address this important yet underexplored scenario in FL, where clients hold multi-label data with skewed label distributions. Neural Collapse (NC) describes a geometric structure in the latent feature space where features of each class collapse to their class mean with vanishing intra-class variance, and the class means form a maximally separated configuration. Motivated by this theory, we propose a method to align feature distributions across clients and to learn high-quality, well-clustered representations. To make the NC-structure applicable to multi-label settings, where image-level features may contain multiple semantic concepts, we introduce a feature disentanglement module that extracts semantically specific features. The clustering of these disentangled class-wise features is guided by a predefined shared NC structure, which mitigates potential conflicts between client models due to diverse local data distributions. In addition, we design regularisation losses to encourage compact clustering in the latent feature space. Experiments conducted on four benchmark datasets across eight diverse settings demonstrate that our approach outperforms existing methods, validating its effectiveness in this challenging FL scenario.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.12544v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Can Peng, Yuyuan Liu, Yingyu Yang, Pramit Saha, Qianye Yang, J. Alison Noble</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Robust Federated Inference</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00310</link>
   <description>Federated inference, in the form of one-shot federated learning, edge ensembles, or federated ensembles, has emerged as an attractive solution to combine predictions from multiple models. This paradigm enables each model to remain local and proprietary while a central server queries them and aggregates predictions. Yet, the robustness of federated inference has been largely neglected, leaving them vulnerable to even simple attacks. To address this critical gap, we formalize the problem of robust federated inference and provide the first robustness analysis of this class of methods. Our analysis of averaging-based aggregators shows that the error of the aggregator is small either when the dissimilarity between honest responses is small or the margin between the two most probable classes is large. Moving beyond linear averaging, we show that problem of robust federated inference with non-linear aggregators can be cast as an adversarial machine learning problem. We then introduce an advanced technique using the DeepSet aggregation model, proposing a novel composition of adversarial training and test-time robust aggregation to robustify non-linear aggregators. Our composition yields significant improvements, surpassing existing robust aggregation methods by 4.7 - 22.2% in accuracy points across diverse benchmarks.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.00310v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.MA</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Akash Dhasade, Sadegh Farhadkhani, Rachid Guerraoui, Nirupam Gupta, Maxime Jacovella, Anne-Marie Kermarrec, Rafael Pinot</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>EpidemIQs: Prompt-to-Paper LLM Agents for Epidemic Modeling and Analysis</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00024</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) offer new opportunities to automate complex interdisciplinary research domains. Epidemic modeling, characterized by its complexity and reliance on network science, dynamical systems, epidemiology, and stochastic simulations, represents a prime candidate for leveraging LLM-driven automation. We introduce \textbf{EpidemIQs}, a novel multi-agent LLM framework that integrates user inputs and autonomously conducts literature review, analytical derivation, network modeling, mechanistic modeling, stochastic simulations, data visualization and analysis, and finally documentation of findings in a structured manuscript. We introduced two types of agents: a scientist agent for planning, coordination, reflection, and generation of final results, and a task-expert agent to focus exclusively on one specific duty serving as a tool to the scientist agent. The framework consistently generated complete reports in scientific article format. Specifically, using GPT 4.1 and GPT 4.1 mini as backbone LLMs for scientist and task-expert agents, respectively, the autonomous process completed with average total token usage 870K at a cost of about \$1.57 per study, achieving a 100\% completion success rate through our experiments. We evaluate EpidemIQs across different epidemic scenarios, measuring computational cost, completion success rate, and AI and human expert reviews of generated reports. We compare EpidemIQs to the single-agent LLM, which has the same system prompts and tools, iteratively planning, invoking tools, and revising outputs until task completion. The comparison shows consistently higher performance of the proposed framework across five different scenarios. EpidemIQs represents a step forward in accelerating scientific research by significantly reducing costs and turnaround time of discovery processes, and enhancing accessibility to advanced modeling tools.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.00024v1</guid>
   <category>cs.SI</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mohammad Hossein Samaei, Faryad Darabi Sahneh, Lee W. Cohnstaedt, Caterina Scoglio</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Learning Meets LLMs: Feature Extraction From Heterogeneous Clients</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00065</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) enables collaborative model training without sharing raw data, making it attractive for privacy-sensitive domains such as healthcare, finance, and IoT. A major obstacle, however, is the heterogeneity of tabular data across clients, where divergent schemas and incompatible feature spaces prevent straightforward aggregation. To address this challenge, we propose FedLLM-Align, a federated framework that leverages pre-trained large language models (LLMs) as universal feature extractors. Tabular records are serialized into text, and embeddings from models such as DistilBERT, ALBERT, RoBERTa, and ClinicalBERT provide semantically aligned representations that support lightweight local classifiers under the standard FedAvg protocol. This approach removes the need for manual schema harmonization while preserving privacy, since raw data remain strictly local. We evaluate FedLLM-Align on coronary heart disease prediction using partitioned Framingham datasets with simulated schema divergence. Across all client settings and LLM backbones, our method consistently outperforms state-of-the-art baselines, achieving up to +0.25 improvement in F1-score and a 65% reduction in communication cost. Stress testing under extreme schema divergence further demonstrates graceful degradation, unlike traditional methods that collapse entirely. These results establish FedLLM-Align as a robust, privacy-preserving, and communication-efficient solution for federated learning in heterogeneous environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.00065v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Abdelrhman Gaber, Hassan Abd-Eltawab, Youssif Abuzied, Muhammad ElMahdy, Tamer ElBatt</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LoRAFusion: Efficient LoRA Fine-Tuning for LLMs</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00206</link>
   <description>Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA) has become the leading Parameter-Efficient Fine-Tuning (PEFT) method for Large Language Models (LLMs), as it significantly reduces GPU memory usage while maintaining competitive fine-tuned model quality on downstream tasks. Despite these benefits, we identify two key inefficiencies in existing LoRA fine-tuning systems. First, they incur substantial runtime overhead due to redundant memory accesses on large activation tensors. Second, they miss the opportunity to concurrently fine-tune multiple independent LoRA adapters that share the same base model on the same set of GPUs. This leads to missed performance gains such as reduced pipeline bubbles, better communication overlap, and improved GPU load balance.
  To address these issues, we introduce LoRAFusion, an efficient LoRA fine-tuning system for LLMs. At the kernel level, we propose a graph-splitting method that fuses memory-bound operations. This design eliminates unnecessary memory accesses and preserves the performance of compute-bound GEMMs without incurring the cost of recomputation or synchronization. At the scheduling level, LoRAFusion introduces an adaptive batching algorithm for multi-job fine-tuning. It first splits LoRA adapters into groups to intentionally stagger batch execution across jobs, and then solves a bin-packing problem within each group to generate balanced, dependency-aware microbatches. LoRAFusion achieves up to $1.96\times$ ($1.47\times$ on average) end-to-end speedup compared to Megatron-LM, and up to $1.46\times$ ($1.29\times$ on average) improvement over mLoRA, the state-of-the-art multi-LoRA fine-tuning system. Our fused kernel achieves up to $1.39\times$ ($1.27\times$ on average) kernel performance improvement and can directly serve as a plug-and-play replacement in existing LoRA systems. We open-source LoRAFusion at https://github.com/CentML/lorafusion.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.00206v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhanda Zhu, Qidong Su, Yaoyao Ding, Kevin Song, Shang Wang, Gennady Pekhimenko</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Robust Federated Inference</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00310</link>
   <description>Federated inference, in the form of one-shot federated learning, edge ensembles, or federated ensembles, has emerged as an attractive solution to combine predictions from multiple models. This paradigm enables each model to remain local and proprietary while a central server queries them and aggregates predictions. Yet, the robustness of federated inference has been largely neglected, leaving them vulnerable to even simple attacks. To address this critical gap, we formalize the problem of robust federated inference and provide the first robustness analysis of this class of methods. Our analysis of averaging-based aggregators shows that the error of the aggregator is small either when the dissimilarity between honest responses is small or the margin between the two most probable classes is large. Moving beyond linear averaging, we show that problem of robust federated inference with non-linear aggregators can be cast as an adversarial machine learning problem. We then introduce an advanced technique using the DeepSet aggregation model, proposing a novel composition of adversarial training and test-time robust aggregation to robustify non-linear aggregators. Our composition yields significant improvements, surpassing existing robust aggregation methods by 4.7 - 22.2% in accuracy points across diverse benchmarks.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.00310v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.MA</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Akash Dhasade, Sadegh Farhadkhani, Rachid Guerraoui, Nirupam Gupta, Maxime Jacovella, Anne-Marie Kermarrec, Rafael Pinot</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Privacy Preserved Federated Learning with Attention-Based Aggregation for Biometric Recognition</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01113</link>
   <description>Because biometric data is sensitive, centralized training poses a privacy risk, even though biometric recognition is essential for contemporary applications. Federated learning (FL), which permits decentralized training, provides a privacy-preserving substitute. Conventional FL, however, has trouble with interpretability and heterogeneous data (non-IID). In order to handle non-IID biometric data, this framework adds an attention mechanism at the central server that weights local model updates according to their significance. Differential privacy and secure update protocols safeguard data while preserving accuracy. The A3-FL framework is evaluated in this study using FVC2004 fingerprint data, with each client's features extracted using a Siamese Convolutional Neural Network (Siamese-CNN). By dynamically modifying client contributions, the attention mechanism increases the accuracy of the global model.The accuracy, convergence speed, and robustness of the A3-FL framework are superior to those of standard FL (FedAvg) and static baselines, according to experimental evaluations using fingerprint data (FVC2004). The accuracy of the attention-based approach was 0.8413, while FedAvg, Local-only, and Centralized approaches were 0.8164, 0.7664, and 0.7997, respectively. Accuracy stayed high at 0.8330 even with differential privacy. A scalable and privacy-sensitive biometric system for secure and effective recognition in dispersed environments is presented in this work.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.01113v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kassahun Azezew, Minyechil Alehegn, Tsega Asresa, Bitew Mekuria, Tizazu Bayh, Ayenew Kassie, Amsalu Tesema, Animut Embiyale</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Benchmarking Machine Learning Models for Fault Classification and Localization in Power System Protection</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00831</link>
   <description>The increasing integration of distributed energy resources (DERs), particularly renewables, poses significant challenges for power system protection, with fault classification (FC) and fault localization (FL) being among the most critical tasks. Conventional protection schemes, based on fixed thresholds, cannot reliably identify and localize short circuits with the increasing complexity of the grid under dynamic conditions. Machine learning (ML) offers a promising alternative; however, systematic benchmarks across models and settings remain limited. This work presents, for the first time, a comparative benchmarking study of classical ML models for FC and FL in power system protection based on EMT data. Using voltage and current waveforms segmented into sliding windows of 10 ms to 50 ms, we evaluate models under realistic real-time constraints. Performance is assessed in terms of accuracy, robustness to window size, and runtime efficiency. The best-performing FC model achieved an F1 score of 0.992$\pm$0.001, while the top FL model reached an R2 of 0.806$\pm$0.008 with a mean processing time of 0.563 ms.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.00831v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>eess.SP</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Julian Oelhaf, Georg Kordowich, Changhun Kim, Paula Andrea P\'erez-Toro, Christian Bergler, Andreas Maier, Johann J\&quot;ager, Siming Bayer</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Mitigating Domain Shift in Federated Learning via Intra- and Inter-Domain Prototypes</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08521</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) has emerged as a decentralized machine learning technique, allowing clients to train a global model collaboratively without sharing private data. However, most FL studies ignore the crucial challenge of heterogeneous domains where each client has a distinct feature distribution, which is popular in real-world scenarios. Prototype learning, which leverages the mean feature vectors within the same classes, has become a prominent solution for federated learning under domain shift. However, existing federated prototype learning methods focus soley on inter-domain prototypes and neglect intra-domain perspectives. In this work, we introduce a novel federated prototype learning method, namely I$^2$PFL, which incorporates $\textbf{I}$ntra-domain and $\textbf{I}$nter-domain $\textbf{P}$rototypes, to mitigate domain shift from both perspectives and learn a generalized global model across multiple domains in federated learning. To construct intra-domain prototypes, we propose feature alignment with MixUp-based augmented prototypes to capture the diversity within local domains and enhance the generalization of local features. Additionally, we introduce a reweighting mechanism for inter-domain prototypes to generate generalized prototypes that reduce domain shift while providing inter-domain knowledge across multiple clients. Extensive experiments on the Digits, Office-10, and PACS datasets illustrate the superior performance of our method compared to other baselines.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.08521v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Huy Q. Le, Ye Lin Tun, Yu Qiao, Minh N. H. Nguyen, Keon Oh Kim, Eui-Nam Huh, Choong Seon Hong</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Dynamic Modeling and Learning for Spatiotemporal Data Forecasting</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04528</link>
   <description>This paper presents an advanced Federated Learning (FL) framework for forecasting complex spatiotemporal data, improving upon recent state-of-the-art models. In the proposed approach, the original Gated Recurrent Unit (GRU) module within previous Dynamic Spatial--Temporal Graph Convolutional Recurrent Network (DSTGCRN) modeling is first replaced with a Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) network, enabling the resulting model to more effectively capture long-term dependencies inherent to time series data. The resulting architecture significantly improves the model's capacity to handle complex temporal patterns in diverse forecasting applications. Furthermore, the proposed FL framework integrates a novel Client-Side Validation (CSV) mechanism, introducing a critical validation step at the client level before incorporating aggregated parameters from the central server into local models, ensuring only the most effective updates are retained and improving both the robustness and accuracy of the forecasting model across clients. The efficiency of our approach is demonstrated through extensive experiments on real-world applications, including public datasets for multimodal transport demand forecasting and private datasets for Origin-Destination (OD) matrix forecasting in urban areas. The results demonstrate substantial improvements over conventional methods, highlighting the framework's ability to capture complex spatiotemporal dependencies while preserving data privacy. This work not only provides a scalable and privacy-preserving solution for real-time, region-specific forecasting and management but also underscores the potential of leveraging distributed data sources in a FL context. We provide our algorithms as open-source on GitHub</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.04528v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Thien Pham, Angelo Furno, Fa\&quot;icel Chamroukhi, Latifa Oukhellou</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Model Parallelism With Subnetwork Data Parallelism</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09029</link>
   <description>Distributed pre-training of large models at scale often imposes heavy memory demands on individual nodes and incurs significant intra-node communication costs. We propose a novel alternative approach that reduces the memory requirements by training small, structured subnetworks of the model on separate workers. Unlike pipelining, our method avoids inter-node activation communication and maintains bandwidth requirements that are comparable to or lower than standard data parallel communication schemes based on all-reduce. We evaluate two subnetwork construction strategies guided by the principle of ensuring uniform representation of each parameter across the distributed training setup. Our results show that the stochastic block dropping technique consistently outperforms the width-wise subnetwork construction previously explored in federated learning. We empirically attribute this superior performance to stronger gradient alignment in subnetworks that retain blocks having skip connections. Preliminary experiments highlight the promise of our approach, achieving a 20-40% reduction in memory usage without any loss in performance.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09029v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Vaibhav Singh, Zafir Khalid, Edouard Oyallon, Eugene Belilovsky</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Robust Estimation Under Heterogeneous Corruption Rates</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15051</link>
   <description>We study the problem of robust estimation under heterogeneous corruption rates, where each sample may be independently corrupted with a known but non-identical probability. This setting arises naturally in distributed and federated learning, crowdsourcing, and sensor networks, yet existing robust estimators typically assume uniform or worst-case corruption, ignoring structural heterogeneity. For mean estimation for multivariate bounded distributions and univariate gaussian distributions, we give tight minimax rates for all heterogeneous corruption patterns. For multivariate gaussian mean estimation and linear regression, we establish the minimax rate for squared error up to a factor of $\sqrt{d}$, where $d$ is the dimension. Roughly, our findings suggest that samples beyond a certain corruption threshold may be discarded by the optimal estimators -- this threshold is determined by the empirical distribution of the corruption rates given.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.15051v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.IT</category>
   <category>math.IT</category>
   <category>math.ST</category>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <category>stat.TH</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Syomantak Chaudhuri, Jerry Li, Thomas A. Courtade</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Communication-Aware Knowledge Distillation for Federated LLM Fine-Tuning over Wireless Networks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01750</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) for large language models (LLMs) offers a privacy-preserving scheme, enabling clients to collaboratively fine-tune locally deployed LLMs or smaller language models (SLMs) without exchanging raw data. While parameter-sharing methods in traditional FL models solves number of technical challenges, they still incur high communication overhead and struggle with adapting to heterogeneous model architectures. Federated distillation, a framework for mutual knowledge transfer via shared logits, typically offers lower communication overhead than parameter-sharing methods. However, transmitting logits from LLMs remains challenging for bandwidth-limited clients due to their high dimensionality. In this work, we focus on a federated LLM distillation with efficient communication overhead. To achieve this, we first propose an adaptive Top-k logit selection mechanism, dynamically sparsifying logits according to real-time communication conditions. Then to tackle the dimensional inconsistency introduced by the adaptive sparsification, we design an adaptive logits aggregation scheme, effectively alleviating the artificial and uninformative inputs introduced by conventional zero-padding methods. Finally, to enhance the distillation effect, we incorporate LoRA-adapted hidden-layer projection from LLM into the distillation loss, reducing the communication overhead further while providing richer representation. Experimental results demonstrate that our scheme achieves superior performance compared to baseline methods while effectively reducing communication overhead by approximately 50%.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.01750v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xinlu Zhang, Na Yan, Yang Su, Yansha Deng, Toktam Mahmoodi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Robust Estimation Under Heterogeneous Corruption Rates</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15051</link>
   <description>We study the problem of robust estimation under heterogeneous corruption rates, where each sample may be independently corrupted with a known but non-identical probability. This setting arises naturally in distributed and federated learning, crowdsourcing, and sensor networks, yet existing robust estimators typically assume uniform or worst-case corruption, ignoring structural heterogeneity. For mean estimation for multivariate bounded distributions and univariate gaussian distributions, we give tight minimax rates for all heterogeneous corruption patterns. For multivariate gaussian mean estimation and linear regression, we establish the minimax rate for squared error up to a factor of $\sqrt{d}$, where $d$ is the dimension. Roughly, our findings suggest that samples beyond a certain corruption threshold may be discarded by the optimal estimators -- this threshold is determined by the empirical distribution of the corruption rates given.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.15051v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.IT</category>
   <category>math.IT</category>
   <category>math.ST</category>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <category>stat.TH</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Syomantak Chaudhuri, Jerry Li, Thomas A. Courtade</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Benchmarking Machine Learning Models for Fault Classification and Localization in Power System Protection</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00831</link>
   <description>The increasing integration of distributed energy resources (DERs), particularly renewables, poses significant challenges for power system protection, with fault classification (FC) and fault localization (FL) being among the most critical tasks. Conventional protection schemes, based on fixed thresholds, cannot reliably identify and localize short circuits with the increasing complexity of the grid under dynamic conditions. Machine learning (ML) offers a promising alternative; however, systematic benchmarks across models and settings remain limited. This work presents, for the first time, a comparative benchmarking study of classical ML models for FC and FL in power system protection based on EMT data. Using voltage and current waveforms segmented into sliding windows of 10 ms to 50 ms, we evaluate models under realistic real-time constraints. Performance is assessed in terms of accuracy, robustness to window size, and runtime efficiency. The best-performing FC model achieved an F1 score of 0.992$\pm$0.001, while the top FL model reached an R2 of 0.806$\pm$0.008 with a mean processing time of 0.563 ms.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.00831v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>eess.SP</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Julian Oelhaf, Georg Kordowich, Changhun Kim, Paula Andrea P\'erez-Toro, Christian Bergler, Andreas Maier, Johann J\&quot;ager, Siming Bayer</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>EpidemIQs: Prompt-to-Paper LLM Agents for Epidemic Modeling and Analysis</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00024</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) offer new opportunities to automate complex interdisciplinary research domains. Epidemic modeling, characterized by its complexity and reliance on network science, dynamical systems, epidemiology, and stochastic simulations, represents a prime candidate for leveraging LLM-driven automation. We introduce \textbf{EpidemIQs}, a novel multi-agent LLM framework that integrates user inputs and autonomously conducts literature review, analytical derivation, network modeling, mechanistic modeling, stochastic simulations, data visualization and analysis, and finally documentation of findings in a structured manuscript. We introduced two types of agents: a scientist agent for planning, coordination, reflection, and generation of final results, and a task-expert agent to focus exclusively on one specific duty serving as a tool to the scientist agent. The framework consistently generated complete reports in scientific article format. Specifically, using GPT 4.1 and GPT 4.1 mini as backbone LLMs for scientist and task-expert agents, respectively, the autonomous process completed with average total token usage 870K at a cost of about \$1.57 per study, achieving a 100\% completion success rate through our experiments. We evaluate EpidemIQs across different epidemic scenarios, measuring computational cost, completion success rate, and AI and human expert reviews of generated reports. We compare EpidemIQs to the single-agent LLM, which has the same system prompts and tools, iteratively planning, invoking tools, and revising outputs until task completion. The comparison shows consistently higher performance of the proposed framework across five different scenarios. EpidemIQs represents a step forward in accelerating scientific research by significantly reducing costs and turnaround time of discovery processes, and enhancing accessibility to advanced modeling tools.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.00024v1</guid>
   <category>cs.SI</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mohammad Hossein Samaei, Faryad Darabi Sahneh, Lee W. Cohnstaedt, Caterina Scoglio</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Direct Token Optimization: A Self-contained Approach to Large Language Model Unlearning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00125</link>
   <description>Machine unlearning is an emerging technique that removes the influence of a subset of training data (forget set) from a model without full retraining, with applications including privacy protection, content moderation, and model correction. The key challenge lies in ensuring that the model completely forgets the knowledge of the forget set without compromising its overall utility. Existing unlearning methods for large language models (LLMs) often utilize auxiliary language models, retain datasets, or even commercial AI services for effective unlearning and maintaining the model utility. However, dependence on these external resources is often impractical and could potentially introduce additional privacy risks. In this work, we propose direct token optimization (DTO), a novel self-contained unlearning approach for LLMs that directly optimizes the token level objectives and eliminates the need for external resources. Given a sequence to unlearn, we identify two categories of tokens: target tokens, which capture critical knowledge for unlearning, and the remaining non-target tokens, which are crucial for maintaining the model utility. The former are used to optimize the unlearning objective, while the latter serve to preserve the model's performance. The experimental results show that the proposed DTO achieves up to 16.8$\times$ improvement in forget quality on several benchmark datasets than the latest baselines while maintaining a comparable level of model utility.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.00125v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hong kyu Lee, Ruixuan Liu, Li Xiong</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Personalized Reasoning: Just-In-Time Personalization and Why LLMs Fail At It</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00177</link>
   <description>Current large language model (LLM) development treats task-solving and preference alignment as separate challenges, optimizing first for objective correctness, then for alignment to aggregated human preferences. This paradigm fails in human-facing applications where solving a problem correctly is insufficient if the response mismatches the user's needs. This challenge intensifies in just-in-time scenarios where no prior user interaction history exists due to cold-start conditions or privacy constraints. LLMs need to identify what they don't know about user preferences, strategically elicit preference values through questioning, then adapt their reasoning processes and responses accordingly -- a complicated chain of cognitive processes which we term personalized reasoning. We introduce PREFDISCO, an evaluation methodology that transforms static benchmarks into interactive personalization tasks using psychologically-grounded personas with sparse preferences. Our framework creates scenarios where identical questions require different reasoning chains depending on user context, as optimal explanation approaches vary by individual expertise and preferences while maintaining factual accuracy. Evaluation of 21 frontier models across 10 tasks reveals 29.0% of naive personalization attempts produce worse preference alignment than generic responses, yet generic responses also fail to serve individual user needs effectively. These findings suggest personalized reasoning requires dedicated development rather than emerging naturally. PREFDISCO establishes personalized reasoning as a measurable research frontier and reveals fundamental limitations in current LLMs' interactive capabilities, providing a foundation for developing systems that can adapt to individual users in education, healthcare, and technical domains where personalization is critical.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.00177v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shuyue Stella Li, Avinandan Bose, Faeze Brahman, Simon Shaolei Du, Pang Wei Koh, Maryam Fazel, Yulia Tsvetkov</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LoRAFusion: Efficient LoRA Fine-Tuning for LLMs</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00206</link>
   <description>Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA) has become the leading Parameter-Efficient Fine-Tuning (PEFT) method for Large Language Models (LLMs), as it significantly reduces GPU memory usage while maintaining competitive fine-tuned model quality on downstream tasks. Despite these benefits, we identify two key inefficiencies in existing LoRA fine-tuning systems. First, they incur substantial runtime overhead due to redundant memory accesses on large activation tensors. Second, they miss the opportunity to concurrently fine-tune multiple independent LoRA adapters that share the same base model on the same set of GPUs. This leads to missed performance gains such as reduced pipeline bubbles, better communication overlap, and improved GPU load balance.
  To address these issues, we introduce LoRAFusion, an efficient LoRA fine-tuning system for LLMs. At the kernel level, we propose a graph-splitting method that fuses memory-bound operations. This design eliminates unnecessary memory accesses and preserves the performance of compute-bound GEMMs without incurring the cost of recomputation or synchronization. At the scheduling level, LoRAFusion introduces an adaptive batching algorithm for multi-job fine-tuning. It first splits LoRA adapters into groups to intentionally stagger batch execution across jobs, and then solves a bin-packing problem within each group to generate balanced, dependency-aware microbatches. LoRAFusion achieves up to $1.96\times$ ($1.47\times$ on average) end-to-end speedup compared to Megatron-LM, and up to $1.46\times$ ($1.29\times$ on average) improvement over mLoRA, the state-of-the-art multi-LoRA fine-tuning system. Our fused kernel achieves up to $1.39\times$ ($1.27\times$ on average) kernel performance improvement and can directly serve as a plug-and-play replacement in existing LoRA systems. We open-source LoRAFusion at https://github.com/CentML/lorafusion.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.00206v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhanda Zhu, Qidong Su, Yaoyao Ding, Kevin Song, Shang Wang, Gennady Pekhimenko</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Graph2Eval: Automatic Multimodal Task Generation for Agents via Knowledge Graphs</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00507</link>
   <description>As multimodal LLM-driven agents continue to advance in autonomy and generalization, evaluation based on static datasets can no longer adequately assess their true capabilities in dynamic environments and diverse tasks. Existing LLM-based synthetic data methods are largely designed for LLM training and evaluation, and thus cannot be directly applied to agent tasks that require tool use and interactive capabilities. While recent studies have explored automatic agent task generation with LLMs, most efforts remain limited to text or image analysis, without systematically modeling multi-step interactions in web environments. To address these challenges, we propose Graph2Eval, a knowledge graph-based framework that automatically generates both multimodal document comprehension tasks and web interaction tasks, enabling comprehensive evaluation of agents' reasoning, collaboration, and interactive capabilities. In our approach, knowledge graphs constructed from multi-source external data serve as the task space, where we translate semantic relations into structured multimodal tasks using subgraph sampling, task templates, and meta-paths. A multi-stage filtering pipeline based on node reachability, LLM scoring, and similarity analysis is applied to guarantee the quality and executability of the generated tasks. Furthermore, Graph2Eval supports end-to-end evaluation of multiple agent types (Single-Agent, Multi-Agent, Web Agent) and measures reasoning, collaboration, and interaction capabilities. We instantiate the framework with Graph2Eval-Bench, a curated dataset of 1,319 tasks spanning document comprehension and web interaction scenarios. Experiments show that Graph2Eval efficiently generates tasks that differentiate agent and model performance, revealing gaps in reasoning, collaboration, and web interaction across different settings and offering a new perspective for agent evaluation.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.00507v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yurun Chen, Xavier Hu, Yuhan Liu, Ziqi Wang, Zeyi Liao, Lin Chen, Feng Wei, Yuxi Qian, Bo Zheng, Keting Yin, Shengyu Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Whose Journey Matters? Investigating Identity Biases in Large Language Models (LLMs) for Travel Planning Assistance</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17333</link>
   <description>As large language models (LLMs) become increasingly integral to the hospitality and tourism industry, concerns about their fairness in serving diverse identity groups persist. Grounded in social identity theory and sociotechnical systems theory, this study examines ethnic and gender biases in travel recommendations generated by LLMs. Using fairness probing, we analyze outputs from three leading open-source LLMs. The results show that test accuracy for both ethnicity and gender classifiers exceed random chance. Analysis of the most influential features reveals the presence of stereotype bias in LLM-generated recommendations. We also found hallucinations among these features, occurring more frequently in recommendations for minority groups. These findings indicate that LLMs exhibit ethnic and gender bias when functioning as travel planning assistants. This study underscores the need for bias mitigation strategies to improve the inclusivity and reliability of generative AI-driven travel planning assistance.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.17333v2</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ruiping Ren, Xing Yao, Shu Cole, Haining Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Mitigating Domain Shift in Federated Learning via Intra- and Inter-Domain Prototypes</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08521</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) has emerged as a decentralized machine learning technique, allowing clients to train a global model collaboratively without sharing private data. However, most FL studies ignore the crucial challenge of heterogeneous domains where each client has a distinct feature distribution, which is popular in real-world scenarios. Prototype learning, which leverages the mean feature vectors within the same classes, has become a prominent solution for federated learning under domain shift. However, existing federated prototype learning methods focus soley on inter-domain prototypes and neglect intra-domain perspectives. In this work, we introduce a novel federated prototype learning method, namely I$^2$PFL, which incorporates $\textbf{I}$ntra-domain and $\textbf{I}$nter-domain $\textbf{P}$rototypes, to mitigate domain shift from both perspectives and learn a generalized global model across multiple domains in federated learning. To construct intra-domain prototypes, we propose feature alignment with MixUp-based augmented prototypes to capture the diversity within local domains and enhance the generalization of local features. Additionally, we introduce a reweighting mechanism for inter-domain prototypes to generate generalized prototypes that reduce domain shift while providing inter-domain knowledge across multiple clients. Extensive experiments on the Digits, Office-10, and PACS datasets illustrate the superior performance of our method compared to other baselines.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.08521v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Huy Q. Le, Ye Lin Tun, Yu Qiao, Minh N. H. Nguyen, Keon Oh Kim, Eui-Nam Huh, Choong Seon Hong</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Addressing Moral Uncertainty using Large Language Models for Ethical Decision-Making</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05724</link>
   <description>We present an ethical decision-making framework that refines a pre-trained reinforcement learning (RL) model using a task-agnostic ethical layer. Following initial training, the RL model undergoes ethical fine-tuning, where human feedback is replaced by feedback generated from a large language model (LLM). The LLM embodies consequentialist, deontological, virtue, social justice, and care ethics as moral principles to assign belief values to recommended actions during ethical decision-making. An ethical layer aggregates belief scores from multiple LLM-derived moral perspectives using Belief Jensen-Shannon Divergence and Dempster-Shafer Theory into probability scores that also serve as the shaping reward, steering the agent toward choices that align with a balanced ethical framework. This integrated learning framework helps the RL agent navigate moral uncertainty in complex environments and enables it to make morally sound decisions across diverse tasks. Our approach, tested across different LLM variants and compared with other belief aggregation techniques, demonstrates improved consistency, adaptability, and reduced reliance on handcrafted ethical rewards. This method is especially effective in dynamic scenarios where ethical challenges arise unexpectedly, making it well-suited for real-world applications.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.05724v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Rohit K. Dubey, Damian Dailisan, Sachit Mahajan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Causal Inference from Multi-Site Observational Data via Propensity Score Aggregation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17961</link>
   <description>Causal inference typically assumes centralized access to individual-level data. Yet, in practice, data are often decentralized across multiple sites, making centralization infeasible due to privacy, logistical, or legal constraints. We address this problem by estimating the Average Treatment Effect (ATE) from decentralized observational data via a Federated Learning (FL) approach, allowing inference through the exchange of aggregate statistics rather than individual-level data. We propose a novel method to estimate propensity scores by computing a federated weighted average of local scores with Membership Weights (MW)--probabilities of site membership conditional on covariates--which can be flexibly estimated using parametric or non-parametric classification models. Unlike density ratio weights (DW) from the transportability and generalization literature, which either rely on strong modeling assumptions or cannot be implemented in FL, MW can be estimated using standard FL algorithms and are more robust, as they support flexible, non-parametric models--making them the preferred choice in multi-site settings with strict data-sharing constraints. The resulting propensity scores are used to construct Federated Inverse Propensity Weighting (Fed-IPW) and Augmented IPW (Fed-AIPW) estimators. Unlike meta-analysis methods, which fail when any site violates positivity, our approach leverages heterogeneity in treatment assignment across sites to improve overlap. We show that Fed-IPW and Fed-AIPW perform well under site-level heterogeneity in sample sizes, treatment mechanisms, and covariate distributions. Both theoretical analysis and experiments on simulated and real-world data highlight their advantages over meta-analysis and related methods.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.17961v2</guid>
   <category>stat.ME</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>math.ST</category>
   <category>stat.AP</category>
   <category>stat.TH</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Khellaf R\'emi, Bellet Aur\'elien, Josse Julie</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Model Parallelism With Subnetwork Data Parallelism</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09029</link>
   <description>Distributed pre-training of large models at scale often imposes heavy memory demands on individual nodes and incurs significant intra-node communication costs. We propose a novel alternative approach that reduces the memory requirements by training small, structured subnetworks of the model on separate workers. Unlike pipelining, our method avoids inter-node activation communication and maintains bandwidth requirements that are comparable to or lower than standard data parallel communication schemes based on all-reduce. We evaluate two subnetwork construction strategies guided by the principle of ensuring uniform representation of each parameter across the distributed training setup. Our results show that the stochastic block dropping technique consistently outperforms the width-wise subnetwork construction previously explored in federated learning. We empirically attribute this superior performance to stronger gradient alignment in subnetworks that retain blocks having skip connections. Preliminary experiments highlight the promise of our approach, achieving a 20-40% reduction in memory usage without any loss in performance.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09029v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Vaibhav Singh, Zafir Khalid, Edouard Oyallon, Eugene Belilovsky</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Metaphor identification using large language models: A comparison of RAG, prompt engineering, and fine-tuning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24866</link>
   <description>Metaphor is a pervasive feature of discourse and a powerful lens for examining cognition, emotion, and ideology. Large-scale analysis, however, has been constrained by the need for manual annotation due to the context-sensitive nature of metaphor. This study investigates the potential of large language models (LLMs) to automate metaphor identification in full texts. We compare three methods: (i) retrieval-augmented generation (RAG), where the model is provided with a codebook and instructed to annotate texts based on its rules and examples; (ii) prompt engineering, where we design task-specific verbal instructions; and (iii) fine-tuning, where the model is trained on hand-coded texts to optimize performance. Within prompt engineering, we test zero-shot, few-shot, and chain-of-thought strategies. Our results show that state-of-the-art closed-source LLMs can achieve high accuracy, with fine-tuning yielding a median F1 score of 0.79. A comparison of human and LLM outputs reveals that most discrepancies are systematic, reflecting well-known grey areas and conceptual challenges in metaphor theory. We propose that LLMs can be used to at least partly automate metaphor identification and can serve as a testbed for developing and refining metaphor identification protocols and the theory that underpins them.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.24866v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Matteo Fuoli, Weihang Huang, Jeannette Littlemore, Sarah Turner, Ellen Wilding</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LoRAFusion: Efficient LoRA Fine-Tuning for LLMs</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00206</link>
   <description>Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA) has become the leading Parameter-Efficient Fine-Tuning (PEFT) method for Large Language Models (LLMs), as it significantly reduces GPU memory usage while maintaining competitive fine-tuned model quality on downstream tasks. Despite these benefits, we identify two key inefficiencies in existing LoRA fine-tuning systems. First, they incur substantial runtime overhead due to redundant memory accesses on large activation tensors. Second, they miss the opportunity to concurrently fine-tune multiple independent LoRA adapters that share the same base model on the same set of GPUs. This leads to missed performance gains such as reduced pipeline bubbles, better communication overlap, and improved GPU load balance.
  To address these issues, we introduce LoRAFusion, an efficient LoRA fine-tuning system for LLMs. At the kernel level, we propose a graph-splitting method that fuses memory-bound operations. This design eliminates unnecessary memory accesses and preserves the performance of compute-bound GEMMs without incurring the cost of recomputation or synchronization. At the scheduling level, LoRAFusion introduces an adaptive batching algorithm for multi-job fine-tuning. It first splits LoRA adapters into groups to intentionally stagger batch execution across jobs, and then solves a bin-packing problem within each group to generate balanced, dependency-aware microbatches. LoRAFusion achieves up to $1.96\times$ ($1.47\times$ on average) end-to-end speedup compared to Megatron-LM, and up to $1.46\times$ ($1.29\times$ on average) improvement over mLoRA, the state-of-the-art multi-LoRA fine-tuning system. Our fused kernel achieves up to $1.39\times$ ($1.27\times$ on average) kernel performance improvement and can directly serve as a plug-and-play replacement in existing LoRA systems. We open-source LoRAFusion at https://github.com/CentML/lorafusion.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.00206v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhanda Zhu, Qidong Su, Yaoyao Ding, Kevin Song, Shang Wang, Gennady Pekhimenko</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Predictive and Synergistic Two-Layer Scheduling Framework for LLM Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23384</link>
   <description>LLM inference serving typically scales out with a two-tier architecture: a cluster router distributes requests to multiple inference engines, each of which then in turn performs its own internal scheduling. However, this commonly used paradigm suffers from critical, systemic inefficiency caused by the information gaps across two layers. At the cluster-layer, the router mainly relies on lagging, coarse-grained metrics, such as average latency and queue length to make decisions, resulting in &quot;decision lag&quot; that leads to suboptimal request routing. At the engine-layer, static heuristic scheduling policies cannot effectively handle the dynamic workloads, leading a poor balance between latency and throughput. Besides, these gaps may cause SLO violations and resource waste, especially in heterogeneous cloud environments.
  To bridge such gaps, we propose NexusSched, a cross-layer framework that shifts LLM serving system from reactive load balancing to predictive orchestration. The core of NexusSched lies in a structurally-informed online performance model that provides accurate, forward-looking per-step latency and capacity estimations. This model empowers two key components. At the engine-layer, LENS performs SLO-aware, adaptive scheduling, dynamically optimizing batching to meet SLOs under real-time loads. At the cluster-layer, PRISM uses predictive signals to perform state-driven routing, maximizing cluster-wide performance and SLO attainment. Performance evaluations show that NexusSched improves SLO attainment by 43% on average and achieves up to 3x throughput speedup in long-context and heterogeneous scenarios. Besides, we also deploy NexusSched on FlowGPT's clusters to demonstrate its advantages in production environment.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.23384v3</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yue Zhang, Yuansheng Chen, Xuan Mo, Alex Xi, Jialun Li, WeiGang Wu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Direct Token Optimization: A Self-contained Approach to Large Language Model Unlearning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00125</link>
   <description>Machine unlearning is an emerging technique that removes the influence of a subset of training data (forget set) from a model without full retraining, with applications including privacy protection, content moderation, and model correction. The key challenge lies in ensuring that the model completely forgets the knowledge of the forget set without compromising its overall utility. Existing unlearning methods for large language models (LLMs) often utilize auxiliary language models, retain datasets, or even commercial AI services for effective unlearning and maintaining the model utility. However, dependence on these external resources is often impractical and could potentially introduce additional privacy risks. In this work, we propose direct token optimization (DTO), a novel self-contained unlearning approach for LLMs that directly optimizes the token level objectives and eliminates the need for external resources. Given a sequence to unlearn, we identify two categories of tokens: target tokens, which capture critical knowledge for unlearning, and the remaining non-target tokens, which are crucial for maintaining the model utility. The former are used to optimize the unlearning objective, while the latter serve to preserve the model's performance. The experimental results show that the proposed DTO achieves up to 16.8$\times$ improvement in forget quality on several benchmark datasets than the latest baselines while maintaining a comparable level of model utility.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.00125v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hong kyu Lee, Ruixuan Liu, Li Xiong</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Personalized Reasoning: Just-In-Time Personalization and Why LLMs Fail At It</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00177</link>
   <description>Current large language model (LLM) development treats task-solving and preference alignment as separate challenges, optimizing first for objective correctness, then for alignment to aggregated human preferences. This paradigm fails in human-facing applications where solving a problem correctly is insufficient if the response mismatches the user's needs. This challenge intensifies in just-in-time scenarios where no prior user interaction history exists due to cold-start conditions or privacy constraints. LLMs need to identify what they don't know about user preferences, strategically elicit preference values through questioning, then adapt their reasoning processes and responses accordingly -- a complicated chain of cognitive processes which we term personalized reasoning. We introduce PREFDISCO, an evaluation methodology that transforms static benchmarks into interactive personalization tasks using psychologically-grounded personas with sparse preferences. Our framework creates scenarios where identical questions require different reasoning chains depending on user context, as optimal explanation approaches vary by individual expertise and preferences while maintaining factual accuracy. Evaluation of 21 frontier models across 10 tasks reveals 29.0% of naive personalization attempts produce worse preference alignment than generic responses, yet generic responses also fail to serve individual user needs effectively. These findings suggest personalized reasoning requires dedicated development rather than emerging naturally. PREFDISCO establishes personalized reasoning as a measurable research frontier and reveals fundamental limitations in current LLMs' interactive capabilities, providing a foundation for developing systems that can adapt to individual users in education, healthcare, and technical domains where personalization is critical.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.00177v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shuyue Stella Li, Avinandan Bose, Faeze Brahman, Simon Shaolei Du, Pang Wei Koh, Maryam Fazel, Yulia Tsvetkov</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Graph2Eval: Automatic Multimodal Task Generation for Agents via Knowledge Graphs</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00507</link>
   <description>As multimodal LLM-driven agents continue to advance in autonomy and generalization, evaluation based on static datasets can no longer adequately assess their true capabilities in dynamic environments and diverse tasks. Existing LLM-based synthetic data methods are largely designed for LLM training and evaluation, and thus cannot be directly applied to agent tasks that require tool use and interactive capabilities. While recent studies have explored automatic agent task generation with LLMs, most efforts remain limited to text or image analysis, without systematically modeling multi-step interactions in web environments. To address these challenges, we propose Graph2Eval, a knowledge graph-based framework that automatically generates both multimodal document comprehension tasks and web interaction tasks, enabling comprehensive evaluation of agents' reasoning, collaboration, and interactive capabilities. In our approach, knowledge graphs constructed from multi-source external data serve as the task space, where we translate semantic relations into structured multimodal tasks using subgraph sampling, task templates, and meta-paths. A multi-stage filtering pipeline based on node reachability, LLM scoring, and similarity analysis is applied to guarantee the quality and executability of the generated tasks. Furthermore, Graph2Eval supports end-to-end evaluation of multiple agent types (Single-Agent, Multi-Agent, Web Agent) and measures reasoning, collaboration, and interaction capabilities. We instantiate the framework with Graph2Eval-Bench, a curated dataset of 1,319 tasks spanning document comprehension and web interaction scenarios. Experiments show that Graph2Eval efficiently generates tasks that differentiate agent and model performance, revealing gaps in reasoning, collaboration, and web interaction across different settings and offering a new perspective for agent evaluation.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.00507v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yurun Chen, Xavier Hu, Yuhan Liu, Ziqi Wang, Zeyi Liao, Lin Chen, Feng Wei, Yuxi Qian, Bo Zheng, Keting Yin, Shengyu Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Metaphor identification using large language models: A comparison of RAG, prompt engineering, and fine-tuning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24866</link>
   <description>Metaphor is a pervasive feature of discourse and a powerful lens for examining cognition, emotion, and ideology. Large-scale analysis, however, has been constrained by the need for manual annotation due to the context-sensitive nature of metaphor. This study investigates the potential of large language models (LLMs) to automate metaphor identification in full texts. We compare three methods: (i) retrieval-augmented generation (RAG), where the model is provided with a codebook and instructed to annotate texts based on its rules and examples; (ii) prompt engineering, where we design task-specific verbal instructions; and (iii) fine-tuning, where the model is trained on hand-coded texts to optimize performance. Within prompt engineering, we test zero-shot, few-shot, and chain-of-thought strategies. Our results show that state-of-the-art closed-source LLMs can achieve high accuracy, with fine-tuning yielding a median F1 score of 0.79. A comparison of human and LLM outputs reveals that most discrepancies are systematic, reflecting well-known grey areas and conceptual challenges in metaphor theory. We propose that LLMs can be used to at least partly automate metaphor identification and can serve as a testbed for developing and refining metaphor identification protocols and the theory that underpins them.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.24866v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Matteo Fuoli, Weihang Huang, Jeannette Littlemore, Sarah Turner, Ellen Wilding</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Whose Journey Matters? Investigating Identity Biases in Large Language Models (LLMs) for Travel Planning Assistance</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17333</link>
   <description>As large language models (LLMs) become increasingly integral to the hospitality and tourism industry, concerns about their fairness in serving diverse identity groups persist. Grounded in social identity theory and sociotechnical systems theory, this study examines ethnic and gender biases in travel recommendations generated by LLMs. Using fairness probing, we analyze outputs from three leading open-source LLMs. The results show that test accuracy for both ethnicity and gender classifiers exceed random chance. Analysis of the most influential features reveals the presence of stereotype bias in LLM-generated recommendations. We also found hallucinations among these features, occurring more frequently in recommendations for minority groups. These findings indicate that LLMs exhibit ethnic and gender bias when functioning as travel planning assistants. This study underscores the need for bias mitigation strategies to improve the inclusivity and reliability of generative AI-driven travel planning assistance.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.17333v2</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ruiping Ren, Xing Yao, Shu Cole, Haining Wang</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
