<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 04:14:51 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 04:14:51 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>DuoServe-MoE: Dual-Phase Expert Prefetch and Cache Scheduling for Efficient MoE LLM Inference</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07379</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated impressive performance across a wide range of deep learning tasks. Mixture of Experts (MoE) further enhances their capabilities by increasing model width through sparsely activated expert branches, which keeps inference computation efficient. However, the large number of expert weights introduces significant GPU memory pressure, especially in resource-constrained environments such as single-GPU servers. More importantly, MoE inference consists of two fundamentally different stages: a prefill stage where most experts are activated densely, and a decode stage where only a few experts are triggered sparsely. Treating these stages with a uniform scheduling strategy often leads to suboptimal latency and memory usage. To address this, we propose DuoServe-MoE, an inference serving system that explicitly separates prefill and decode stages and applies tailored expert scheduling strategies to each. In the prefill stage, DuoServe-MoE uses a two-stream CUDA pipeline that overlaps expert weight prefetching with the computation of non-MoE layers, limiting expert residency in GPU memory. In the decode stage, a lightweight layer-level predictor trained offline from activation traces is used to prefetch only the most likely activated experts, without requiring any changes to the model. Experiments on 4-bit Mixtral-8x7B and 8x22B models show that DuoServe-MoE improves end-to-end latency by 1.42 to 7.54 times while keeping peak memory usage at only 15 percent of the full model size.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.07379v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yuning Zhang, Grant Pinkert, Nan Yang, Yanli Li, Dong Yuan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Astra: A Multi-Agent System for GPU Kernel Performance Optimization</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07506</link>
   <description>GPU kernel optimization has long been a central challenge at the intersection of high-performance computing and machine learning. Efficient kernels are crucial for accelerating large language model (LLM) training and serving, yet attaining high performance typically requires extensive manual tuning. Compiler-based systems reduce some of this burden, but still demand substantial manual design and engineering effort. Recently, researchers have explored using LLMs for GPU kernel generation, though prior work has largely focused on translating high-level PyTorch modules into CUDA code. In this work, we introduce Astra, the first LLM-based multi-agent system for GPU kernel optimization. Unlike previous approaches, Astra starts from existing CUDA implementations extracted from SGLang, a widely deployed framework for serving LLMs, rather than treating PyTorch modules as the specification. Within Astra, specialized LLM agents collaborate through iterative code generation, testing, profiling, and planning to produce kernels that are both correct and high-performance. On kernels from SGLang, Astra achieves an average speedup of 1.32x using zero-shot prompting with OpenAI o4-mini. A detailed case study further demonstrates that LLMs can autonomously apply loop transformations, optimize memory access patterns, exploit CUDA intrinsics, and leverage fast math operations to yield substantial performance gains. Our work highlights multi-agent LLM systems as a promising new paradigm for GPU kernel optimization.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.07506v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Anjiang Wei, Tianran Sun, Yogesh Seenichamy, Hang Song, Anne Ouyang, Azalia Mirhoseini, Ke Wang, Alex Aiken</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Fed-REACT: Federated Representation Learning for Heterogeneous and Evolving Data</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07198</link>
   <description>Motivated by the high resource costs and privacy concerns associated with centralized machine learning, federated learning (FL) has emerged as an efficient alternative that enables clients to collaboratively train a global model while keeping their data local. However, in real-world deployments, client data distributions often evolve over time and differ significantly across clients, introducing heterogeneity that degrades the performance of standard FL algorithms. In this work, we introduce Fed-REACT, a federated learning framework designed for heterogeneous and evolving client data. Fed-REACT combines representation learning with evolutionary clustering in a two-stage process: (1) in the first stage, each client learns a local model to extracts feature representations from its data; (2) in the second stage, the server dynamically groups clients into clusters based on these representations and coordinates cluster-wise training of task-specific models for downstream objectives such as classification or regression. We provide a theoretical analysis of the representation learning stage, and empirically demonstrate that Fed-REACT achieves superior accuracy and robustness on real-world datasets.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.07198v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yiyue Chen, Usman Akram, Chianing Wang, Haris Vikalo</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>MoE-Compression: How the Compression Error of Experts Affects the Inference Accuracy of MoE Model?</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07727</link>
   <description>With the widespread application of Mixture of Experts (MoE) reasoning models in the field of LLM learning, efficiently serving MoE models under limited GPU memory constraints has emerged as a significant challenge. Offloading the non-activated experts to main memory has been identified as an efficient approach to address such a problem, while it brings the challenges of transferring the expert between the GPU memory and main memory. We need to explore an efficient approach to compress the expert and analyze how the compression error affects the inference performance.
  To bridge this gap, we propose employing error-bounded lossy compression algorithms (such as SZ3 and CuSZp) to compress non-activated experts, thereby reducing data transfer overhead during MoE inference. We conduct extensive experiments across various benchmarks and present a comprehensive analysis of how compression-induced errors in different experts affect overall inference accuracy. The results indicate that experts in the shallow layers, which are primarily responsible for the attention mechanism and the transformation of input tokens into vector representations, exhibit minimal degradation in inference accuracy when subjected to bounded errors. In contrast, errors in the middle-layer experts, which are central to model reasoning, significantly impair inference accuracy. Interestingly, introducing bounded errors in the deep-layer experts, which are mainly responsible for instruction following and output integration, can sometimes lead to improvements in inference accuracy.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.07727v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Songkai Ma, Zhaorui Zhang, Sheng Di, Benben Liu, Xiaodong Yu, Xiaoyi Lu, Dan Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Astra: A Multi-Agent System for GPU Kernel Performance Optimization</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07506</link>
   <description>GPU kernel optimization has long been a central challenge at the intersection of high-performance computing and machine learning. Efficient kernels are crucial for accelerating large language model (LLM) training and serving, yet attaining high performance typically requires extensive manual tuning. Compiler-based systems reduce some of this burden, but still demand substantial manual design and engineering effort. Recently, researchers have explored using LLMs for GPU kernel generation, though prior work has largely focused on translating high-level PyTorch modules into CUDA code. In this work, we introduce Astra, the first LLM-based multi-agent system for GPU kernel optimization. Unlike previous approaches, Astra starts from existing CUDA implementations extracted from SGLang, a widely deployed framework for serving LLMs, rather than treating PyTorch modules as the specification. Within Astra, specialized LLM agents collaborate through iterative code generation, testing, profiling, and planning to produce kernels that are both correct and high-performance. On kernels from SGLang, Astra achieves an average speedup of 1.32x using zero-shot prompting with OpenAI o4-mini. A detailed case study further demonstrates that LLMs can autonomously apply loop transformations, optimize memory access patterns, exploit CUDA intrinsics, and leverage fast math operations to yield substantial performance gains. Our work highlights multi-agent LLM systems as a promising new paradigm for GPU kernel optimization.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.07506v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Anjiang Wei, Tianran Sun, Yogesh Seenichamy, Hang Song, Anne Ouyang, Azalia Mirhoseini, Ke Wang, Alex Aiken</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Astra: A Multi-Agent System for GPU Kernel Performance Optimization</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07506</link>
   <description>GPU kernel optimization has long been a central challenge at the intersection of high-performance computing and machine learning. Efficient kernels are crucial for accelerating large language model (LLM) training and serving, yet attaining high performance typically requires extensive manual tuning. Compiler-based systems reduce some of this burden, but still demand substantial manual design and engineering effort. Recently, researchers have explored using LLMs for GPU kernel generation, though prior work has largely focused on translating high-level PyTorch modules into CUDA code. In this work, we introduce Astra, the first LLM-based multi-agent system for GPU kernel optimization. Unlike previous approaches, Astra starts from existing CUDA implementations extracted from SGLang, a widely deployed framework for serving LLMs, rather than treating PyTorch modules as the specification. Within Astra, specialized LLM agents collaborate through iterative code generation, testing, profiling, and planning to produce kernels that are both correct and high-performance. On kernels from SGLang, Astra achieves an average speedup of 1.32x using zero-shot prompting with OpenAI o4-mini. A detailed case study further demonstrates that LLMs can autonomously apply loop transformations, optimize memory access patterns, exploit CUDA intrinsics, and leverage fast math operations to yield substantial performance gains. Our work highlights multi-agent LLM systems as a promising new paradigm for GPU kernel optimization.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.07506v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Anjiang Wei, Tianran Sun, Yogesh Seenichamy, Hang Song, Anne Ouyang, Azalia Mirhoseini, Ke Wang, Alex Aiken</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Trust but Verify! A Survey on Verification Design for Test-time Scaling</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.16665</link>
   <description>Test-time scaling (TTS) has emerged as a new frontier for scaling the performance of Large Language Models. In test-time scaling, by using more computational resources during inference, LLMs can improve their reasoning process and task performance. Several approaches have emerged for TTS such as distilling reasoning traces from another model or exploring the vast decoding search space by employing a verifier. The verifiers serve as reward models that help score the candidate outputs from the decoding process to diligently explore the vast solution space and select the best outcome. This paradigm commonly termed has emerged as a superior approach owing to parameter free scaling at inference time and high performance gains. The verifiers could be prompt-based, fine-tuned as a discriminative or generative model to verify process paths, outcomes or both. Despite their widespread adoption, there is no detailed collection, clear categorization and discussion of diverse verification approaches and their training mechanisms. In this survey, we cover the diverse approaches in the literature and present a unified view of verifier training, types and their utility in test-time scaling. Our repository can be found at https://github.com/elixir-research-group/Verifierstesttimescaling.github.io.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.16665v3</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>V Venktesh, Mandeep Rathee, Avishek Anand</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Understanding Museum Exhibits using Vision-Language Reasoning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01370</link>
   <description>Museums serve as repositories of cultural heritage and historical artifacts from diverse epochs, civilizations, and regions, preserving well-documented collections that encapsulate vast knowledge, which, when systematically structured into large-scale datasets, can train specialized models. Visitors engage with exhibits through curiosity and questions, making expert domain-specific models essential for interactive query resolution and gaining historical insights. Understanding exhibits from images requires analyzing visual features and linking them to historical knowledge to derive meaningful correlations. We facilitate such reasoning by (a) collecting and curating a large-scale dataset of 65M images and 200M question-answer pairs for exhibits from all around the world; (b) training large vision-language models (VLMs) on the collected dataset; (c) benchmarking their ability on five visual question answering tasks, specifically designed to reflect real-world inquiries and challenges observed in museum settings. The complete dataset is labeled by museum experts, ensuring the quality and the practical significance of the labels. We train two VLMs from different categories: BLIP with vision-language aligned embeddings, but lacking the expressive power of large language models, and the LLaVA model, a powerful instruction-tuned LLM enriched with vision-language reasoning capabilities. Through extensive experiments, we find that while both model types effectively answer visually grounded questions, large vision-language models excel in queries requiring deeper historical context and reasoning. We further demonstrate the necessity of fine-tuning models on large-scale domain-specific datasets by showing that our fine-tuned models significantly outperform current SOTA VLMs in answering questions related to specific attributes, highlighting their limitations in handling complex, nuanced queries.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.01370v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ada-Astrid Balauca, Sanjana Garai, Stefan Balauca, Rasesh Udayakumar Shetty, Naitik Agrawal, Dhwanil Subhashbhai Shah, Yuqian Fu, Xi Wang, Kristina Toutanova, Danda Pani Paudel, Luc Van Gool</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Understanding Museum Exhibits using Vision-Language Reasoning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01370</link>
   <description>Museums serve as repositories of cultural heritage and historical artifacts from diverse epochs, civilizations, and regions, preserving well-documented collections that encapsulate vast knowledge, which, when systematically structured into large-scale datasets, can train specialized models. Visitors engage with exhibits through curiosity and questions, making expert domain-specific models essential for interactive query resolution and gaining historical insights. Understanding exhibits from images requires analyzing visual features and linking them to historical knowledge to derive meaningful correlations. We facilitate such reasoning by (a) collecting and curating a large-scale dataset of 65M images and 200M question-answer pairs for exhibits from all around the world; (b) training large vision-language models (VLMs) on the collected dataset; (c) benchmarking their ability on five visual question answering tasks, specifically designed to reflect real-world inquiries and challenges observed in museum settings. The complete dataset is labeled by museum experts, ensuring the quality and the practical significance of the labels. We train two VLMs from different categories: BLIP with vision-language aligned embeddings, but lacking the expressive power of large language models, and the LLaVA model, a powerful instruction-tuned LLM enriched with vision-language reasoning capabilities. Through extensive experiments, we find that while both model types effectively answer visually grounded questions, large vision-language models excel in queries requiring deeper historical context and reasoning. We further demonstrate the necessity of fine-tuning models on large-scale domain-specific datasets by showing that our fine-tuned models significantly outperform current SOTA VLMs in answering questions related to specific attributes, highlighting their limitations in handling complex, nuanced queries.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.01370v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ada-Astrid Balauca, Sanjana Garai, Stefan Balauca, Rasesh Udayakumar Shetty, Naitik Agrawal, Dhwanil Subhashbhai Shah, Yuqian Fu, Xi Wang, Kristina Toutanova, Danda Pani Paudel, Luc Van Gool</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Hybrid-Regularized Magnitude Pruning for Robust Federated Learning under Covariate Shift</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15010</link>
   <description>Federated Learning offers a solution for decentralised model training, addressing the difficulties associated with distributed data and privacy in machine learning. However, the fact of data heterogeneity in federated learning frequently hinders the global model's generalisation, leading to low performance and adaptability to unseen data. This problem is particularly critical for specialised applications such as medical imaging, where both the data and the number of clients are limited. In this paper, we empirically demonstrate that inconsistencies in client-side training distributions substantially degrade the performance of federated learning models across multiple benchmark datasets. We propose a novel FL framework using a combination of pruning and regularisation of clients' training to improve the sparsity, redundancy, and robustness of neural connections, and thereby the resilience to model aggregation. To address a relatively unexplored dimension of data heterogeneity, we further introduce a novel benchmark dataset, CelebA-Gender, specifically designed to control for within-class distributional shifts across clients based on attribute variations, thereby complementing the predominant focus on inter-class imbalance in prior federated learning research. Comprehensive experiments on many datasets like CIFAR-10, MNIST, and the newly introduced CelebA-Gender dataset demonstrate that our method consistently outperforms standard FL baselines, yielding more robust and generalizable models in heterogeneous settings.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.15010v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ozgu Goksu, Nicolas Pugeault</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FediLoRA: Heterogeneous LoRA for Federated Multimodal Fine-tuning under Missing Modalities</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06984</link>
   <description>Foundation models have demonstrated remarkable performance across a wide range of tasks, yet their large parameter sizes pose challenges for practical deployment, especially in decentralized environments. Parameter-efficient fine-tuning (PEFT), such as Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA), reduces local computing and memory overhead, making it attractive for federated learning. However, existing federated LoRA methods typically assume uniform rank configurations and unimodal inputs, overlooking two key real-world challenges: (1) heterogeneous client resources have different LoRA ranks, and (2) multimodal data settings with potentially missing modalities. In this work, we propose FediLoRA, a simple yet effective framework for federated multimodal fine-tuning under heterogeneous LoRA ranks and missing modalities. FediLoRA introduces a dimension-wise aggregation strategy that reweights LoRA updates without information dilution during aggregation. It also includes a lightweight layer-wise model editing method that selectively incorporates global parameters to repair local components which improves both client and global model performances. Experimental results on three multimodal benchmark datasets demonstrate that FediLoRA achieves superior performance over competitive baselines in both global and personalized settings, particularly in the presence of modality incompleteness.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.06984v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Lishan Yang, Nam Kha Nguygen, Po Hu, Wei Emma Zhang, Yanjun Shu, Mong Yuan Sim, Weitong Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Fed-REACT: Federated Representation Learning for Heterogeneous and Evolving Data</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07198</link>
   <description>Motivated by the high resource costs and privacy concerns associated with centralized machine learning, federated learning (FL) has emerged as an efficient alternative that enables clients to collaboratively train a global model while keeping their data local. However, in real-world deployments, client data distributions often evolve over time and differ significantly across clients, introducing heterogeneity that degrades the performance of standard FL algorithms. In this work, we introduce Fed-REACT, a federated learning framework designed for heterogeneous and evolving client data. Fed-REACT combines representation learning with evolutionary clustering in a two-stage process: (1) in the first stage, each client learns a local model to extracts feature representations from its data; (2) in the second stage, the server dynamically groups clients into clusters based on these representations and coordinates cluster-wise training of task-specific models for downstream objectives such as classification or regression. We provide a theoretical analysis of the representation learning stage, and empirically demonstrate that Fed-REACT achieves superior accuracy and robustness on real-world datasets.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.07198v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yiyue Chen, Usman Akram, Chianing Wang, Haris Vikalo</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>MoE-Compression: How the Compression Error of Experts Affects the Inference Accuracy of MoE Model?</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07727</link>
   <description>With the widespread application of Mixture of Experts (MoE) reasoning models in the field of LLM learning, efficiently serving MoE models under limited GPU memory constraints has emerged as a significant challenge. Offloading the non-activated experts to main memory has been identified as an efficient approach to address such a problem, while it brings the challenges of transferring the expert between the GPU memory and main memory. We need to explore an efficient approach to compress the expert and analyze how the compression error affects the inference performance.
  To bridge this gap, we propose employing error-bounded lossy compression algorithms (such as SZ3 and CuSZp) to compress non-activated experts, thereby reducing data transfer overhead during MoE inference. We conduct extensive experiments across various benchmarks and present a comprehensive analysis of how compression-induced errors in different experts affect overall inference accuracy. The results indicate that experts in the shallow layers, which are primarily responsible for the attention mechanism and the transformation of input tokens into vector representations, exhibit minimal degradation in inference accuracy when subjected to bounded errors. In contrast, errors in the middle-layer experts, which are central to model reasoning, significantly impair inference accuracy. Interestingly, introducing bounded errors in the deep-layer experts, which are mainly responsible for instruction following and output integration, can sometimes lead to improvements in inference accuracy.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.07727v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Songkai Ma, Zhaorui Zhang, Sheng Di, Benben Liu, Xiaodong Yu, Xiaoyi Lu, Dan Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Bringing Multi-Modal Multi-Task Federated Foundation Models to Education Domain: Prospects and Challenges</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07946</link>
   <description>Multi-modal multi-task (M3T) foundation models (FMs) have recently shown transformative potential in artificial intelligence, with emerging applications in education. However, their deployment in real-world educational settings is hindered by privacy regulations, data silos, and limited domain-specific data availability. We introduce M3T Federated Foundation Models (FedFMs) for education: a paradigm that integrates federated learning (FL) with M3T FMs to enable collaborative, privacy-preserving training across decentralized institutions while accommodating diverse modalities and tasks. Subsequently, this position paper aims to unveil M3T FedFMs as a promising yet underexplored approach to the education community, explore its potentials, and reveal its related future research directions. We outline how M3T FedFMs can advance three critical pillars of next-generation intelligent education systems: (i) privacy preservation, by keeping sensitive multi-modal student and institutional data local; (ii) personalization, through modular architectures enabling tailored models for students, instructors, and institutions; and (iii) equity and inclusivity, by facilitating participation from underrepresented and resource-constrained entities. We finally identify various open research challenges, including studying of (i) inter-institution heterogeneous privacy regulations, (ii) the non-uniformity of data modalities' characteristics, (iii) the unlearning approaches for M3T FedFMs, (iv) the continual learning frameworks for M3T FedFMs, and (v) M3T FedFM model interpretability, which must be collectively addressed for practical deployment.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.07946v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.ET</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kasra Borazjani, Naji Khosravan, Rajeev Sahay, Bita Akram, Seyyedali Hosseinalipour</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>VoltanaLLM: Feedback-Driven Frequency Control and State-Space Routing for Energy-Efficient LLM Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04827</link>
   <description>Modern Large Language Model (LLM) serving systems increasingly support interactive applications, like real-time chat assistants, code generation tools, and agentic workflows. However, the soaring energy cost of LLM inference presents a growing challenge for sustainable and cost-effective deployment. This paper introduces VoltanaLLM, a system for SLO-aware, energy-efficient LLM serving, built from a control theory perspective. VoltanaLLM co-designs frequency scaling and request routing in emerging prefill/decode disaggregated architectures, leveraging their decoupled execution to enable fine-grained phase-specific control. It consists of a feedback-driven frequency controller that dynamically adapts GPU frequency for prefill and decode phases, and a state-space router that explores routing decisions across frequency-scaled instances to minimize energy under latency constraints. We implement VoltanaLLM in SGLang and evaluate its performance over multiple state-of-the-art LLMs and real-world datasets. The results demonstrate that VoltanaLLM achieves up to 36.3% energy savings while maintaining near-perfect SLO attainment rate, paving the way for sustainable and intelligent LLM serving.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.04827v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jiahuan Yu (University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign), Aryan Taneja (University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign), Junfeng Lin (Tsinghua University), Minjia Zhang (University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign)</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Astra: A Multi-Agent System for GPU Kernel Performance Optimization</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07506</link>
   <description>GPU kernel optimization has long been a central challenge at the intersection of high-performance computing and machine learning. Efficient kernels are crucial for accelerating large language model (LLM) training and serving, yet attaining high performance typically requires extensive manual tuning. Compiler-based systems reduce some of this burden, but still demand substantial manual design and engineering effort. Recently, researchers have explored using LLMs for GPU kernel generation, though prior work has largely focused on translating high-level PyTorch modules into CUDA code. In this work, we introduce Astra, the first LLM-based multi-agent system for GPU kernel optimization. Unlike previous approaches, Astra starts from existing CUDA implementations extracted from SGLang, a widely deployed framework for serving LLMs, rather than treating PyTorch modules as the specification. Within Astra, specialized LLM agents collaborate through iterative code generation, testing, profiling, and planning to produce kernels that are both correct and high-performance. On kernels from SGLang, Astra achieves an average speedup of 1.32x using zero-shot prompting with OpenAI o4-mini. A detailed case study further demonstrates that LLMs can autonomously apply loop transformations, optimize memory access patterns, exploit CUDA intrinsics, and leverage fast math operations to yield substantial performance gains. Our work highlights multi-agent LLM systems as a promising new paradigm for GPU kernel optimization.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.07506v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Anjiang Wei, Tianran Sun, Yogesh Seenichamy, Hang Song, Anne Ouyang, Azalia Mirhoseini, Ke Wang, Alex Aiken</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FilterFL: Knowledge Filtering-based Data-Free Backdoor Defense for Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.11333</link>
   <description>As a distributed machine learning paradigm, Federated Learning (FL) enables large-scale clients to collaboratively train a model without sharing their raw data. However, due to the lack of data auditing for untrusted clients, FL is vulnerable to poisoning attacks, especially backdoor attacks. By using poisoned data for local training or directly changing the model parameters, attackers can easily inject backdoors into the model, which can trigger the model to make misclassification of targeted patterns in images. To address these issues, we propose a novel data-free trigger-generation-based defense approach based on the two characteristics of backdoor attacks: i) triggers are learned faster than normal knowledge, and ii) trigger patterns have a greater effect on image classification than normal class patterns. Our approach generates the images with newly learned knowledge by identifying the differences between the old and new global models, and filters trigger images by evaluating the effect of these generated images. By using these trigger images, our approach eliminates poisoned models to ensure the updated global model is benign. Comprehensive experiments demonstrate that our approach can defend against almost all the existing types of backdoor attacks and outperform all the seven state-of-the-art defense methods with both IID and non-IID scenarios. Especially, our approach can successfully defend against the backdoor attack even when 80\% of the clients are malicious.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2308.11333v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yanxin Yang, Ming Hu, Xiaofei Xie, Yue Cao, Pengyu Zhang, Yihao Huang, Mingsong Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Hybrid-Regularized Magnitude Pruning for Robust Federated Learning under Covariate Shift</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15010</link>
   <description>Federated Learning offers a solution for decentralised model training, addressing the difficulties associated with distributed data and privacy in machine learning. However, the fact of data heterogeneity in federated learning frequently hinders the global model's generalisation, leading to low performance and adaptability to unseen data. This problem is particularly critical for specialised applications such as medical imaging, where both the data and the number of clients are limited. In this paper, we empirically demonstrate that inconsistencies in client-side training distributions substantially degrade the performance of federated learning models across multiple benchmark datasets. We propose a novel FL framework using a combination of pruning and regularisation of clients' training to improve the sparsity, redundancy, and robustness of neural connections, and thereby the resilience to model aggregation. To address a relatively unexplored dimension of data heterogeneity, we further introduce a novel benchmark dataset, CelebA-Gender, specifically designed to control for within-class distributional shifts across clients based on attribute variations, thereby complementing the predominant focus on inter-class imbalance in prior federated learning research. Comprehensive experiments on many datasets like CIFAR-10, MNIST, and the newly introduced CelebA-Gender dataset demonstrate that our method consistently outperforms standard FL baselines, yielding more robust and generalizable models in heterogeneous settings.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.15010v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ozgu Goksu, Nicolas Pugeault</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Bringing Multi-Modal Multi-Task Federated Foundation Models to Education Domain: Prospects and Challenges</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07946</link>
   <description>Multi-modal multi-task (M3T) foundation models (FMs) have recently shown transformative potential in artificial intelligence, with emerging applications in education. However, their deployment in real-world educational settings is hindered by privacy regulations, data silos, and limited domain-specific data availability. We introduce M3T Federated Foundation Models (FedFMs) for education: a paradigm that integrates federated learning (FL) with M3T FMs to enable collaborative, privacy-preserving training across decentralized institutions while accommodating diverse modalities and tasks. Subsequently, this position paper aims to unveil M3T FedFMs as a promising yet underexplored approach to the education community, explore its potentials, and reveal its related future research directions. We outline how M3T FedFMs can advance three critical pillars of next-generation intelligent education systems: (i) privacy preservation, by keeping sensitive multi-modal student and institutional data local; (ii) personalization, through modular architectures enabling tailored models for students, instructors, and institutions; and (iii) equity and inclusivity, by facilitating participation from underrepresented and resource-constrained entities. We finally identify various open research challenges, including studying of (i) inter-institution heterogeneous privacy regulations, (ii) the non-uniformity of data modalities' characteristics, (iii) the unlearning approaches for M3T FedFMs, (iv) the continual learning frameworks for M3T FedFMs, and (v) M3T FedFM model interpretability, which must be collectively addressed for practical deployment.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.07946v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.ET</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kasra Borazjani, Naji Khosravan, Rajeev Sahay, Bita Akram, Seyyedali Hosseinalipour</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>TrojanRobot: Physical-world Backdoor Attacks Against VLM-based Robotic Manipulation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11683</link>
   <description>Robotic manipulation in the physical world is increasingly empowered by \textit{large language models} (LLMs) and \textit{vision-language models} (VLMs), leveraging their understanding and perception capabilities. Recently, various attacks against such robotic policies have been proposed, with backdoor attacks drawing considerable attention for their high stealth and strong persistence capabilities. However, existing backdoor efforts are limited to simulators and suffer from physical-world realization. To address this, we propose \textit{TrojanRobot}, a highly stealthy and broadly effective robotic backdoor attack in the physical world. Specifically, we introduce a module-poisoning approach by embedding a backdoor module into the modular robotic policy, enabling backdoor control over the policy's visual perception module thereby backdooring the entire robotic policy. Our vanilla implementation leverages a backdoor-finetuned VLM to serve as the backdoor module. To enhance its generalization in physical environments, we propose a prime implementation, leveraging the LVLM-as-a-backdoor paradigm and developing three types of prime attacks, \ie, \textit{permutation}, \textit{stagnation}, and \textit{intentional} attacks, thus achieving finer-grained backdoors. Extensive experiments on the UR3e manipulator with 18 task instructions using robotic policies based on four VLMs demonstrate the broad effectiveness and physical-world stealth of TrojanRobot. Our attack's video demonstrations are available via a github link https://trojanrobot.github.io.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2411.11683v4</guid>
   <category>cs.RO</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xianlong Wang, Hewen Pan, Hangtao Zhang, Minghui Li, Shengshan Hu, Ziqi Zhou, Lulu Xue, Peijin Guo, Aishan Liu, Leo Yu Zhang, Xiaohua Jia</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Generative AI as a Tool for Enhancing Reflective Learning in Students</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02603</link>
   <description>Reflection is widely recognized as a cornerstone of student development, fostering critical thinking, self-regulation, and deep conceptual understanding. Traditionally, reflective skills have been cultivated through structured feedback, mentorship, and guided self-assessment. However, these approaches often face challenges such as limited scalability, difficulties in delivering individualized feedback, and a shortage of instructors proficient in facilitating meaningful reflection. This study pioneers the use of generative AI, specifically large language models (LLMs), as an innovative solution to these limitations. By leveraging the capacity of LLMs to deliver personalized, context-sensitive feedback at scale, this research investigates their potential to serve as effective facilitators of reflective exercises, sustaining deep engagement and promoting critical thinking. Through in-depth analyses of prompt engineering strategies and simulated multi-turn dialogues grounded in a project-based learning (PBL) context, the study demonstrates that, with pedagogically aligned prompts, LLMs can serve as accessible and adaptive tools for scalable reflective guidance. Furthermore, LLM-assisted evaluation is employed to objectively assess the performance of both tutors and students across multiple dimensions of reflective learning. The findings contribute to the evolving understanding of AI's role in reflective pedagogy and point to new opportunities for advancing AI-driven intelligent tutoring systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.02603v2</guid>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Bo Yuan, Jiazi Hu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>VoltanaLLM: Feedback-Driven Frequency Control and State-Space Routing for Energy-Efficient LLM Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04827</link>
   <description>Modern Large Language Model (LLM) serving systems increasingly support interactive applications, like real-time chat assistants, code generation tools, and agentic workflows. However, the soaring energy cost of LLM inference presents a growing challenge for sustainable and cost-effective deployment. This paper introduces VoltanaLLM, a system for SLO-aware, energy-efficient LLM serving, built from a control theory perspective. VoltanaLLM co-designs frequency scaling and request routing in emerging prefill/decode disaggregated architectures, leveraging their decoupled execution to enable fine-grained phase-specific control. It consists of a feedback-driven frequency controller that dynamically adapts GPU frequency for prefill and decode phases, and a state-space router that explores routing decisions across frequency-scaled instances to minimize energy under latency constraints. We implement VoltanaLLM in SGLang and evaluate its performance over multiple state-of-the-art LLMs and real-world datasets. The results demonstrate that VoltanaLLM achieves up to 36.3% energy savings while maintaining near-perfect SLO attainment rate, paving the way for sustainable and intelligent LLM serving.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.04827v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jiahuan Yu (University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign), Aryan Taneja (University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign), Junfeng Lin (Tsinghua University), Minjia Zhang (University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign)</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FediLoRA: Heterogeneous LoRA for Federated Multimodal Fine-tuning under Missing Modalities</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06984</link>
   <description>Foundation models have demonstrated remarkable performance across a wide range of tasks, yet their large parameter sizes pose challenges for practical deployment, especially in decentralized environments. Parameter-efficient fine-tuning (PEFT), such as Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA), reduces local computing and memory overhead, making it attractive for federated learning. However, existing federated LoRA methods typically assume uniform rank configurations and unimodal inputs, overlooking two key real-world challenges: (1) heterogeneous client resources have different LoRA ranks, and (2) multimodal data settings with potentially missing modalities. In this work, we propose FediLoRA, a simple yet effective framework for federated multimodal fine-tuning under heterogeneous LoRA ranks and missing modalities. FediLoRA introduces a dimension-wise aggregation strategy that reweights LoRA updates without information dilution during aggregation. It also includes a lightweight layer-wise model editing method that selectively incorporates global parameters to repair local components which improves both client and global model performances. Experimental results on three multimodal benchmark datasets demonstrate that FediLoRA achieves superior performance over competitive baselines in both global and personalized settings, particularly in the presence of modality incompleteness.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.06984v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Lishan Yang, Nam Kha Nguygen, Po Hu, Wei Emma Zhang, Yanjun Shu, Mong Yuan Sim, Weitong Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Astra: A Multi-Agent System for GPU Kernel Performance Optimization</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07506</link>
   <description>GPU kernel optimization has long been a central challenge at the intersection of high-performance computing and machine learning. Efficient kernels are crucial for accelerating large language model (LLM) training and serving, yet attaining high performance typically requires extensive manual tuning. Compiler-based systems reduce some of this burden, but still demand substantial manual design and engineering effort. Recently, researchers have explored using LLMs for GPU kernel generation, though prior work has largely focused on translating high-level PyTorch modules into CUDA code. In this work, we introduce Astra, the first LLM-based multi-agent system for GPU kernel optimization. Unlike previous approaches, Astra starts from existing CUDA implementations extracted from SGLang, a widely deployed framework for serving LLMs, rather than treating PyTorch modules as the specification. Within Astra, specialized LLM agents collaborate through iterative code generation, testing, profiling, and planning to produce kernels that are both correct and high-performance. On kernels from SGLang, Astra achieves an average speedup of 1.32x using zero-shot prompting with OpenAI o4-mini. A detailed case study further demonstrates that LLMs can autonomously apply loop transformations, optimize memory access patterns, exploit CUDA intrinsics, and leverage fast math operations to yield substantial performance gains. Our work highlights multi-agent LLM systems as a promising new paradigm for GPU kernel optimization.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.07506v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Anjiang Wei, Tianran Sun, Yogesh Seenichamy, Hang Song, Anne Ouyang, Azalia Mirhoseini, Ke Wang, Alex Aiken</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Bringing Multi-Modal Multi-Task Federated Foundation Models to Education Domain: Prospects and Challenges</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07946</link>
   <description>Multi-modal multi-task (M3T) foundation models (FMs) have recently shown transformative potential in artificial intelligence, with emerging applications in education. However, their deployment in real-world educational settings is hindered by privacy regulations, data silos, and limited domain-specific data availability. We introduce M3T Federated Foundation Models (FedFMs) for education: a paradigm that integrates federated learning (FL) with M3T FMs to enable collaborative, privacy-preserving training across decentralized institutions while accommodating diverse modalities and tasks. Subsequently, this position paper aims to unveil M3T FedFMs as a promising yet underexplored approach to the education community, explore its potentials, and reveal its related future research directions. We outline how M3T FedFMs can advance three critical pillars of next-generation intelligent education systems: (i) privacy preservation, by keeping sensitive multi-modal student and institutional data local; (ii) personalization, through modular architectures enabling tailored models for students, instructors, and institutions; and (iii) equity and inclusivity, by facilitating participation from underrepresented and resource-constrained entities. We finally identify various open research challenges, including studying of (i) inter-institution heterogeneous privacy regulations, (ii) the non-uniformity of data modalities' characteristics, (iii) the unlearning approaches for M3T FedFMs, (iv) the continual learning frameworks for M3T FedFMs, and (v) M3T FedFM model interpretability, which must be collectively addressed for practical deployment.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.07946v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.ET</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kasra Borazjani, Naji Khosravan, Rajeev Sahay, Bita Akram, Seyyedali Hosseinalipour</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>TrojanRobot: Physical-world Backdoor Attacks Against VLM-based Robotic Manipulation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11683</link>
   <description>Robotic manipulation in the physical world is increasingly empowered by \textit{large language models} (LLMs) and \textit{vision-language models} (VLMs), leveraging their understanding and perception capabilities. Recently, various attacks against such robotic policies have been proposed, with backdoor attacks drawing considerable attention for their high stealth and strong persistence capabilities. However, existing backdoor efforts are limited to simulators and suffer from physical-world realization. To address this, we propose \textit{TrojanRobot}, a highly stealthy and broadly effective robotic backdoor attack in the physical world. Specifically, we introduce a module-poisoning approach by embedding a backdoor module into the modular robotic policy, enabling backdoor control over the policy's visual perception module thereby backdooring the entire robotic policy. Our vanilla implementation leverages a backdoor-finetuned VLM to serve as the backdoor module. To enhance its generalization in physical environments, we propose a prime implementation, leveraging the LVLM-as-a-backdoor paradigm and developing three types of prime attacks, \ie, \textit{permutation}, \textit{stagnation}, and \textit{intentional} attacks, thus achieving finer-grained backdoors. Extensive experiments on the UR3e manipulator with 18 task instructions using robotic policies based on four VLMs demonstrate the broad effectiveness and physical-world stealth of TrojanRobot. Our attack's video demonstrations are available via a github link https://trojanrobot.github.io.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2411.11683v4</guid>
   <category>cs.RO</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xianlong Wang, Hewen Pan, Hangtao Zhang, Minghui Li, Shengshan Hu, Ziqi Zhou, Lulu Xue, Peijin Guo, Aishan Liu, Leo Yu Zhang, Xiaohua Jia</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Trust but Verify! A Survey on Verification Design for Test-time Scaling</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.16665</link>
   <description>Test-time scaling (TTS) has emerged as a new frontier for scaling the performance of Large Language Models. In test-time scaling, by using more computational resources during inference, LLMs can improve their reasoning process and task performance. Several approaches have emerged for TTS such as distilling reasoning traces from another model or exploring the vast decoding search space by employing a verifier. The verifiers serve as reward models that help score the candidate outputs from the decoding process to diligently explore the vast solution space and select the best outcome. This paradigm commonly termed has emerged as a superior approach owing to parameter free scaling at inference time and high performance gains. The verifiers could be prompt-based, fine-tuned as a discriminative or generative model to verify process paths, outcomes or both. Despite their widespread adoption, there is no detailed collection, clear categorization and discussion of diverse verification approaches and their training mechanisms. In this survey, we cover the diverse approaches in the literature and present a unified view of verifier training, types and their utility in test-time scaling. Our repository can be found at https://github.com/elixir-research-group/Verifierstesttimescaling.github.io.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.16665v3</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>V Venktesh, Mandeep Rathee, Avishek Anand</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
