<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 04:25:04 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 04:25:04 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>Proxy Model-Guided Reinforcement Learning for Client Selection in Federated Recommendation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10401</link>
   <description>Federated recommender systems have emerged as a promising privacy-preserving paradigm, enabling personalized recommendation services without exposing users' raw data. By keeping data local and relying on a central server to coordinate training across distributed clients, FedRSs protect user privacy while collaboratively learning global models. However, most existing FedRS frameworks adopt fully random client selection strategy in each training round, overlooking the statistical heterogeneity of user data arising from diverse preferences and behavior patterns, thereby resulting in suboptimal model performance. While some client selection strategies have been proposed in the broader federated learning literature, these methods are typically designed for generic tasks and fail to address the unique challenges of recommendation scenarios, such as expensive contribution evaluation due to the large number of clients, and sparse updates resulting from long-tail item distributions. To bridge this gap, we propose ProxyRL-FRS, a proxy model-guided reinforcement learning framework tailored for client selection in federated recommendation. Specifically, we first introduce ProxyNCF, a dual-branch model deployed on each client, which augments standard Neural Collaborative Filtering with an additional proxy model branch that provides lightweight contribution estimation, thus eliminating the need for expensive per-round local training traditionally required to evaluate a client's contribution. Furthermore, we design a staleness-aware SA reinforcement learning agent that selects clients based on the proxy-estimated contribution, and is guided by a reward function balancing recommendation accuracy and embedding staleness, thereby enriching the update coverage of item embeddings. Experiments conducted on public recommendation datasets demonstrate the effectiveness of ProxyRL-FRS.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10401v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Liang Qu, Jianxin Li, Wei Yuan, Penghui Ruan, Yuhui Shi, Hongzhi Yin</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>DAS: Dual-Aligned Semantic IDs Empowered Industrial Recommender System</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10584</link>
   <description>Semantic IDs are discrete identifiers generated by quantizing the Multi-modal Large Language Models (MLLMs) embeddings, enabling efficient multi-modal content integration in recommendation systems. However, their lack of collaborative signals results in a misalignment with downstream discriminative and generative recommendation objectives. Recent studies have introduced various alignment mechanisms to address this problem, but their two-stage framework design still leads to two main limitations: (1) inevitable information loss during alignment, and (2) inflexibility in applying adaptive alignment strategies, consequently constraining the mutual information maximization during the alignment process. To address these limitations, we propose a novel and flexible one-stage Dual-Aligned Semantic IDs (DAS) method that simultaneously optimizes quantization and alignment, preserving semantic integrity and alignment quality while avoiding the information loss typically associated with two-stage methods. Meanwhile, DAS achieves more efficient alignment between the semantic IDs and collaborative signals, with the following two innovative and effective approaches: (1) Multi-view Constrative Alignment: To maximize mutual information between semantic IDs and collaborative signals, we first incorporate an ID-based CF debias module, and then design three effective contrastive alignment methods: dual user-to-item (u2i), dual item-to-item/user-to-user (i2i/u2u), and dual co-occurrence item-to-item/user-to-user (i2i/u2u). (2) Dual Learning: By aligning the dual quantizations of users and ads, the constructed semantic IDs for users and ads achieve stronger alignment. Finally, we conduct extensive offline experiments and online A/B tests to evaluate DAS's effectiveness, which is now successfully deployed across various advertising scenarios at Kuaishou App, serving over 400 million users daily.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10584v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Wencai Ye, Mingjie Sun, Shaoyun Shi, Peng Wang, Wenjin Wu, Peng Jiang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Reflect then Learn: Active Prompting for Information Extraction Guided by Introspective Confusion</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10036</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) show remarkable potential for few-shot information extraction (IE), yet their performance is highly sensitive to the choice of in-context examples. Conventional selection strategies often fail to provide informative guidance, as they overlook a key source of model fallibility: confusion stemming not just from semantic content, but also from the generation of well-structured formats required by IE tasks. To address this, we introduce Active Prompting for Information Extraction (APIE), a novel active prompting framework guided by a principle we term introspective confusion. Our method empowers an LLM to assess its own confusion through a dual-component uncertainty metric that uniquely quantifies both Format Uncertainty (difficulty in generating correct syntax) and Content Uncertainty (inconsistency in extracted semantics). By ranking unlabeled data with this comprehensive score, our framework actively selects the most challenging and informative samples to serve as few-shot exemplars. Extensive experiments on four benchmarks show that our approach consistently outperforms strong baselines, yielding significant improvements in both extraction accuracy and robustness. Our work highlights the critical importance of a fine-grained, dual-level view of model uncertainty when it comes to building effective and reliable structured generation systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10036v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Dong Zhao, Yadong Wang, Xiang Chen, Chenxi Wang, Hongliang Dai, Chuanxing Geng, Shengzhong Zhang, Shaoyuan Li, Sheng-Jun Huang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Learning Over LoRa Networks: Simulator Design and Performance Evaluation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10574</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) over long-range (LoRa) low-power wide area networks faces unique challenges due to limited bandwidth, interference, and strict duty-cycle constraints. We develop a Python-based simulator that integrates and extends the Flower and LoRaSim frameworks to evaluate centralized FL over LoRa networks. The simulator employs a detailed link-level model for FL update transfer over LoRa channels, capturing LoRa's receiver sensitivity, interference characteristics, block-fading effects, and constraints on the maximum transmission unit. It supports update sparsification, quantization, compression, forward frame-erasure correction (FEC), and duty cycling. Numerical results illustrate the impact of transmission parameters (spreading factor, FEC rate) and interference on FL performance. Demonstrating the critical role of FEC in enabling FL over LoRa networks, we perform an in-depth evaluation of the impact of FEC on FL convergence and device airtime, providing insights for communication protocol design for FL over LoRa networks.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10574v1</guid>
   <category>cs.NI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Anshika Singh, Siddhartha S. Borkotoky</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedABC: Attention-Based Client Selection for Federated Learning with Long-Term View</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.20871</link>
   <description>Native AI support is a key objective in the evolution of 6G networks, with Federated Learning (FL) emerging as a promising paradigm. FL allows decentralized clients to collaboratively train an AI model without directly sharing their data, preserving privacy. Clients train local models on private data and share model updates, which a central server aggregates to refine the global model and redistribute it for the next iteration. However, client data heterogeneity slows convergence and reduces model accuracy, and frequent client participation imposes communication and computational burdens. To address these challenges, we propose FedABC, an innovative client selection algorithm designed to take a long-term view in managing data heterogeneity and optimizing client participation. Inspired by attention mechanisms, FedABC prioritizes informative clients by evaluating both model similarity and each model's unique contributions to the global model. Moreover, considering the evolving demands of the global model, we formulate an optimization problem to guide FedABC throughout the training process. Following the &quot;later-is-better&quot; principle, FedABC adaptively adjusts the client selection threshold, encouraging greater participation in later training stages. Extensive simulations on CIFAR-10 demonstrate that FedABC significantly outperforms existing approaches in model accuracy and client participation efficiency, achieving comparable performance with 32% fewer clients than the classical FL algorithm FedAvg, and 3.5% higher accuracy with 2% fewer clients than the state-of-the-art. This work marks a step toward deploying FL in heterogeneous, resource-constrained environments, thereby supporting native AI capabilities in 6G networks.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.20871v2</guid>
   <category>cs.NI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Wenxuan Ye, Xueli An, Junfan Wang, Xueqiang Yan, Georg Carle</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Anomaly Detection for Multi-Tenant Cloud Platforms with Personalized Modeling</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10255</link>
   <description>This paper proposes an anomaly detection method based on federated learning to address key challenges in multi-tenant cloud environments, including data privacy leakage, heterogeneous resource behavior, and the limitations of centralized modeling. The method establishes a federated training framework involving multiple tenants. Each tenant trains the model locally using private resource usage data. Through parameter aggregation, a global model is optimized, enabling cross-tenant collaborative anomaly detection while preserving data privacy. To improve adaptability to diverse resource usage patterns, a personalized parameter adjustment mechanism is introduced. This allows the model to retain tenant-specific feature representations while sharing global knowledge. In the model output stage, the Mahalanobis distance is used to compute anomaly scores. This enhances both the accuracy and stability of anomaly detection. The experiments use real telemetry data from a cloud platform to construct a simulated multi-tenant environment. The study evaluates the model's performance under varying participation rates and noise injection levels. These comparisons demonstrate the proposed method's robustness and detection accuracy. Experimental results show that the proposed method outperforms existing mainstream models across key metrics such as Precision, Recall, and F1-Score. It also maintains stable performance in various complex scenarios. These findings highlight the method's practical potential for intelligent resource monitoring and anomaly diagnosis in cloud computing environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10255v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yuxi Wang, Heyao Liu, Nyutian Long, Guanzi Yao</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Improving Learning of New Diseases through Knowledge-Enhanced Initialization for Federated Adapter Tuning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10299</link>
   <description>In healthcare, federated learning (FL) is a widely adopted framework that enables privacy-preserving collaboration among medical institutions. With large foundation models (FMs) demonstrating impressive capabilities, using FMs in FL through cost-efficient adapter tuning has become a popular approach. Given the rapidly evolving healthcare environment, it is crucial for individual clients to quickly adapt to new tasks or diseases by tuning adapters while drawing upon past experiences. In this work, we introduce Federated Knowledge-Enhanced Initialization (FedKEI), a novel framework that leverages cross-client and cross-task transfer from past knowledge to generate informed initializations for learning new tasks with adapters. FedKEI begins with a global clustering process at the server to generalize knowledge across tasks, followed by the optimization of aggregation weights across clusters (inter-cluster weights) and within each cluster (intra-cluster weights) to personalize knowledge transfer for each new task. To facilitate more effective learning of the inter- and intra-cluster weights, we adopt a bi-level optimization scheme that collaboratively learns the global intra-cluster weights across clients and optimizes the local inter-cluster weights toward each client's task objective. Extensive experiments on three benchmark datasets of different modalities, including dermatology, chest X-rays, and retinal OCT, demonstrate FedKEI's advantage in adapting to new diseases compared to state-of-the-art methods.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10299v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Danni Peng, Yuan Wang, Kangning Cai, Peiyan Ning, Jiming Xu, Yong Liu, Rick Siow Mong Goh, Qingsong Wei, Huazhu Fu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Vision-Language Pre-training Model-Guided Approach for Mitigating Backdoor Attacks in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10315</link>
   <description>Existing backdoor defense methods in Federated Learning (FL) rely on the assumption of homogeneous client data distributions or the availability of a clean serve dataset, which limits the practicality and effectiveness. Defending against backdoor attacks under heterogeneous client data distributions while preserving model performance remains a significant challenge. In this paper, we propose a FL backdoor defense framework named CLIP-Fed, which leverages the zero-shot learning capabilities of vision-language pre-training models. By integrating both pre-aggregation and post-aggregation defense strategies, CLIP-Fed overcomes the limitations of Non-IID imposed on defense effectiveness. To address privacy concerns and enhance the coverage of the dataset against diverse triggers, we construct and augment the server dataset using the multimodal large language model and frequency analysis without any client samples. To address class prototype deviations caused by backdoor samples and eliminate the correlation between trigger patterns and target labels, CLIP-Fed aligns the knowledge of the global model and CLIP on the augmented dataset using prototype contrastive loss and Kullback-Leibler divergence. Extensive experiments on representative datasets validate the effectiveness of CLIP-Fed. Compared to state-of-the-art methods, CLIP-Fed achieves an average reduction in ASR, i.e., 2.03\% on CIFAR-10 and 1.35\% on CIFAR-10-LT, while improving average MA by 7.92\% and 0.48\%, respectively.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10315v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Keke Gai, Dongjue Wang, Jing Yu, Liehuang Zhu, Qi Wu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>GraphFedMIG: Tackling Class Imbalance in Federated Graph Learning via Mutual Information-Guided Generation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10471</link>
   <description>Federated graph learning (FGL) enables multiple clients to collaboratively train powerful graph neural networks without sharing their private, decentralized graph data. Inherited from generic federated learning, FGL is critically challenged by statistical heterogeneity, where non-IID data distributions across clients can severely impair model performance. A particularly destructive form of this is class imbalance, which causes the global model to become biased towards majority classes and fail at identifying rare but critical events. This issue is exacerbated in FGL, as nodes from a minority class are often surrounded by biased neighborhood information, hindering the learning of expressive embeddings. To grapple with this challenge, we propose GraphFedMIG, a novel FGL framework that reframes the problem as a federated generative data augmentation task. GraphFedMIG employs a hierarchical generative adversarial network where each client trains a local generator to synthesize high-fidelity feature representations. To provide tailored supervision, clients are grouped into clusters, each sharing a dedicated discriminator. Crucially, the framework designs a mutual information-guided mechanism to steer the evolution of these client generators. By calculating each client's unique informational value, this mechanism corrects the local generator parameters, ensuring that subsequent rounds of mutual information-guided generation are focused on producing high-value, minority-class features. We conduct extensive experiments on four real-world datasets, and the results demonstrate the superiority of the proposed GraphFedMIG compared with other baselines.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10471v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xinrui Li, Qilin Fan, Tianfu Wang, Kaiwen Wei, Ke Yu, Xu Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>APFL: Analytic Personalized Federated Learning via Dual-Stream Least Squares</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10732</link>
   <description>Personalized Federated Learning (PFL) has presented a significant challenge to deliver personalized models to individual clients through collaborative training. Existing PFL methods are often vulnerable to non-IID data, which severely hinders collective generalization and then compromises the subsequent personalization efforts. In this paper, to address this non-IID issue in PFL, we propose an Analytic Personalized Federated Learning (APFL) approach via dual-stream least squares. In our APFL, we use a foundation model as a frozen backbone for feature extraction. Subsequent to the feature extractor, we develop dual-stream analytic models to achieve both collective generalization and individual personalization. Specifically, our APFL incorporates a shared primary stream for global generalization across all clients, and a dedicated refinement stream for local personalization of each individual client. The analytical solutions of our APFL enable its ideal property of heterogeneity invariance, theoretically meaning that each personalized model remains identical regardless of how heterogeneous the data are distributed across all other clients. Empirical results across various datasets also validate the superiority of our APFL over state-of-the-art baselines, with advantages of at least 1.10%-15.45% in accuracy.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10732v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kejia Fan, Jianheng Tang, Zhirui Yang, Feijiang Han, Jiaxu Li, Run He, Yajiang Huang, Anfeng Liu, Houbing Herbert Song, Yunhuai Liu, Huiping Zhuang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Robust Pipeline for Differentially Private Federated Learning on Imbalanced Clinical Data using SMOTETomek and FedProx</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10017</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) presents a groundbreaking approach for collaborative health research, allowing model training on decentralized data while safeguarding patient privacy. FL offers formal security guarantees when combined with Differential Privacy (DP). The integration of these technologies, however, introduces a significant trade-off between privacy and clinical utility, a challenge further complicated by the severe class imbalance often present in medical datasets. The research presented herein addresses these interconnected issues through a systematic, multi-stage analysis. An FL framework was implemented for cardiovascular risk prediction, where initial experiments showed that standard methods struggled with imbalanced data, resulting in a recall of zero. To overcome such a limitation, we first integrated the hybrid Synthetic Minority Over-sampling Technique with Tomek Links (SMOTETomek) at the client level, successfully developing a clinically useful model. Subsequently, the framework was optimized for non-IID data using a tuned FedProx algorithm. Our final results reveal a clear, non-linear trade-off between the privacy budget (epsilon) and model recall, with the optimized FedProx consistently out-performing standard FedAvg. An optimal operational region was identified on the privacy-utility frontier, where strong privacy guarantees (with epsilon 9.0) can be achieved while maintaining high clinical utility (recall greater than 77%). Ultimately, our study provides a practical methodological blueprint for creating effective, secure, and accurate diagnostic tools that can be applied to real-world, heterogeneous healthcare data.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10017v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Rodrigo Tertulino</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Reflect then Learn: Active Prompting for Information Extraction Guided by Introspective Confusion</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10036</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) show remarkable potential for few-shot information extraction (IE), yet their performance is highly sensitive to the choice of in-context examples. Conventional selection strategies often fail to provide informative guidance, as they overlook a key source of model fallibility: confusion stemming not just from semantic content, but also from the generation of well-structured formats required by IE tasks. To address this, we introduce Active Prompting for Information Extraction (APIE), a novel active prompting framework guided by a principle we term introspective confusion. Our method empowers an LLM to assess its own confusion through a dual-component uncertainty metric that uniquely quantifies both Format Uncertainty (difficulty in generating correct syntax) and Content Uncertainty (inconsistency in extracted semantics). By ranking unlabeled data with this comprehensive score, our framework actively selects the most challenging and informative samples to serve as few-shot exemplars. Extensive experiments on four benchmarks show that our approach consistently outperforms strong baselines, yielding significant improvements in both extraction accuracy and robustness. Our work highlights the critical importance of a fine-grained, dual-level view of model uncertainty when it comes to building effective and reliable structured generation systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10036v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Dong Zhao, Yadong Wang, Xiang Chen, Chenxi Wang, Hongliang Dai, Chuanxing Geng, Shengzhong Zhang, Shaoyuan Li, Sheng-Jun Huang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Flexible Personalized Split Federated Learning for On-Device Fine-Tuning of Foundation Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10349</link>
   <description>Fine-tuning foundation models is critical for superior performance on personalized downstream tasks, compared to using pre-trained models. Collaborative learning can leverage local clients' datasets for fine-tuning, but limited client data and heterogeneous data distributions hinder effective collaboration. To address the challenge, we propose a flexible personalized federated learning paradigm that enables clients to engage in collaborative learning while maintaining personalized objectives. Given the limited and heterogeneous computational resources available on clients, we introduce \textbf{flexible personalized split federated learning (FlexP-SFL)}. Based on split learning, FlexP-SFL allows each client to train a portion of the model locally while offloading the rest to a server, according to resource constraints. Additionally, we propose an alignment strategy to improve personalized model performance on global data. Experimental results show that FlexP-SFL outperforms baseline models in personalized fine-tuning efficiency and final accuracy.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10349v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Tianjun Yuan, Jiaxiang Geng, Pengchao Han, Xianhao Chen, Bing Luo</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Time Series Generation on Feature and Temporally Misaligned Data</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21072</link>
   <description>Distributed time series data presents a challenge for federated learning, as clients often possess different feature sets and have misaligned time steps. Existing federated time series models are limited by the assumption of perfect temporal or feature alignment across clients. In this paper, we propose FedTDD, a novel federated time series diffusion model that jointly learns a synthesizer across clients. At the core of FedTDD is a novel data distillation and aggregation framework that reconciles the differences between clients by imputing the misaligned timesteps and features. In contrast to traditional federated learning, FedTDD learns the correlation across clients' time series through the exchange of local synthetic outputs instead of model parameters. A coordinator iteratively improves a global distiller network by leveraging shared knowledge from clients through the exchange of synthetic data. As the distiller becomes more refined over time, it subsequently enhances the quality of the clients' local feature estimates, allowing each client to then improve its local imputations for missing data using the latest, more accurate distiller. Experimental results on five datasets demonstrate FedTDD's effectiveness compared to centralized training, and the effectiveness of sharing synthetic outputs to transfer knowledge of local time series. Notably, FedTDD achieves 79.4% and 62.8% improvement over local training in Context-FID and Correlational scores.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.21072v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhi Wen Soi, Chenrui Fan, Aditya Shankar, Abele M\u{a}lan, Lydia Y. Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Decentralized Weather Forecasting via Distributed Machine Learning and Blockchain-Based Model Validation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09299</link>
   <description>Weather forecasting plays a vital role in disaster preparedness, agriculture, and resource management, yet current centralized forecasting systems are increasingly strained by security vulnerabilities, limited scalability, and susceptibility to single points of failure. To address these challenges, we propose a decentralized weather forecasting framework that integrates Federated Learning (FL) with blockchain technology. FL enables collaborative model training without exposing sensitive local data; this approach enhances privacy and reduces data transfer overhead. Meanwhile, the Ethereum blockchain ensures transparent and dependable verification of model updates. To further enhance the system's security, we introduce a reputation-based voting mechanism that assesses the trustworthiness of submitted models while utilizing the Interplanetary File System (IPFS) for efficient off-chain storage. Experimental results demonstrate that our approach not only improves forecasting accuracy but also enhances system resilience and scalability, making it a viable candidate for deployment in real-world, security-critical environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.09299v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Rilwan Umar, Aydin Abadi, Basil Aldali, Benito Vincent, Elliot A. J. Hurley, Hotoon Aljazaeri, Jamie Hedley-Cook, Jamie-Lee Bell, Lambert Uwuigbusun, Mujeeb Ahmed, Shishir Nagaraja, Suleiman Sabo, Weaam Alrbeiqi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedABC: Attention-Based Client Selection for Federated Learning with Long-Term View</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.20871</link>
   <description>Native AI support is a key objective in the evolution of 6G networks, with Federated Learning (FL) emerging as a promising paradigm. FL allows decentralized clients to collaboratively train an AI model without directly sharing their data, preserving privacy. Clients train local models on private data and share model updates, which a central server aggregates to refine the global model and redistribute it for the next iteration. However, client data heterogeneity slows convergence and reduces model accuracy, and frequent client participation imposes communication and computational burdens. To address these challenges, we propose FedABC, an innovative client selection algorithm designed to take a long-term view in managing data heterogeneity and optimizing client participation. Inspired by attention mechanisms, FedABC prioritizes informative clients by evaluating both model similarity and each model's unique contributions to the global model. Moreover, considering the evolving demands of the global model, we formulate an optimization problem to guide FedABC throughout the training process. Following the &quot;later-is-better&quot; principle, FedABC adaptively adjusts the client selection threshold, encouraging greater participation in later training stages. Extensive simulations on CIFAR-10 demonstrate that FedABC significantly outperforms existing approaches in model accuracy and client participation efficiency, achieving comparable performance with 32% fewer clients than the classical FL algorithm FedAvg, and 3.5% higher accuracy with 2% fewer clients than the state-of-the-art. This work marks a step toward deploying FL in heterogeneous, resource-constrained environments, thereby supporting native AI capabilities in 6G networks.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.20871v2</guid>
   <category>cs.NI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Wenxuan Ye, Xueli An, Junfan Wang, Xueqiang Yan, Georg Carle</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Blockchain-Enabled Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06406</link>
   <description>Blockchain-enabled federated learning (BCFL) addresses fundamental challenges of trust, privacy, and coordination in collaborative AI systems. This chapter provides comprehensive architectural analysis of BCFL systems through a systematic four-dimensional taxonomy examining coordination structures, consensus mechanisms, storage architectures, and trust models. We analyze design patterns from blockchain-verified centralized coordination to fully decentralized peer-to-peer networks, evaluating trade-offs in scalability, security, and performance. Through detailed examination of consensus mechanisms designed for federated learning contexts, including Proof of Quality and Proof of Federated Learning, we demonstrate how computational work can be repurposed from arbitrary cryptographic puzzles to productive machine learning tasks. The chapter addresses critical storage challenges by examining multi-tier architectures that balance blockchain's transaction constraints with neural networks' large parameter requirements while maintaining cryptographic integrity. A technical case study of the TrustMesh framework illustrates practical implementation considerations in BCFL systems through distributed image classification training, demonstrating effective collaborative learning across IoT devices with highly non-IID data distributions while maintaining complete transparency and fault tolerance. Analysis of real-world deployments across healthcare consortiums, financial services, and IoT security applications validates the practical viability of BCFL systems, achieving performance comparable to centralized approaches while providing enhanced security guarantees and enabling new models of trustless collaborative intelligence.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.06406v3</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Murtaza Rangwala, KR Venugopal, Rajkumar Buyya</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Flexible Personalized Split Federated Learning for On-Device Fine-Tuning of Foundation Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10349</link>
   <description>Fine-tuning foundation models is critical for superior performance on personalized downstream tasks, compared to using pre-trained models. Collaborative learning can leverage local clients' datasets for fine-tuning, but limited client data and heterogeneous data distributions hinder effective collaboration. To address the challenge, we propose a flexible personalized federated learning paradigm that enables clients to engage in collaborative learning while maintaining personalized objectives. Given the limited and heterogeneous computational resources available on clients, we introduce \textbf{flexible personalized split federated learning (FlexP-SFL)}. Based on split learning, FlexP-SFL allows each client to train a portion of the model locally while offloading the rest to a server, according to resource constraints. Additionally, we propose an alignment strategy to improve personalized model performance on global data. Experimental results show that FlexP-SFL outperforms baseline models in personalized fine-tuning efficiency and final accuracy.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10349v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Tianjun Yuan, Jiaxiang Geng, Pengchao Han, Xianhao Chen, Bing Luo</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Blockchain-Enabled Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06406</link>
   <description>Blockchain-enabled federated learning (BCFL) addresses fundamental challenges of trust, privacy, and coordination in collaborative AI systems. This chapter provides comprehensive architectural analysis of BCFL systems through a systematic four-dimensional taxonomy examining coordination structures, consensus mechanisms, storage architectures, and trust models. We analyze design patterns from blockchain-verified centralized coordination to fully decentralized peer-to-peer networks, evaluating trade-offs in scalability, security, and performance. Through detailed examination of consensus mechanisms designed for federated learning contexts, including Proof of Quality and Proof of Federated Learning, we demonstrate how computational work can be repurposed from arbitrary cryptographic puzzles to productive machine learning tasks. The chapter addresses critical storage challenges by examining multi-tier architectures that balance blockchain's transaction constraints with neural networks' large parameter requirements while maintaining cryptographic integrity. A technical case study of the TrustMesh framework illustrates practical implementation considerations in BCFL systems through distributed image classification training, demonstrating effective collaborative learning across IoT devices with highly non-IID data distributions while maintaining complete transparency and fault tolerance. Analysis of real-world deployments across healthcare consortiums, financial services, and IoT security applications validates the practical viability of BCFL systems, achieving performance comparable to centralized approaches while providing enhanced security guarantees and enabling new models of trustless collaborative intelligence.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.06406v3</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Murtaza Rangwala, KR Venugopal, Rajkumar Buyya</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Time Series Generation on Feature and Temporally Misaligned Data</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21072</link>
   <description>Distributed time series data presents a challenge for federated learning, as clients often possess different feature sets and have misaligned time steps. Existing federated time series models are limited by the assumption of perfect temporal or feature alignment across clients. In this paper, we propose FedTDD, a novel federated time series diffusion model that jointly learns a synthesizer across clients. At the core of FedTDD is a novel data distillation and aggregation framework that reconciles the differences between clients by imputing the misaligned timesteps and features. In contrast to traditional federated learning, FedTDD learns the correlation across clients' time series through the exchange of local synthetic outputs instead of model parameters. A coordinator iteratively improves a global distiller network by leveraging shared knowledge from clients through the exchange of synthetic data. As the distiller becomes more refined over time, it subsequently enhances the quality of the clients' local feature estimates, allowing each client to then improve its local imputations for missing data using the latest, more accurate distiller. Experimental results on five datasets demonstrate FedTDD's effectiveness compared to centralized training, and the effectiveness of sharing synthetic outputs to transfer knowledge of local time series. Notably, FedTDD achieves 79.4% and 62.8% improvement over local training in Context-FID and Correlational scores.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.21072v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhi Wen Soi, Chenrui Fan, Aditya Shankar, Abele M\u{a}lan, Lydia Y. Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Robust Pipeline for Differentially Private Federated Learning on Imbalanced Clinical Data using SMOTETomek and FedProx</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10017</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) presents a groundbreaking approach for collaborative health research, allowing model training on decentralized data while safeguarding patient privacy. FL offers formal security guarantees when combined with Differential Privacy (DP). The integration of these technologies, however, introduces a significant trade-off between privacy and clinical utility, a challenge further complicated by the severe class imbalance often present in medical datasets. The research presented herein addresses these interconnected issues through a systematic, multi-stage analysis. An FL framework was implemented for cardiovascular risk prediction, where initial experiments showed that standard methods struggled with imbalanced data, resulting in a recall of zero. To overcome such a limitation, we first integrated the hybrid Synthetic Minority Over-sampling Technique with Tomek Links (SMOTETomek) at the client level, successfully developing a clinically useful model. Subsequently, the framework was optimized for non-IID data using a tuned FedProx algorithm. Our final results reveal a clear, non-linear trade-off between the privacy budget (epsilon) and model recall, with the optimized FedProx consistently out-performing standard FedAvg. An optimal operational region was identified on the privacy-utility frontier, where strong privacy guarantees (with epsilon 9.0) can be achieved while maintaining high clinical utility (recall greater than 77%). Ultimately, our study provides a practical methodological blueprint for creating effective, secure, and accurate diagnostic tools that can be applied to real-world, heterogeneous healthcare data.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10017v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Rodrigo Tertulino</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>CodeJudgeBench: Benchmarking LLM-as-a-Judge for Coding Tasks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10535</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) have significantly advanced the state-of-the-art in various coding tasks. Beyond directly answering user queries, LLMs can also serve as judges, assessing and comparing the quality of responses generated by other models. Such an evaluation capability is crucial both for benchmarking different LLMs and for improving response quality through response ranking. However, despite the growing adoption of the LLM-as-a-Judge paradigm, its effectiveness in coding scenarios remains underexplored due to the absence of dedicated benchmarks. To address this gap, we introduce CodeJudgeBench, a benchmark explicitly designed to evaluate the performance of LLM-as-a-Judge models across three critical coding tasks: code generation, code repair, and unit test generation. Through comprehensive benchmarking of 26 LLM-as-a-Judge models, we find that recent thinking models significantly outperform non-thinking models on our carefully designed code judging tasks. Notably, even relatively small thinking models, such as Qwen3-8B, can outperform specially trained LLM-as-a-Judge models up to 70B in size. Nevertheless, all models still exhibit significant randomness in their judgment of coding tasks. For pairwise judging tasks, simply changing the order in which responses are presented can substantially impact accuracy. In addition, when judging code and unit tests written by different LLMs, LLM-as-a-Judge models also show variance in performance. This sensitivity raises concerns about the reliability and consistency of LLM-as-a-Judge in coding scenarios. Lastly, we study optimal prompting strategies for LLM-as-a-Judge. We find that using pair-wise comparison outperforms scalar point-wise judging. Furthermore, retaining comments and reasoning in the full, unprocessed LLM response leads to improved judge performance.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10535v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hongchao Jiang, Yiming Chen, Yushi Cao, Hung-yi Lee, Robby T. Tan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedCoT: Communication-Efficient Federated Reasoning Enhancement for Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10020</link>
   <description>Efficiently enhancing the reasoning capabilities of large language models (LLMs) in federated learning environments remains challenging, particularly when balancing performance gains with strict computational, communication, and privacy constraints. This challenge is especially acute in healthcare, where decisions-spanning clinical, operational, and patient-facing contexts-demand not only accurate outputs but also interpretable, traceable rationales to ensure safety, accountability, and regulatory compliance. Conventional federated tuning approaches on LLM fail to address this need: they optimize primarily for answer correctness while neglecting rationale quality, leaving CoT capabilities dependent on models' innate pre-training abilities. Moreover, existing methods for improving rationales typically rely on privacy-violating knowledge distillation from centralized models. Additionally, the communication overhead in traditional federated fine-tuning on LLMs remains substantial. We addresses this gap by proposing FedCoT, a novel framework specifically designed to enhance reasoning in federated settings. FedCoT leverages a lightweight chain-of-thought enhancement mechanism: local models generate multiple reasoning paths, and a compact discriminator dynamically selects the most promising one. This approach improves reasoning accuracy and robustness while providing valuable interpretability, which is particularly critical for medical applications. To manage client heterogeneity efficiently, we adopt an improved aggregation approach building upon advanced LoRA module stacking, incorporating client classifier-awareness to achieve noise-free aggregation across diverse clients. Comprehensive experiments on medical reasoning tasks demonstrate that FedCoT significantly boosts client-side reasoning performance under stringent resource budgets while fully preserving data privacy.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10020v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chuan Li, Qianyi Zhao, Fengran Mo, Cen Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Reflect then Learn: Active Prompting for Information Extraction Guided by Introspective Confusion</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10036</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) show remarkable potential for few-shot information extraction (IE), yet their performance is highly sensitive to the choice of in-context examples. Conventional selection strategies often fail to provide informative guidance, as they overlook a key source of model fallibility: confusion stemming not just from semantic content, but also from the generation of well-structured formats required by IE tasks. To address this, we introduce Active Prompting for Information Extraction (APIE), a novel active prompting framework guided by a principle we term introspective confusion. Our method empowers an LLM to assess its own confusion through a dual-component uncertainty metric that uniquely quantifies both Format Uncertainty (difficulty in generating correct syntax) and Content Uncertainty (inconsistency in extracted semantics). By ranking unlabeled data with this comprehensive score, our framework actively selects the most challenging and informative samples to serve as few-shot exemplars. Extensive experiments on four benchmarks show that our approach consistently outperforms strong baselines, yielding significant improvements in both extraction accuracy and robustness. Our work highlights the critical importance of a fine-grained, dual-level view of model uncertainty when it comes to building effective and reliable structured generation systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10036v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Dong Zhao, Yadong Wang, Xiang Chen, Chenxi Wang, Hongliang Dai, Chuanxing Geng, Shengzhong Zhang, Shaoyuan Li, Sheng-Jun Huang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>SSRL: Self-Search Reinforcement Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10874</link>
   <description>We investigate the potential of large language models (LLMs) to serve as efficient simulators for agentic search tasks in reinforcement learning (RL), thereby reducing dependence on costly interactions with external search engines. To this end, we first quantify the intrinsic search capability of LLMs via structured prompting and repeated sampling, which we term Self-Search. Our results reveal that LLMs exhibit strong scaling behavior with respect to the inference budget, achieving high pass@k on question-answering benchmarks, including the challenging BrowseComp task. Building on these observations, we introduce Self-Search RL (SSRL), which enhances LLMs' Self-Search capability through format-based and rule-based rewards. SSRL enables models to iteratively refine their knowledge utilization internally, without requiring access to external tools. Empirical evaluations demonstrate that SSRL-trained policy models provide a cost-effective and stable environment for search-driven RL training, reducing reliance on external search engines and facilitating robust sim-to-real transfer. We draw the following conclusions: 1) LLMs possess world knowledge that can be effectively elicited to achieve high performance; 2) SSRL demonstrates the potential of leveraging internal knowledge to reduce hallucination; 3) SSRL-trained models integrate seamlessly with external search engines without additional effort. Our findings highlight the potential of LLMs to support more scalable RL agent training.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10874v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yuchen Fan, Kaiyan Zhang, Heng Zhou, Yuxin Zuo, Yanxu Chen, Yu Fu, Xinwei Long, Xuekai Zhu, Che Jiang, Yuchen Zhang, Li Kang, Gang Chen, Cheng Huang, Zhizhou He, Bingning Wang, Lei Bai, Ning Ding, Bowen Zhou</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Reverse Physician-AI Relationship: Full-process Clinical Diagnosis Driven by a Large Language Model</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10492</link>
   <description>Full-process clinical diagnosis in the real world encompasses the entire diagnostic workflow that begins with only an ambiguous chief complaint. While artificial intelligence (AI), particularly large language models (LLMs), is transforming clinical diagnosis, its role remains largely as an assistant to physicians. This AI-assisted working pattern makes AI can only answer specific medical questions at certain parts within the diagnostic process, but lack the ability to drive the entire diagnostic process starting from an ambiguous complaint, which still relies heavily on human physicians. This gap limits AI's ability to fully reduce physicians' workload and enhance diagnostic efficiency. To address this, we propose a paradigm shift that reverses the relationship between physicians and AI: repositioning AI as the primary director, with physicians serving as its assistants. So we present DxDirector-7B, an LLM endowed with advanced deep thinking capabilities, enabling it to drive the full-process diagnosis with minimal physician involvement. Furthermore, DxDirector-7B establishes a robust accountability framework for misdiagnoses, delineating responsibility between AI and human physicians. In evaluations across rare, complex, and real-world cases under full-process diagnosis setting, DxDirector-7B not only achieves significant superior diagnostic accuracy but also substantially reduces physician workload than state-of-the-art medical LLMs as well as general-purpose LLMs. Fine-grained analyses across multiple clinical departments and tasks validate its efficacy, with expert evaluations indicating its potential to serve as a viable substitute for medical specialists. These findings mark a new era where AI, traditionally a physicians' assistant, now drives the entire diagnostic process to drastically reduce physicians' workload, indicating an efficient and accurate diagnostic solution.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10492v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CE</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shicheng Xu, Xin Huang, Zihao Wei, Liang Pang, Huawei Shen, Xueqi Cheng</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>CodeJudgeBench: Benchmarking LLM-as-a-Judge for Coding Tasks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10535</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) have significantly advanced the state-of-the-art in various coding tasks. Beyond directly answering user queries, LLMs can also serve as judges, assessing and comparing the quality of responses generated by other models. Such an evaluation capability is crucial both for benchmarking different LLMs and for improving response quality through response ranking. However, despite the growing adoption of the LLM-as-a-Judge paradigm, its effectiveness in coding scenarios remains underexplored due to the absence of dedicated benchmarks. To address this gap, we introduce CodeJudgeBench, a benchmark explicitly designed to evaluate the performance of LLM-as-a-Judge models across three critical coding tasks: code generation, code repair, and unit test generation. Through comprehensive benchmarking of 26 LLM-as-a-Judge models, we find that recent thinking models significantly outperform non-thinking models on our carefully designed code judging tasks. Notably, even relatively small thinking models, such as Qwen3-8B, can outperform specially trained LLM-as-a-Judge models up to 70B in size. Nevertheless, all models still exhibit significant randomness in their judgment of coding tasks. For pairwise judging tasks, simply changing the order in which responses are presented can substantially impact accuracy. In addition, when judging code and unit tests written by different LLMs, LLM-as-a-Judge models also show variance in performance. This sensitivity raises concerns about the reliability and consistency of LLM-as-a-Judge in coding scenarios. Lastly, we study optimal prompting strategies for LLM-as-a-Judge. We find that using pair-wise comparison outperforms scalar point-wise judging. Furthermore, retaining comments and reasoning in the full, unprocessed LLM response leads to improved judge performance.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10535v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hongchao Jiang, Yiming Chen, Yushi Cao, Hung-yi Lee, Robby T. Tan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>TextQuests: How Good are LLMs at Text-Based Video Games?</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23701</link>
   <description>Evaluating AI agents within complex, interactive environments that mirror real-world challenges is critical for understanding their practical capabilities. While existing agent benchmarks effectively assess skills like tool use or performance on structured tasks, they often do not fully capture an agent's ability to operate autonomously in exploratory environments that demand sustained, self-directed reasoning over a long and growing context. To enable a more accurate assessment of AI agents in challenging exploratory environments, we introduce TextQuests, a benchmark based on the Infocom suite of interactive fiction games. These text-based adventures, which can take human players over 30 hours and require hundreds of precise actions to solve, serve as an effective proxy for evaluating AI agents on focused, stateful tasks. The benchmark is specifically designed to assess an LLM agent's capacity for self-contained problem-solving by precluding the use of external tools, thereby focusing on intrinsic long-context reasoning capabilities in an exploratory environment characterized by the need for trial-and-error learning and sustained problem-solving within a single interactive session. We release TextQuests at https://textquests.ai.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.23701v3</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Long Phan, Mantas Mazeika, Andy Zou, Dan Hendrycks</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>HumanSense: From Multimodal Perception to Empathetic Context-Aware Responses through Reasoning MLLMs</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10576</link>
   <description>While Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) show immense promise for achieving truly human-like interactions, progress is hindered by the lack of fine-grained evaluation frameworks for human-centered scenarios, encompassing both the understanding of complex human intentions and the provision of empathetic, context-aware responses. Here we introduce HumanSense, a comprehensive benchmark designed to evaluate the human-centered perception and interaction capabilities of MLLMs, with a particular focus on deep understanding of extended multimodal contexts and the formulation of rational feedback. Our evaluation reveals that leading MLLMs still have considerable room for improvement, particularly for advanced interaction-oriented tasks. Supplementing visual input with audio and text information yields substantial improvements, and Omni-modal models show advantages on these tasks. Furthermore, we argue that appropriate feedback stems from a contextual analysis of the interlocutor's needs and emotions, with reasoning ability serving as the key to unlocking it. Accordingly, we employ a multi-stage, modality-progressive reinforcement learning to enhance the reasoning abilities of an Omni model, achieving substantial gains on evaluation results. Additionally, we observe that successful reasoning processes exhibit highly consistent thought patterns. By designing corresponding prompts, we also enhance the performance of non-reasoning models in a training-free manner. Project page: \textcolor{brightpink}https://digital-avatar.github.io/ai/HumanSense/</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10576v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zheng Qin, Ruobing Zheng, Yabing Wang, Tianqi Li, Yi Yuan, Jingdong Chen, Le Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>EgoCross: Benchmarking Multimodal Large Language Models for Cross-Domain Egocentric Video Question Answering</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10729</link>
   <description>Recent advances in Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have significantly pushed the frontier of egocentric video question answering (EgocentricQA). However, existing benchmarks and studies are mainly limited to common daily activities such as cooking and cleaning. In contrast, real-world deployment inevitably encounters domain shifts, where target domains differ substantially in both visual style and semantic content. To bridge this gap, we introduce \textbf{EgoCross}, a comprehensive benchmark designed to evaluate the cross-domain generalization of MLLMs in EgocentricQA. EgoCross covers four diverse and challenging domains, including surgery, industry, extreme sports, and animal perspective, representing realistic and high-impact application scenarios. It comprises approximately 1,000 QA pairs across 798 video clips, spanning four key QA tasks: prediction, recognition, localization, and counting. Each QA pair provides both OpenQA and CloseQA formats to support fine-grained evaluation. Extensive experiments show that most existing MLLMs, whether general-purpose or egocentric-specialized, struggle to generalize to domains beyond daily life, highlighting the limitations of current models. Furthermore, we conduct several pilot studies, \eg, fine-tuning and reinforcement learning, to explore potential improvements. We hope EgoCross and our accompanying analysis will serve as a foundation for advancing domain-adaptive, robust egocentric video understanding. Data and codes will be released at: \href{https://github.com/MyUniverse0726/EgoCross}{https://github.com/MyUniverse0726/EgoCross.}</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10729v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yanjun Li, Yuqian Fu, Tianwen Qian, Qi'ao Xu, Silong Dai, Danda Pani Paudel, Luc Van Gool, Xiaoling Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Generalizable Federated Learning using Client Adaptive Focal Modulation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10840</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) has proven essential for privacy-preserving, collaborative training across distributed clients. Our prior work, TransFed, introduced a robust transformer-based FL framework that leverages a learn-to-adapt hypernetwork to generate personalized focal modulation layers per client, outperforming traditional methods in non-IID and cross-domain settings. In this extended version, we propose AdaptFED, where we deepen the investigation of focal modulation in generalizable FL by incorporating: (1) a refined adaptation strategy that integrates task-aware client embeddings to personalize modulation dynamics further, (2) enhanced theoretical bounds on adaptation performance, and (3) broader empirical validation across additional modalities, including time-series and multilingual data. We also introduce an efficient variant of TransFed that reduces server-client communication overhead via low-rank hypernetwork conditioning, enabling scalable deployment in resource-constrained environments. Extensive experiments on eight diverse datasets reaffirm the superiority of our method over state-of-the-art baselines, particularly in source-free and cross-task federated setups. Our findings not only extend the capabilities of focal modulation in FL but also pave the way for more adaptive, scalable, and generalizable transformer-based federated systems. The code is available at http://github.com/Tajamul21/TransFed</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10840v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Tajamul Ashraf, Iqra Altaf Gillani</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Improving Learning of New Diseases through Knowledge-Enhanced Initialization for Federated Adapter Tuning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10299</link>
   <description>In healthcare, federated learning (FL) is a widely adopted framework that enables privacy-preserving collaboration among medical institutions. With large foundation models (FMs) demonstrating impressive capabilities, using FMs in FL through cost-efficient adapter tuning has become a popular approach. Given the rapidly evolving healthcare environment, it is crucial for individual clients to quickly adapt to new tasks or diseases by tuning adapters while drawing upon past experiences. In this work, we introduce Federated Knowledge-Enhanced Initialization (FedKEI), a novel framework that leverages cross-client and cross-task transfer from past knowledge to generate informed initializations for learning new tasks with adapters. FedKEI begins with a global clustering process at the server to generalize knowledge across tasks, followed by the optimization of aggregation weights across clusters (inter-cluster weights) and within each cluster (intra-cluster weights) to personalize knowledge transfer for each new task. To facilitate more effective learning of the inter- and intra-cluster weights, we adopt a bi-level optimization scheme that collaboratively learns the global intra-cluster weights across clients and optimizes the local inter-cluster weights toward each client's task objective. Extensive experiments on three benchmark datasets of different modalities, including dermatology, chest X-rays, and retinal OCT, demonstrate FedKEI's advantage in adapting to new diseases compared to state-of-the-art methods.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10299v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Danni Peng, Yuan Wang, Kangning Cai, Peiyan Ning, Jiming Xu, Yong Liu, Rick Siow Mong Goh, Qingsong Wei, Huazhu Fu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Reverse Physician-AI Relationship: Full-process Clinical Diagnosis Driven by a Large Language Model</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10492</link>
   <description>Full-process clinical diagnosis in the real world encompasses the entire diagnostic workflow that begins with only an ambiguous chief complaint. While artificial intelligence (AI), particularly large language models (LLMs), is transforming clinical diagnosis, its role remains largely as an assistant to physicians. This AI-assisted working pattern makes AI can only answer specific medical questions at certain parts within the diagnostic process, but lack the ability to drive the entire diagnostic process starting from an ambiguous complaint, which still relies heavily on human physicians. This gap limits AI's ability to fully reduce physicians' workload and enhance diagnostic efficiency. To address this, we propose a paradigm shift that reverses the relationship between physicians and AI: repositioning AI as the primary director, with physicians serving as its assistants. So we present DxDirector-7B, an LLM endowed with advanced deep thinking capabilities, enabling it to drive the full-process diagnosis with minimal physician involvement. Furthermore, DxDirector-7B establishes a robust accountability framework for misdiagnoses, delineating responsibility between AI and human physicians. In evaluations across rare, complex, and real-world cases under full-process diagnosis setting, DxDirector-7B not only achieves significant superior diagnostic accuracy but also substantially reduces physician workload than state-of-the-art medical LLMs as well as general-purpose LLMs. Fine-grained analyses across multiple clinical departments and tasks validate its efficacy, with expert evaluations indicating its potential to serve as a viable substitute for medical specialists. These findings mark a new era where AI, traditionally a physicians' assistant, now drives the entire diagnostic process to drastically reduce physicians' workload, indicating an efficient and accurate diagnostic solution.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10492v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CE</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shicheng Xu, Xin Huang, Zihao Wei, Liang Pang, Huawei Shen, Xueqi Cheng</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Reverse Physician-AI Relationship: Full-process Clinical Diagnosis Driven by a Large Language Model</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10492</link>
   <description>Full-process clinical diagnosis in the real world encompasses the entire diagnostic workflow that begins with only an ambiguous chief complaint. While artificial intelligence (AI), particularly large language models (LLMs), is transforming clinical diagnosis, its role remains largely as an assistant to physicians. This AI-assisted working pattern makes AI can only answer specific medical questions at certain parts within the diagnostic process, but lack the ability to drive the entire diagnostic process starting from an ambiguous complaint, which still relies heavily on human physicians. This gap limits AI's ability to fully reduce physicians' workload and enhance diagnostic efficiency. To address this, we propose a paradigm shift that reverses the relationship between physicians and AI: repositioning AI as the primary director, with physicians serving as its assistants. So we present DxDirector-7B, an LLM endowed with advanced deep thinking capabilities, enabling it to drive the full-process diagnosis with minimal physician involvement. Furthermore, DxDirector-7B establishes a robust accountability framework for misdiagnoses, delineating responsibility between AI and human physicians. In evaluations across rare, complex, and real-world cases under full-process diagnosis setting, DxDirector-7B not only achieves significant superior diagnostic accuracy but also substantially reduces physician workload than state-of-the-art medical LLMs as well as general-purpose LLMs. Fine-grained analyses across multiple clinical departments and tasks validate its efficacy, with expert evaluations indicating its potential to serve as a viable substitute for medical specialists. These findings mark a new era where AI, traditionally a physicians' assistant, now drives the entire diagnostic process to drastically reduce physicians' workload, indicating an efficient and accurate diagnostic solution.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10492v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CE</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shicheng Xu, Xin Huang, Zihao Wei, Liang Pang, Huawei Shen, Xueqi Cheng</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Robust Pipeline for Differentially Private Federated Learning on Imbalanced Clinical Data using SMOTETomek and FedProx</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10017</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) presents a groundbreaking approach for collaborative health research, allowing model training on decentralized data while safeguarding patient privacy. FL offers formal security guarantees when combined with Differential Privacy (DP). The integration of these technologies, however, introduces a significant trade-off between privacy and clinical utility, a challenge further complicated by the severe class imbalance often present in medical datasets. The research presented herein addresses these interconnected issues through a systematic, multi-stage analysis. An FL framework was implemented for cardiovascular risk prediction, where initial experiments showed that standard methods struggled with imbalanced data, resulting in a recall of zero. To overcome such a limitation, we first integrated the hybrid Synthetic Minority Over-sampling Technique with Tomek Links (SMOTETomek) at the client level, successfully developing a clinically useful model. Subsequently, the framework was optimized for non-IID data using a tuned FedProx algorithm. Our final results reveal a clear, non-linear trade-off between the privacy budget (epsilon) and model recall, with the optimized FedProx consistently out-performing standard FedAvg. An optimal operational region was identified on the privacy-utility frontier, where strong privacy guarantees (with epsilon 9.0) can be achieved while maintaining high clinical utility (recall greater than 77%). Ultimately, our study provides a practical methodological blueprint for creating effective, secure, and accurate diagnostic tools that can be applied to real-world, heterogeneous healthcare data.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10017v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Rodrigo Tertulino</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedCoT: Communication-Efficient Federated Reasoning Enhancement for Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10020</link>
   <description>Efficiently enhancing the reasoning capabilities of large language models (LLMs) in federated learning environments remains challenging, particularly when balancing performance gains with strict computational, communication, and privacy constraints. This challenge is especially acute in healthcare, where decisions-spanning clinical, operational, and patient-facing contexts-demand not only accurate outputs but also interpretable, traceable rationales to ensure safety, accountability, and regulatory compliance. Conventional federated tuning approaches on LLM fail to address this need: they optimize primarily for answer correctness while neglecting rationale quality, leaving CoT capabilities dependent on models' innate pre-training abilities. Moreover, existing methods for improving rationales typically rely on privacy-violating knowledge distillation from centralized models. Additionally, the communication overhead in traditional federated fine-tuning on LLMs remains substantial. We addresses this gap by proposing FedCoT, a novel framework specifically designed to enhance reasoning in federated settings. FedCoT leverages a lightweight chain-of-thought enhancement mechanism: local models generate multiple reasoning paths, and a compact discriminator dynamically selects the most promising one. This approach improves reasoning accuracy and robustness while providing valuable interpretability, which is particularly critical for medical applications. To manage client heterogeneity efficiently, we adopt an improved aggregation approach building upon advanced LoRA module stacking, incorporating client classifier-awareness to achieve noise-free aggregation across diverse clients. Comprehensive experiments on medical reasoning tasks demonstrate that FedCoT significantly boosts client-side reasoning performance under stringent resource budgets while fully preserving data privacy.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10020v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chuan Li, Qianyi Zhao, Fengran Mo, Cen Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Reflect then Learn: Active Prompting for Information Extraction Guided by Introspective Confusion</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10036</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) show remarkable potential for few-shot information extraction (IE), yet their performance is highly sensitive to the choice of in-context examples. Conventional selection strategies often fail to provide informative guidance, as they overlook a key source of model fallibility: confusion stemming not just from semantic content, but also from the generation of well-structured formats required by IE tasks. To address this, we introduce Active Prompting for Information Extraction (APIE), a novel active prompting framework guided by a principle we term introspective confusion. Our method empowers an LLM to assess its own confusion through a dual-component uncertainty metric that uniquely quantifies both Format Uncertainty (difficulty in generating correct syntax) and Content Uncertainty (inconsistency in extracted semantics). By ranking unlabeled data with this comprehensive score, our framework actively selects the most challenging and informative samples to serve as few-shot exemplars. Extensive experiments on four benchmarks show that our approach consistently outperforms strong baselines, yielding significant improvements in both extraction accuracy and robustness. Our work highlights the critical importance of a fine-grained, dual-level view of model uncertainty when it comes to building effective and reliable structured generation systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10036v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Dong Zhao, Yadong Wang, Xiang Chen, Chenxi Wang, Hongliang Dai, Chuanxing Geng, Shengzhong Zhang, Shaoyuan Li, Sheng-Jun Huang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FIDELIS: Blockchain-Enabled Protection Against Poisoning Attacks in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10042</link>
   <description>Federated learning enhances traditional deep learning by enabling the joint training of a model with the use of IoT device's private data. It ensures privacy for clients, but is susceptible to data poisoning attacks during training that degrade model performance and integrity. Current poisoning detection methods in federated learning lack a standardized detection method or take significant liberties with trust. In this paper, we present \Sys, a novel blockchain-enabled poison detection framework in federated learning. The framework decentralizes the role of the global server across participating clients. We introduce a judge model used to detect data poisoning in model updates. The judge model is produced by each client and verified to reach consensus on a single judge model. We implement our solution to show \Sys is robust against data poisoning attacks and the creation of our judge model is scalable.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10042v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jane Carney, Kushal Upreti, Gaby G. Dagher, Tim Andersen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Vision-Language Pre-training Model-Guided Approach for Mitigating Backdoor Attacks in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10315</link>
   <description>Existing backdoor defense methods in Federated Learning (FL) rely on the assumption of homogeneous client data distributions or the availability of a clean serve dataset, which limits the practicality and effectiveness. Defending against backdoor attacks under heterogeneous client data distributions while preserving model performance remains a significant challenge. In this paper, we propose a FL backdoor defense framework named CLIP-Fed, which leverages the zero-shot learning capabilities of vision-language pre-training models. By integrating both pre-aggregation and post-aggregation defense strategies, CLIP-Fed overcomes the limitations of Non-IID imposed on defense effectiveness. To address privacy concerns and enhance the coverage of the dataset against diverse triggers, we construct and augment the server dataset using the multimodal large language model and frequency analysis without any client samples. To address class prototype deviations caused by backdoor samples and eliminate the correlation between trigger patterns and target labels, CLIP-Fed aligns the knowledge of the global model and CLIP on the augmented dataset using prototype contrastive loss and Kullback-Leibler divergence. Extensive experiments on representative datasets validate the effectiveness of CLIP-Fed. Compared to state-of-the-art methods, CLIP-Fed achieves an average reduction in ASR, i.e., 2.03\% on CIFAR-10 and 1.35\% on CIFAR-10-LT, while improving average MA by 7.92\% and 0.48\%, respectively.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10315v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Keke Gai, Dongjue Wang, Jing Yu, Liehuang Zhu, Qi Wu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>EgoCross: Benchmarking Multimodal Large Language Models for Cross-Domain Egocentric Video Question Answering</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10729</link>
   <description>Recent advances in Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have significantly pushed the frontier of egocentric video question answering (EgocentricQA). However, existing benchmarks and studies are mainly limited to common daily activities such as cooking and cleaning. In contrast, real-world deployment inevitably encounters domain shifts, where target domains differ substantially in both visual style and semantic content. To bridge this gap, we introduce \textbf{EgoCross}, a comprehensive benchmark designed to evaluate the cross-domain generalization of MLLMs in EgocentricQA. EgoCross covers four diverse and challenging domains, including surgery, industry, extreme sports, and animal perspective, representing realistic and high-impact application scenarios. It comprises approximately 1,000 QA pairs across 798 video clips, spanning four key QA tasks: prediction, recognition, localization, and counting. Each QA pair provides both OpenQA and CloseQA formats to support fine-grained evaluation. Extensive experiments show that most existing MLLMs, whether general-purpose or egocentric-specialized, struggle to generalize to domains beyond daily life, highlighting the limitations of current models. Furthermore, we conduct several pilot studies, \eg, fine-tuning and reinforcement learning, to explore potential improvements. We hope EgoCross and our accompanying analysis will serve as a foundation for advancing domain-adaptive, robust egocentric video understanding. Data and codes will be released at: \href{https://github.com/MyUniverse0726/EgoCross}{https://github.com/MyUniverse0726/EgoCross.}</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10729v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yanjun Li, Yuqian Fu, Tianwen Qian, Qi'ao Xu, Silong Dai, Danda Pani Paudel, Luc Van Gool, Xiaoling Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>APFL: Analytic Personalized Federated Learning via Dual-Stream Least Squares</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10732</link>
   <description>Personalized Federated Learning (PFL) has presented a significant challenge to deliver personalized models to individual clients through collaborative training. Existing PFL methods are often vulnerable to non-IID data, which severely hinders collective generalization and then compromises the subsequent personalization efforts. In this paper, to address this non-IID issue in PFL, we propose an Analytic Personalized Federated Learning (APFL) approach via dual-stream least squares. In our APFL, we use a foundation model as a frozen backbone for feature extraction. Subsequent to the feature extractor, we develop dual-stream analytic models to achieve both collective generalization and individual personalization. Specifically, our APFL incorporates a shared primary stream for global generalization across all clients, and a dedicated refinement stream for local personalization of each individual client. The analytical solutions of our APFL enable its ideal property of heterogeneity invariance, theoretically meaning that each personalized model remains identical regardless of how heterogeneous the data are distributed across all other clients. Empirical results across various datasets also validate the superiority of our APFL over state-of-the-art baselines, with advantages of at least 1.10%-15.45% in accuracy.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.10732v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kejia Fan, Jianheng Tang, Zhirui Yang, Feijiang Han, Jiaxu Li, Run He, Yajiang Huang, Anfeng Liu, Houbing Herbert Song, Yunhuai Liu, Huiping Zhuang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Cross-Training Learners for Robust Generalization under Data Heterogeneity</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20046</link>
   <description>Federated learning benefits from cross-training strategies, which enables models to train on data from distinct sources to improve generalization capability. However, due to inherent differences in data distributions, the optimization goals of local models remain misaligned, and this mismatch continues to manifest as feature space heterogeneity even after cross-training. We argue that knowledge distillation from the personalized view preserves client-specific characteristics and expands the local knowledge base, while distillation from the global view provides consistent semantic anchors that facilitate feature alignment across clients. To achieve this goal, this paper presents a cross-training scheme, termed FedCT, includes three main modules, where the consistency-aware knowledge broadcasting module aims to optimize model assignment strategies, which enhances collaborative advantages between clients and achieves an efficient federated learning process. The multi-view knowledge-guided representation learning module leverages fused prototypical knowledge from both global and local views to enhance the preservation of local knowledge before and after model exchange, as well as to ensure consistency between local and global knowledge. The mixup-based feature augmentation module aggregates rich information to further increase the diversity of feature spaces, which enables the model to better discriminate complex samples. Extensive experiments were conducted on four datasets in terms of performance comparison, ablation study, in-depth analysis and case study. The results demonstrated that FedCT alleviates knowledge forgetting from both local and global views, which enables it outperform state-of-the-art methods.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2405.20046v3</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhuang Qi, Lei Meng, Ruohan Zhang, Yu Wang, Xin Qi, Xiangxu Meng, Han Yu, Qiang Yang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>TextQuests: How Good are LLMs at Text-Based Video Games?</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23701</link>
   <description>Evaluating AI agents within complex, interactive environments that mirror real-world challenges is critical for understanding their practical capabilities. While existing agent benchmarks effectively assess skills like tool use or performance on structured tasks, they often do not fully capture an agent's ability to operate autonomously in exploratory environments that demand sustained, self-directed reasoning over a long and growing context. To enable a more accurate assessment of AI agents in challenging exploratory environments, we introduce TextQuests, a benchmark based on the Infocom suite of interactive fiction games. These text-based adventures, which can take human players over 30 hours and require hundreds of precise actions to solve, serve as an effective proxy for evaluating AI agents on focused, stateful tasks. The benchmark is specifically designed to assess an LLM agent's capacity for self-contained problem-solving by precluding the use of external tools, thereby focusing on intrinsic long-context reasoning capabilities in an exploratory environment characterized by the need for trial-and-error learning and sustained problem-solving within a single interactive session. We release TextQuests at https://textquests.ai.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.23701v3</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Long Phan, Mantas Mazeika, Andy Zou, Dan Hendrycks</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>CodeJudgeBench: Benchmarking LLM-as-a-Judge for Coding Tasks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10535</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) have significantly advanced the state-of-the-art in various coding tasks. Beyond directly answering user queries, LLMs can also serve as judges, assessing and comparing the quality of responses generated by other models. Such an evaluation capability is crucial both for benchmarking different LLMs and for improving response quality through response ranking. However, despite the growing adoption of the LLM-as-a-Judge paradigm, its effectiveness in coding scenarios remains underexplored due to the absence of dedicated benchmarks. To address this gap, we introduce CodeJudgeBench, a benchmark explicitly designed to evaluate the performance of LLM-as-a-Judge models across three critical coding tasks: code generation, code repair, and unit test generation. Through comprehensive benchmarking of 26 LLM-as-a-Judge models, we find that recent thinking models significantly outperform non-thinking models on our carefully designed code judging tasks. Notably, even relatively small thinking models, such as Qwen3-8B, can outperform specially trained LLM-as-a-Judge models up to 70B in size. Nevertheless, all models still exhibit significant randomness in their judgment of coding tasks. For pairwise judging tasks, simply changing the order in which responses are presented can substantially impact accuracy. In addition, when judging code and unit tests written by different LLMs, LLM-as-a-Judge models also show variance in performance. This sensitivity raises concerns about the reliability and consistency of LLM-as-a-Judge in coding scenarios. Lastly, we study optimal prompting strategies for LLM-as-a-Judge. We find that using pair-wise comparison outperforms scalar point-wise judging. Furthermore, retaining comments and reasoning in the full, unprocessed LLM response leads to improved judge performance.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10535v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hongchao Jiang, Yiming Chen, Yushi Cao, Hung-yi Lee, Robby T. Tan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Decentralized Weather Forecasting via Distributed Machine Learning and Blockchain-Based Model Validation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09299</link>
   <description>Weather forecasting plays a vital role in disaster preparedness, agriculture, and resource management, yet current centralized forecasting systems are increasingly strained by security vulnerabilities, limited scalability, and susceptibility to single points of failure. To address these challenges, we propose a decentralized weather forecasting framework that integrates Federated Learning (FL) with blockchain technology. FL enables collaborative model training without exposing sensitive local data; this approach enhances privacy and reduces data transfer overhead. Meanwhile, the Ethereum blockchain ensures transparent and dependable verification of model updates. To further enhance the system's security, we introduce a reputation-based voting mechanism that assesses the trustworthiness of submitted models while utilizing the Interplanetary File System (IPFS) for efficient off-chain storage. Experimental results demonstrate that our approach not only improves forecasting accuracy but also enhances system resilience and scalability, making it a viable candidate for deployment in real-world, security-critical environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.09299v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Rilwan Umar, Aydin Abadi, Basil Aldali, Benito Vincent, Elliot A. J. Hurley, Hotoon Aljazaeri, Jamie Hedley-Cook, Jamie-Lee Bell, Lambert Uwuigbusun, Mujeeb Ahmed, Shishir Nagaraja, Suleiman Sabo, Weaam Alrbeiqi</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
