<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 04:15:57 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 04:15:57 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>When to Reason: Semantic Router for vLLM</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08731</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) demonstrate substantial accuracy gains when augmented with reasoning modes such as chain-of-thought and inference-time scaling. However, reasoning also incurs significant costs in inference latency and token usage, with environmental and financial impacts, which are unnecessary for many simple prompts. We present a semantic router that classifies queries based on their reasoning requirements and selectively applies reasoning only when beneficial. Our approach achieves a 10.2 percentage point improvement in accuracy on the MMLU-Pro benchmark while reducing response latency by 47.1% and token consumption by 48.5% compared to direct inference with vLLM. These results demonstrate that semantic routing offers an effective mechanism for striking a balance between accuracy and efficiency in open-source LLM serving systems</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.08731v1</guid>
   <category>cs.ET</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.SY</category>
   <category>eess.SY</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chen Wang, Xunzhuo Liu, Yuhan Liu, Yue Zhu, Xiangxi Mo, Junchen Jiang, Huamin Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>When to Reason: Semantic Router for vLLM</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08731</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) demonstrate substantial accuracy gains when augmented with reasoning modes such as chain-of-thought and inference-time scaling. However, reasoning also incurs significant costs in inference latency and token usage, with environmental and financial impacts, which are unnecessary for many simple prompts. We present a semantic router that classifies queries based on their reasoning requirements and selectively applies reasoning only when beneficial. Our approach achieves a 10.2 percentage point improvement in accuracy on the MMLU-Pro benchmark while reducing response latency by 47.1% and token consumption by 48.5% compared to direct inference with vLLM. These results demonstrate that semantic routing offers an effective mechanism for striking a balance between accuracy and efficiency in open-source LLM serving systems</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.08731v1</guid>
   <category>cs.ET</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.SY</category>
   <category>eess.SY</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chen Wang, Xunzhuo Liu, Yuhan Liu, Yue Zhu, Xiangxi Mo, Junchen Jiang, Huamin Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Site-Level Fine-Tuning with Progressive Layer Freezing: Towards Robust Prediction of Bronchopulmonary Dysplasia from Day-1 Chest Radiographs in Extremely Preterm Infants</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12269</link>
   <description>Bronchopulmonary dysplasia (BPD) is a chronic lung disease affecting 35% of extremely low birth weight infants. Defined by oxygen dependence at 36 weeks postmenstrual age, it causes lifelong respiratory complications. However, preventive interventions carry severe risks, including neurodevelopmental impairment, ventilator-induced lung injury, and systemic complications. Therefore, early BPD prognosis and prediction of BPD outcome is crucial to avoid unnecessary toxicity in low risk infants. Admission radiographs of extremely preterm infants are routinely acquired within 24h of life and could serve as a non-invasive prognostic tool. In this work, we developed and investigated a deep learning approach using chest X-rays from 163 extremely low-birth-weight infants ($\leq$32 weeks gestation, 401-999g) obtained within 24 hours of birth. We fine-tuned a ResNet-50 pretrained specifically on adult chest radiographs, employing progressive layer freezing with discriminative learning rates to prevent overfitting and evaluated a CutMix augmentation and linear probing. For moderate/severe BPD outcome prediction, our best performing model with progressive freezing, linear probing and CutMix achieved an AUROC of 0.78 $\pm$ 0.10, balanced accuracy of 0.69 $\pm$ 0.10, and an F1-score of 0.67 $\pm$ 0.11. In-domain pre-training significantly outperformed ImageNet initialization (p = 0.031) which confirms domain-specific pretraining to be important for BPD outcome prediction. Routine IRDS grades showed limited prognostic value (AUROC 0.57 $\pm$ 0.11), confirming the need of learned markers. Our approach demonstrates that domain-specific pretraining enables accurate BPD prediction from routine day-1 radiographs. Through progressive freezing and linear probing, the method remains computationally feasible for site-level implementation and future federated learning deployments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.12269v3</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sybelle Goedicke-Fritz (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Michelle Bous (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Annika Engel (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany), Matthias Flotho (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany, Helmholtz Institute for Pharmaceutical Research Saarland), Pascal Hirsch (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany), Hannah Wittig (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Dino Milanovic (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany), Dominik Mohr (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Mathias Kaspar (Digital Medicine, University Hospital of Augsburg, Augsburg, Germany), Sogand Nemat (Department of Radiology, and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital of Saarland, Homburg, Germany), Dorothea Kerner (Department of Radiology, and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital of Saarland, Homburg, Germany), Arno B\&quot;ucker (Department of Radiology, and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital of Saarland, Homburg, Germany), Andreas Keller (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany, Helmholtz Institute for Pharmaceutical Research Saarland, Pharma Science Hub), Sascha Meyer (Clinical Centre Karlsruhe, Franz-Lust Clinic for Paediatrics, Karlsruhe, Germany), Michael Zemlin (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Philipp Flotho (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany, Helmholtz Institute for Pharmaceutical Research Saarland)</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>UniLiP: Adapting CLIP for Unified Multimodal Understanding, Generation and Editing</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23278</link>
   <description>In this paper, we propose UniLIP, a unified framework that adapts CLIP for multimodal understanding, generation and editing. Although CLIP excels at understanding, it lacks reconstruction abilities required to be a unified visual encoder. However, previous CLIP-based unified methods fail to balance understanding and reconstruction, leading to semantic degradation or inconsistent reconstructions. In contrast, we introduce a novel two-stage training scheme with a self-distillation strategy that progressively endows CLIP with high-fidelity reconstruction abilities while preserving its original comprehension performance. For enhanced reasoning and consistency in generation and editing, we further develop a dual-condition architecture built upon the MetaQuery framework. Our architecture jointly utilizes multimodal hidden states for rich contextual details and learnable query embeddings to harness the powerful reasoning abilities of Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs). Leveraging advanced image representation and architectural design, UniLIP demonstrates superior instruction following and edit fidelity. With only 1B and 3B parameters, UniLIP can outperform larger unified models such as BAGEL (7B) and Uniworld-V1 (12B), achieving state-of-the-art performance of 0.90 on GenEval, 0.63 on WISE, and 3.94 on ImgEdit. These results demonstrate that UniLIP successfully expands the application of CLIP, establishing its continuous features to not only serve as the optimal choice for understanding tasks but also achieve highly competitive performance in generation and editing tasks. Code and models are available at https://github.com/nnnth/UniLIP.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.23278v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hao Tang, Chenwei Xie, Xiaoyi Bao, Tingyu Weng, Pandeng Li, Yun Zheng, Liwei Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Covariances for Free: Exploiting Mean Distributions for Training-free Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14326</link>
   <description>Using pre-trained models has been found to reduce the effect of data heterogeneity and speed up federated learning algorithms. Recent works have explored training-free methods using first- and second-order statistics to aggregate local client data distributions at the server and achieve high performance without any training. In this work, we propose a training-free method based on an unbiased estimator of class covariance matrices which only uses first-order statistics in the form of class means communicated by clients to the server. We show how these estimated class covariances can be used to initialize the global classifier, thus exploiting the covariances without actually sharing them. We also show that using only within-class covariances results in a better classifier initialization. Our approach improves performance in the range of 4-26% with exactly the same communication cost when compared to methods sharing only class means and achieves performance competitive or superior to methods sharing second-order statistics with dramatically less communication overhead. The proposed method is much more communication-efficient than federated prompt-tuning methods and still outperforms them. Finally, using our method to initialize classifiers and then performing federated fine-tuning or linear probing again yields better performance. Code is available at https://github.com/dipamgoswami/FedCOF.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.14326v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Dipam Goswami, Simone Magistri, Kai Wang, Bart{\l}omiej Twardowski, Andrew D. Bagdanov, Joost van de Weijer</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Mozart: A Chiplet Ecosystem-Accelerator Codesign Framework for Composable Bespoke Application Specific Integrated Circuits</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08873</link>
   <description>Modern AI acceleration faces a fundamental challenge: conventional assumptions about memory requirements, batching effectiveness, and latency-throughput tradeoffs are systemwide generalizations that ignore the heterogeneous computational patterns of individual neural network operators. However, going towards network-level customization and operator-level heterogeneity incur substantial Non-Recurring Engineering (NRE) costs. While chiplet-based approaches have been proposed to amortize NRE costs, reuse opportunities remain limited without carefully identifying which chiplets are truly necessary. This paper introduces Mozart, a chiplet ecosystem and accelerator codesign framework that systematically constructs low cost bespoke application-specific integrated circuits (BASICs). BASICs leverage operator-level disaggregation to explore chiplet and memory heterogeneity, tensor fusion, and tensor parallelism, with place-and-route validation ensuring physical implementability. The framework also enables constraint-aware system-level optimization across deployment contexts ranging from datacenter inference serving to edge computing in autonomous vehicles. The evaluation confirms that with just 8 strategically selected chiplets, Mozart-generated composite BASICs achieve 43.5%, 25.4%, 67.7%, and 78.8% reductions in energy, energy-cost product, energy-delay product (EDP), and energy-delay-cost product compared to traditional homogeneous accelerators. For datacenter LLM serving, Mozart achieves 15-19% energy reduction and 35-39% energy-cost improvement. In speculative decoding, Mozart delivers throughput improvements of 24.6-58.6% while reducing energy consumption by 38.6-45.6%. For autonomous vehicle perception, Mozart reduces energy-cost by 25.54% and energy by 10.53% under real-time constraints.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.08873v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AR</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Haoran Jin, Jirong Yang, Yunpeng Liu, Barry Lyu, Kangqi Zhang, Nathaniel Bleier</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>RegexPSPACE: A Benchmark for Evaluating LLM Reasoning on PSPACE-complete Regex Problems</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09227</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) show strong performance across natural language processing (NLP), mathematical reasoning, and programming, and recent large reasoning models (LRMs) further emphasize explicit reasoning. Yet their computational limits, particularly spatial complexity constrained by finite context windows, remain poorly understood. While recent works often focus on problems within the NP complexity class, we push the boundary by introducing a novel benchmark grounded in two PSPACE-complete regular expression (regex) problems: equivalence decision (RegexEQ) and minimization (RegexMin). PSPACE-complete problems serve as a more rigorous standard for assessing computational capacity, as their solutions require massive search space exploration. We perform a double-exponential space exploration to construct a labeled dataset of over a million regex instances with a sound filtering process to build the benchmark. We conduct extensive evaluations on 6 LLMs and 5 LRMs of varying scales, revealing common failure patterns such as verbosity and repetition. With its well-defined structure and quantitative evaluation metrics, this work presents the first empirical investigation into the spatial computational limitations of LLMs and LRMs, offering a new framework for evaluating their advanced reasoning capabilities. Our code is available at https://github.com/hyundong98/RegexPSPACE .</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.09227v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.FL</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hyundong Jin, Joonghyuk Hahn, Yo-Sub Han</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedL2T: Personalized Federated Learning with Two-Teacher Distillation for Seizure Prediction</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08984</link>
   <description>The training of deep learning models in seizure prediction requires large amounts of Electroencephalogram (EEG) data. However, acquiring sufficient labeled EEG data is difficult due to annotation costs and privacy constraints. Federated Learning (FL) enables privacy-preserving collaborative training by sharing model updates instead of raw data. However, due to the inherent inter-patient variability in real-world scenarios, existing FL-based seizure prediction methods struggle to achieve robust performance under heterogeneous client settings. To address this challenge, we propose FedL2T, a personalized federated learning framework that leverages a novel two-teacher knowledge distillation strategy to generate superior personalized models for each client. Specifically, each client simultaneously learns from a globally aggregated model and a dynamically assigned peer model, promoting more direct and enriched knowledge exchange. To ensure reliable knowledge transfer, FedL2T employs an adaptive multi-level distillation strategy that aligns both prediction outputs and intermediate feature representations based on task confidence. In addition, a proximal regularization term is introduced to constrain personalized model updates, thereby enhancing training stability. Extensive experiments on two EEG datasets demonstrate that FedL2T consistently outperforms state-of-the-art FL methods, particularly under low-label conditions. Moreover, FedL2T exhibits rapid and stable convergence toward optimal performance, thereby reducing the number of communication rounds and associated overhead. These results underscore the potential of FedL2T as a reliable and personalized solution for seizure prediction in privacy-sensitive healthcare scenarios.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.08984v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.NE</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jionghao Lou, Jian Zhang, Zhongmei Li, Lanlan Chen, Enbo Feng</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Automating eHMI Action Design with LLMs for Automated Vehicle Communication</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20711</link>
   <description>The absence of explicit communication channels between automated vehicles (AVs) and other road users requires the use of external Human-Machine Interfaces (eHMIs) to convey messages effectively in uncertain scenarios. Currently, most eHMI studies employ predefined text messages and manually designed actions to perform these messages, which limits the real-world deployment of eHMIs, where adaptability in dynamic scenarios is essential. Given the generalizability and versatility of large language models (LLMs), they could potentially serve as automated action designers for the message-action design task. To validate this idea, we make three contributions: (1) We propose a pipeline that integrates LLMs and 3D renderers, using LLMs as action designers to generate executable actions for controlling eHMIs and rendering action clips. (2) We collect a user-rated Action-Design Scoring dataset comprising a total of 320 action sequences for eight intended messages and four representative eHMI modalities. The dataset validates that LLMs can translate intended messages into actions close to a human level, particularly for reasoning-enabled LLMs. (3) We introduce two automated raters, Action Reference Score (ARS) and Vision-Language Models (VLMs), to benchmark 18 LLMs, finding that the VLM aligns with human preferences yet varies across eHMI modalities.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.20711v2</guid>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <category>cs.RO</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ding Xia, Xinyue Gui, Fan Gao, Dongyuan Li, Mark Colley, Takeo Igarashi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Prompt-Aware Scheduling for Low-Latency LLM Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03243</link>
   <description>Efficient scheduling of LLM inference tasks is essential for achieving low latency and high throughput, particularly with the growing use of reasoning-capable LLMs. Traditional strategies like First-Come-First-Serve (FCFS) often suffer from Head-of-Line (HOL) blocking, where long-running tasks delay shorter ones queued behind them. In this paper, we introduce PARS, a prompt-aware LLM task scheduler that improves serving efficiency by approximating shortest-job-first (SJF) scheduling through pairwise ranking with margin ranking loss. PARS focuses on impactful scheduling decisions and is seamlessly integrated into the state-of-the-art LLM serving system vLLM. It effectively predicts response-length-based task ordering, reducing latency with minimal overhead. Extensive experiments across multiple LLMs and real-world inference datasets show that PARS significantly improves performance, including for reasoning workloads. Furthermore, our cross-model evaluations demonstrate that the design generalizes well, enabling effective scheduling even when predictors are trained on different LLMs.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.03243v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.PF</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yiheng Tao, Yihe Zhang, Matthew T. Dearing, Xin Wang, Yuping Fan, Zhiling Lan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Exploring Cross-Client Memorization of Training Data in Large Language Models for Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08750</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) enables collaborative training without raw data sharing, but still risks training data memorization. Existing FL memorization detection techniques focus on one sample at a time, underestimating more subtle risks of cross-sample memorization. In contrast, recent work on centralized learning (CL) has introduced fine-grained methods to assess memorization across all samples in training data, but these assume centralized access to data and cannot be applied directly to FL. We bridge this gap by proposing a framework that quantifies both intra- and inter-client memorization in FL using fine-grained cross-sample memorization measurement across all clients. Based on this framework, we conduct two studies: (1) measuring subtle memorization across clients and (2) examining key factors that influence memorization, including decoding strategies, prefix length, and FL algorithms. Our findings reveal that FL models do memorize client data, particularly intra-client data, more than inter-client data, with memorization influenced by training and inferencing factors.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.08750v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Tinnakit Udsa, Can Udomcharoenchaikit, Patomporn Payoungkhamdee, Sarana Nutanong, Norrathep Rattanavipanon</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedL2T: Personalized Federated Learning with Two-Teacher Distillation for Seizure Prediction</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08984</link>
   <description>The training of deep learning models in seizure prediction requires large amounts of Electroencephalogram (EEG) data. However, acquiring sufficient labeled EEG data is difficult due to annotation costs and privacy constraints. Federated Learning (FL) enables privacy-preserving collaborative training by sharing model updates instead of raw data. However, due to the inherent inter-patient variability in real-world scenarios, existing FL-based seizure prediction methods struggle to achieve robust performance under heterogeneous client settings. To address this challenge, we propose FedL2T, a personalized federated learning framework that leverages a novel two-teacher knowledge distillation strategy to generate superior personalized models for each client. Specifically, each client simultaneously learns from a globally aggregated model and a dynamically assigned peer model, promoting more direct and enriched knowledge exchange. To ensure reliable knowledge transfer, FedL2T employs an adaptive multi-level distillation strategy that aligns both prediction outputs and intermediate feature representations based on task confidence. In addition, a proximal regularization term is introduced to constrain personalized model updates, thereby enhancing training stability. Extensive experiments on two EEG datasets demonstrate that FedL2T consistently outperforms state-of-the-art FL methods, particularly under low-label conditions. Moreover, FedL2T exhibits rapid and stable convergence toward optimal performance, thereby reducing the number of communication rounds and associated overhead. These results underscore the potential of FedL2T as a reliable and personalized solution for seizure prediction in privacy-sensitive healthcare scenarios.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.08984v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.NE</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jionghao Lou, Jian Zhang, Zhongmei Li, Lanlan Chen, Enbo Feng</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Adaptive Attacks on Trusted Monitors Subvert AI Control Protocols</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09462</link>
   <description>AI control protocols serve as a defense mechanism to stop untrusted LLM agents from causing harm in autonomous settings. Prior work treats this as a security problem, stress testing with exploits that use the deployment context to subtly complete harmful side tasks, such as backdoor insertion. In practice, most AI control protocols are fundamentally based on LLM monitors, which can become a central point of failure. We study adaptive attacks by an untrusted model that knows the protocol and the monitor model, which is plausible if the untrusted model was trained with a later knowledge cutoff or can search for this information autonomously. We instantiate a simple adaptive attack vector by which the attacker embeds publicly known or zero-shot prompt injections in the model outputs. Using this tactic, frontier models consistently evade diverse monitors and complete malicious tasks on two main AI control benchmarks. The attack works universally against current protocols that rely on a monitor. Furthermore, the recent Defer-to-Resample protocol even backfires, as its resampling amplifies the prompt injection and effectively reframes it as a best-of-$n$ attack. In general, adaptive attacks on monitor models represent a major blind spot in current control protocols and should become a standard component of evaluations for future AI control mechanisms.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.09462v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mikhail Terekhov, Alexander Panfilov, Daniil Dzenhaliou, Caglar Gulcehre, Maksym Andriushchenko, Ameya Prabhu, Jonas Geiping</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Model-Driven Engineering Approach to AI-Powered Healthcare Platforms</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09308</link>
   <description>Artificial intelligence (AI) has the potential to transform healthcare by supporting more accurate diagnoses and personalized treatments. However, its adoption in practice remains constrained by fragmented data sources, strict privacy rules, and the technical complexity of building reliable clinical systems. To address these challenges, we introduce a model driven engineering (MDE) framework designed specifically for healthcare AI. The framework relies on formal metamodels, domain-specific languages (DSLs), and automated transformations to move from high level specifications to running software. At its core is the Medical Interoperability Language (MILA), a graphical DSL that enables clinicians and data scientists to define queries and machine learning pipelines using shared ontologies. When combined with a federated learning architecture, MILA allows institutions to collaborate without exchanging raw patient data, ensuring semantic consistency across sites while preserving privacy. We evaluate this approach in a multi center cancer immunotherapy study. The generated pipelines delivered strong predictive performance, with support vector machines achieving up to 98.5 percent and 98.3 percent accuracy in key tasks, while substantially reducing manual coding effort. These findings suggest that MDE principles metamodeling, semantic integration, and automated code generation can provide a practical path toward interoperable, reproducible, and trustworthy digital health platforms.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.09308v1</guid>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mira Raheem, Amal Elgammal, Michael Papazoglou, Bernd Kr\&quot;amer, Neamat El-Tazi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LiveOIBench: Can Large Language Models Outperform Human Contestants in Informatics Olympiads?</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09595</link>
   <description>Competitive programming problems increasingly serve as valuable benchmarks to evaluate the coding capabilities of large language models (LLMs) due to their complexity and ease of verification. Yet, current coding benchmarks face limitations such as lack of exceptionally challenging problems, insufficient test case coverage, reliance on online platform APIs that limit accessibility. To address these issues, we introduce LiveOIBench, a comprehensive benchmark featuring 403 expert-curated Olympiad-level competitive programming problems, each with an average of 60 expert-designed test cases. The problems are sourced directly from 72 official Informatics Olympiads in different regions conducted between 2023 and 2025. LiveOIBench distinguishes itself through four key features: (1) meticulously curated high-quality tasks with detailed subtask rubrics and extensive private test cases; (2) direct integration of elite contestant performance data to enable informative comparison against top-performing humans; (3) planned continuous, contamination-free updates from newly released Olympiad problems; and (4) a self-contained evaluation system facilitating offline and easy-to-reproduce assessments. Benchmarking 32 popular general-purpose and reasoning LLMs, we find that GPT-5 achieves a notable 81.76th percentile, a strong result that nonetheless falls short of top human contestant performance, who usually place above 90th. In contrast, among open-weight reasoning models, GPT-OSS-120B achieves only a 60th percentile, underscoring significant capability disparities from frontier closed models. Detailed analyses indicate that robust reasoning models prioritize precise problem analysis over excessive exploration, suggesting future models should emphasize structured analysis and minimize unnecessary exploration. All data, code, and leaderboard results will be made publicly available on our website.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.09595v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kaijian Zou, Aaron Xiong, Yunxiang Zhang, Frederick Zhang, Yueqi Ren, Jirong Yang, Ayoung Lee, Shitanshu Bhushan, Lu Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Covariances for Free: Exploiting Mean Distributions for Training-free Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14326</link>
   <description>Using pre-trained models has been found to reduce the effect of data heterogeneity and speed up federated learning algorithms. Recent works have explored training-free methods using first- and second-order statistics to aggregate local client data distributions at the server and achieve high performance without any training. In this work, we propose a training-free method based on an unbiased estimator of class covariance matrices which only uses first-order statistics in the form of class means communicated by clients to the server. We show how these estimated class covariances can be used to initialize the global classifier, thus exploiting the covariances without actually sharing them. We also show that using only within-class covariances results in a better classifier initialization. Our approach improves performance in the range of 4-26% with exactly the same communication cost when compared to methods sharing only class means and achieves performance competitive or superior to methods sharing second-order statistics with dramatically less communication overhead. The proposed method is much more communication-efficient than federated prompt-tuning methods and still outperforms them. Finally, using our method to initialize classifiers and then performing federated fine-tuning or linear probing again yields better performance. Code is available at https://github.com/dipamgoswami/FedCOF.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.14326v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Dipam Goswami, Simone Magistri, Kai Wang, Bart{\l}omiej Twardowski, Andrew D. Bagdanov, Joost van de Weijer</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Aggregation on Learnable Manifolds for Asynchronous Federated Optimization</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14396</link>
   <description>Asynchronous federated learning (FL) with heterogeneous clients faces two key issues: curvature-induced loss barriers encountered by standard linear parameter interpolation techniques (e.g. FedAvg) and interference from stale updates misaligned with the server's current optimisation state. To alleviate these issues, we introduce a geometric framework that casts aggregation as curve learning in a Riemannian model space and decouples trajectory selection from update conflict resolution. Within this, we propose AsyncBezier, which replaces linear aggregation with low-degree polynomial (Bezier) trajectories to bypass loss barriers, and OrthoDC, which projects delayed updates via inner product-based orthogonality to reduce interference. We establish framework-level convergence guarantees covering each variant given simple assumptions on their components. On three datasets spanning general-purpose and healthcare domains, including LEAF Shakespeare and FEMNIST, our approach consistently improves accuracy and client fairness over strong asynchronous baselines; finally, we show that these gains are preserved even when other methods are allocated a higher local compute budget.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.14396v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Archie Licudi, Anshul Thakur, Soheila Molaei, Danielle Belgrave, David Clifton</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Enabling Self-Improving Agents to Learn at Test Time With Human-In-The-Loop Guidance</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17131</link>
   <description>Large language model (LLM) agents often struggle in environments where rules and required domain knowledge frequently change, such as regulatory compliance and user risk screening. Current approaches, like offline fine-tuning and standard prompting, are insufficient because they cannot effectively adapt to new knowledge during actual operation. To address this limitation, we propose the Adaptive Reflective Interactive Agent (ARIA), an LLM agent framework designed specifically to continuously learn updated domain knowledge at test time. ARIA assesses its own uncertainty through structured self-dialogue, proactively identifying knowledge gaps and requesting targeted explanations or corrections from human experts. It then systematically updates an internal, timestamped knowledge repository with provided human guidance, detecting and resolving conflicting or outdated knowledge through comparisons and clarification queries. We evaluate ARIA on the realistic customer due diligence name screening task on TikTok Pay, alongside publicly available dynamic knowledge tasks. Results demonstrate significant improvements in adaptability and accuracy compared to baselines using standard offline fine-tuning and existing self-improving agents. ARIA is deployed within TikTok Pay serving over 150 million monthly active users, confirming its practicality and effectiveness for operational use in rapidly evolving environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.17131v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yufei He, Ruoyu Li, Alex Chen, Yue Liu, Yulin Chen, Yuan Sui, Cheng Chen, Yi Zhu, Luca Luo, Frank Yang, Bryan Hooi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>From Federated Learning to X-Learning: Breaking the Barriers of Decentrality Through Random Walks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03709</link>
   <description>We provide our perspective on X-Learning (XL), a novel distributed learning architecture that generalizes and extends the concept of decentralization. Our goal is to present a vision for XL, introducing its unexplored design considerations and degrees of freedom. To this end, we shed light on the intuitive yet non-trivial connections between XL, graph theory, and Markov chains. We also present a series of open research directions to stimulate further research.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.03709v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Allan Salihovic, Payam Abdisarabshali, Michael Langberg, Seyyedali Hosseinalipour</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Adaptive LoRA Experts Allocation and Selection for Federated Fine-Tuning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15087</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated impressive capabilities across various tasks, but fine-tuning them for domain-specific applications often requires substantial domain-specific data that may be distributed across multiple organizations. Federated Learning (FL) offers a privacy-preserving solution, but faces challenges with computational constraints when applied to LLMs. Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA) has emerged as a parameter-efficient fine-tuning approach, though a single LoRA module often struggles with heterogeneous data across diverse domains. This paper addresses two critical challenges in federated LoRA fine-tuning: 1. determining the optimal number and allocation of LoRA experts across heterogeneous clients, and 2. enabling clients to selectively utilize these experts based on their specific data characteristics. We propose FedLEASE (Federated adaptive LoRA Expert Allocation and SElection), a novel framework that adaptively clusters clients based on representation similarity to allocate and train domain-specific LoRA experts. It also introduces an adaptive top-$M$ Mixture-of-Experts mechanism that allows each client to select the optimal number of utilized experts. Our extensive experiments on diverse benchmark datasets demonstrate that FedLEASE significantly outperforms existing federated fine-tuning approaches in heterogeneous client settings while maintaining communication efficiency.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.15087v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Lei Wang, Jieming Bian, Letian Zhang, Jie Xu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Prompt-Aware Scheduling for Low-Latency LLM Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03243</link>
   <description>Efficient scheduling of LLM inference tasks is essential for achieving low latency and high throughput, particularly with the growing use of reasoning-capable LLMs. Traditional strategies like First-Come-First-Serve (FCFS) often suffer from Head-of-Line (HOL) blocking, where long-running tasks delay shorter ones queued behind them. In this paper, we introduce PARS, a prompt-aware LLM task scheduler that improves serving efficiency by approximating shortest-job-first (SJF) scheduling through pairwise ranking with margin ranking loss. PARS focuses on impactful scheduling decisions and is seamlessly integrated into the state-of-the-art LLM serving system vLLM. It effectively predicts response-length-based task ordering, reducing latency with minimal overhead. Extensive experiments across multiple LLMs and real-world inference datasets show that PARS significantly improves performance, including for reasoning workloads. Furthermore, our cross-model evaluations demonstrate that the design generalizes well, enabling effective scheduling even when predictors are trained on different LLMs.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.03243v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.PF</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yiheng Tao, Yihe Zhang, Matthew T. Dearing, Xin Wang, Yuping Fan, Zhiling Lan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>CAFL-L: Constraint-Aware Federated Learning with Lagrangian Dual Optimization for On-Device Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03298</link>
   <description>We introduce Constraint-Aware Federated Learning with Lagrangian Dual Optimization (CAFL-L), a principled extension of FedAvg that explicitly incorporates device-level resource constraints including energy, communication, memory, and thermal budgets. CAFL-L employs Lagrangian dual optimization to dynamically adapt training hyperparameters -- freezing depth, local steps, batch size, and communication compression -- while preserving training stability through token-budget preservation via gradient accumulation. Experiments on a character-level language model demonstrate that CAFL-L achieves superior constraint satisfaction compared to standard FedAvg (reducing memory usage by 20% and communication by 95%) while maintaining competitive validation performance, making it practical for deployment on resource-constrained edge devices.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.03298v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Dongqi Zheng, Wenjin Fu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Revealing Interconnections between Diseases: from Statistical Methods to Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04888</link>
   <description>Identifying disease interconnections through manual analysis of large-scale clinical data is labor-intensive, subjective, and prone to expert disagreement. While machine learning (ML) shows promise, three critical challenges remain: (1) selecting optimal methods from the vast ML landscape, (2) determining whether real-world clinical data (e.g., electronic health records, EHRs) or structured disease descriptions yield more reliable insights, (3) the lack of &quot;ground truth,&quot; as some disease interconnections remain unexplored in medicine. Large language models (LLMs) demonstrate broad utility, yet they often lack specialized medical knowledge. To address these gaps, we conduct a systematic evaluation of seven approaches for uncovering disease relationships based on two data sources: (i) sequences of ICD-10 codes from MIMIC-IV EHRs and (ii) the full set of ICD-10 codes, both with and without textual descriptions. Our framework integrates the following: (i) a statistical co-occurrence analysis and a masked language modeling (MLM) approach using real clinical data; (ii) domain-specific BERT variants (Med-BERT and BioClinicalBERT); (iii) a general-purpose BERT and document retrieval; and (iv) four LLMs (Mistral, DeepSeek, Qwen, and YandexGPT). Our graph-based comparison of the obtained interconnection matrices shows that the LLM-based approach produces interconnections with the lowest diversity of ICD code connections to different diseases compared to other methods, including text-based and domain-based approaches. This suggests an important implication: LLMs have limited potential for discovering new interconnections. In the absence of ground truth databases for medical interconnections between ICD codes, our results constitute a valuable medical disease ontology that can serve as a foundational resource for future clinical research and artificial intelligence applications in healthcare.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.04888v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Alina Ermilova, Dmitrii Kornilov, Sofia Samoilova, Ekaterina Laptenkova, Anastasia Kolesnikova, Ekaterina Podplutova, Senotrusova Sofya, Maksim G. Sharaev</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>SketchGuard: Scaling Byzantine-Robust Decentralized Federated Learning via Sketch-Based Screening</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07922</link>
   <description>Decentralized Federated Learning (DFL) enables privacy-preserving collaborative training without centralized servers, but remains vulnerable to Byzantine attacks where malicious clients submit corrupted model updates. Existing Byzantine-robust DFL defenses rely on similarity-based neighbor screening that requires every client to exchange and compare complete high-dimensional model vectors with all neighbors in each training round, creating prohibitive communication and computational costs that prevent deployment at web scale. We propose SketchGuard, a general framework that decouples Byzantine filtering from model aggregation through sketch-based neighbor screening. SketchGuard compresses $d$-dimensional models to $k$-dimensional sketches ($k \ll d$) using Count Sketch for similarity comparisons, then selectively fetches full models only from accepted neighbors, reducing per-round communication complexity from $O(d|N_i|)$ to $O(k|N_i| + d|S_i|)$, where $|N_i|$ is the neighbor count and $|S_i| \le |N_i|$ is the accepted neighbor count. We establish rigorous convergence guarantees in both strongly convex and non-convex settings, proving that Count Sketch compression preserves Byzantine resilience with controlled degradation bounds where approximation errors introduce only a $(1+O(\epsilon))$ factor in the effective threshold parameter. Comprehensive experiments across multiple datasets, network topologies, and attack scenarios demonstrate that SketchGuard maintains identical robustness to state-of-the-art methods while reducing computation time by up to 82% and communication overhead by 50-70% depending on filtering effectiveness, with benefits scaling multiplicatively with model dimensionality and network connectivity. These results establish the viability of sketch-based compression as a fundamental enabler of robust DFL at web scale.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.07922v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Murtaza Rangwala, Farag Azzedin, Richard O. Sinnott, Rajkumar Buyya</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Site-Level Fine-Tuning with Progressive Layer Freezing: Towards Robust Prediction of Bronchopulmonary Dysplasia from Day-1 Chest Radiographs in Extremely Preterm Infants</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12269</link>
   <description>Bronchopulmonary dysplasia (BPD) is a chronic lung disease affecting 35% of extremely low birth weight infants. Defined by oxygen dependence at 36 weeks postmenstrual age, it causes lifelong respiratory complications. However, preventive interventions carry severe risks, including neurodevelopmental impairment, ventilator-induced lung injury, and systemic complications. Therefore, early BPD prognosis and prediction of BPD outcome is crucial to avoid unnecessary toxicity in low risk infants. Admission radiographs of extremely preterm infants are routinely acquired within 24h of life and could serve as a non-invasive prognostic tool. In this work, we developed and investigated a deep learning approach using chest X-rays from 163 extremely low-birth-weight infants ($\leq$32 weeks gestation, 401-999g) obtained within 24 hours of birth. We fine-tuned a ResNet-50 pretrained specifically on adult chest radiographs, employing progressive layer freezing with discriminative learning rates to prevent overfitting and evaluated a CutMix augmentation and linear probing. For moderate/severe BPD outcome prediction, our best performing model with progressive freezing, linear probing and CutMix achieved an AUROC of 0.78 $\pm$ 0.10, balanced accuracy of 0.69 $\pm$ 0.10, and an F1-score of 0.67 $\pm$ 0.11. In-domain pre-training significantly outperformed ImageNet initialization (p = 0.031) which confirms domain-specific pretraining to be important for BPD outcome prediction. Routine IRDS grades showed limited prognostic value (AUROC 0.57 $\pm$ 0.11), confirming the need of learned markers. Our approach demonstrates that domain-specific pretraining enables accurate BPD prediction from routine day-1 radiographs. Through progressive freezing and linear probing, the method remains computationally feasible for site-level implementation and future federated learning deployments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.12269v3</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sybelle Goedicke-Fritz (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Michelle Bous (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Annika Engel (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany), Matthias Flotho (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany, Helmholtz Institute for Pharmaceutical Research Saarland), Pascal Hirsch (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany), Hannah Wittig (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Dino Milanovic (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany), Dominik Mohr (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Mathias Kaspar (Digital Medicine, University Hospital of Augsburg, Augsburg, Germany), Sogand Nemat (Department of Radiology, and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital of Saarland, Homburg, Germany), Dorothea Kerner (Department of Radiology, and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital of Saarland, Homburg, Germany), Arno B\&quot;ucker (Department of Radiology, and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital of Saarland, Homburg, Germany), Andreas Keller (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany, Helmholtz Institute for Pharmaceutical Research Saarland, Pharma Science Hub), Sascha Meyer (Clinical Centre Karlsruhe, Franz-Lust Clinic for Paediatrics, Karlsruhe, Germany), Michael Zemlin (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Philipp Flotho (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany, Helmholtz Institute for Pharmaceutical Research Saarland)</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>COMPACT: Common-token Optimized Model Pruning Across Channels and Tokens</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06836</link>
   <description>Making large language models (LLMs) more efficient in memory, latency, and serving cost is crucial for edge deployment, interactive applications, and sustainable inference at scale. Pruning is a promising technique, but existing pruning methods are limited: width pruning often breaks the standard transformer layout, requiring custom inference code, while depth pruning can cause abrupt accuracy drops. Also, while many pruning approaches are effective against LLMs, they struggle to maintain performance on small language models (SLMs). In this work, we propose COMPACT, which jointly (i) prunes rare vocabulary to shrink embedding/LM head layers and (ii) prunes FFN intermediate channels using common-token-weighted activations, aligning importance with the post-pruning token distribution. COMPACT inherits strengths of both depth and width pruning, such as: deployment-friendliness (keeps a standard transformer architecture), scale-adaptivity (trade off vocab. vs. FFN pruning), competitive pruning times, and strong memory savings alongside throughput gains. Experiments across Qwen, LLaMA, and Gemma families (0.5B-70B) show state-of-the-art downstream performance, with substantial reductions in parameters, GPU memory, and latency.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.06836v3</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Eugene Kwek, Wenpeng Yin</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>RegexPSPACE: A Benchmark for Evaluating LLM Reasoning on PSPACE-complete Regex Problems</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09227</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) show strong performance across natural language processing (NLP), mathematical reasoning, and programming, and recent large reasoning models (LRMs) further emphasize explicit reasoning. Yet their computational limits, particularly spatial complexity constrained by finite context windows, remain poorly understood. While recent works often focus on problems within the NP complexity class, we push the boundary by introducing a novel benchmark grounded in two PSPACE-complete regular expression (regex) problems: equivalence decision (RegexEQ) and minimization (RegexMin). PSPACE-complete problems serve as a more rigorous standard for assessing computational capacity, as their solutions require massive search space exploration. We perform a double-exponential space exploration to construct a labeled dataset of over a million regex instances with a sound filtering process to build the benchmark. We conduct extensive evaluations on 6 LLMs and 5 LRMs of varying scales, revealing common failure patterns such as verbosity and repetition. With its well-defined structure and quantitative evaluation metrics, this work presents the first empirical investigation into the spatial computational limitations of LLMs and LRMs, offering a new framework for evaluating their advanced reasoning capabilities. Our code is available at https://github.com/hyundong98/RegexPSPACE .</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.09227v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.FL</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hyundong Jin, Joonghyuk Hahn, Yo-Sub Han</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LiveOIBench: Can Large Language Models Outperform Human Contestants in Informatics Olympiads?</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09595</link>
   <description>Competitive programming problems increasingly serve as valuable benchmarks to evaluate the coding capabilities of large language models (LLMs) due to their complexity and ease of verification. Yet, current coding benchmarks face limitations such as lack of exceptionally challenging problems, insufficient test case coverage, reliance on online platform APIs that limit accessibility. To address these issues, we introduce LiveOIBench, a comprehensive benchmark featuring 403 expert-curated Olympiad-level competitive programming problems, each with an average of 60 expert-designed test cases. The problems are sourced directly from 72 official Informatics Olympiads in different regions conducted between 2023 and 2025. LiveOIBench distinguishes itself through four key features: (1) meticulously curated high-quality tasks with detailed subtask rubrics and extensive private test cases; (2) direct integration of elite contestant performance data to enable informative comparison against top-performing humans; (3) planned continuous, contamination-free updates from newly released Olympiad problems; and (4) a self-contained evaluation system facilitating offline and easy-to-reproduce assessments. Benchmarking 32 popular general-purpose and reasoning LLMs, we find that GPT-5 achieves a notable 81.76th percentile, a strong result that nonetheless falls short of top human contestant performance, who usually place above 90th. In contrast, among open-weight reasoning models, GPT-OSS-120B achieves only a 60th percentile, underscoring significant capability disparities from frontier closed models. Detailed analyses indicate that robust reasoning models prioritize precise problem analysis over excessive exploration, suggesting future models should emphasize structured analysis and minimize unnecessary exploration. All data, code, and leaderboard results will be made publicly available on our website.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.09595v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kaijian Zou, Aaron Xiong, Yunxiang Zhang, Frederick Zhang, Yueqi Ren, Jirong Yang, Ayoung Lee, Shitanshu Bhushan, Lu Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>When to Reason: Semantic Router for vLLM</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08731</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) demonstrate substantial accuracy gains when augmented with reasoning modes such as chain-of-thought and inference-time scaling. However, reasoning also incurs significant costs in inference latency and token usage, with environmental and financial impacts, which are unnecessary for many simple prompts. We present a semantic router that classifies queries based on their reasoning requirements and selectively applies reasoning only when beneficial. Our approach achieves a 10.2 percentage point improvement in accuracy on the MMLU-Pro benchmark while reducing response latency by 47.1% and token consumption by 48.5% compared to direct inference with vLLM. These results demonstrate that semantic routing offers an effective mechanism for striking a balance between accuracy and efficiency in open-source LLM serving systems</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.08731v1</guid>
   <category>cs.ET</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.SY</category>
   <category>eess.SY</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chen Wang, Xunzhuo Liu, Yuhan Liu, Yue Zhu, Xiangxi Mo, Junchen Jiang, Huamin Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Model-Driven Engineering Approach to AI-Powered Healthcare Platforms</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09308</link>
   <description>Artificial intelligence (AI) has the potential to transform healthcare by supporting more accurate diagnoses and personalized treatments. However, its adoption in practice remains constrained by fragmented data sources, strict privacy rules, and the technical complexity of building reliable clinical systems. To address these challenges, we introduce a model driven engineering (MDE) framework designed specifically for healthcare AI. The framework relies on formal metamodels, domain-specific languages (DSLs), and automated transformations to move from high level specifications to running software. At its core is the Medical Interoperability Language (MILA), a graphical DSL that enables clinicians and data scientists to define queries and machine learning pipelines using shared ontologies. When combined with a federated learning architecture, MILA allows institutions to collaborate without exchanging raw patient data, ensuring semantic consistency across sites while preserving privacy. We evaluate this approach in a multi center cancer immunotherapy study. The generated pipelines delivered strong predictive performance, with support vector machines achieving up to 98.5 percent and 98.3 percent accuracy in key tasks, while substantially reducing manual coding effort. These findings suggest that MDE principles metamodeling, semantic integration, and automated code generation can provide a practical path toward interoperable, reproducible, and trustworthy digital health platforms.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.09308v1</guid>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mira Raheem, Amal Elgammal, Michael Papazoglou, Bernd Kr\&quot;amer, Neamat El-Tazi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Adaptive Attacks on Trusted Monitors Subvert AI Control Protocols</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09462</link>
   <description>AI control protocols serve as a defense mechanism to stop untrusted LLM agents from causing harm in autonomous settings. Prior work treats this as a security problem, stress testing with exploits that use the deployment context to subtly complete harmful side tasks, such as backdoor insertion. In practice, most AI control protocols are fundamentally based on LLM monitors, which can become a central point of failure. We study adaptive attacks by an untrusted model that knows the protocol and the monitor model, which is plausible if the untrusted model was trained with a later knowledge cutoff or can search for this information autonomously. We instantiate a simple adaptive attack vector by which the attacker embeds publicly known or zero-shot prompt injections in the model outputs. Using this tactic, frontier models consistently evade diverse monitors and complete malicious tasks on two main AI control benchmarks. The attack works universally against current protocols that rely on a monitor. Furthermore, the recent Defer-to-Resample protocol even backfires, as its resampling amplifies the prompt injection and effectively reframes it as a best-of-$n$ attack. In general, adaptive attacks on monitor models represent a major blind spot in current control protocols and should become a standard component of evaluations for future AI control mechanisms.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.09462v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mikhail Terekhov, Alexander Panfilov, Daniil Dzenhaliou, Caglar Gulcehre, Maksym Andriushchenko, Ameya Prabhu, Jonas Geiping</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Site-Level Fine-Tuning with Progressive Layer Freezing: Towards Robust Prediction of Bronchopulmonary Dysplasia from Day-1 Chest Radiographs in Extremely Preterm Infants</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12269</link>
   <description>Bronchopulmonary dysplasia (BPD) is a chronic lung disease affecting 35% of extremely low birth weight infants. Defined by oxygen dependence at 36 weeks postmenstrual age, it causes lifelong respiratory complications. However, preventive interventions carry severe risks, including neurodevelopmental impairment, ventilator-induced lung injury, and systemic complications. Therefore, early BPD prognosis and prediction of BPD outcome is crucial to avoid unnecessary toxicity in low risk infants. Admission radiographs of extremely preterm infants are routinely acquired within 24h of life and could serve as a non-invasive prognostic tool. In this work, we developed and investigated a deep learning approach using chest X-rays from 163 extremely low-birth-weight infants ($\leq$32 weeks gestation, 401-999g) obtained within 24 hours of birth. We fine-tuned a ResNet-50 pretrained specifically on adult chest radiographs, employing progressive layer freezing with discriminative learning rates to prevent overfitting and evaluated a CutMix augmentation and linear probing. For moderate/severe BPD outcome prediction, our best performing model with progressive freezing, linear probing and CutMix achieved an AUROC of 0.78 $\pm$ 0.10, balanced accuracy of 0.69 $\pm$ 0.10, and an F1-score of 0.67 $\pm$ 0.11. In-domain pre-training significantly outperformed ImageNet initialization (p = 0.031) which confirms domain-specific pretraining to be important for BPD outcome prediction. Routine IRDS grades showed limited prognostic value (AUROC 0.57 $\pm$ 0.11), confirming the need of learned markers. Our approach demonstrates that domain-specific pretraining enables accurate BPD prediction from routine day-1 radiographs. Through progressive freezing and linear probing, the method remains computationally feasible for site-level implementation and future federated learning deployments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.12269v3</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sybelle Goedicke-Fritz (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Michelle Bous (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Annika Engel (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany), Matthias Flotho (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany, Helmholtz Institute for Pharmaceutical Research Saarland), Pascal Hirsch (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany), Hannah Wittig (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Dino Milanovic (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany), Dominik Mohr (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Mathias Kaspar (Digital Medicine, University Hospital of Augsburg, Augsburg, Germany), Sogand Nemat (Department of Radiology, and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital of Saarland, Homburg, Germany), Dorothea Kerner (Department of Radiology, and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital of Saarland, Homburg, Germany), Arno B\&quot;ucker (Department of Radiology, and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital of Saarland, Homburg, Germany), Andreas Keller (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany, Helmholtz Institute for Pharmaceutical Research Saarland, Pharma Science Hub), Sascha Meyer (Clinical Centre Karlsruhe, Franz-Lust Clinic for Paediatrics, Karlsruhe, Germany), Michael Zemlin (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Philipp Flotho (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany, Helmholtz Institute for Pharmaceutical Research Saarland)</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Enabling Self-Improving Agents to Learn at Test Time With Human-In-The-Loop Guidance</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17131</link>
   <description>Large language model (LLM) agents often struggle in environments where rules and required domain knowledge frequently change, such as regulatory compliance and user risk screening. Current approaches, like offline fine-tuning and standard prompting, are insufficient because they cannot effectively adapt to new knowledge during actual operation. To address this limitation, we propose the Adaptive Reflective Interactive Agent (ARIA), an LLM agent framework designed specifically to continuously learn updated domain knowledge at test time. ARIA assesses its own uncertainty through structured self-dialogue, proactively identifying knowledge gaps and requesting targeted explanations or corrections from human experts. It then systematically updates an internal, timestamped knowledge repository with provided human guidance, detecting and resolving conflicting or outdated knowledge through comparisons and clarification queries. We evaluate ARIA on the realistic customer due diligence name screening task on TikTok Pay, alongside publicly available dynamic knowledge tasks. Results demonstrate significant improvements in adaptability and accuracy compared to baselines using standard offline fine-tuning and existing self-improving agents. ARIA is deployed within TikTok Pay serving over 150 million monthly active users, confirming its practicality and effectiveness for operational use in rapidly evolving environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.17131v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yufei He, Ruoyu Li, Alex Chen, Yue Liu, Yulin Chen, Yuan Sui, Cheng Chen, Yi Zhu, Luca Luo, Frank Yang, Bryan Hooi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>From Federated Learning to X-Learning: Breaking the Barriers of Decentrality Through Random Walks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03709</link>
   <description>We provide our perspective on X-Learning (XL), a novel distributed learning architecture that generalizes and extends the concept of decentralization. Our goal is to present a vision for XL, introducing its unexplored design considerations and degrees of freedom. To this end, we shed light on the intuitive yet non-trivial connections between XL, graph theory, and Markov chains. We also present a series of open research directions to stimulate further research.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.03709v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Allan Salihovic, Payam Abdisarabshali, Michael Langberg, Seyyedali Hosseinalipour</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>COMPACT: Common-token Optimized Model Pruning Across Channels and Tokens</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06836</link>
   <description>Making large language models (LLMs) more efficient in memory, latency, and serving cost is crucial for edge deployment, interactive applications, and sustainable inference at scale. Pruning is a promising technique, but existing pruning methods are limited: width pruning often breaks the standard transformer layout, requiring custom inference code, while depth pruning can cause abrupt accuracy drops. Also, while many pruning approaches are effective against LLMs, they struggle to maintain performance on small language models (SLMs). In this work, we propose COMPACT, which jointly (i) prunes rare vocabulary to shrink embedding/LM head layers and (ii) prunes FFN intermediate channels using common-token-weighted activations, aligning importance with the post-pruning token distribution. COMPACT inherits strengths of both depth and width pruning, such as: deployment-friendliness (keeps a standard transformer architecture), scale-adaptivity (trade off vocab. vs. FFN pruning), competitive pruning times, and strong memory savings alongside throughput gains. Experiments across Qwen, LLaMA, and Gemma families (0.5B-70B) show state-of-the-art downstream performance, with substantial reductions in parameters, GPU memory, and latency.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.06836v3</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Eugene Kwek, Wenpeng Yin</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Prompt-Aware Scheduling for Low-Latency LLM Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03243</link>
   <description>Efficient scheduling of LLM inference tasks is essential for achieving low latency and high throughput, particularly with the growing use of reasoning-capable LLMs. Traditional strategies like First-Come-First-Serve (FCFS) often suffer from Head-of-Line (HOL) blocking, where long-running tasks delay shorter ones queued behind them. In this paper, we introduce PARS, a prompt-aware LLM task scheduler that improves serving efficiency by approximating shortest-job-first (SJF) scheduling through pairwise ranking with margin ranking loss. PARS focuses on impactful scheduling decisions and is seamlessly integrated into the state-of-the-art LLM serving system vLLM. It effectively predicts response-length-based task ordering, reducing latency with minimal overhead. Extensive experiments across multiple LLMs and real-world inference datasets show that PARS significantly improves performance, including for reasoning workloads. Furthermore, our cross-model evaluations demonstrate that the design generalizes well, enabling effective scheduling even when predictors are trained on different LLMs.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.03243v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.PF</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yiheng Tao, Yihe Zhang, Matthew T. Dearing, Xin Wang, Yuping Fan, Zhiling Lan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>P2P: A Poison-to-Poison Remedy for Reliable Backdoor Defense in LLMs</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04503</link>
   <description>During fine-tuning, large language models (LLMs) are increasingly vulnerable to data-poisoning backdoor attacks, which compromise their reliability and trustworthiness. However, existing defense strategies suffer from limited generalization: they only work on specific attack types or task settings. In this study, we propose Poison-to-Poison (P2P), a general and effective backdoor defense algorithm. P2P injects benign triggers with safe alternative labels into a subset of training samples and fine-tunes the model on this re-poisoned dataset by leveraging prompt-based learning. This enforces the model to associate trigger-induced representations with safe outputs, thereby overriding the effects of original malicious triggers. Thanks to this robust and generalizable trigger-based fine-tuning, P2P is effective across task settings and attack types. Theoretically and empirically, we show that P2P can neutralize malicious backdoors while preserving task performance. We conduct extensive experiments on classification, mathematical reasoning, and summary generation tasks, involving multiple state-of-the-art LLMs. The results demonstrate that our P2P algorithm significantly reduces the attack success rate compared with baseline models. We hope that the P2P can serve as a guideline for defending against backdoor attacks and foster the development of a secure and trustworthy LLM community.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.04503v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shuai Zhao, Xinyi Wu, Shiqian Zhao, Xiaobao Wu, Zhongliang Guo, Yanhao Jia, Anh Tuan Luu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Revealing Interconnections between Diseases: from Statistical Methods to Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04888</link>
   <description>Identifying disease interconnections through manual analysis of large-scale clinical data is labor-intensive, subjective, and prone to expert disagreement. While machine learning (ML) shows promise, three critical challenges remain: (1) selecting optimal methods from the vast ML landscape, (2) determining whether real-world clinical data (e.g., electronic health records, EHRs) or structured disease descriptions yield more reliable insights, (3) the lack of &quot;ground truth,&quot; as some disease interconnections remain unexplored in medicine. Large language models (LLMs) demonstrate broad utility, yet they often lack specialized medical knowledge. To address these gaps, we conduct a systematic evaluation of seven approaches for uncovering disease relationships based on two data sources: (i) sequences of ICD-10 codes from MIMIC-IV EHRs and (ii) the full set of ICD-10 codes, both with and without textual descriptions. Our framework integrates the following: (i) a statistical co-occurrence analysis and a masked language modeling (MLM) approach using real clinical data; (ii) domain-specific BERT variants (Med-BERT and BioClinicalBERT); (iii) a general-purpose BERT and document retrieval; and (iv) four LLMs (Mistral, DeepSeek, Qwen, and YandexGPT). Our graph-based comparison of the obtained interconnection matrices shows that the LLM-based approach produces interconnections with the lowest diversity of ICD code connections to different diseases compared to other methods, including text-based and domain-based approaches. This suggests an important implication: LLMs have limited potential for discovering new interconnections. In the absence of ground truth databases for medical interconnections between ICD codes, our results constitute a valuable medical disease ontology that can serve as a foundational resource for future clinical research and artificial intelligence applications in healthcare.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.04888v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Alina Ermilova, Dmitrii Kornilov, Sofia Samoilova, Ekaterina Laptenkova, Anastasia Kolesnikova, Ekaterina Podplutova, Senotrusova Sofya, Maksim G. Sharaev</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Prompt-Aware Scheduling for Low-Latency LLM Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03243</link>
   <description>Efficient scheduling of LLM inference tasks is essential for achieving low latency and high throughput, particularly with the growing use of reasoning-capable LLMs. Traditional strategies like First-Come-First-Serve (FCFS) often suffer from Head-of-Line (HOL) blocking, where long-running tasks delay shorter ones queued behind them. In this paper, we introduce PARS, a prompt-aware LLM task scheduler that improves serving efficiency by approximating shortest-job-first (SJF) scheduling through pairwise ranking with margin ranking loss. PARS focuses on impactful scheduling decisions and is seamlessly integrated into the state-of-the-art LLM serving system vLLM. It effectively predicts response-length-based task ordering, reducing latency with minimal overhead. Extensive experiments across multiple LLMs and real-world inference datasets show that PARS significantly improves performance, including for reasoning workloads. Furthermore, our cross-model evaluations demonstrate that the design generalizes well, enabling effective scheduling even when predictors are trained on different LLMs.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.03243v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.PF</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yiheng Tao, Yihe Zhang, Matthew T. Dearing, Xin Wang, Yuping Fan, Zhiling Lan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>CAFL-L: Constraint-Aware Federated Learning with Lagrangian Dual Optimization for On-Device Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03298</link>
   <description>We introduce Constraint-Aware Federated Learning with Lagrangian Dual Optimization (CAFL-L), a principled extension of FedAvg that explicitly incorporates device-level resource constraints including energy, communication, memory, and thermal budgets. CAFL-L employs Lagrangian dual optimization to dynamically adapt training hyperparameters -- freezing depth, local steps, batch size, and communication compression -- while preserving training stability through token-budget preservation via gradient accumulation. Experiments on a character-level language model demonstrate that CAFL-L achieves superior constraint satisfaction compared to standard FedAvg (reducing memory usage by 20% and communication by 95%) while maintaining competitive validation performance, making it practical for deployment on resource-constrained edge devices.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.03298v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Dongqi Zheng, Wenjin Fu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>SketchGuard: Scaling Byzantine-Robust Decentralized Federated Learning via Sketch-Based Screening</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07922</link>
   <description>Decentralized Federated Learning (DFL) enables privacy-preserving collaborative training without centralized servers, but remains vulnerable to Byzantine attacks where malicious clients submit corrupted model updates. Existing Byzantine-robust DFL defenses rely on similarity-based neighbor screening that requires every client to exchange and compare complete high-dimensional model vectors with all neighbors in each training round, creating prohibitive communication and computational costs that prevent deployment at web scale. We propose SketchGuard, a general framework that decouples Byzantine filtering from model aggregation through sketch-based neighbor screening. SketchGuard compresses $d$-dimensional models to $k$-dimensional sketches ($k \ll d$) using Count Sketch for similarity comparisons, then selectively fetches full models only from accepted neighbors, reducing per-round communication complexity from $O(d|N_i|)$ to $O(k|N_i| + d|S_i|)$, where $|N_i|$ is the neighbor count and $|S_i| \le |N_i|$ is the accepted neighbor count. We establish rigorous convergence guarantees in both strongly convex and non-convex settings, proving that Count Sketch compression preserves Byzantine resilience with controlled degradation bounds where approximation errors introduce only a $(1+O(\epsilon))$ factor in the effective threshold parameter. Comprehensive experiments across multiple datasets, network topologies, and attack scenarios demonstrate that SketchGuard maintains identical robustness to state-of-the-art methods while reducing computation time by up to 82% and communication overhead by 50-70% depending on filtering effectiveness, with benefits scaling multiplicatively with model dimensionality and network connectivity. These results establish the viability of sketch-based compression as a fundamental enabler of robust DFL at web scale.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.07922v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Murtaza Rangwala, Farag Azzedin, Richard O. Sinnott, Rajkumar Buyya</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>StatEval: A Comprehensive Benchmark for Large Language Models in Statistics</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09517</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable advances in mathematical and logical reasoning, yet statistics, as a distinct and integrative discipline, remains underexplored in benchmarking efforts. To address this gap, we introduce \textbf{StatEval}, the first comprehensive benchmark dedicated to statistics, spanning both breadth and depth across difficulty levels. StatEval consists of 13,817 foundational problems covering undergraduate and graduate curricula, together with 2374 research-level proof tasks extracted from leading journals. To construct the benchmark, we design a scalable multi-agent pipeline with human-in-the-loop validation that automates large-scale problem extraction, rewriting, and quality control, while ensuring academic rigor. We further propose a robust evaluation framework tailored to both computational and proof-based tasks, enabling fine-grained assessment of reasoning ability. Experimental results reveal that while closed-source models such as GPT5-mini achieve below 57\% on research-level problems, with open-source models performing significantly lower. These findings highlight the unique challenges of statistical reasoning and the limitations of current LLMs. We expect StatEval to serve as a rigorous benchmark for advancing statistical intelligence in large language models. All data and code are available on our web platform: https://stateval.github.io/.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.09517v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yuchen Lu, Run Yang, Yichen Zhang, Shuguang Yu, Runpeng Dai, Ziwei Wang, Jiayi Xiang, Wenxin E, Siran Gao, Xinyao Ruan, Yirui Huang, Chenjing Xi, Haibo Hu, Yueming Fu, Qinglan Yu, Xiaobing Wei, Jiani Gu, Rui Sun, Jiaxuan Jia, Fan Zhou</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>When to Reason: Semantic Router for vLLM</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08731</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) demonstrate substantial accuracy gains when augmented with reasoning modes such as chain-of-thought and inference-time scaling. However, reasoning also incurs significant costs in inference latency and token usage, with environmental and financial impacts, which are unnecessary for many simple prompts. We present a semantic router that classifies queries based on their reasoning requirements and selectively applies reasoning only when beneficial. Our approach achieves a 10.2 percentage point improvement in accuracy on the MMLU-Pro benchmark while reducing response latency by 47.1% and token consumption by 48.5% compared to direct inference with vLLM. These results demonstrate that semantic routing offers an effective mechanism for striking a balance between accuracy and efficiency in open-source LLM serving systems</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.08731v1</guid>
   <category>cs.ET</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.SY</category>
   <category>eess.SY</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chen Wang, Xunzhuo Liu, Yuhan Liu, Yue Zhu, Xiangxi Mo, Junchen Jiang, Huamin Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Exploring Cross-Client Memorization of Training Data in Large Language Models for Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08750</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) enables collaborative training without raw data sharing, but still risks training data memorization. Existing FL memorization detection techniques focus on one sample at a time, underestimating more subtle risks of cross-sample memorization. In contrast, recent work on centralized learning (CL) has introduced fine-grained methods to assess memorization across all samples in training data, but these assume centralized access to data and cannot be applied directly to FL. We bridge this gap by proposing a framework that quantifies both intra- and inter-client memorization in FL using fine-grained cross-sample memorization measurement across all clients. Based on this framework, we conduct two studies: (1) measuring subtle memorization across clients and (2) examining key factors that influence memorization, including decoding strategies, prefix length, and FL algorithms. Our findings reveal that FL models do memorize client data, particularly intra-client data, more than inter-client data, with memorization influenced by training and inferencing factors.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.08750v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Tinnakit Udsa, Can Udomcharoenchaikit, Patomporn Payoungkhamdee, Sarana Nutanong, Norrathep Rattanavipanon</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LiveOIBench: Can Large Language Models Outperform Human Contestants in Informatics Olympiads?</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09595</link>
   <description>Competitive programming problems increasingly serve as valuable benchmarks to evaluate the coding capabilities of large language models (LLMs) due to their complexity and ease of verification. Yet, current coding benchmarks face limitations such as lack of exceptionally challenging problems, insufficient test case coverage, reliance on online platform APIs that limit accessibility. To address these issues, we introduce LiveOIBench, a comprehensive benchmark featuring 403 expert-curated Olympiad-level competitive programming problems, each with an average of 60 expert-designed test cases. The problems are sourced directly from 72 official Informatics Olympiads in different regions conducted between 2023 and 2025. LiveOIBench distinguishes itself through four key features: (1) meticulously curated high-quality tasks with detailed subtask rubrics and extensive private test cases; (2) direct integration of elite contestant performance data to enable informative comparison against top-performing humans; (3) planned continuous, contamination-free updates from newly released Olympiad problems; and (4) a self-contained evaluation system facilitating offline and easy-to-reproduce assessments. Benchmarking 32 popular general-purpose and reasoning LLMs, we find that GPT-5 achieves a notable 81.76th percentile, a strong result that nonetheless falls short of top human contestant performance, who usually place above 90th. In contrast, among open-weight reasoning models, GPT-OSS-120B achieves only a 60th percentile, underscoring significant capability disparities from frontier closed models. Detailed analyses indicate that robust reasoning models prioritize precise problem analysis over excessive exploration, suggesting future models should emphasize structured analysis and minimize unnecessary exploration. All data, code, and leaderboard results will be made publicly available on our website.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.09595v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kaijian Zou, Aaron Xiong, Yunxiang Zhang, Frederick Zhang, Yueqi Ren, Jirong Yang, Ayoung Lee, Shitanshu Bhushan, Lu Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>COMPACT: Common-token Optimized Model Pruning Across Channels and Tokens</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06836</link>
   <description>Making large language models (LLMs) more efficient in memory, latency, and serving cost is crucial for edge deployment, interactive applications, and sustainable inference at scale. Pruning is a promising technique, but existing pruning methods are limited: width pruning often breaks the standard transformer layout, requiring custom inference code, while depth pruning can cause abrupt accuracy drops. Also, while many pruning approaches are effective against LLMs, they struggle to maintain performance on small language models (SLMs). In this work, we propose COMPACT, which jointly (i) prunes rare vocabulary to shrink embedding/LM head layers and (ii) prunes FFN intermediate channels using common-token-weighted activations, aligning importance with the post-pruning token distribution. COMPACT inherits strengths of both depth and width pruning, such as: deployment-friendliness (keeps a standard transformer architecture), scale-adaptivity (trade off vocab. vs. FFN pruning), competitive pruning times, and strong memory savings alongside throughput gains. Experiments across Qwen, LLaMA, and Gemma families (0.5B-70B) show state-of-the-art downstream performance, with substantial reductions in parameters, GPU memory, and latency.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.06836v3</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Eugene Kwek, Wenpeng Yin</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>CAFL-L: Constraint-Aware Federated Learning with Lagrangian Dual Optimization for On-Device Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03298</link>
   <description>We introduce Constraint-Aware Federated Learning with Lagrangian Dual Optimization (CAFL-L), a principled extension of FedAvg that explicitly incorporates device-level resource constraints including energy, communication, memory, and thermal budgets. CAFL-L employs Lagrangian dual optimization to dynamically adapt training hyperparameters -- freezing depth, local steps, batch size, and communication compression -- while preserving training stability through token-budget preservation via gradient accumulation. Experiments on a character-level language model demonstrate that CAFL-L achieves superior constraint satisfaction compared to standard FedAvg (reducing memory usage by 20% and communication by 95%) while maintaining competitive validation performance, making it practical for deployment on resource-constrained edge devices.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.03298v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Dongqi Zheng, Wenjin Fu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>P2P: A Poison-to-Poison Remedy for Reliable Backdoor Defense in LLMs</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04503</link>
   <description>During fine-tuning, large language models (LLMs) are increasingly vulnerable to data-poisoning backdoor attacks, which compromise their reliability and trustworthiness. However, existing defense strategies suffer from limited generalization: they only work on specific attack types or task settings. In this study, we propose Poison-to-Poison (P2P), a general and effective backdoor defense algorithm. P2P injects benign triggers with safe alternative labels into a subset of training samples and fine-tunes the model on this re-poisoned dataset by leveraging prompt-based learning. This enforces the model to associate trigger-induced representations with safe outputs, thereby overriding the effects of original malicious triggers. Thanks to this robust and generalizable trigger-based fine-tuning, P2P is effective across task settings and attack types. Theoretically and empirically, we show that P2P can neutralize malicious backdoors while preserving task performance. We conduct extensive experiments on classification, mathematical reasoning, and summary generation tasks, involving multiple state-of-the-art LLMs. The results demonstrate that our P2P algorithm significantly reduces the attack success rate compared with baseline models. We hope that the P2P can serve as a guideline for defending against backdoor attacks and foster the development of a secure and trustworthy LLM community.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.04503v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shuai Zhao, Xinyi Wu, Shiqian Zhao, Xiaobao Wu, Zhongliang Guo, Yanhao Jia, Anh Tuan Luu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Model-Driven Engineering Approach to AI-Powered Healthcare Platforms</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09308</link>
   <description>Artificial intelligence (AI) has the potential to transform healthcare by supporting more accurate diagnoses and personalized treatments. However, its adoption in practice remains constrained by fragmented data sources, strict privacy rules, and the technical complexity of building reliable clinical systems. To address these challenges, we introduce a model driven engineering (MDE) framework designed specifically for healthcare AI. The framework relies on formal metamodels, domain-specific languages (DSLs), and automated transformations to move from high level specifications to running software. At its core is the Medical Interoperability Language (MILA), a graphical DSL that enables clinicians and data scientists to define queries and machine learning pipelines using shared ontologies. When combined with a federated learning architecture, MILA allows institutions to collaborate without exchanging raw patient data, ensuring semantic consistency across sites while preserving privacy. We evaluate this approach in a multi center cancer immunotherapy study. The generated pipelines delivered strong predictive performance, with support vector machines achieving up to 98.5 percent and 98.3 percent accuracy in key tasks, while substantially reducing manual coding effort. These findings suggest that MDE principles metamodeling, semantic integration, and automated code generation can provide a practical path toward interoperable, reproducible, and trustworthy digital health platforms.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.09308v1</guid>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mira Raheem, Amal Elgammal, Michael Papazoglou, Bernd Kr\&quot;amer, Neamat El-Tazi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Automating eHMI Action Design with LLMs for Automated Vehicle Communication</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20711</link>
   <description>The absence of explicit communication channels between automated vehicles (AVs) and other road users requires the use of external Human-Machine Interfaces (eHMIs) to convey messages effectively in uncertain scenarios. Currently, most eHMI studies employ predefined text messages and manually designed actions to perform these messages, which limits the real-world deployment of eHMIs, where adaptability in dynamic scenarios is essential. Given the generalizability and versatility of large language models (LLMs), they could potentially serve as automated action designers for the message-action design task. To validate this idea, we make three contributions: (1) We propose a pipeline that integrates LLMs and 3D renderers, using LLMs as action designers to generate executable actions for controlling eHMIs and rendering action clips. (2) We collect a user-rated Action-Design Scoring dataset comprising a total of 320 action sequences for eight intended messages and four representative eHMI modalities. The dataset validates that LLMs can translate intended messages into actions close to a human level, particularly for reasoning-enabled LLMs. (3) We introduce two automated raters, Action Reference Score (ARS) and Vision-Language Models (VLMs), to benchmark 18 LLMs, finding that the VLM aligns with human preferences yet varies across eHMI modalities.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.20711v2</guid>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <category>cs.RO</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ding Xia, Xinyue Gui, Fan Gao, Dongyuan Li, Mark Colley, Takeo Igarashi</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
