<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2024 04:14:17 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2024 04:14:17 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>More than Chit-Chat: Developing Robots for Small-Talk Interactions</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18023</link>
   <description>Beyond mere formality, small talk plays a pivotal role in social dynamics, serving as a verbal handshake for building rapport and understanding. For conversational AI and social robots, the ability to engage in small talk enhances their perceived sociability, leading to more comfortable and natural user interactions. In this study, we evaluate the capacity of current Large Language Models (LLMs) to drive the small talk of a social robot and identify key areas for improvement. We introduce a novel method that autonomously generates feedback and ensures LLM-generated responses align with small talk conventions. Through several evaluations -- involving chatbot interactions and human-robot interactions -- we demonstrate the system's effectiveness in guiding LLM-generated responses toward realistic, human-like, and natural small-talk exchanges.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18023v1</guid>
   <category>cs.RO</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Rebecca Ramnauth, Dra\v{z}en Br\v{s}\v{c}i\'c, Brian Scassellati</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Tackling the Dynamicity in a Production LLM Serving System with SOTA Optimizations via Hybrid Prefill/Decode/Verify Scheduling on Efficient Meta-kernels</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18106</link>
   <description>Meeting growing demands for low latency and cost efficiency in production-grade large language model (LLM) serving systems requires integrating advanced optimization techniques. However, dynamic and unpredictable input-output lengths of LLM, compounded by these optimizations, exacerbate the issues of workload variability, making it difficult to maintain high efficiency on AI accelerators, especially DSAs with tile-based programming models. To address this challenge, we introduce XY-Serve, a versatile, Ascend native, end-to-end production LLM-serving system. The core idea is an abstraction mechanism that smooths out the workload variability by decomposing computations into unified, hardware-friendly, fine-grained meta primitives. For attention, we propose a meta-kernel that computes the basic pattern of matmul-softmax-matmul with architectural-aware tile sizes. For GEMM, we introduce a virtual padding scheme that adapts to dynamic shape changes while using highly efficient GEMM primitives with assorted fixed tile sizes. XY-Serve sits harmoniously with vLLM. Experimental results show up to 89% end-to-end throughput improvement compared with current publicly available baselines on Ascend NPUs. Additionally, our approach outperforms existing GEMM (average 14.6% faster) and attention (average 21.5% faster) kernels relative to existing libraries. While the work is Ascend native, we believe the approach can be readily applicable to SIMT architectures as well.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18106v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mingcong Song, Xinru Tang, Fengfan Hou, Jing Li, Wei Wei, Yipeng Ma, Runqiu Xiao, Hongjie Si, Dingcheng Jiang, Shouyi Yin, Yang Hu, Guoping Long</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>AutoDroid-V2: Boosting SLM-based GUI Agents via Code Generation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18116</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) have brought exciting new advances to mobile UI agents, a long-standing research field that aims to complete arbitrary natural language tasks through mobile UI interactions. However, existing UI agents usually demand high reasoning capabilities of powerful large models that are difficult to be deployed locally on end-users' devices, which raises huge concerns about user privacy and centralized serving cost. One way to reduce the required model size is to customize a smaller domain-specific model with high-quality training data, e.g. large-scale human demonstrations of diverse types of apps and tasks, while such datasets are extremely difficult to obtain. Inspired by the remarkable coding abilities of recent small language models (SLMs), we propose to convert the UI task automation problem to a code generation problem, which can be effectively solved by an on-device SLM and efficiently executed with an on-device code interpreter. Unlike normal coding tasks that can be extensively pretrained with public datasets, generating UI automation code is challenging due to the diversity, complexity, and variability of target apps. Therefore, we adopt a document-centered approach that automatically builds fine-grained API documentation for each app and generates diverse task samples based on this documentation. By guiding the agent with the synthetic documents and task samples, it learns to generate precise and efficient scripts to complete unseen tasks. Based on detailed comparisons with state-of-the-art mobile UI agents, our approach effectively improves the mobile task automation with significantly higher success rates and lower latency/token consumption. Code will be open-sourced.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18116v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hao Wen, Shizuo Tian, Borislav Pavlov, Wenjie Du, Yixuan Li, Ge Chang, Shanhui Zhao, Jiacheng Liu, Yunxin Liu, Ya-Qin Zhang, Yuanchun Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>More than Chit-Chat: Developing Robots for Small-Talk Interactions</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18023</link>
   <description>Beyond mere formality, small talk plays a pivotal role in social dynamics, serving as a verbal handshake for building rapport and understanding. For conversational AI and social robots, the ability to engage in small talk enhances their perceived sociability, leading to more comfortable and natural user interactions. In this study, we evaluate the capacity of current Large Language Models (LLMs) to drive the small talk of a social robot and identify key areas for improvement. We introduce a novel method that autonomously generates feedback and ensures LLM-generated responses align with small talk conventions. Through several evaluations -- involving chatbot interactions and human-robot interactions -- we demonstrate the system's effectiveness in guiding LLM-generated responses toward realistic, human-like, and natural small-talk exchanges.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18023v1</guid>
   <category>cs.RO</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Rebecca Ramnauth, Dra\v{z}en Br\v{s}\v{c}i\'c, Brian Scassellati</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>KunServe: Elastic and Efficient Large Language Model Serving with Parameter-centric Memory Management</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18169</link>
   <description>The stateful nature of large language model (LLM) servingcan easily throttle precious GPU memory under load burstor long-generation requests like chain-of-thought reasoning,causing latency spikes due to queuing incoming requests. However, state-of-the-art KVCache centric approaches handleload spikes by dropping, migrating, or swapping KVCache,which faces an essential tradeoff between the performance ofongoing vs. incoming requests and thus still severely violatesSLO.This paper makes a key observation such that model param-eters are independent of the requests and are replicated acrossGPUs, and thus proposes a parameter-centric approach byselectively dropping replicated parameters to leave preciousmemory for requests. However, LLM requires KVCache tobe saved in bound with model parameters and thus droppingparameters can cause either huge computation waste or longnetwork delay, affecting all ongoing requests. Based on the ob-servation that attention operators can be decoupled from otheroperators, this paper further proposes a novel remote attentionmechanism through pipeline parallelism so as to serve up-coming requests with the additional memory borrowed fromparameters on remote GPUs. This paper further addresses sev-eral other challenges including lively exchanging KVCachewith incomplete parameters, generating an appropriate planthat balances memory requirements with cooperative exe-cution overhead, and seamlessly restoring parameters whenthe throttling has gone. Evaluations show thatKUNSERVEreduces the tail TTFT of requests under throttling by up to 27.3x compared to the state-of-the-art.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18169v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Rongxin Cheng, Yifan Peng, Yuxin Lai, Xingda Wei, Rong Chen, Haibo Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>An Automatic Graph Construction Framework based on Large Language Models for Recommendation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18241</link>
   <description>Graph neural networks (GNNs) have emerged as state-of-the-art methods to learn from graph-structured data for recommendation. However, most existing GNN-based recommendation methods focus on the optimization of model structures and learning strategies based on pre-defined graphs, neglecting the importance of the graph construction stage. Earlier works for graph construction usually rely on speciffic rules or crowdsourcing, which are either too simplistic or too labor-intensive. Recent works start to utilize large language models (LLMs) to automate the graph construction, in view of their abundant open-world knowledge and remarkable reasoning capabilities. Nevertheless, they generally suffer from two limitations: (1) invisibility of global view (e.g., overlooking contextual information) and (2) construction inefficiency. To this end, we introduce AutoGraph, an automatic graph construction framework based on LLMs for recommendation. Specifically, we first use LLMs to infer the user preference and item knowledge, which is encoded as semantic vectors. Next, we employ vector quantization to extract the latent factors from the semantic vectors. The latent factors are then incorporated as extra nodes to link the user/item nodes, resulting in a graph with in-depth global-view semantics. We further design metapath-based message aggregation to effectively aggregate the semantic and collaborative information. The framework is model-agnostic and compatible with different backbone models. Extensive experiments on three real-world datasets demonstrate the efficacy and efffciency of AutoGraph compared to existing baseline methods. We have deployed AutoGraph in Huawei advertising platform, and gain a 2.69% improvement on RPM and a 7.31% improvement on eCPM in the online A/B test. Currently AutoGraph has been used as the main trafffc model, serving hundreds of millions of people.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18241v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Rong Shan, Jianghao Lin, Chenxu Zhu, Bo Chen, Menghui Zhu, Kangning Zhang, Jieming Zhu, Ruiming Tang, Yong Yu, Weinan Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Addressing Spatial-Temporal Data Heterogeneity in Federated Continual Learning via Tail Anchor</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18355</link>
   <description>Federated continual learning (FCL) allows each client to continually update its knowledge from task streams, enhancing the applicability of federated learning in real-world scenarios. However, FCL needs to address not only spatial data heterogeneity between clients but also temporal data heterogeneity between tasks. In this paper, empirical experiments demonstrate that such input-level heterogeneity significantly affects the model's internal parameters and outputs, leading to severe spatial-temporal catastrophic forgetting of local and previous knowledge. To this end, we propose Federated Tail Anchor (FedTA) to mix trainable Tail Anchor with the frozen output features to adjust their position in the feature space, thereby overcoming parameter-forgetting and output-forgetting. Moreover, three novel components are also included in FedTA: Input Enhancement for improving the performance of pre-trained models on downstream tasks; Selective Input Knowledge Fusion for fusion of heterogeneous local knowledge on the server side; and Best Global Prototype Selection for finding the best anchor point for each class in the feature space. Extensive experiments demonstrate that FedTA not only outperforms existing FCL methods but also effectively preserves the relative positions of features, remaining unaffected by spatial and temporal changes.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18355v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hao Yu, Xin Yang, Le Zhang, Hanlin Gu, Tianrui Li, Lixin Fan, Qiang Yang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>GeFL: Model-Agnostic Federated Learning with Generative Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18460</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) is a promising paradigm in distributed learning while preserving the privacy of users. However, the increasing size of recent models makes it unaffordable for a few users to encompass the model. It leads the users to adopt heterogeneous models based on their diverse computing capabilities and network bandwidth. Correspondingly, FL with heterogeneous models should be addressed, given that FL typically involves training a single global model. In this paper, we propose Generative Model-Aided Federated Learning (GeFL), incorporating a generative model that aggregates global knowledge across users of heterogeneous models. Our experiments on various classification tasks demonstrate notable performance improvements of GeFL compared to baselines, as well as limitations in terms of privacy and scalability. To tackle these concerns, we introduce a novel framework, GeFL-F. It trains target networks aided by feature-generative models. We empirically demonstrate the consistent performance gains of GeFL-F, while demonstrating better privacy preservation and robustness to a large number of clients. Codes are available at [1].</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18460v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Honggu Kang, Seohyeon Cha, Joonhyuk Kang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Bridging Data Islands: Geographic Heterogeneity-Aware Federated Learning for Collaborative Remote Sensing Semantic Segmentation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09292</link>
   <description>Remote sensing semantic segmentation (RSS) is an essential technology in earth observation missions. Due to concerns over geographic information security, data privacy, storage bottleneck and industry competition, high-quality annotated remote sensing images are often isolated and distributed across institutions. The issue of remote sensing data islands poses challenges for fully utilizing isolated datasets to train a global model. Federated learning (FL), a privacy-preserving distributed collaborative learning technology, offers a potential solution to leverage isolated remote sensing data. Typically, remote sensing images from different institutions exhibit significant geographic heterogeneity, characterized by coupled class-distribution heterogeneity and object-appearance heterogeneity. However, existing FL methods lack consideration of them, leading to a decline in the performance of the global model when FL is directly applied to RSS. We propose a novel Geographic heterogeneity-aware Federated learning (GeoFed) framework to bridge data islands in RSS. Our framework consists of three modules, including the Global Insight Enhancement (GIE) module, the Essential Feature Mining (EFM) module and the Local-Global Balance (LoGo) module. Through the GIE module, class distribution heterogeneity is alleviated by introducing a prior global class distribution vector. We design an EFM module to alleviate object appearance heterogeneity by constructing essential features. Furthermore, the LoGo module enables the model to possess both global generalization capability and local adaptation. Extensive experiments on three public datasets (i.e., FedFBP, FedCASID, FedInria) demonstrate that our GeoFed framework consistently outperforms the current state-of-the-art methods.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2404.09292v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jieyi Tan, Yansheng Li, Sergey A. Bartalev, Shinkarenko Stanislav, Bo Dang, Yongjun Zhang, Liangqi Yuan, Wei Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Enhancing LLM-based Hatred and Toxicity Detection with Meta-Toxic Knowledge Graph</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15268</link>
   <description>The rapid growth of social media platforms has raised significant concerns regarding online content toxicity. When Large Language Models (LLMs) are used for toxicity detection, two key challenges emerge: 1) the absence of domain-specific toxic knowledge leads to false negatives; 2) the excessive sensitivity of LLMs to toxic speech results in false positives, limiting freedom of speech. To address these issues, we propose a novel method called MetaTox, leveraging graph search on a meta-toxic knowledge graph to enhance hatred and toxicity detection. First, we construct a comprehensive meta-toxic knowledge graph by utilizing LLMs to extract toxic information through a three-step pipeline, with toxic benchmark datasets serving as corpora. Second, we query the graph via retrieval and ranking processes to supplement accurate, relevant toxic knowledge. Extensive experiments and in-depth case studies across multiple datasets demonstrate that our MetaTox significantly decreases the false positive rate while boosting overall toxicity detection performance. Our code will be available soon.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.15268v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yibo Zhao, Jiapeng Zhu, Can Xu, Xiang Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Exploring Embedding Priors in Prompt-Tuning for Improved Interpretability and Control</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18582</link>
   <description>Prompt-Tuning is an efficient method for adapting pre-trained language models to new tasks with minimal computational overhead by modifying prompt embeddings. In this work, we investigate how crucial the phenomenon of embedding collapse, frequently observed in Prompt-Tuning, is for the final performance of the model. To address this question, we designed embedding priors and compared them with posteriors of the converged Soft and Deep Prompt-Tuning methods. Our findings suggest that priors strongly affect the position of the tuned embeddings, and models can effectively work with embeddings from different parts of activation spaces, including completely new regions. As the final Prompt-Tuning capabilities are limited, we hypothesize that controllable Prompt-Tuning posteriors may serve as a good starting point for tasks such as chain-of-thought (COT) distillation. Our experiments also show that generated trajectories are not localized in the activation space of the models. However, there are distinct clusters of activations for distant tasks (e.g., NLP and arithmetic), while activations between NLP tasks (e.g., Question-Answering and MLM) lie in the same cluster. These observations raise questions about the importance of a single activation cluster for the generalization abilities of large language models.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18582v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sergey Sedov, Sumanth Bharadwaj Hachalli Karanam, Venu Gopal Kadamba</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Large Language Model Safety: A Holistic Survey</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17686</link>
   <description>The rapid development and deployment of large language models (LLMs) have introduced a new frontier in artificial intelligence, marked by unprecedented capabilities in natural language understanding and generation. However, the increasing integration of these models into critical applications raises substantial safety concerns, necessitating a thorough examination of their potential risks and associated mitigation strategies.
  This survey provides a comprehensive overview of the current landscape of LLM safety, covering four major categories: value misalignment, robustness to adversarial attacks, misuse, and autonomous AI risks. In addition to the comprehensive review of the mitigation methodologies and evaluation resources on these four aspects, we further explore four topics related to LLM safety: the safety implications of LLM agents, the role of interpretability in enhancing LLM safety, the technology roadmaps proposed and abided by a list of AI companies and institutes for LLM safety, and AI governance aimed at LLM safety with discussions on international cooperation, policy proposals, and prospective regulatory directions.
  Our findings underscore the necessity for a proactive, multifaceted approach to LLM safety, emphasizing the integration of technical solutions, ethical considerations, and robust governance frameworks. This survey is intended to serve as a foundational resource for academy researchers, industry practitioners, and policymakers, offering insights into the challenges and opportunities associated with the safe integration of LLMs into society. Ultimately, it seeks to contribute to the safe and beneficial development of LLMs, aligning with the overarching goal of harnessing AI for societal advancement and well-being. A curated list of related papers has been publicly available at https://github.com/tjunlp-lab/Awesome-LLM-Safety-Papers.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.17686v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Dan Shi, Tianhao Shen, Yufei Huang, Zhigen Li, Yongqi Leng, Renren Jin, Chuang Liu, Xinwei Wu, Zishan Guo, Linhao Yu, Ling Shi, Bojian Jiang, Deyi Xiong</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Enhancing LLM-based Hatred and Toxicity Detection with Meta-Toxic Knowledge Graph</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15268</link>
   <description>The rapid growth of social media platforms has raised significant concerns regarding online content toxicity. When Large Language Models (LLMs) are used for toxicity detection, two key challenges emerge: 1) the absence of domain-specific toxic knowledge leads to false negatives; 2) the excessive sensitivity of LLMs to toxic speech results in false positives, limiting freedom of speech. To address these issues, we propose a novel method called MetaTox, leveraging graph search on a meta-toxic knowledge graph to enhance hatred and toxicity detection. First, we construct a comprehensive meta-toxic knowledge graph by utilizing LLMs to extract toxic information through a three-step pipeline, with toxic benchmark datasets serving as corpora. Second, we query the graph via retrieval and ranking processes to supplement accurate, relevant toxic knowledge. Extensive experiments and in-depth case studies across multiple datasets demonstrate that our MetaTox significantly decreases the false positive rate while boosting overall toxicity detection performance. Our code will be available soon.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.15268v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yibo Zhao, Jiapeng Zhu, Can Xu, Xiang Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>More than Chit-Chat: Developing Robots for Small-Talk Interactions</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18023</link>
   <description>Beyond mere formality, small talk plays a pivotal role in social dynamics, serving as a verbal handshake for building rapport and understanding. For conversational AI and social robots, the ability to engage in small talk enhances their perceived sociability, leading to more comfortable and natural user interactions. In this study, we evaluate the capacity of current Large Language Models (LLMs) to drive the small talk of a social robot and identify key areas for improvement. We introduce a novel method that autonomously generates feedback and ensures LLM-generated responses align with small talk conventions. Through several evaluations -- involving chatbot interactions and human-robot interactions -- we demonstrate the system's effectiveness in guiding LLM-generated responses toward realistic, human-like, and natural small-talk exchanges.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18023v1</guid>
   <category>cs.RO</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Rebecca Ramnauth, Dra\v{z}en Br\v{s}\v{c}i\'c, Brian Scassellati</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>An Automatic Graph Construction Framework based on Large Language Models for Recommendation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18241</link>
   <description>Graph neural networks (GNNs) have emerged as state-of-the-art methods to learn from graph-structured data for recommendation. However, most existing GNN-based recommendation methods focus on the optimization of model structures and learning strategies based on pre-defined graphs, neglecting the importance of the graph construction stage. Earlier works for graph construction usually rely on speciffic rules or crowdsourcing, which are either too simplistic or too labor-intensive. Recent works start to utilize large language models (LLMs) to automate the graph construction, in view of their abundant open-world knowledge and remarkable reasoning capabilities. Nevertheless, they generally suffer from two limitations: (1) invisibility of global view (e.g., overlooking contextual information) and (2) construction inefficiency. To this end, we introduce AutoGraph, an automatic graph construction framework based on LLMs for recommendation. Specifically, we first use LLMs to infer the user preference and item knowledge, which is encoded as semantic vectors. Next, we employ vector quantization to extract the latent factors from the semantic vectors. The latent factors are then incorporated as extra nodes to link the user/item nodes, resulting in a graph with in-depth global-view semantics. We further design metapath-based message aggregation to effectively aggregate the semantic and collaborative information. The framework is model-agnostic and compatible with different backbone models. Extensive experiments on three real-world datasets demonstrate the efficacy and efffciency of AutoGraph compared to existing baseline methods. We have deployed AutoGraph in Huawei advertising platform, and gain a 2.69% improvement on RPM and a 7.31% improvement on eCPM in the online A/B test. Currently AutoGraph has been used as the main trafffc model, serving hundreds of millions of people.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18241v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Rong Shan, Jianghao Lin, Chenxu Zhu, Bo Chen, Menghui Zhu, Kangning Zhang, Jieming Zhu, Ruiming Tang, Yong Yu, Weinan Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>GeFL: Model-Agnostic Federated Learning with Generative Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18460</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) is a promising paradigm in distributed learning while preserving the privacy of users. However, the increasing size of recent models makes it unaffordable for a few users to encompass the model. It leads the users to adopt heterogeneous models based on their diverse computing capabilities and network bandwidth. Correspondingly, FL with heterogeneous models should be addressed, given that FL typically involves training a single global model. In this paper, we propose Generative Model-Aided Federated Learning (GeFL), incorporating a generative model that aggregates global knowledge across users of heterogeneous models. Our experiments on various classification tasks demonstrate notable performance improvements of GeFL compared to baselines, as well as limitations in terms of privacy and scalability. To tackle these concerns, we introduce a novel framework, GeFL-F. It trains target networks aided by feature-generative models. We empirically demonstrate the consistent performance gains of GeFL-F, while demonstrating better privacy preservation and robustness to a large number of clients. Codes are available at [1].</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18460v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Honggu Kang, Seohyeon Cha, Joonhyuk Kang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>An Empirical Analysis of Federated Learning Models Subject to Label-Flipping Adversarial Attack</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18507</link>
   <description>In this paper, we empirically analyze adversarial attacks on selected federated learning models. The specific learning models considered are Multinominal Logistic Regression (MLR), Support Vector Classifier (SVC), Multilayer Perceptron (MLP), Convolution Neural Network (CNN), %Recurrent Neural Network (RNN), Random Forest, XGBoost, and Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM). For each model, we simulate label-flipping attacks, experimenting extensively with 10 federated clients and 100 federated clients. We vary the percentage of adversarial clients from 10% to 100% and, simultaneously, the percentage of labels flipped by each adversarial client is also varied from 10% to 100%. Among other results, we find that models differ in their inherent robustness to the two vectors in our label-flipping attack, i.e., the percentage of adversarial clients, and the percentage of labels flipped by each adversarial client. We discuss the potential practical implications of our results.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18507v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kunal Bhatnagar, Sagana Chattanathan, Angela Dang, Bhargav Eranki, Ronnit Rana, Charan Sridhar, Siddharth Vedam, Angie Yao, Mark Stamp</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedGIG: Graph Inversion from Gradient in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18513</link>
   <description>Recent studies have shown that Federated learning (FL) is vulnerable to Gradient Inversion Attacks (GIA), which can recover private training data from shared gradients. However, existing methods are designed for dense, continuous data such as images or vectorized texts, and cannot be directly applied to sparse and discrete graph data. This paper first explores GIA's impact on Federated Graph Learning (FGL) and introduces Graph Inversion from Gradient in Federated Learning (FedGIG), a novel GIA method specifically designed for graph-structured data. FedGIG includes the adjacency matrix constraining module, which ensures the sparsity and discreteness of the reconstructed graph data, and the subgraph reconstruction module, which is designed to complete missing common subgraph structures. Extensive experiments on molecular datasets demonstrate FedGIG's superior accuracy over existing GIA techniques.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18513v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Tianzhe Xiao, Yichen Li, Yining Qi, Haozhao Wang, Ruixuan Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedVCK: Non-IID Robust and Communication-Efficient Federated Learning via Valuable Condensed Knowledge for Medical Image Analysis</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18557</link>
   <description>Federated learning has become a promising solution for collaboration among medical institutions. However, data owned by each institution would be highly heterogeneous and the distribution is always non-independent and identical distribution (non-IID), resulting in client drift and unsatisfactory performance. Despite existing federated learning methods attempting to solve the non-IID problems, they still show marginal advantages but rely on frequent communication which would incur high costs and privacy concerns. In this paper, we propose a novel federated learning method: \textbf{Fed}erated learning via \textbf{V}aluable \textbf{C}ondensed \textbf{K}nowledge (FedVCK). We enhance the quality of condensed knowledge and select the most necessary knowledge guided by models, to tackle the non-IID problem within limited communication budgets effectively. Specifically, on the client side, we condense the knowledge of each client into a small dataset and further enhance the condensation procedure with latent distribution constraints, facilitating the effective capture of high-quality knowledge. During each round, we specifically target and condense knowledge that has not been assimilated by the current model, thereby preventing unnecessary repetition of homogeneous knowledge and minimizing the frequency of communications required. On the server side, we propose relational supervised contrastive learning to provide more supervision signals to aid the global model updating. Comprehensive experiments across various medical tasks show that FedVCK can outperform state-of-the-art methods, demonstrating that it's non-IID robust and communication-efficient.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18557v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Guochen Yan, Luyuan Xie, Xinyi Gao, Wentao Zhang, Qingni Shen, Yuejian Fang, Zhonghai Wu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Addressing Spatial-Temporal Data Heterogeneity in Federated Continual Learning via Tail Anchor</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18355</link>
   <description>Federated continual learning (FCL) allows each client to continually update its knowledge from task streams, enhancing the applicability of federated learning in real-world scenarios. However, FCL needs to address not only spatial data heterogeneity between clients but also temporal data heterogeneity between tasks. In this paper, empirical experiments demonstrate that such input-level heterogeneity significantly affects the model's internal parameters and outputs, leading to severe spatial-temporal catastrophic forgetting of local and previous knowledge. To this end, we propose Federated Tail Anchor (FedTA) to mix trainable Tail Anchor with the frozen output features to adjust their position in the feature space, thereby overcoming parameter-forgetting and output-forgetting. Moreover, three novel components are also included in FedTA: Input Enhancement for improving the performance of pre-trained models on downstream tasks; Selective Input Knowledge Fusion for fusion of heterogeneous local knowledge on the server side; and Best Global Prototype Selection for finding the best anchor point for each class in the feature space. Extensive experiments demonstrate that FedTA not only outperforms existing FCL methods but also effectively preserves the relative positions of features, remaining unaffected by spatial and temporal changes.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18355v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hao Yu, Xin Yang, Le Zhang, Hanlin Gu, Tianrui Li, Lixin Fan, Qiang Yang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Exploring Embedding Priors in Prompt-Tuning for Improved Interpretability and Control</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18582</link>
   <description>Prompt-Tuning is an efficient method for adapting pre-trained language models to new tasks with minimal computational overhead by modifying prompt embeddings. In this work, we investigate how crucial the phenomenon of embedding collapse, frequently observed in Prompt-Tuning, is for the final performance of the model. To address this question, we designed embedding priors and compared them with posteriors of the converged Soft and Deep Prompt-Tuning methods. Our findings suggest that priors strongly affect the position of the tuned embeddings, and models can effectively work with embeddings from different parts of activation spaces, including completely new regions. As the final Prompt-Tuning capabilities are limited, we hypothesize that controllable Prompt-Tuning posteriors may serve as a good starting point for tasks such as chain-of-thought (COT) distillation. Our experiments also show that generated trajectories are not localized in the activation space of the models. However, there are distinct clusters of activations for distant tasks (e.g., NLP and arithmetic), while activations between NLP tasks (e.g., Question-Answering and MLM) lie in the same cluster. These observations raise questions about the importance of a single activation cluster for the generalization abilities of large language models.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18582v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sergey Sedov, Sumanth Bharadwaj Hachalli Karanam, Venu Gopal Kadamba</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Exploring Parameter-Efficient Fine-Tuning to Enable Foundation Models in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01708</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) has emerged as a promising paradigm for enabling the collaborative training of models without centralized access to the raw data on local devices. In the typical FL paradigm (e.g., FedAvg), model weights are sent to and from the server each round to participating clients. Recently, the use of small pre-trained models has been shown to be effective in federated learning optimization and improving convergence. However, recent state-of-the-art pre-trained models are getting more capable but also have more parameters, known as the &quot;Foundation Models.&quot; In conventional FL, sharing the enormous model weights can quickly put a massive communication burden on the system, especially if more capable models are employed. Can we find a solution to enable those strong and readily available pre-trained models in FL to achieve excellent performance while simultaneously reducing the communication burden? To this end, we investigate the use of parameter-efficient fine-tuning in federated learning and thus introduce a new framework: FedPEFT. Specifically, we systemically evaluate the performance of FedPEFT across a variety of client stability, data distribution, and differential privacy settings. By only locally tuning and globally sharing a small portion of the model weights, significant reductions in the total communication overhead can be achieved while maintaining competitive or even better performance in a wide range of federated learning scenarios, providing insight into a new paradigm for practical and effective federated systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2210.01708v5</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Guangyu Sun, Umar Khalid, Matias Mendieta, Pu Wang, Chen Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Tackling Intertwined Data and Device Heterogeneities in Federated Learning with Unlimited Staleness</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.13536</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) can be affected by data and device heterogeneities, caused by clients' different local data distributions and latencies in uploading model updates (i.e., staleness). Traditional schemes consider these heterogeneities as two separate and independent aspects, but this assumption is unrealistic in practical FL scenarios where these heterogeneities are intertwined. In these cases, traditional FL schemes are ineffective, and a better approach is to convert a stale model update into a unstale one. In this paper, we present a new FL framework that ensures the accuracy and computational efficiency of this conversion, hence effectively tackling the intertwined heterogeneities that may cause unlimited staleness in model updates. Our basic idea is to estimate the distributions of clients' local training data from their uploaded stale model updates, and use these estimations to compute unstale client model updates. In this way, our approach does not require any auxiliary dataset nor the clients' local models to be fully trained, and does not incur any additional computation or communication overhead at client devices. We compared our approach with the existing FL strategies on mainstream datasets and models, and showed that our approach can improve the trained model accuracy by up to 25% and reduce the number of required training epochs by up to 35%. Source codes can be found at: https://github.com/pittisl/FL-with-intertwined-heterogeneity.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2309.13536v4</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Haoming Wang, Wei Gao</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FPPL: An Efficient and Non-IID Robust Federated Continual Learning Framework</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01904</link>
   <description>Federated continual learning (FCL) aims to learn from sequential data stream in the decentralized federated learning setting, while simultaneously mitigating the catastrophic forgetting issue in classical continual learning. Existing FCL methods usually employ typical rehearsal mechanisms, which could result in privacy violations or additional onerous storage and computational burdens. In this work, an efficient and non-IID robust federated continual learning framework, called Federated Prototype-Augmented Prompt Learning (FPPL), is proposed. The FPPL can collaboratively learn lightweight prompts augmented by prototypes without rehearsal. On the client side, a fusion function is employed to fully leverage the knowledge contained in task-specific prompts for alleviating catastrophic forgetting. Additionally, global prototypes aggregated from the server are used to obtain unified representation through contrastive learning, mitigating the impact of non-IID-derived data heterogeneity. On the server side, locally uploaded prototypes are utilized to perform debiasing on the classifier, further alleviating the performance degradation caused by both non-IID and catastrophic forgetting. Empirical evaluations demonstrate the effectiveness of FPPL, achieving notable performance with an efficient design while remaining robust to diverse non-IID degrees. Code is available at: https://github.com/ycheoo/FPPL.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2411.01904v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yuchen He, Chuyun Shen, Xiangfeng Wang, Bo Jin</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Addressing Spatial-Temporal Data Heterogeneity in Federated Continual Learning via Tail Anchor</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18355</link>
   <description>Federated continual learning (FCL) allows each client to continually update its knowledge from task streams, enhancing the applicability of federated learning in real-world scenarios. However, FCL needs to address not only spatial data heterogeneity between clients but also temporal data heterogeneity between tasks. In this paper, empirical experiments demonstrate that such input-level heterogeneity significantly affects the model's internal parameters and outputs, leading to severe spatial-temporal catastrophic forgetting of local and previous knowledge. To this end, we propose Federated Tail Anchor (FedTA) to mix trainable Tail Anchor with the frozen output features to adjust their position in the feature space, thereby overcoming parameter-forgetting and output-forgetting. Moreover, three novel components are also included in FedTA: Input Enhancement for improving the performance of pre-trained models on downstream tasks; Selective Input Knowledge Fusion for fusion of heterogeneous local knowledge on the server side; and Best Global Prototype Selection for finding the best anchor point for each class in the feature space. Extensive experiments demonstrate that FedTA not only outperforms existing FCL methods but also effectively preserves the relative positions of features, remaining unaffected by spatial and temporal changes.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18355v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hao Yu, Xin Yang, Le Zhang, Hanlin Gu, Tianrui Li, Lixin Fan, Qiang Yang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Bridging Data Islands: Geographic Heterogeneity-Aware Federated Learning for Collaborative Remote Sensing Semantic Segmentation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09292</link>
   <description>Remote sensing semantic segmentation (RSS) is an essential technology in earth observation missions. Due to concerns over geographic information security, data privacy, storage bottleneck and industry competition, high-quality annotated remote sensing images are often isolated and distributed across institutions. The issue of remote sensing data islands poses challenges for fully utilizing isolated datasets to train a global model. Federated learning (FL), a privacy-preserving distributed collaborative learning technology, offers a potential solution to leverage isolated remote sensing data. Typically, remote sensing images from different institutions exhibit significant geographic heterogeneity, characterized by coupled class-distribution heterogeneity and object-appearance heterogeneity. However, existing FL methods lack consideration of them, leading to a decline in the performance of the global model when FL is directly applied to RSS. We propose a novel Geographic heterogeneity-aware Federated learning (GeoFed) framework to bridge data islands in RSS. Our framework consists of three modules, including the Global Insight Enhancement (GIE) module, the Essential Feature Mining (EFM) module and the Local-Global Balance (LoGo) module. Through the GIE module, class distribution heterogeneity is alleviated by introducing a prior global class distribution vector. We design an EFM module to alleviate object appearance heterogeneity by constructing essential features. Furthermore, the LoGo module enables the model to possess both global generalization capability and local adaptation. Extensive experiments on three public datasets (i.e., FedFBP, FedCASID, FedInria) demonstrate that our GeoFed framework consistently outperforms the current state-of-the-art methods.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2404.09292v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jieyi Tan, Yansheng Li, Sergey A. Bartalev, Shinkarenko Stanislav, Bo Dang, Yongjun Zhang, Liangqi Yuan, Wei Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Exploring Parameter-Efficient Fine-Tuning to Enable Foundation Models in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01708</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) has emerged as a promising paradigm for enabling the collaborative training of models without centralized access to the raw data on local devices. In the typical FL paradigm (e.g., FedAvg), model weights are sent to and from the server each round to participating clients. Recently, the use of small pre-trained models has been shown to be effective in federated learning optimization and improving convergence. However, recent state-of-the-art pre-trained models are getting more capable but also have more parameters, known as the &quot;Foundation Models.&quot; In conventional FL, sharing the enormous model weights can quickly put a massive communication burden on the system, especially if more capable models are employed. Can we find a solution to enable those strong and readily available pre-trained models in FL to achieve excellent performance while simultaneously reducing the communication burden? To this end, we investigate the use of parameter-efficient fine-tuning in federated learning and thus introduce a new framework: FedPEFT. Specifically, we systemically evaluate the performance of FedPEFT across a variety of client stability, data distribution, and differential privacy settings. By only locally tuning and globally sharing a small portion of the model weights, significant reductions in the total communication overhead can be achieved while maintaining competitive or even better performance in a wide range of federated learning scenarios, providing insight into a new paradigm for practical and effective federated systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2210.01708v5</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Guangyu Sun, Umar Khalid, Matias Mendieta, Pu Wang, Chen Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FPPL: An Efficient and Non-IID Robust Federated Continual Learning Framework</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01904</link>
   <description>Federated continual learning (FCL) aims to learn from sequential data stream in the decentralized federated learning setting, while simultaneously mitigating the catastrophic forgetting issue in classical continual learning. Existing FCL methods usually employ typical rehearsal mechanisms, which could result in privacy violations or additional onerous storage and computational burdens. In this work, an efficient and non-IID robust federated continual learning framework, called Federated Prototype-Augmented Prompt Learning (FPPL), is proposed. The FPPL can collaboratively learn lightweight prompts augmented by prototypes without rehearsal. On the client side, a fusion function is employed to fully leverage the knowledge contained in task-specific prompts for alleviating catastrophic forgetting. Additionally, global prototypes aggregated from the server are used to obtain unified representation through contrastive learning, mitigating the impact of non-IID-derived data heterogeneity. On the server side, locally uploaded prototypes are utilized to perform debiasing on the classifier, further alleviating the performance degradation caused by both non-IID and catastrophic forgetting. Empirical evaluations demonstrate the effectiveness of FPPL, achieving notable performance with an efficient design while remaining robust to diverse non-IID degrees. Code is available at: https://github.com/ycheoo/FPPL.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2411.01904v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yuchen He, Chuyun Shen, Xiangfeng Wang, Bo Jin</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>KunServe: Elastic and Efficient Large Language Model Serving with Parameter-centric Memory Management</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18169</link>
   <description>The stateful nature of large language model (LLM) servingcan easily throttle precious GPU memory under load burstor long-generation requests like chain-of-thought reasoning,causing latency spikes due to queuing incoming requests. However, state-of-the-art KVCache centric approaches handleload spikes by dropping, migrating, or swapping KVCache,which faces an essential tradeoff between the performance ofongoing vs. incoming requests and thus still severely violatesSLO.This paper makes a key observation such that model param-eters are independent of the requests and are replicated acrossGPUs, and thus proposes a parameter-centric approach byselectively dropping replicated parameters to leave preciousmemory for requests. However, LLM requires KVCache tobe saved in bound with model parameters and thus droppingparameters can cause either huge computation waste or longnetwork delay, affecting all ongoing requests. Based on the ob-servation that attention operators can be decoupled from otheroperators, this paper further proposes a novel remote attentionmechanism through pipeline parallelism so as to serve up-coming requests with the additional memory borrowed fromparameters on remote GPUs. This paper further addresses sev-eral other challenges including lively exchanging KVCachewith incomplete parameters, generating an appropriate planthat balances memory requirements with cooperative exe-cution overhead, and seamlessly restoring parameters whenthe throttling has gone. Evaluations show thatKUNSERVEreduces the tail TTFT of requests under throttling by up to 27.3x compared to the state-of-the-art.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18169v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Rongxin Cheng, Yifan Peng, Yuxin Lai, Xingda Wei, Rong Chen, Haibo Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Tackling the Dynamicity in a Production LLM Serving System with SOTA Optimizations via Hybrid Prefill/Decode/Verify Scheduling on Efficient Meta-kernels</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18106</link>
   <description>Meeting growing demands for low latency and cost efficiency in production-grade large language model (LLM) serving systems requires integrating advanced optimization techniques. However, dynamic and unpredictable input-output lengths of LLM, compounded by these optimizations, exacerbate the issues of workload variability, making it difficult to maintain high efficiency on AI accelerators, especially DSAs with tile-based programming models. To address this challenge, we introduce XY-Serve, a versatile, Ascend native, end-to-end production LLM-serving system. The core idea is an abstraction mechanism that smooths out the workload variability by decomposing computations into unified, hardware-friendly, fine-grained meta primitives. For attention, we propose a meta-kernel that computes the basic pattern of matmul-softmax-matmul with architectural-aware tile sizes. For GEMM, we introduce a virtual padding scheme that adapts to dynamic shape changes while using highly efficient GEMM primitives with assorted fixed tile sizes. XY-Serve sits harmoniously with vLLM. Experimental results show up to 89% end-to-end throughput improvement compared with current publicly available baselines on Ascend NPUs. Additionally, our approach outperforms existing GEMM (average 14.6% faster) and attention (average 21.5% faster) kernels relative to existing libraries. While the work is Ascend native, we believe the approach can be readily applicable to SIMT architectures as well.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18106v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mingcong Song, Xinru Tang, Fengfan Hou, Jing Li, Wei Wei, Yipeng Ma, Runqiu Xiao, Hongjie Si, Dingcheng Jiang, Shouyi Yin, Yang Hu, Guoping Long</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Tackling Intertwined Data and Device Heterogeneities in Federated Learning with Unlimited Staleness</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.13536</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) can be affected by data and device heterogeneities, caused by clients' different local data distributions and latencies in uploading model updates (i.e., staleness). Traditional schemes consider these heterogeneities as two separate and independent aspects, but this assumption is unrealistic in practical FL scenarios where these heterogeneities are intertwined. In these cases, traditional FL schemes are ineffective, and a better approach is to convert a stale model update into a unstale one. In this paper, we present a new FL framework that ensures the accuracy and computational efficiency of this conversion, hence effectively tackling the intertwined heterogeneities that may cause unlimited staleness in model updates. Our basic idea is to estimate the distributions of clients' local training data from their uploaded stale model updates, and use these estimations to compute unstale client model updates. In this way, our approach does not require any auxiliary dataset nor the clients' local models to be fully trained, and does not incur any additional computation or communication overhead at client devices. We compared our approach with the existing FL strategies on mainstream datasets and models, and showed that our approach can improve the trained model accuracy by up to 25% and reduce the number of required training epochs by up to 35%. Source codes can be found at: https://github.com/pittisl/FL-with-intertwined-heterogeneity.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2309.13536v4</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Haoming Wang, Wei Gao</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
