<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 02:49:07 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 02:49:07 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>FinBloom: Knowledge Grounding Large Language Model with Real-time Financial Data</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18471</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) excel at generating human-like responses but often struggle with interactive tasks that require access to real-time information. This limitation poses challenges in finance, where models must access up-to-date information, such as recent news or price movements, to support decision-making. To address this, we introduce Financial Agent, a knowledge-grounding approach for LLMs to handle financial queries using real-time text and tabular data. Our contributions are threefold: First, we develop a Financial Context Dataset of over 50,000 financial queries paired with the required context. Second, we train FinBloom 7B, a custom 7 billion parameter LLM, on 14 million financial news articles from Reuters and Deutsche Presse-Agentur, alongside 12 million Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) filings. Third, we fine-tune FinBloom 7B using the Financial Context Dataset to serve as a Financial Agent. This agent generates relevant financial context, enabling efficient real-time data retrieval to answer user queries. By reducing latency and eliminating the need for users to manually provide accurate data, our approach significantly enhances the capability of LLMs to handle dynamic financial tasks. Our proposed approach makes real-time financial decisions, algorithmic trading and other related tasks streamlined, and is valuable in contexts with high-velocity data flows.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.18471v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>q-fin.ST</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ankur Sinha, Chaitanya Agarwal, Pekka Malo</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>H-FLTN: A Privacy-Preserving Hierarchical Framework for Electric Vehicle Spatio-Temporal Charge Prediction</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18697</link>
   <description>The widespread adoption of Electric Vehicles (EVs) poses critical challenges for energy providers, particularly in predicting charging time (temporal prediction), ensuring user privacy, and managing resources efficiently in mobility-driven networks. This paper introduces the Hierarchical Federated Learning Transformer Network (H-FLTN) framework to address these challenges. H-FLTN employs a three-tier hierarchical architecture comprising EVs, community Distributed Energy Resource Management Systems (DERMS), and the Energy Provider Data Centre (EPDC) to enable accurate spatio-temporal predictions of EV charging needs while preserving privacy. Temporal prediction is enhanced using Transformer-based learning, capturing complex dependencies in charging behavior. Privacy is ensured through Secure Aggregation, Additive Secret Sharing, and Peer-to-Peer (P2P) Sharing with Augmentation, which allow only secret shares of model weights to be exchanged while securing all transmissions. To improve training efficiency and resource management, H-FLTN integrates Dynamic Client Capping Mechanism (DCCM) and Client Rotation Management (CRM), ensuring that training remains both computationally and temporally efficient as the number of participating EVs increases. DCCM optimises client participation by limiting excessive computational loads, while CRM balances training contributions across epochs, preventing imbalanced participation. Our simulation results based on large-scale empirical vehicle mobility data reveal that DCCM and CRM reduce the training time complexity with increasing EVs from linear to constant. Its integration into real-world smart city infrastructure enhances energy demand forecasting, resource allocation, and grid stability, ensuring reliability and sustainability in future mobility ecosystems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.18697v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Robert Marlin, Raja Jurdak, Alsharif Abuadbba</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Robust Over-the-Air Computation with Type-Based Multiple Access</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19014</link>
   <description>This paper utilizes the properties of type-based multiple access (TBMA) to investigate its effectiveness as a robust approach for over-the-air computation (AirComp) in the presence of Byzantine attacks, this is, adversarial strategies where malicious nodes intentionally distort their transmissions to corrupt the aggregated result. Unlike classical direct aggregation (DA) AirComp, which aggregates data in the amplitude of the signals and are highly vulnerable to attacks, TBMA distributes data over multiple radio resources, enabling the receiver to construct a histogram representation of the transmitted data. This structure allows the integration of classical robust estimators and supports the computation of diverse functions beyond the arithmetic mean, which is not feasible with DA. Through extensive simulations, we demonstrate that robust TBMA significantly outperforms DA, maintaining high accuracy even under adversarial conditions, and showcases its applicability in federated learning (FEEL) scenarios. Additionally, TBMA reduces channel state information (CSI) requirements, lowers energy consumption, and enhances resiliency by leveraging the diversity of the transmitted data. These results establish TBMA as a scalable and robust solution for AirComp, paving the way for secure and efficient aggregation in next-generation networks.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.19014v1</guid>
   <category>eess.SP</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Marc Martinez-Gost, Ana P\'erez-Neira, Miguel \'Angel Lagunas</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LW-FedSSL: Resource-efficient Layer-wise Federated Self-supervised Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.11647</link>
   <description>Many studies integrate federated learning (FL) with self-supervised learning (SSL) to take advantage of raw data distributed across edge devices. However, edge devices often struggle with high computational and communication costs imposed by SSL and FL algorithms. With the deployment of more complex and large-scale models, such as Transformers, these challenges are exacerbated. To tackle this, we propose the Layer-Wise Federated Self-Supervised Learning (LW-FedSSL) approach, which allows edge devices to incrementally train a small part of the model at a time. Specifically, in LW-FedSSL, training is decomposed into multiple stages, with each stage responsible for only a specific layer (or a block of layers) of the model. Since only a portion of the model is active for training at any given time, LW-FedSSL significantly reduces computational requirements. Additionally, only the active model portion needs to be exchanged between the FL server and clients, reducing the communication overhead. This enables LW-FedSSL to jointly address both computational and communication challenges in FL. Depending on the SSL algorithm used, it can achieve up to a $3.34 \times$ reduction in memory usage, $4.20 \times$ fewer computational operations (GFLOPs), and a $5.07 \times$ lower communication cost while maintaining performance comparable to its end-to-end training counterpart. Furthermore, we explore a progressive training strategy called Prog-FedSSL, which offers a $1.84\times$ reduction in GFLOPs and a $1.67\times$ reduction in communication costs while maintaining the same memory requirements as end-to-end training. While the resource efficiency of Prog-FedSSL is lower than that of LW-FedSSL, its performance improvements make it a viable candidate for FL environments with more lenient resource constraints.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2401.11647v4</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ye Lin Tun, Chu Myaet Thwal, Huy Q. Le, Minh N. H. Nguyen, Choong Seon Hong</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Mixed-Precision Federated Learning via Multi-Precision Over-The-Air Aggregation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.03402</link>
   <description>Over-the-Air Federated Learning (OTA-FL) is a privacy-preserving distributed learning mechanism, by aggregating updates in the electromagnetic channel rather than at the server. A critical research gap in existing OTA-FL research is the assumption of homogeneous client computational bit precision. While in real world application, clients with varying hardware resources may exploit approximate computing (AxC) to operate at different bit precisions optimized for energy and computational efficiency. And model updates of various precisions amongst clients poses an open challenge for OTA-FL, as it is incompatible in the wireless modulation superposition. Here, we propose an mixed-precision OTA-FL framework of clients with multiple bit precisions, demonstrating the following innovations: (i) the superior trade-off for both server and clients within the constraints of varying edge computing capabilities, energy efficiency, and learning accuracy requirements comparing to homogeneous client bit precision, and (ii) a multi-precision gradient modulation scheme to ensure compatibility with OTA aggregation and eliminate the overheads of precision conversion. Through case study with real world data, we validate our modulation scheme that enables AxC based mixed-precision OTA-FL. In comparison to homogeneous standard precision of 32-bit and 16-bit, our framework presents more than 10% in 4-bit ultra low precision client performance and over 65%and 13% of energy savings respectively. This demonstrates the great potential of our mixed-precision OTA-FL approach in heterogeneous edge computing environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2406.03402v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jinsheng Yuan, Zhuangkun Wei, Weisi Guo</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>From Exploration to Mastery: Enabling LLMs to Master Tools via Self-Driven Interactions</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08197</link>
   <description>Tool learning enables Large Language Models (LLMs) to interact with external environments by invoking tools, serving as an effective strategy to mitigate the limitations inherent in their pre-training data. In this process, tool documentation plays a crucial role by providing usage instructions for LLMs, thereby facilitating effective tool utilization. This paper concentrates on the critical challenge of bridging the comprehension gap between LLMs and external tools due to the inadequacies and inaccuracies inherent in existing human-centric tool documentation. We propose a novel framework, DRAFT, aimed at Dynamically Refining tool documentation through the Analysis of Feedback and Trials emanating from LLMs' interactions with external tools. This methodology pivots on an innovative trial-and-error approach, consisting of three distinct learning phases: experience gathering, learning from experience, and documentation rewriting, to iteratively enhance the tool documentation. This process is further optimized by implementing a diversity-promoting exploration strategy to ensure explorative diversity and a tool-adaptive termination mechanism to prevent overfitting while enhancing efficiency. Extensive experiments on multiple datasets demonstrate that DRAFT's iterative, feedback-based refinement significantly ameliorates documentation quality, fostering a deeper comprehension and more effective utilization of tools by LLMs. Notably, our analysis reveals that the tool documentation refined via our approach demonstrates robust cross-model generalization capabilities.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.08197v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Changle Qu, Sunhao Dai, Xiaochi Wei, Hengyi Cai, Shuaiqiang Wang, Dawei Yin, Jun Xu, Ji-Rong Wen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Predicting Quality of Video Gaming Experience Using Global-Scale Telemetry Data and Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08950</link>
   <description>Frames Per Second (FPS) significantly affects the gaming experience. Providing players with accurate FPS estimates prior to purchase benefits both players and game developers. However, we have a limited understanding of how to predict a game's FPS performance on a specific device. In this paper, we first conduct a comprehensive analysis of a wide range of factors that may affect game FPS on a global-scale dataset to identify the determinants of FPS. This includes player-side and game-side characteristics, as well as country-level socio-economic statistics. Furthermore, recognizing that accurate FPS predictions require extensive user data, which raises privacy concerns, we propose a federated learning-based model to ensure user privacy. Each player and game is assigned a unique learnable knowledge kernel that gradually extracts latent features for improved accuracy. We also introduce a novel training and prediction scheme that allows these kernels to be dynamically plug-and-play, effectively addressing cold start issues. To train this model with minimal bias, we collected a large telemetry dataset from 224 countries and regions, 100,000 users, and 835 games. Our model achieved a mean Wasserstein distance of 0.469 between predicted and ground truth FPS distributions, outperforming all baseline methods.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.08950v3</guid>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhongyang Zhang, Jinhe Wen, Zixi Chen, Dara Arbab, Sruti Sahani, Kent Giard, Bijan Arbab, Haojian Jin, Tauhidur Rahman</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedCDC: A Collaborative Framework for Data Consumers in Federated Learning Market</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19109</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) allows machine learning models to be trained on distributed datasets without directly accessing local data. In FL markets, numerous Data Consumers compete to recruit Data Owners for their respective training tasks, but budget constraints and competition can prevent them from securing sufficient data. While existing solutions focus on optimizing one-to-one matching between Data Owners and Data Consumers, we propose \methodname{}, a novel framework that facilitates collaborative recruitment and training for Data Consumers with similar tasks. Specifically, \methodname{} detects shared subtasks among multiple Data Consumers and coordinates the joint training of submodels specialized for these subtasks. Then, through ensemble distillation, these submodels are integrated into each Data Consumer global model. Experimental evaluations on three benchmark datasets demonstrate that restricting Data Consumers access to Data Owners significantly degrades model performance; however, by incorporating \methodname{}, this performance loss is effectively mitigated, resulting in substantial accuracy gains for all participating Data Consumers.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.19109v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhuan Shi, Patrick Ohl, Boi Faltings</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Differentially Private Federated Learning With Time-Adaptive Privacy Spending</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18706</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) with differential privacy (DP) provides a framework for collaborative machine learning, enabling clients to train a shared model while adhering to strict privacy constraints. The framework allows each client to have an individual privacy guarantee, e.g., by adding different amounts of noise to each client's model updates. One underlying assumption is that all clients spend their privacy budgets uniformly over time (learning rounds). However, it has been shown in the literature that learning in early rounds typically focuses on more coarse-grained features that can be learned at lower signal-to-noise ratios while later rounds learn fine-grained features that benefit from higher signal-to-noise ratios. Building on this intuition, we propose a time-adaptive DP-FL framework that expends the privacy budget non-uniformly across both time and clients. Our framework enables each client to save privacy budget in early rounds so as to be able to spend more in later rounds when additional accuracy is beneficial in learning more fine-grained features. We theoretically prove utility improvements in the case that clients with stricter privacy budgets spend budgets unevenly across rounds, compared to clients with more relaxed budgets, who have sufficient budgets to distribute their spend more evenly. Our practical experiments on standard benchmark datasets support our theoretical results and show that, in practice, our algorithms improve the privacy-utility trade-offs compared to baseline schemes.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.18706v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shahrzad Kiani, Nupur Kulkarni, Adam Dziedzic, Stark Draper, Franziska Boenisch</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>CLLoRA: An Approach to Measure the Effects of the Context Length for LLM Fine-Tuning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18910</link>
   <description>Large language model fine-tuning has been identified as an efficient approach to applying the pre-trained Large language models to other domains. To guarantee data privacy for different data owners, models are often fine-tuned in federated learning environments across different data owners, which often involve data heterogeneity issues and affect the fine-tuning performance. In addition, the length of the context for the training data has been identified as a major factor that affects the LLM's model performance.
  To efficiently measure how the context length affects the LLM's model performance in heterogeneous federated learning environments, we propose CLLoRA. CLLoRA utilizes the parameter-efficient fine-tuning approach LoRA based on different kinds of LLMs with varying sizes as the fine-tuning approach to investigate whether the quality and length of contexts can serve as standards for measuring non-IID context. The findings indicate that an imbalance in context quality not only affects local training on clients but also impacts the global model's performance. However, context length has a minimal effect on local training but a more significant influence on the global model. These results provide insights into how context quality and length affect the model performance for LLM fine-tuning in federated learning environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.18910v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ping Zhang, Zhaorui Zhang, Sheng Di, Yao Xin, Benben Liu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Robust Federated Learning in Unreliable Wireless Networks: A Client Selection Approach</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17260</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) has emerged as a promising distributed learning paradigm for training deep neural networks (DNNs) at the wireless edge, but its performance can be severely hindered by unreliable wireless transmission and inherent data heterogeneity among clients. Existing solutions primarily address these challenges by incorporating wireless resource optimization strategies, often focusing on uplink resource allocation across clients under the assumption of homogeneous client-server network standards. However, these approaches overlooked the fact that mobile clients may connect to the server via diverse network standards (e.g., 4G, 5G, Wi-Fi) with customized configurations, limiting the flexibility of server-side modifications and restricting applicability in real-world commercial networks. This paper presents a novel theoretical analysis about how transmission failures in unreliable networks distort the effective label distributions of local samples, causing deviations from the global data distribution and introducing convergence bias in FL. Our analysis reveals that a carefully designed client selection strategy can mitigate biases induced by network unreliability and data heterogeneity. Motivated by this insight, we propose FedCote, a client selection approach that optimizes client selection probabilities without relying on wireless resource scheduling. Experimental results demonstrate the robustness of FedCote in DNN-based classification tasks under unreliable networks with frequent transmission failures.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.17260v2</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yanmeng Wang, Wenkai Ji, Jian Zhou, Fu Xiao, Tsung-Hui Chang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>H-FLTN: A Privacy-Preserving Hierarchical Framework for Electric Vehicle Spatio-Temporal Charge Prediction</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18697</link>
   <description>The widespread adoption of Electric Vehicles (EVs) poses critical challenges for energy providers, particularly in predicting charging time (temporal prediction), ensuring user privacy, and managing resources efficiently in mobility-driven networks. This paper introduces the Hierarchical Federated Learning Transformer Network (H-FLTN) framework to address these challenges. H-FLTN employs a three-tier hierarchical architecture comprising EVs, community Distributed Energy Resource Management Systems (DERMS), and the Energy Provider Data Centre (EPDC) to enable accurate spatio-temporal predictions of EV charging needs while preserving privacy. Temporal prediction is enhanced using Transformer-based learning, capturing complex dependencies in charging behavior. Privacy is ensured through Secure Aggregation, Additive Secret Sharing, and Peer-to-Peer (P2P) Sharing with Augmentation, which allow only secret shares of model weights to be exchanged while securing all transmissions. To improve training efficiency and resource management, H-FLTN integrates Dynamic Client Capping Mechanism (DCCM) and Client Rotation Management (CRM), ensuring that training remains both computationally and temporally efficient as the number of participating EVs increases. DCCM optimises client participation by limiting excessive computational loads, while CRM balances training contributions across epochs, preventing imbalanced participation. Our simulation results based on large-scale empirical vehicle mobility data reveal that DCCM and CRM reduce the training time complexity with increasing EVs from linear to constant. Its integration into real-world smart city infrastructure enhances energy demand forecasting, resource allocation, and grid stability, ensuring reliability and sustainability in future mobility ecosystems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.18697v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Robert Marlin, Raja Jurdak, Alsharif Abuadbba</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Differentially Private Federated Learning With Time-Adaptive Privacy Spending</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18706</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) with differential privacy (DP) provides a framework for collaborative machine learning, enabling clients to train a shared model while adhering to strict privacy constraints. The framework allows each client to have an individual privacy guarantee, e.g., by adding different amounts of noise to each client's model updates. One underlying assumption is that all clients spend their privacy budgets uniformly over time (learning rounds). However, it has been shown in the literature that learning in early rounds typically focuses on more coarse-grained features that can be learned at lower signal-to-noise ratios while later rounds learn fine-grained features that benefit from higher signal-to-noise ratios. Building on this intuition, we propose a time-adaptive DP-FL framework that expends the privacy budget non-uniformly across both time and clients. Our framework enables each client to save privacy budget in early rounds so as to be able to spend more in later rounds when additional accuracy is beneficial in learning more fine-grained features. We theoretically prove utility improvements in the case that clients with stricter privacy budgets spend budgets unevenly across rounds, compared to clients with more relaxed budgets, who have sufficient budgets to distribute their spend more evenly. Our practical experiments on standard benchmark datasets support our theoretical results and show that, in practice, our algorithms improve the privacy-utility trade-offs compared to baseline schemes.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.18706v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shahrzad Kiani, Nupur Kulkarni, Adam Dziedzic, Stark Draper, Franziska Boenisch</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>CLLoRA: An Approach to Measure the Effects of the Context Length for LLM Fine-Tuning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18910</link>
   <description>Large language model fine-tuning has been identified as an efficient approach to applying the pre-trained Large language models to other domains. To guarantee data privacy for different data owners, models are often fine-tuned in federated learning environments across different data owners, which often involve data heterogeneity issues and affect the fine-tuning performance. In addition, the length of the context for the training data has been identified as a major factor that affects the LLM's model performance.
  To efficiently measure how the context length affects the LLM's model performance in heterogeneous federated learning environments, we propose CLLoRA. CLLoRA utilizes the parameter-efficient fine-tuning approach LoRA based on different kinds of LLMs with varying sizes as the fine-tuning approach to investigate whether the quality and length of contexts can serve as standards for measuring non-IID context. The findings indicate that an imbalance in context quality not only affects local training on clients but also impacts the global model's performance. However, context length has a minimal effect on local training but a more significant influence on the global model. These results provide insights into how context quality and length affect the model performance for LLM fine-tuning in federated learning environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.18910v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ping Zhang, Zhaorui Zhang, Sheng Di, Yao Xin, Benben Liu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FinBloom: Knowledge Grounding Large Language Model with Real-time Financial Data</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18471</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) excel at generating human-like responses but often struggle with interactive tasks that require access to real-time information. This limitation poses challenges in finance, where models must access up-to-date information, such as recent news or price movements, to support decision-making. To address this, we introduce Financial Agent, a knowledge-grounding approach for LLMs to handle financial queries using real-time text and tabular data. Our contributions are threefold: First, we develop a Financial Context Dataset of over 50,000 financial queries paired with the required context. Second, we train FinBloom 7B, a custom 7 billion parameter LLM, on 14 million financial news articles from Reuters and Deutsche Presse-Agentur, alongside 12 million Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) filings. Third, we fine-tune FinBloom 7B using the Financial Context Dataset to serve as a Financial Agent. This agent generates relevant financial context, enabling efficient real-time data retrieval to answer user queries. By reducing latency and eliminating the need for users to manually provide accurate data, our approach significantly enhances the capability of LLMs to handle dynamic financial tasks. Our proposed approach makes real-time financial decisions, algorithmic trading and other related tasks streamlined, and is valuable in contexts with high-velocity data flows.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.18471v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>q-fin.ST</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ankur Sinha, Chaitanya Agarwal, Pekka Malo</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LW-FedSSL: Resource-efficient Layer-wise Federated Self-supervised Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.11647</link>
   <description>Many studies integrate federated learning (FL) with self-supervised learning (SSL) to take advantage of raw data distributed across edge devices. However, edge devices often struggle with high computational and communication costs imposed by SSL and FL algorithms. With the deployment of more complex and large-scale models, such as Transformers, these challenges are exacerbated. To tackle this, we propose the Layer-Wise Federated Self-Supervised Learning (LW-FedSSL) approach, which allows edge devices to incrementally train a small part of the model at a time. Specifically, in LW-FedSSL, training is decomposed into multiple stages, with each stage responsible for only a specific layer (or a block of layers) of the model. Since only a portion of the model is active for training at any given time, LW-FedSSL significantly reduces computational requirements. Additionally, only the active model portion needs to be exchanged between the FL server and clients, reducing the communication overhead. This enables LW-FedSSL to jointly address both computational and communication challenges in FL. Depending on the SSL algorithm used, it can achieve up to a $3.34 \times$ reduction in memory usage, $4.20 \times$ fewer computational operations (GFLOPs), and a $5.07 \times$ lower communication cost while maintaining performance comparable to its end-to-end training counterpart. Furthermore, we explore a progressive training strategy called Prog-FedSSL, which offers a $1.84\times$ reduction in GFLOPs and a $1.67\times$ reduction in communication costs while maintaining the same memory requirements as end-to-end training. While the resource efficiency of Prog-FedSSL is lower than that of LW-FedSSL, its performance improvements make it a viable candidate for FL environments with more lenient resource constraints.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2401.11647v4</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ye Lin Tun, Chu Myaet Thwal, Huy Q. Le, Minh N. H. Nguyen, Choong Seon Hong</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Mixed-Precision Federated Learning via Multi-Precision Over-The-Air Aggregation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.03402</link>
   <description>Over-the-Air Federated Learning (OTA-FL) is a privacy-preserving distributed learning mechanism, by aggregating updates in the electromagnetic channel rather than at the server. A critical research gap in existing OTA-FL research is the assumption of homogeneous client computational bit precision. While in real world application, clients with varying hardware resources may exploit approximate computing (AxC) to operate at different bit precisions optimized for energy and computational efficiency. And model updates of various precisions amongst clients poses an open challenge for OTA-FL, as it is incompatible in the wireless modulation superposition. Here, we propose an mixed-precision OTA-FL framework of clients with multiple bit precisions, demonstrating the following innovations: (i) the superior trade-off for both server and clients within the constraints of varying edge computing capabilities, energy efficiency, and learning accuracy requirements comparing to homogeneous client bit precision, and (ii) a multi-precision gradient modulation scheme to ensure compatibility with OTA aggregation and eliminate the overheads of precision conversion. Through case study with real world data, we validate our modulation scheme that enables AxC based mixed-precision OTA-FL. In comparison to homogeneous standard precision of 32-bit and 16-bit, our framework presents more than 10% in 4-bit ultra low precision client performance and over 65%and 13% of energy savings respectively. This demonstrates the great potential of our mixed-precision OTA-FL approach in heterogeneous edge computing environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2406.03402v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jinsheng Yuan, Zhuangkun Wei, Weisi Guo</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Gradient Purification: Defense Against Poisoning Attack in Decentralized Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04453</link>
   <description>Decentralized federated learning (DFL) is inherently vulnerable to poisoning attacks, as malicious clients can transmit manipulated model gradients to neighboring clients. Existing defense methods either reject suspicious gradients per iteration or restart DFL aggregation after detecting all malicious clients. They overlook the potential accuracy benefit from the discarded malicious gradients. In this paper, we propose a novel gradient purification defense, named GPD, that integrates seamlessly with existing DFL aggregation to defend against poisoning attacks. It aims to mitigate the harm in model gradients while retaining the benefit in model weights for enhancing accuracy. For each benign client in GPD, a recording variable is designed to track the historically aggregated gradients from one of its neighbors. It allows benign clients to precisely detect malicious neighbors and swiftly mitigate aggregated malicious gradients via historical consistency checks. Upon mitigation, GPD optimizes model weights via aggregating gradients solely from benign clients. This retains the previously beneficial portions from malicious clients and exploits the contributions from benign clients, thereby significantly enhancing the model accuracy. We analyze the convergence of GPD, as well as its ability to harvest high accuracy. Extensive experiments over three datasets demonstrate that, GPD is capable of mitigating poisoning attacks under both iid and non-iid data distributions. It significantly outperforms state-of-the-art defenses in terms of accuracy against various poisoning attacks.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.04453v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Bin Li, Xiaoye Miao, Yan Zhang, Jianwei Yin</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Robust Federated Learning in Unreliable Wireless Networks: A Client Selection Approach</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17260</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) has emerged as a promising distributed learning paradigm for training deep neural networks (DNNs) at the wireless edge, but its performance can be severely hindered by unreliable wireless transmission and inherent data heterogeneity among clients. Existing solutions primarily address these challenges by incorporating wireless resource optimization strategies, often focusing on uplink resource allocation across clients under the assumption of homogeneous client-server network standards. However, these approaches overlooked the fact that mobile clients may connect to the server via diverse network standards (e.g., 4G, 5G, Wi-Fi) with customized configurations, limiting the flexibility of server-side modifications and restricting applicability in real-world commercial networks. This paper presents a novel theoretical analysis about how transmission failures in unreliable networks distort the effective label distributions of local samples, causing deviations from the global data distribution and introducing convergence bias in FL. Our analysis reveals that a carefully designed client selection strategy can mitigate biases induced by network unreliability and data heterogeneity. Motivated by this insight, we propose FedCote, a client selection approach that optimizes client selection probabilities without relying on wireless resource scheduling. Experimental results demonstrate the robustness of FedCote in DNN-based classification tasks under unreliable networks with frequent transmission failures.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.17260v2</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yanmeng Wang, Wenkai Ji, Jian Zhou, Fu Xiao, Tsung-Hui Chang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FinBloom: Knowledge Grounding Large Language Model with Real-time Financial Data</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18471</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) excel at generating human-like responses but often struggle with interactive tasks that require access to real-time information. This limitation poses challenges in finance, where models must access up-to-date information, such as recent news or price movements, to support decision-making. To address this, we introduce Financial Agent, a knowledge-grounding approach for LLMs to handle financial queries using real-time text and tabular data. Our contributions are threefold: First, we develop a Financial Context Dataset of over 50,000 financial queries paired with the required context. Second, we train FinBloom 7B, a custom 7 billion parameter LLM, on 14 million financial news articles from Reuters and Deutsche Presse-Agentur, alongside 12 million Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) filings. Third, we fine-tune FinBloom 7B using the Financial Context Dataset to serve as a Financial Agent. This agent generates relevant financial context, enabling efficient real-time data retrieval to answer user queries. By reducing latency and eliminating the need for users to manually provide accurate data, our approach significantly enhances the capability of LLMs to handle dynamic financial tasks. Our proposed approach makes real-time financial decisions, algorithmic trading and other related tasks streamlined, and is valuable in contexts with high-velocity data flows.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.18471v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>q-fin.ST</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ankur Sinha, Chaitanya Agarwal, Pekka Malo</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>UQABench: Evaluating User Embedding for Prompting LLMs in Personalized Question Answering</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19178</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) achieve remarkable success in natural language processing (NLP). In practical scenarios like recommendations, as users increasingly seek personalized experiences, it becomes crucial to incorporate user interaction history into the context of LLMs to enhance personalization. However, from a practical utility perspective, user interactions' extensive length and noise present challenges when used directly as text prompts. A promising solution is to compress and distill interactions into compact embeddings, serving as soft prompts to assist LLMs in generating personalized responses. Although this approach brings efficiency, a critical concern emerges: Can user embeddings adequately capture valuable information and prompt LLMs? To address this concern, we propose \name, a benchmark designed to evaluate the effectiveness of user embeddings in prompting LLMs for personalization. We establish a fair and standardized evaluation process, encompassing pre-training, fine-tuning, and evaluation stages. To thoroughly evaluate user embeddings, we design three dimensions of tasks: sequence understanding, action prediction, and interest perception. These evaluation tasks cover the industry's demands in traditional recommendation tasks, such as improving prediction accuracy, and its aspirations for LLM-based methods, such as accurately understanding user interests and enhancing the user experience. We conduct extensive experiments on various state-of-the-art methods for modeling user embeddings. Additionally, we reveal the scaling laws of leveraging user embeddings to prompt LLMs. The benchmark is available online.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.19178v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Langming Liu, Shilei Liu, Yujin Yuan, Yizhen Zhang, Bencheng Yan, Zhiyuan Zeng, Zihao Wang, Jiaqi Liu, Di Wang, Wenbo Su, Pengjie Wang, Jian Xu, Bo Zheng</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Predicting Quality of Video Gaming Experience Using Global-Scale Telemetry Data and Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08950</link>
   <description>Frames Per Second (FPS) significantly affects the gaming experience. Providing players with accurate FPS estimates prior to purchase benefits both players and game developers. However, we have a limited understanding of how to predict a game's FPS performance on a specific device. In this paper, we first conduct a comprehensive analysis of a wide range of factors that may affect game FPS on a global-scale dataset to identify the determinants of FPS. This includes player-side and game-side characteristics, as well as country-level socio-economic statistics. Furthermore, recognizing that accurate FPS predictions require extensive user data, which raises privacy concerns, we propose a federated learning-based model to ensure user privacy. Each player and game is assigned a unique learnable knowledge kernel that gradually extracts latent features for improved accuracy. We also introduce a novel training and prediction scheme that allows these kernels to be dynamically plug-and-play, effectively addressing cold start issues. To train this model with minimal bias, we collected a large telemetry dataset from 224 countries and regions, 100,000 users, and 835 games. Our model achieved a mean Wasserstein distance of 0.469 between predicted and ground truth FPS distributions, outperforming all baseline methods.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.08950v3</guid>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhongyang Zhang, Jinhe Wen, Zixi Chen, Dara Arbab, Sruti Sahani, Kent Giard, Bijan Arbab, Haojian Jin, Tauhidur Rahman</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Predicting Quality of Video Gaming Experience Using Global-Scale Telemetry Data and Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08950</link>
   <description>Frames Per Second (FPS) significantly affects the gaming experience. Providing players with accurate FPS estimates prior to purchase benefits both players and game developers. However, we have a limited understanding of how to predict a game's FPS performance on a specific device. In this paper, we first conduct a comprehensive analysis of a wide range of factors that may affect game FPS on a global-scale dataset to identify the determinants of FPS. This includes player-side and game-side characteristics, as well as country-level socio-economic statistics. Furthermore, recognizing that accurate FPS predictions require extensive user data, which raises privacy concerns, we propose a federated learning-based model to ensure user privacy. Each player and game is assigned a unique learnable knowledge kernel that gradually extracts latent features for improved accuracy. We also introduce a novel training and prediction scheme that allows these kernels to be dynamically plug-and-play, effectively addressing cold start issues. To train this model with minimal bias, we collected a large telemetry dataset from 224 countries and regions, 100,000 users, and 835 games. Our model achieved a mean Wasserstein distance of 0.469 between predicted and ground truth FPS distributions, outperforming all baseline methods.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.08950v3</guid>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhongyang Zhang, Jinhe Wen, Zixi Chen, Dara Arbab, Sruti Sahani, Kent Giard, Bijan Arbab, Haojian Jin, Tauhidur Rahman</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FinBloom: Knowledge Grounding Large Language Model with Real-time Financial Data</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18471</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) excel at generating human-like responses but often struggle with interactive tasks that require access to real-time information. This limitation poses challenges in finance, where models must access up-to-date information, such as recent news or price movements, to support decision-making. To address this, we introduce Financial Agent, a knowledge-grounding approach for LLMs to handle financial queries using real-time text and tabular data. Our contributions are threefold: First, we develop a Financial Context Dataset of over 50,000 financial queries paired with the required context. Second, we train FinBloom 7B, a custom 7 billion parameter LLM, on 14 million financial news articles from Reuters and Deutsche Presse-Agentur, alongside 12 million Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) filings. Third, we fine-tune FinBloom 7B using the Financial Context Dataset to serve as a Financial Agent. This agent generates relevant financial context, enabling efficient real-time data retrieval to answer user queries. By reducing latency and eliminating the need for users to manually provide accurate data, our approach significantly enhances the capability of LLMs to handle dynamic financial tasks. Our proposed approach makes real-time financial decisions, algorithmic trading and other related tasks streamlined, and is valuable in contexts with high-velocity data flows.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.18471v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>q-fin.ST</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ankur Sinha, Chaitanya Agarwal, Pekka Malo</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>From Exploration to Mastery: Enabling LLMs to Master Tools via Self-Driven Interactions</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08197</link>
   <description>Tool learning enables Large Language Models (LLMs) to interact with external environments by invoking tools, serving as an effective strategy to mitigate the limitations inherent in their pre-training data. In this process, tool documentation plays a crucial role by providing usage instructions for LLMs, thereby facilitating effective tool utilization. This paper concentrates on the critical challenge of bridging the comprehension gap between LLMs and external tools due to the inadequacies and inaccuracies inherent in existing human-centric tool documentation. We propose a novel framework, DRAFT, aimed at Dynamically Refining tool documentation through the Analysis of Feedback and Trials emanating from LLMs' interactions with external tools. This methodology pivots on an innovative trial-and-error approach, consisting of three distinct learning phases: experience gathering, learning from experience, and documentation rewriting, to iteratively enhance the tool documentation. This process is further optimized by implementing a diversity-promoting exploration strategy to ensure explorative diversity and a tool-adaptive termination mechanism to prevent overfitting while enhancing efficiency. Extensive experiments on multiple datasets demonstrate that DRAFT's iterative, feedback-based refinement significantly ameliorates documentation quality, fostering a deeper comprehension and more effective utilization of tools by LLMs. Notably, our analysis reveals that the tool documentation refined via our approach demonstrates robust cross-model generalization capabilities.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.08197v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Changle Qu, Sunhao Dai, Xiaochi Wei, Hengyi Cai, Shuaiqiang Wang, Dawei Yin, Jun Xu, Ji-Rong Wen</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
