<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 02:56:46 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 02:56:46 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>Enhancing Air Quality Monitoring: A Brief Review of Federated Learning Advances</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02909</link>
   <description>Monitoring air quality and environmental conditions is crucial for public health and effective urban planning. Current environmental monitoring approaches often rely on centralized data collection and processing, which pose significant privacy, security, and scalability challenges. Federated Learning (FL) offers a promising solution to these limitations by enabling collaborative model training across multiple devices without sharing raw data. This decentralized approach addresses privacy concerns while still leveraging distributed data sources. This paper provides a comprehensive review of FL applications in air quality and environmental monitoring, emphasizing its effectiveness in predicting pollutants and managing environmental data. However, the paper also identifies key limitations of FL when applied in this domain, including challenges such as communication overhead, infrastructure demands, generalizability issues, computational complexity, and security vulnerabilities. For instance, communication overhead, caused by the frequent exchange of model updates between local devices and central servers, is a notable challenge. To address this, future research should focus on optimizing communication protocols and reducing the frequency of updates to lessen the burden on network resources. Additionally, the paper suggests further research directions to refine FL frameworks and enhance their applicability in real-world environmental monitoring scenarios. By synthesizing findings from existing studies, this paper highlights the potential of FL to improve air quality management while maintaining data privacy and security, and it provides valuable insights for future developments in the field.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.02909v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sara Yarham, Mehran Behjati</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Integrating Identity-Based Identification against Adaptive Adversaries in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03077</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) has recently emerged as a promising paradigm for privacy-preserving, distributed machine learning. However, FL systems face significant security threats, particularly from adaptive adversaries capable of modifying their attack strategies to evade detection. One such threat is the presence of Reconnecting Malicious Clients (RMCs), which exploit FLs open connectivity by reconnecting to the system with modified attack strategies. To address this vulnerability, we propose integration of Identity-Based Identification (IBI) as a security measure within FL environments. By leveraging IBI, we enable FL systems to authenticate clients based on cryptographic identity schemes, effectively preventing previously disconnected malicious clients from re-entering the system. Our approach is implemented using the TNC-IBI (Tan-Ng-Chin) scheme over elliptic curves to ensure computational efficiency, particularly in resource-constrained environments like Internet of Things (IoT). Experimental results demonstrate that integrating IBI with secure aggregation algorithms, such as Krum and Trimmed Mean, significantly improves FL robustness by mitigating the impact of RMCs. We further discuss the broader implications of IBI in FL security, highlighting research directions for adaptive adversary detection, reputation-based mechanisms, and the applicability of identity-based cryptographic frameworks in decentralized FL architectures. Our findings advocate for a holistic approach to FL security, emphasizing the necessity of proactive defence strategies against evolving adaptive adversarial threats.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.03077v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jakub Kacper Szelag, Ji-Jian Chin, Lauren Ansell, Sook-Chin Yip</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LLMSched: Uncertainty-Aware Workload Scheduling for Compound LLM Applications</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03444</link>
   <description>Developing compound Large Language Model (LLM) applications is becoming an increasingly prevalent approach to solving real-world problems. In these applications, an LLM collaborates with various external modules, including APIs and even other LLMs, to realize complex intelligent services. However, we reveal that the intrinsic duration and structural uncertainty in compound LLM applications pose great challenges for LLM service providers in serving and scheduling them efficiently. In this paper, we propose LLMSched, an uncertainty-aware scheduling framework for emerging compound LLM applications. In LLMSched, we first design a novel DAG-based model to describe the uncertain compound LLM applications. Then, we adopt the Bayesian network to comprehensively profile compound LLM applications and identify uncertainty-reducing stages, along with an entropy-based mechanism to quantify their uncertainty reduction. Combining an uncertainty reduction strategy and a job completion time (JCT)-efficient scheme, we further propose an efficient scheduler to reduce the average JCT. Evaluation of both simulation and testbed experiments on various representative compound LLM applications shows that compared to existing state-of-the-art scheduling schemes, LLMSched can reduce the average JCT by 14~79%.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.03444v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Botao Zhu, Chen Chen, Xiaoyi Fan, Yifei Zhu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>PPFPL: Cross-silo Privacy-preserving Federated Prototype Learning Against Data Poisoning Attacks on Non-IID Data</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03173</link>
   <description>Privacy-Preserving Federated Learning (PPFL) allows multiple clients to collaboratively train a deep learning model by submitting hidden model updates. Nonetheless, PPFL is vulnerable to data poisoning attacks due to the distributed training nature of clients. Existing solutions have struggled to improve the performance of cross-silo PPFL in poisoned Non-IID data. To address the issues, this paper proposes a privacy-preserving federated prototype learning framework, named PPFPL, which enhances the cross-silo FL performance in poisoned Non-IID data while effectively resisting data poisoning attacks. Specifically, we adopt prototypes as client-submitted model updates to eliminate the impact of tampered data distribution on federated learning. Moreover, we utilize two servers to achieve Byzantine-robust aggregation by secure aggregation protocol, which greatly reduces the impact of malicious clients. Theoretical analyses confirm the convergence of PPFPL, and experimental results on publicly available datasets show that PPFPL is effective for resisting data poisoning attacks with Non-IID conditions.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.03173v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hongliang Zhang, Jiguo Yu, Fenghua Xu, Chunqiang Hu, Yongzhao Zhang, Xiaofen Wang, Zhongyuan Yu, Xiaosong Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Learning in Adversarial Environments: Testbed Design and Poisoning Resilience in Cybersecurity</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09794</link>
   <description>This paper presents the design and implementation of a Federated Learning (FL) testbed, focusing on its application in cybersecurity and evaluating its resilience against poisoning attacks. Federated Learning allows multiple clients to collaboratively train a global model while keeping their data decentralized, addressing critical needs for data privacy and security, particularly in sensitive fields like cybersecurity. Our testbed, built using Raspberry Pi and Nvidia Jetson hardware by running the Flower framework, facilitates experimentation with various FL frameworks, assessing their performance, scalability, and ease of integration. Through a case study on federated intrusion detection systems, the testbed's capabilities are shown in detecting anomalies and securing critical infrastructure without exposing sensitive network data. Comprehensive poisoning tests, targeting both model and data integrity, evaluate the system's robustness under adversarial conditions. The results show that while federated learning enhances data privacy and distributed learning, it remains vulnerable to poisoning attacks, which must be mitigated to ensure its reliability in real-world applications.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2409.09794v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hao Jian Huang, Hakan T. Otal, M. Abdullah Canbaz</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Hierarchical Knowledge Structuring for Effective Federated Learning in Heterogeneous Environments</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03505</link>
   <description>Federated learning enables collaborative model training across distributed entities while maintaining individual data privacy. A key challenge in federated learning is balancing the personalization of models for local clients with generalization for the global model. Recent efforts leverage logit-based knowledge aggregation and distillation to overcome these issues. However, due to the non-IID nature of data across diverse clients and the imbalance in the client's data distribution, directly aggregating the logits often produces biased knowledge that fails to apply to individual clients and obstructs the convergence of local training. To solve this issue, we propose a Hierarchical Knowledge Structuring (HKS) framework that formulates sample logits into a multi-granularity codebook to represent logits from personalized per-sample insights to globalized per-class knowledge. The unsupervised bottom-up clustering method is leveraged to enable the global server to provide multi-granularity responses to local clients. These responses allow local training to integrate supervised learning objectives with global generalization constraints, which results in more robust representations and improved knowledge sharing in subsequent training rounds. The proposed framework's effectiveness is validated across various benchmarks and model architectures.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.03505v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Wai Fong Tam, Qilei Li, Ahmed M. Abdelmonie</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Enhancing Air Quality Monitoring: A Brief Review of Federated Learning Advances</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02909</link>
   <description>Monitoring air quality and environmental conditions is crucial for public health and effective urban planning. Current environmental monitoring approaches often rely on centralized data collection and processing, which pose significant privacy, security, and scalability challenges. Federated Learning (FL) offers a promising solution to these limitations by enabling collaborative model training across multiple devices without sharing raw data. This decentralized approach addresses privacy concerns while still leveraging distributed data sources. This paper provides a comprehensive review of FL applications in air quality and environmental monitoring, emphasizing its effectiveness in predicting pollutants and managing environmental data. However, the paper also identifies key limitations of FL when applied in this domain, including challenges such as communication overhead, infrastructure demands, generalizability issues, computational complexity, and security vulnerabilities. For instance, communication overhead, caused by the frequent exchange of model updates between local devices and central servers, is a notable challenge. To address this, future research should focus on optimizing communication protocols and reducing the frequency of updates to lessen the burden on network resources. Additionally, the paper suggests further research directions to refine FL frameworks and enhance their applicability in real-world environmental monitoring scenarios. By synthesizing findings from existing studies, this paper highlights the potential of FL to improve air quality management while maintaining data privacy and security, and it provides valuable insights for future developments in the field.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.02909v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sara Yarham, Mehran Behjati</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>CacheBlend: Fast Large Language Model Serving for RAG with Cached Knowledge Fusion</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.16444</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) often incorporate multiple text chunks in their inputs to provide the necessary contexts. To speed up the prefill of the long LLM inputs, one can pre-compute the KV cache of a text and re-use the KV cache when the context is reused as the prefix of another LLM input. However, the reused text chunks are not always the input prefix, which makes precomputed KV caches not directly usable since they ignore the text's cross-attention with the preceding texts. Thus, the benefits of reusing KV caches remain largely unrealized.
  This paper tackles just one challenge: when an LLM input contains multiple text chunks, how to quickly combine their precomputed KV caches in order to achieve the same generation quality as the expensive full prefill (i.e., without reusing KV cache)? This challenge naturally arises in retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) where the input is supplemented with multiple retrieved texts as the context. We present CacheBlend, a scheme that reuses the precomputed KV caches, regardless prefix or not, and selectively recomputes the KV values of a small subset of tokens to partially update each reused KV cache. In the meantime, the small extra delay for recomputing some tokens can be pipelined with the retrieval of KV caches within the same job, allowing CacheBlend to store KV caches in slower devices with more storage capacity while retrieving them without increasing the inference delay. By comparing CacheBlend with the state-of-the-art KV cache reusing schemes on three open-source LLMs of various sizes and four popular benchmark datasets of different tasks, we show that CacheBlend reduces time-to-first-token (TTFT) by 2.2-3.3x and increases the inference throughput by 2.8-5x from full KV recompute without compromising generation quality. The code is available at https://github.com/LMCache/LMCache.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2405.16444v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jiayi Yao, Hanchen Li, Yuhan Liu, Siddhant Ray, Yihua Cheng, Qizheng Zhang, Kuntai Du, Shan Lu, Junchen Jiang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>One-Shot Heterogeneous Federated Learning with Local Model-Guided Diffusion Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.08870</link>
   <description>In recent years, One-shot Federated Learning methods based on Diffusion Models have garnered increasing attention due to their remarkable performance. However, most of these methods require the deployment of foundation models on client devices, which significantly raises the computational requirements and reduces their adaptability to heterogeneous client models compared to traditional FL methods. In this paper, we propose FedLMG, a heterogeneous one-shot Federated learning method with Local Model-Guided diffusion models. Briefly speaking, in FedLMG, clients do not need access to any foundation models but only train and upload their local models, which is consistent with traditional FL methods. On the clients, we employ classification loss and BN loss to capture the broad category features and detailed contextual features of the client distributions. On the server, based on the uploaded client models, we utilize backpropagation to guide the server's DM in generating synthetic datasets that comply with the client distributions, which are then used to train the aggregated model. By using the locally trained client models as a medium to transfer client knowledge, our method significantly reduces the computational requirements on client devices and effectively adapts to scenarios with heterogeneous clients. Extensive quantitation and visualization experiments on three large-scale real-world datasets, along with theoretical analysis, demonstrate that the synthetic datasets generated by FedLMG exhibit comparable quality and diversity to the client datasets, which leads to an aggregated model that outperforms all compared methods and even the performance ceiling, further elucidating the significant potential of utilizing DMs in FL.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2311.08870v3</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mingzhao Yang, Shangchao Su, Bin Li, Xiangyang Xue</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Learning in Adversarial Environments: Testbed Design and Poisoning Resilience in Cybersecurity</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09794</link>
   <description>This paper presents the design and implementation of a Federated Learning (FL) testbed, focusing on its application in cybersecurity and evaluating its resilience against poisoning attacks. Federated Learning allows multiple clients to collaboratively train a global model while keeping their data decentralized, addressing critical needs for data privacy and security, particularly in sensitive fields like cybersecurity. Our testbed, built using Raspberry Pi and Nvidia Jetson hardware by running the Flower framework, facilitates experimentation with various FL frameworks, assessing their performance, scalability, and ease of integration. Through a case study on federated intrusion detection systems, the testbed's capabilities are shown in detecting anomalies and securing critical infrastructure without exposing sensitive network data. Comprehensive poisoning tests, targeting both model and data integrity, evaluate the system's robustness under adversarial conditions. The results show that while federated learning enhances data privacy and distributed learning, it remains vulnerable to poisoning attacks, which must be mitigated to ensure its reliability in real-world applications.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2409.09794v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hao Jian Huang, Hakan T. Otal, M. Abdullah Canbaz</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Short-PHD: Detecting Short LLM-generated Text with Topological Data Analysis After Off-topic Content Insertion</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02873</link>
   <description>The malicious usage of large language models (LLMs) has motivated the detection of LLM-generated texts. Previous work in topological data analysis shows that the persistent homology dimension (PHD) of text embeddings can serve as a more robust and promising score than other zero-shot methods. However, effectively detecting short LLM-generated texts remains a challenge. This paper presents Short-PHD, a zero-shot LLM-generated text detection method tailored for short texts. Short-PHD stabilizes the estimation of the previous PHD method for short texts by inserting off-topic content before the given input text and identifies LLM-generated text based on an established detection threshold. Experimental results on both public and generated datasets demonstrate that Short-PHD outperforms existing zero-shot methods in short LLM-generated text detection. Implementation codes are available online.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.02873v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Dongjun Wei, Minjia Mao, Xiao Fang, Michael Chau</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>One-Shot Heterogeneous Federated Learning with Local Model-Guided Diffusion Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.08870</link>
   <description>In recent years, One-shot Federated Learning methods based on Diffusion Models have garnered increasing attention due to their remarkable performance. However, most of these methods require the deployment of foundation models on client devices, which significantly raises the computational requirements and reduces their adaptability to heterogeneous client models compared to traditional FL methods. In this paper, we propose FedLMG, a heterogeneous one-shot Federated learning method with Local Model-Guided diffusion models. Briefly speaking, in FedLMG, clients do not need access to any foundation models but only train and upload their local models, which is consistent with traditional FL methods. On the clients, we employ classification loss and BN loss to capture the broad category features and detailed contextual features of the client distributions. On the server, based on the uploaded client models, we utilize backpropagation to guide the server's DM in generating synthetic datasets that comply with the client distributions, which are then used to train the aggregated model. By using the locally trained client models as a medium to transfer client knowledge, our method significantly reduces the computational requirements on client devices and effectively adapts to scenarios with heterogeneous clients. Extensive quantitation and visualization experiments on three large-scale real-world datasets, along with theoretical analysis, demonstrate that the synthetic datasets generated by FedLMG exhibit comparable quality and diversity to the client datasets, which leads to an aggregated model that outperforms all compared methods and even the performance ceiling, further elucidating the significant potential of utilizing DMs in FL.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2311.08870v3</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mingzhao Yang, Shangchao Su, Bin Li, Xiangyang Xue</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
