<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 04:33:51 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 04:33:51 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>Privacy-Preserving Multi-Stage Fall Detection Framework with Semi-supervised Federated Learning and Robotic Vision Confirmation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10474</link>
   <description>The aging population is growing rapidly, and so is the danger of falls in older adults. A major cause of injury is falling, and detection in time can greatly save medical expenses and recovery time. However, to provide timely intervention and avoid unnecessary alarms, detection systems must be effective and reliable while addressing privacy concerns regarding the user. In this work, we propose a framework for detecting falls using several complementary systems: a semi-supervised federated learning-based fall detection system (SF2D), an indoor localization and navigation system, and a vision-based human fall recognition system. A wearable device and an edge device identify a fall scenario in the first system. On top of that, the second system uses an indoor localization technique first to localize the fall location and then navigate a robot to inspect the scenario. A vision-based detection system running on an edge device with a mounted camera on a robot is used to recognize fallen people. Each of the systems of this proposed framework achieves different accuracy rates. Specifically, the SF2D has a 0.81% failure rate equivalent to 99.19% accuracy, while the vision-based fallen people detection achieves 96.3% accuracy. However, when we combine the accuracy of these two systems with the accuracy of the navigation system (95% success rate), our proposed framework creates a highly reliable performance for fall detection, with an overall accuracy of 99.99%. Not only is the proposed framework safe for older adults, but it is also a privacy-preserving solution for detecting falls.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10474v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.RO</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Seyed Alireza Rahimi Azghadi, Truong-Thanh-Hung Nguyen, Helene Fournier, Monica Wachowicz, Rene Richard, Francis Palma, Hung Cao</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>GI-NAS: Boosting Gradient Inversion Attacks through Adaptive Neural Architecture Search</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20725</link>
   <description>Gradient Inversion Attacks invert the transmitted gradients in Federated Learning (FL) systems to reconstruct the sensitive data of local clients and have raised considerable privacy concerns. A majority of gradient inversion methods rely heavily on explicit prior knowledge (e.g., a well pre-trained generative model), which is often unavailable in realistic scenarios. This is because real-world client data distributions are often highly heterogeneous, domain-specific, and unavailable to attackers, making it impractical for attackers to obtain perfectly matched pre-trained models, which inevitably suffer from fundamental distribution shifts relative to target private data. To alleviate this issue, researchers have proposed to leverage the implicit prior knowledge of an over-parameterized network. However, they only utilize a fixed neural architecture for all the attack settings. This would hinder the adaptive use of implicit architectural priors and consequently limit the generalizability. In this paper, we further exploit such implicit prior knowledge by proposing Gradient Inversion via Neural Architecture Search (GI-NAS), which adaptively searches the network and captures the implicit priors behind neural architectures. Extensive experiments verify that our proposed GI-NAS can achieve superior attack performance compared to state-of-the-art gradient inversion methods, even under more practical settings with high-resolution images, large-sized batches, and advanced defense strategies. To the best of our knowledge, we are the first to successfully introduce NAS to the gradient inversion community. We believe that this work exposes critical vulnerabilities in real-world federated learning by demonstrating high-fidelity reconstruction of sensitive data without requiring domain-specific priors, forcing urgent reassessment of FL privacy safeguards.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2405.20725v3</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Wenbo Yu, Hao Fang, Bin Chen, Xiaohang Sui, Chuan Chen, Hao Wu, Shu-Tao Xia, Ke Xu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Gradients as an Action: Towards Communication-Efficient Federated Recommender Systems via Adaptive Action Sharing</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08842</link>
   <description>As a promising privacy-aware collaborative model training paradigm, Federated Learning (FL) is becoming popular in the design of distributed recommender systems. However, Federated Recommender Systems (FedRecs) greatly suffer from two major problems: i) extremely high communication overhead due to massive item embeddings involved in recommendation systems, and ii) intolerably low training efficiency caused by the entanglement of both heterogeneous network environments and client devices. Although existing methods attempt to employ various compression techniques to reduce communication overhead, due to the parameter errors introduced by model compression, they inevitably suffer from model performance degradation. To simultaneously address the above problems, this paper presents a communication-efficient FedRec framework named FedRAS, which adopts an action-sharing strategy to cluster the gradients of item embedding into a specific number of model updating actions for communication rather than directly compressing the item embeddings. In this way, the cloud server can use the limited actions from clients to update all the items. Since gradient values are significantly smaller than item embeddings, constraining the directions of gradients (i.e., the action space) introduces smaller errors compared to compressing the entire item embedding matrix into a reduced space. To accommodate heterogeneous devices and network environments, FedRAS incorporates an adaptive clustering mechanism that dynamically adjusts the number of actions. Comprehensive experiments on well-known datasets demonstrate that FedRAS can reduce the size of communication payloads by up to 96.88%, while not sacrificing recommendation performance within various heterogeneous scenarios. We have open-sourced FedRAS at https://github.com/mastlab-T3S/FedRAS.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.08842v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhufeng Lu, Chentao Jia, Ming Hu, Xiaofei Xie, Mingsong Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Can We Predict Your Next Move Without Breaking Your Privacy?</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08843</link>
   <description>We propose FLLL3M--Federated Learning with Large Language Models for Mobility Modeling--a privacy-preserving framework for Next-Location Prediction (NxLP). By retaining user data locally and leveraging LLMs through an efficient outer product mechanism, FLLL3M ensures high accuracy with low resource demands. It achieves SOT results on Gowalla (Acc@1: 12.55, MRR: 0.1422), WeePlace (10.71, 0.1285), Brightkite (10.42, 0.1169), and FourSquare (8.71, 0.1023), while reducing parameters by up to 45.6% and memory usage by 52.7%.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.08843v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Arpita Soni, Sahil Tripathi, Gautam Siddharth Kashyap, Manaswi Kulahara, Mohammad Anas Azeez, Zohaib Hasan Siddiqui, Nipun Joshi, Jiechao Gao</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>On Evaluating Performance of LLM Inference Serving Systems</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09019</link>
   <description>The rapid evolution of Large Language Model (LLM) inference systems has yielded significant efficiency improvements. However, our systematic analysis reveals that current evaluation methodologies frequently exhibit fundamental flaws, often manifesting as common evaluation anti-patterns that obscure true performance characteristics and impede scientific progress. Through a comprehensive examination of recent systems, we identify recurring anti-patterns across three key dimensions: Baseline Fairness, Evaluation Setup, and Metric Design. These anti-patterns are uniquely problematic for LLM inference due to its dual-phase nature combining distinct prefill and decode operations, its handling of highly heterogeneous workloads, and its strict temporal requirements for interactive use. We demonstrate how common anti-patterns -- such as inadequate baseline comparisons that conflate engineering effort with algorithmic novelty, workload selections that fail to represent production scenarios, and metric normalizations that hide substantial performance variability like generation stalls-lead to misleading conclusions. To address these challenges, we provide a comprehensive checklist derived from our analysis, establishing a framework for recognizing and avoiding these anti-patterns in favor of robust LLM inference evaluation. To demonstrate the practical application of our framework, we present a case study analyzing speculative decoding, a technique whose bursty, non-uniform token generation is easily misinterpreted when evaluated using approaches characteristic of these anti-patterns. Our work establishes a rigorous foundation for evaluation methodology, enabling meaningful comparisons, ensuring reproducible results, and ultimately accelerating genuine progress in LLM inference systems by moving beyond common anti-patterns to align evaluation with real-world requirements.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09019v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Amey Agrawal, Nitin Kedia, Anmol Agarwal, Jayashree Mohan, Nipun Kwatra, Souvik Kundu, Ramachandran Ramjee, Alexey Tumanov</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Model Parallelism With Subnetwork Data Parallelism</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09029</link>
   <description>Distributed pre-training of large models at scale often imposes heavy memory demands on individual nodes and incurs significant intra-node communication costs. We propose a novel alternative approach that reduces the memory requirements by training small, structured subnetworks of the model on separate workers. Unlike pipelining, our method avoids inter-node activation communication and maintains bandwidth requirements that are comparable to or lower than standard data parallel communication schemes based on all-reduce. We evaluate two subnetwork construction strategies guided by the principle of ensuring uniform representation of each parameter across the distributed training setup. Our results show that the stochastic block dropping technique consistently outperforms the width-wise subnetwork construction previously explored in federated learning. We empirically attribute this superior performance to stronger gradient alignment in subnetworks that retain blocks having skip connections. Preliminary experiments highlight the promise of our approach, achieving a 20-40% reduction in memory usage without any loss in performance.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09029v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Vaibhav Singh, Zafir Khalid, Edouard Oyallon, Eugene Belilovsky</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>DRAGD: A Federated Unlearning Data Reconstruction Attack Based on Gradient Differences</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09602</link>
   <description>Federated learning enables collaborative machine learning while preserving data privacy. However, the rise of federated unlearning, designed to allow clients to erase their data from the global model, introduces new privacy concerns. Specifically, the gradient exchanges during the unlearning process can leak sensitive information about deleted data. In this paper, we introduce DRAGD, a novel attack that exploits gradient discrepancies before and after unlearning to reconstruct forgotten data. We also present DRAGDP, an enhanced version of DRAGD that leverages publicly available prior data to improve reconstruction accuracy, particularly for complex datasets like facial images. Extensive experiments across multiple datasets demonstrate that DRAGD and DRAGDP significantly outperform existing methods in data reconstruction.Our work highlights a critical privacy vulnerability in federated unlearning and offers a practical solution, advancing the security of federated unlearning systems in real-world applications.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09602v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Bocheng Ju, Junchao Fan, Jiaqi Liu, Xiaolin Chang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Cultivating Pluralism In Algorithmic Monoculture: The Community Alignment Dataset</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09650</link>
   <description>How can large language models (LLMs) serve users with varying preferences that may conflict across cultural, political, or other dimensions? To advance this challenge, this paper establishes four key results. First, we demonstrate, through a large-scale multilingual human study with representative samples from five countries (N=15,000), that humans exhibit significantly more variation in preferences than the responses of 21 state-of-the-art LLMs. Second, we show that existing methods for preference dataset collection are insufficient for learning the diversity of human preferences even along two of the most salient dimensions of variability in global values, due to the underlying homogeneity of candidate responses. Third, we argue that this motivates the need for negatively-correlated sampling when generating candidate sets, and we show that simple prompt-based techniques for doing so significantly enhance the performance of alignment methods in learning heterogeneous preferences. Fourth, based on this novel candidate sampling approach, we collect and open-source Community Alignment, the largest and most representative multilingual and multi-turn preference dataset to date, featuring almost 200,000 comparisons from annotators spanning five countries. We hope that the Community Alignment dataset will be a valuable resource for improving the effectiveness of LLMs for a diverse global population.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09650v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Lily Hong Zhang (Wes), Smitha Milli (Wes), Karen Jusko (Wes), Jonathan Smith (Wes), Brandon Amos (Wes),  Wassim (Wes),  Bouaziz, Manon Revel, Jack Kussman, Lisa Titus, Bhaktipriya Radharapu, Jane Yu, Vidya Sarma, Kris Rose, Maximilian Nickel</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Learning with Graph-Based Aggregation for Traffic Forecasting</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09805</link>
   <description>In traffic prediction, the goal is to estimate traffic speed or flow in specific regions or road segments using historical data collected by devices deployed in each area. Each region or road segment can be viewed as an individual client that measures local traffic flow, making Federated Learning (FL) a suitable approach for collaboratively training models without sharing raw data. In centralized FL, a central server collects and aggregates model updates from multiple clients to build a shared model while preserving each client's data privacy. Standard FL methods, such as Federated Averaging (FedAvg), assume that clients are independent, which can limit performance in traffic prediction tasks where spatial relationships between clients are important. Federated Graph Learning methods can capture these dependencies during server-side aggregation, but they often introduce significant computational overhead. In this paper, we propose a lightweight graph-aware FL approach that blends the simplicity of FedAvg with key ideas from graph learning. Rather than training full models, our method applies basic neighbourhood aggregation principles to guide parameter updates, weighting client models based on graph connectivity. This approach captures spatial relationships effectively while remaining computationally efficient. We evaluate our method on two benchmark traffic datasets, METR-LA and PEMS-BAY, and show that it achieves competitive performance compared to standard baselines and recent graph-based federated learning techniques.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09805v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Audri Banik, Glaucio Haroldo Silva de Carvalho, Renata Dividino</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>MTF-Grasp: A Multi-tier Federated Learning Approach for Robotic Grasping</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10158</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) is a promising machine learning paradigm that enables participating devices to train privacy-preserved and collaborative models. FL has proven its benefits for robotic manipulation tasks. However, grasping tasks lack exploration in such settings where robots train a global model without moving data and ensuring data privacy. The main challenge is that each robot learns from data that is nonindependent and identically distributed (non-IID) and of low quantity. This exhibits performance degradation, particularly in robotic grasping. Thus, in this work, we propose MTF-Grasp, a multi-tier FL approach for robotic grasping, acknowledging the unique challenges posed by the non-IID data distribution across robots, including quantitative skewness. MTF-Grasp harnesses data quality and quantity across robots to select a set of &quot;top-level&quot; robots with better data distribution and higher sample count. It then utilizes top-level robots to train initial seed models and distribute them to the remaining &quot;low-level&quot; robots, reducing the risk of model performance degradation in low-level robots. Our approach outperforms the conventional FL setup by up to 8% on the quantity-skewed Cornell and Jacquard grasping datasets.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10158v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.RO</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Obaidullah Zaland, Erik Elmroth, Monowar Bhuyan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Domain Borders Are There to Be Crossed With Federated Few-Shot Adaptation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10160</link>
   <description>Federated Learning has emerged as a leading paradigm for decentralized, privacy-preserving learning, particularly relevant in the era of interconnected edge devices equipped with sensors. However, the practical implementation of Federated Learning faces three primary challenges: the need for human involvement in costly data labelling processes for target adaptation, covariate shift in client device data collection due to environmental factors affecting sensors, leading to discrepancies between source and target samples, and the impracticality of continuous or regular model updates in resource-constrained environments due to limited data transmission capabilities and technical constraints on channel availability and energy efficiency. To tackle these issues, we expand upon an efficient and scalable Federated Learning framework tailored for real-world client adaptation in industrial settings. This framework leverages a pre-trained source model comprising a deep backbone, an adaptation module, and a classifier running on a powerful server. By freezing the backbone and classifier during client adaptation on resource-constrained devices, we allow the domain adaptive linear layer to handle target domain adaptation, thus minimizing overall computational overhead. Furthermore, this setup, designated as FedAcross+, is extended to encompass the processing of streaming data, thereby rendering the solution suitable for non-stationary environments. Extensive experimental results demonstrate the effectiveness of FedAcross+ in achieving competitive adaptation on low-end client devices with limited target samples, successfully addressing the challenge of domain shift. Moreover, our framework accommodates sporadic model updates within resource-constrained environments, ensuring practical and seamless deployment.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10160v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Manuel R\&quot;oder, Christoph Raab, Frank-Michael Schleif</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Convergence of Agnostic Federated Averaging</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10325</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) enables decentralized model training without centralizing raw data. However, practical FL deployments often face a key realistic challenge: Clients participate intermittently in server aggregation and with unknown, possibly biased participation probabilities. Most existing convergence results either assume full-device participation, or rely on knowledge of (in fact uniform) client availability distributions -- assumptions that rarely hold in practice. In this work, we characterize the optimization problem that consistently adheres to the stochastic dynamics of the well-known \emph{agnostic Federated Averaging (FedAvg)} algorithm under random (and variably-sized) client availability, and rigorously establish its convergence for convex, possibly nonsmooth losses, achieving a standard rate of order $\mathcal{O}(1/\sqrt{T})$, where $T$ denotes the aggregation horizon. Our analysis provides the first convergence guarantees for agnostic FedAvg under general, non-uniform, stochastic client participation, without knowledge of the participation distribution. We also empirically demonstrate that agnostic FedAvg in fact outperforms common (and suboptimal) weighted aggregation FedAvg variants, even with server-side knowledge of participation weights.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10325v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>eess.SP</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator> Herlock (SeyedAbolfazl),  Rahimi, Dionysis Kalogerias</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Feature Distillation is the Better Choice for Model-Heterogeneous Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10348</link>
   <description>Model-Heterogeneous Federated Learning (Hetero-FL) has attracted growing attention for its ability to aggregate knowledge from heterogeneous models while keeping private data locally. To better aggregate knowledge from clients, ensemble distillation, as a widely used and effective technique, is often employed after global aggregation to enhance the performance of the global model. However, simply combining Hetero-FL and ensemble distillation does not always yield promising results and can make the training process unstable. The reason is that existing methods primarily focus on logit distillation, which, while being model-agnostic with softmax predictions, fails to compensate for the knowledge bias arising from heterogeneous models. To tackle this challenge, we propose a stable and efficient Feature Distillation for model-heterogeneous Federated learning, dubbed FedFD, that can incorporate aligned feature information via orthogonal projection to integrate knowledge from heterogeneous models better. Specifically, a new feature-based ensemble federated knowledge distillation paradigm is proposed. The global model on the server needs to maintain a projection layer for each client-side model architecture to align the features separately. Orthogonal techniques are employed to re-parameterize the projection layer to mitigate knowledge bias from heterogeneous models and thus maximize the distilled knowledge. Extensive experiments show that FedFD achieves superior performance compared to state-of-the-art methods.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10348v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yichen Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>HedraRAG: Coordinating LLM Generation and Database Retrieval in Heterogeneous RAG Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09138</link>
   <description>This paper addresses emerging system-level challenges in heterogeneous retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) serving, where complex multi-stage workflows and diverse request patterns complicate efficient execution. We present HedraRAG, a runtime system built on a graph-based abstraction that exposes optimization opportunities across stage-level parallelism, intra-request similarity, and inter-request skewness. These opportunities are realized through dynamic graph transformations, such as node splitting, reordering, edge addition, and dependency rewiring, applied to wavefronts of subgraphs spanning concurrent requests. The resulting execution plans are mapped onto hybrid CPU-GPU pipelines to improve resource utilization and reduce latency. Evaluations across a wide range of RAG workflows demonstrate speedups exceeding 1.5x and reaching up to 5x over existing frameworks, showcasing the effectiveness of coordinated generation and retrieval in serving environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09138v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DB</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhengding Hu, Vibha Murthy, Zaifeng Pan, Wanlu Li, Xiaoyi Fang, Yufei Ding, Yuke Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Lightweight Federated Learning over Wireless Edge Networks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09546</link>
   <description>With the exponential growth of smart devices connected to wireless networks, data production is increasing rapidly, requiring machine learning (ML) techniques to unlock its value. However, the centralized ML paradigm raises concerns over communication overhead and privacy. Federated learning (FL) offers an alternative at the network edge, but practical deployment in wireless networks remains challenging. This paper proposes a lightweight FL (LTFL) framework integrating wireless transmission power control, model pruning, and gradient quantization. We derive a closed-form expression of the FL convergence gap, considering transmission error, model pruning error, and gradient quantization error. Based on these insights, we formulate an optimization problem to minimize the convergence gap while meeting delay and energy constraints. To solve the non-convex problem efficiently, we derive closed-form solutions for the optimal model pruning ratio and gradient quantization level, and employ Bayesian optimization for transmission power control. Extensive experiments on real-world datasets show that LTFL outperforms state-of-the-art schemes.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09546v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xiangwang Hou, Jingjing Wang, Jun Du, Chunxiao Jiang, Yong Ren, Dusit Niyato</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>ElasticMM: Efficient Multimodal LLMs Serving with Elastic Multimodal Parallelism</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10069</link>
   <description>Multimodal large language models (MLLMs) extend LLMs to handle images, videos, and audio by incorporating feature extractors and projection modules. However, these additional components -- combined with complex inference pipelines and heterogeneous workloads -- introduce significant inference overhead. Therefore, efficiently serving MLLMs remains a major challenge. Current tightly coupled serving architectures struggle to distinguish between mixed request types or adapt parallelism strategies to different inference stages, leading to increased time-to-first-token (TTFT) latency and poor resource utilization. To address this, we propose Elastic Multimodal Parallelism (EMP), a new serving paradigm that elastically adapts to resource heterogeneity across request types and inference stages. Building upon EMP, we develop ElasticMM, an MLLM serving system that (1) separates requests into independent modality groups with dynamic resource allocation via a modality-aware load balancer; (2) decouples inference stages and enables parallelism adjustment and adaptive scaling via elastic partition scheduling; and (3) improves inference efficiency through unified multimodal prefix caching and non-blocking encoding. Experiments on diverse real-world datasets show that ElasticMM outperforms state-of-the-art (SOTA) serving systems, reducing TTFT by up to 4.2x and achieving 3.2-4.5x higher throughput while meeting service-level objectives (SLOs).</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10069v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zedong Liu, Shenggan Cheng, Guangming Tan, Yang You, Dingwen Tao</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Pimba: A Processing-in-Memory Acceleration for Post-Transformer Large Language Model Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10178</link>
   <description>Transformers are the driving force behind today's Large Language Models (LLMs), serving as the foundation for their performance and versatility. Yet, their compute and memory costs grow with sequence length, posing scalability challenges for long-context inferencing. In response, the algorithm community is exploring alternative architectures, such as state space models (SSMs), linear attention, and recurrent neural networks (RNNs), which we refer to as post-transformers. This shift presents a key challenge: building a serving system that efficiently supports both transformer and post-transformer LLMs within a unified framework. To address this challenge, we analyze the performance characteristics of transformer and post-transformer LLMs. Despite their algorithmic differences, both are fundamentally limited by memory bandwidth under batched inference due to attention in transformers and state updates in post-transformers. Further analyses suggest two additional insights: (1) state update operations, unlike attention, incur high hardware cost, making per-bank PIM acceleration inefficient, and (2) different low-precision arithmetic methods offer varying accuracy-area tradeoffs, while we identify Microsoft's MX as the Pareto-optimal choice. Building on these insights, we design Pimba as an array of State-update Processing Units (SPUs), each shared between two banks to enable interleaved access to PIM. Each SPU includes a State-update Processing Engine (SPE) that comprises element-wise multipliers and adders using MX-based quantized arithmetic, enabling efficient execution of state update and attention operations. Our evaluation shows that, compared to LLM-optimized GPU and GPU+PIM systems, Pimba achieves up to 3.2x and 2.1x higher token generation throughput, respectively.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10178v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Wonung Kim, Yubin Lee, Yoonsung Kim, Jinwoo Hwang, Seongryong Oh, Jiyong Jung, Aziz Huseynov, Woong Gyu Park, Chang Hyun Park, Divya Mahajan, Jongse Park</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Efficient Federated Learning with Heterogeneous Data and Adaptive Dropout</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10430</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) is a promising distributed machine learning approach that enables collaborative training of a global model using multiple edge devices. The data distributed among the edge devices is highly heterogeneous. Thus, FL faces the challenge of data distribution and heterogeneity, where non-Independent and Identically Distributed (non-IID) data across edge devices may yield in significant accuracy drop. Furthermore, the limited computation and communication capabilities of edge devices increase the likelihood of stragglers, thus leading to slow model convergence. In this paper, we propose the FedDHAD FL framework, which comes with two novel methods: Dynamic Heterogeneous model aggregation (FedDH) and Adaptive Dropout (FedAD). FedDH dynamically adjusts the weights of each local model within the model aggregation process based on the non-IID degree of heterogeneous data to deal with the statistical data heterogeneity. FedAD performs neuron-adaptive operations in response to heterogeneous devices to improve accuracy while achieving superb efficiency. The combination of these two methods makes FedDHAD significantly outperform state-of-the-art solutions in terms of accuracy (up to 6.7% higher), efficiency (up to 2.02 times faster), and computation cost (up to 15.0% smaller).</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10430v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ji Liu, Beichen Ma, Yang Zhou, Jingbo Zhou, Ruoming Jin, Dejing Dou, Huaiyu Dai, Haixun Wang, Patrick Valduriez</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Dataset Distillation-based Hybrid Federated Learning on Non-IID Data</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17517</link>
   <description>With the development of edge computing, Federated Learning (FL) has emerged as a promising solution for the intelligent Internet of Things (IoT). However, applying FL in mobile edge-cloud networks is greatly challenged by statistical heterogeneity and high communication overhead. To address it, we propose a hybrid federated learning framework called HFLDD, which integrates dataset distillation to generate approximately independent and equally distributed (IID) data, thereby improving the performance of model training. In particular, we partition the clients into heterogeneous clusters, where the data labels among different clients within a cluster are unbalanced while the data labels among different clusters are balanced. The cluster heads collect distilled data from the corresponding cluster members, and conduct model training in collaboration with the server. This training process is like traditional federated learning on IID data, and hence effectively alleviates the impact of non-IID data on model training. We perform a comprehensive analysis of the convergence behavior, communication overhead, and computational complexity of the proposed HFLDD. Extensive experimental results based on multiple public datasets demonstrate that when data labels are severely imbalanced, the proposed HFLDD outperforms the baseline methods in terms of both test accuracy and communication cost.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2409.17517v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xiufang Shi, Wei Zhang, Mincheng Wu, Guangyi Liu, Zhenyu Wen, Shibo He, Tejal Shah, Rajiv Ranjan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>QFNN-FFD: Quantum Federated Neural Network for Financial Fraud Detection</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02595</link>
   <description>This study introduces the Quantum Federated Neural Network for Financial Fraud Detection (QFNN-FFD), a cutting-edge framework merging Quantum Machine Learning (QML) and quantum computing with Federated Learning (FL) for financial fraud detection. Using quantum technologies' computational power and the robust data privacy protections offered by FL, QFNN-FFD emerges as a secure and efficient method for identifying fraudulent transactions within the financial sector. Implementing a dual-phase training model across distributed clients enhances data integrity and enables superior performance metrics, achieving precision rates consistently above 95%. Additionally, QFNN-FFD demonstrates exceptional resilience by maintaining an impressive 80% accuracy, highlighting its robustness and readiness for real-world applications. This combination of high performance, security, and robustness against noise positions QFNN-FFD as a transformative advancement in financial technology solutions and establishes it as a new benchmark for privacy-focused fraud detection systems. This framework facilitates the broader adoption of secure, quantum-enhanced financial services and inspires future innovations that could use QML to tackle complex challenges in other areas requiring high confidentiality and accuracy.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2404.02595v5</guid>
   <category>quant-ph</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>q-fin.RM</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Nouhaila Innan, Alberto Marchisio, Mohamed Bennai, Muhammad Shafique</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>PREAMBLE: Private and Efficient Aggregation via Block Sparse Vectors</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11897</link>
   <description>We revisit the problem of secure aggregation of high-dimensional vectors in a two-server system such as Prio. These systems are typically used to aggregate vectors such as gradients in private federated learning, where the aggregate itself is protected via noise addition to ensure differential privacy. Existing approaches require communication scaling with the dimensionality, and thus limit the dimensionality of vectors one can efficiently process in this setup.
  We propose PREAMBLE: {\bf Pr}ivate {\bf E}fficient {\bf A}ggregation {\bf M}echanism via {\bf BL}ock-sparse {\bf E}uclidean Vectors. PREAMBLE builds on an extension of distributed point functions that enables communication- and computation-efficient aggregation of {\em block-sparse vectors}, which are sparse vectors where the non-zero entries occur in a small number of clusters of consecutive coordinates. We show that these block-sparse DPFs can be combined with random sampling and privacy amplification by sampling results, to allow asymptotically optimal privacy-utility trade-offs for vector aggregation, at a fraction of the communication cost. When coupled with recent advances in numerical privacy accounting, our approach incurs a negligible overhead in noise variance, compared to the Gaussian mechanism used with Prio.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.11897v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DS</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hilal Asi, Vitaly Feldman, Hannah Keller, Guy N. Rothblum, Kunal Talwar</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>HYPEROFA: Expanding LLM Vocabulary to New Languages via Hypernetwork-Based Embedding Initialization</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21018</link>
   <description>Many pre-trained language models (PLMs) exhibit suboptimal performance on mid- and low-resource languages, largely due to limited exposure to these languages during pre-training. A common strategy to address this is to introduce new tokens specific to the target languages, initialize their embeddings, and apply continual pre-training on target-language data. Among such methods, OFA (Liu et al., 2024a) proposes a similarity-based subword embedding initialization heuristic that is both effective and efficient. However, OFA restricts target-language token embeddings to be convex combinations of a fixed number of source-language embeddings, which may limit expressiveness. To overcome this limitation, we propose HYPEROFA, a hypernetwork-based approach for more adaptive token embedding initialization. The hypernetwork is trained to map from an external multilingual word vector space to the PLMs token embedding space using source-language tokens. Once trained, it can generate flexible embeddings for target-language tokens, serving as a good starting point for continual pretraining. Experiments demonstrate that HYPEROFA consistently outperforms random initialization baseline and matches or exceeds the performance of OFA in both continual pre-training convergence and downstream task performance. We make the code publicly available.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.21018v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Enes \&quot;Ozeren, Yihong Liu, Hinrich Sch\&quot;utze</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>TimberStrike: Dataset Reconstruction Attack Revealing Privacy Leakage in Federated Tree-Based Systems</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.07605</link>
   <description>Federated Learning has emerged as a privacy-oriented alternative to centralized Machine Learning, enabling collaborative model training without direct data sharing. While extensively studied for neural networks, the security and privacy implications of tree-based models remain underexplored. This work introduces TimberStrike, an optimization-based dataset reconstruction attack targeting horizontally federated tree-based models. Our attack, carried out by a single client, exploits the discrete nature of decision trees by using split values and decision paths to infer sensitive training data from other clients. We evaluate TimberStrike on State-of-the-Art federated gradient boosting implementations across multiple frameworks, including Flower, NVFlare, and FedTree, demonstrating their vulnerability to privacy breaches. On a publicly available stroke prediction dataset, TimberStrike consistently reconstructs between 73.05% and 95.63% of the target dataset across all implementations. We further analyze Differential Privacy, showing that while it partially mitigates the attack, it also significantly degrades model performance. Our findings highlight the need for privacy-preserving mechanisms specifically designed for tree-based Federated Learning systems, and we provide preliminary insights into their design.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.07605v3</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Marco Di Gennaro, Giovanni De Lucia, Stefano Longari, Stefano Zanero, Michele Carminati</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>AdRo-FL: Informed and Secure Client Selection for Federated Learning in the Presence of Adversarial Aggregator</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17805</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) enables collaborative learning without exposing clients' data. While clients only share model updates with the aggregator, studies reveal that aggregators can infer sensitive information from these updates. Secure Aggregation (SA) protects individual updates during transmission; however, recent work demonstrates a critical vulnerability where adversarial aggregators manipulate client selection to bypass SA protections, constituting a Biased Selection Attack (BSA). Although verifiable random selection prevents BSA, it precludes informed client selection essential for FL performance. We propose Adversarial Robust Federated Learning (AdRo-FL), which simultaneously enables: informed client selection based on client utility, and robust defense against BSA maintaining privacy-preserving aggregation. AdRo-FL implements two client selection frameworks tailored for distinct settings. The first framework assumes clients are grouped into clusters based on mutual trust, such as different branches of an organization. The second framework handles distributed clients where no trust relationships exist between them. For the cluster-oriented setting, we propose a novel defense against BSA by (1) enforcing a minimum client selection quota from each cluster, supervised by a cluster-head in every round, and (2) introducing a client utility function to prioritize efficient clients. For the distributed setting, we design a two-phase selection protocol: first, the aggregator selects the top clients based on our utility-driven ranking; then, a verifiable random function (VRF) ensures a BSA-resistant final selection. AdRo-FL also applies quantization to reduce communication overhead and sets strict transmission deadlines to improve energy efficiency. AdRo-FL achieves up to $1.85\times$ faster time-to-accuracy and up to $1.06\times$ higher final accuracy compared to insecure baselines.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.17805v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Md. Kamrul Hossain, Walid Aljoby, Anis Elgabli, Ahmed M. Abdelmoniem, Khaled A. Harras</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Lightweight Federated Learning over Wireless Edge Networks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09546</link>
   <description>With the exponential growth of smart devices connected to wireless networks, data production is increasing rapidly, requiring machine learning (ML) techniques to unlock its value. However, the centralized ML paradigm raises concerns over communication overhead and privacy. Federated learning (FL) offers an alternative at the network edge, but practical deployment in wireless networks remains challenging. This paper proposes a lightweight FL (LTFL) framework integrating wireless transmission power control, model pruning, and gradient quantization. We derive a closed-form expression of the FL convergence gap, considering transmission error, model pruning error, and gradient quantization error. Based on these insights, we formulate an optimization problem to minimize the convergence gap while meeting delay and energy constraints. To solve the non-convex problem efficiently, we derive closed-form solutions for the optimal model pruning ratio and gradient quantization level, and employ Bayesian optimization for transmission power control. Extensive experiments on real-world datasets show that LTFL outperforms state-of-the-art schemes.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09546v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xiangwang Hou, Jingjing Wang, Jun Du, Chunxiao Jiang, Yong Ren, Dusit Niyato</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>ElasticMM: Efficient Multimodal LLMs Serving with Elastic Multimodal Parallelism</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10069</link>
   <description>Multimodal large language models (MLLMs) extend LLMs to handle images, videos, and audio by incorporating feature extractors and projection modules. However, these additional components -- combined with complex inference pipelines and heterogeneous workloads -- introduce significant inference overhead. Therefore, efficiently serving MLLMs remains a major challenge. Current tightly coupled serving architectures struggle to distinguish between mixed request types or adapt parallelism strategies to different inference stages, leading to increased time-to-first-token (TTFT) latency and poor resource utilization. To address this, we propose Elastic Multimodal Parallelism (EMP), a new serving paradigm that elastically adapts to resource heterogeneity across request types and inference stages. Building upon EMP, we develop ElasticMM, an MLLM serving system that (1) separates requests into independent modality groups with dynamic resource allocation via a modality-aware load balancer; (2) decouples inference stages and enables parallelism adjustment and adaptive scaling via elastic partition scheduling; and (3) improves inference efficiency through unified multimodal prefix caching and non-blocking encoding. Experiments on diverse real-world datasets show that ElasticMM outperforms state-of-the-art (SOTA) serving systems, reducing TTFT by up to 4.2x and achieving 3.2-4.5x higher throughput while meeting service-level objectives (SLOs).</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10069v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zedong Liu, Shenggan Cheng, Guangming Tan, Yang You, Dingwen Tao</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Past-Future Scheduler for LLM Serving under SLA Guarantees</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10150</link>
   <description>The exploration and application of Large Language Models (LLMs) is thriving. To reduce deployment costs, continuous batching has become an essential feature in current service frameworks. The effectiveness of continuous batching relies on an accurate estimate of the memory requirements of requests. However, due to the diversity in request output lengths, existing frameworks tend to adopt aggressive or conservative schedulers, which often result in significant overestimation or underestimation of memory consumption. Consequently, they suffer from harmful request evictions or prolonged queuing times, failing to achieve satisfactory throughput under strict Service Level Agreement (SLA) guarantees (a.k.a. goodput), across various LLM application scenarios with differing input-output length distributions. To address this issue, we propose a novel Past-Future scheduler that precisely estimates the peak memory resources required by the running batch via considering the historical distribution of request output lengths and calculating memory occupancy at each future time point. It adapts to applications with all types of input-output length distributions, balancing the trade-off between request queuing and harmful evictions, thereby consistently achieving better goodput. Furthermore, to validate the effectiveness of the proposed scheduler, we developed a high-performance LLM serving framework, LightLLM, that implements the Past-Future scheduler. Compared to existing aggressive or conservative schedulers, LightLLM demonstrates superior goodput, achieving up to 2-3$\times$ higher goodput than other schedulers under heavy loads. LightLLM is open source to boost the research in such direction (https://github.com/ModelTC/lightllm).</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10150v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ruihao Gong, Shihao Bai, Siyu Wu, Yunqian Fan, Zaijun Wang, Xiuhong Li, Hailong Yang, Xianglong Liu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Efficient Federated Learning with Heterogeneous Data and Adaptive Dropout</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10430</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) is a promising distributed machine learning approach that enables collaborative training of a global model using multiple edge devices. The data distributed among the edge devices is highly heterogeneous. Thus, FL faces the challenge of data distribution and heterogeneity, where non-Independent and Identically Distributed (non-IID) data across edge devices may yield in significant accuracy drop. Furthermore, the limited computation and communication capabilities of edge devices increase the likelihood of stragglers, thus leading to slow model convergence. In this paper, we propose the FedDHAD FL framework, which comes with two novel methods: Dynamic Heterogeneous model aggregation (FedDH) and Adaptive Dropout (FedAD). FedDH dynamically adjusts the weights of each local model within the model aggregation process based on the non-IID degree of heterogeneous data to deal with the statistical data heterogeneity. FedAD performs neuron-adaptive operations in response to heterogeneous devices to improve accuracy while achieving superb efficiency. The combination of these two methods makes FedDHAD significantly outperform state-of-the-art solutions in terms of accuracy (up to 6.7% higher), efficiency (up to 2.02 times faster), and computation cost (up to 15.0% smaller).</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10430v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ji Liu, Beichen Ma, Yang Zhou, Jingbo Zhou, Ruoming Jin, Dejing Dou, Huaiyu Dai, Haixun Wang, Patrick Valduriez</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>On Evaluating Performance of LLM Inference Serving Systems</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09019</link>
   <description>The rapid evolution of Large Language Model (LLM) inference systems has yielded significant efficiency improvements. However, our systematic analysis reveals that current evaluation methodologies frequently exhibit fundamental flaws, often manifesting as common evaluation anti-patterns that obscure true performance characteristics and impede scientific progress. Through a comprehensive examination of recent systems, we identify recurring anti-patterns across three key dimensions: Baseline Fairness, Evaluation Setup, and Metric Design. These anti-patterns are uniquely problematic for LLM inference due to its dual-phase nature combining distinct prefill and decode operations, its handling of highly heterogeneous workloads, and its strict temporal requirements for interactive use. We demonstrate how common anti-patterns -- such as inadequate baseline comparisons that conflate engineering effort with algorithmic novelty, workload selections that fail to represent production scenarios, and metric normalizations that hide substantial performance variability like generation stalls-lead to misleading conclusions. To address these challenges, we provide a comprehensive checklist derived from our analysis, establishing a framework for recognizing and avoiding these anti-patterns in favor of robust LLM inference evaluation. To demonstrate the practical application of our framework, we present a case study analyzing speculative decoding, a technique whose bursty, non-uniform token generation is easily misinterpreted when evaluated using approaches characteristic of these anti-patterns. Our work establishes a rigorous foundation for evaluation methodology, enabling meaningful comparisons, ensuring reproducible results, and ultimately accelerating genuine progress in LLM inference systems by moving beyond common anti-patterns to align evaluation with real-world requirements.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09019v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Amey Agrawal, Nitin Kedia, Anmol Agarwal, Jayashree Mohan, Nipun Kwatra, Souvik Kundu, Ramachandran Ramjee, Alexey Tumanov</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>SLIM: A Heterogeneous Accelerator for Edge Inference of Sparse Large Language Model via Adaptive Thresholding</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09201</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated exceptional proficiency in understanding and generating human language, but efficient inference on resource-constrained embedded devices remains challenging due to large model sizes and memory-intensive operations in feedforward network (FFN) and multi-head attention (MHA) layers. While existing accelerators offload LLM inference to expensive heterogeneous computing systems, they fail to exploit the significant sparsity inherent in LLM operations, leaving hardware resources underutilized. We propose SLIM, an algorithm-hardware co-design optimized for sparse LLM serving on edge devices. SLIM exploits LLM sparsity through an adaptive thresholding algorithm that enables runtime-configurable sparsity with negligible accuracy loss, fetching only activated neurons to dramatically reduce data movement. Our heterogeneous hardware architecture strategically combines near-storage processing (NSP) and processing-in-memory (PIM): FFN weights are stored in high-density 3D NAND and computed using NSP units, while memory-intensive MHA operations are processed in PIM modules. This design significantly reduces memory footprint, data movement, and energy consumption. Our comprehensive evaluation demonstrates SLIM's effectiveness, achieving 13-18x throughput improvements over SSD-GPU systems and 9-10x better energy efficiency over DRAM-GPU systems while maintaining low latency, making cost-effective LLM deployment viable for edge computing environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09201v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Weihong Xu, Haein Choi, Po-kai Hsu, Shimeng Yu, Tajana Rosing</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Domain Borders Are There to Be Crossed With Federated Few-Shot Adaptation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10160</link>
   <description>Federated Learning has emerged as a leading paradigm for decentralized, privacy-preserving learning, particularly relevant in the era of interconnected edge devices equipped with sensors. However, the practical implementation of Federated Learning faces three primary challenges: the need for human involvement in costly data labelling processes for target adaptation, covariate shift in client device data collection due to environmental factors affecting sensors, leading to discrepancies between source and target samples, and the impracticality of continuous or regular model updates in resource-constrained environments due to limited data transmission capabilities and technical constraints on channel availability and energy efficiency. To tackle these issues, we expand upon an efficient and scalable Federated Learning framework tailored for real-world client adaptation in industrial settings. This framework leverages a pre-trained source model comprising a deep backbone, an adaptation module, and a classifier running on a powerful server. By freezing the backbone and classifier during client adaptation on resource-constrained devices, we allow the domain adaptive linear layer to handle target domain adaptation, thus minimizing overall computational overhead. Furthermore, this setup, designated as FedAcross+, is extended to encompass the processing of streaming data, thereby rendering the solution suitable for non-stationary environments. Extensive experimental results demonstrate the effectiveness of FedAcross+ in achieving competitive adaptation on low-end client devices with limited target samples, successfully addressing the challenge of domain shift. Moreover, our framework accommodates sporadic model updates within resource-constrained environments, ensuring practical and seamless deployment.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10160v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Manuel R\&quot;oder, Christoph Raab, Frank-Michael Schleif</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Convergence of Agnostic Federated Averaging</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10325</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) enables decentralized model training without centralizing raw data. However, practical FL deployments often face a key realistic challenge: Clients participate intermittently in server aggregation and with unknown, possibly biased participation probabilities. Most existing convergence results either assume full-device participation, or rely on knowledge of (in fact uniform) client availability distributions -- assumptions that rarely hold in practice. In this work, we characterize the optimization problem that consistently adheres to the stochastic dynamics of the well-known \emph{agnostic Federated Averaging (FedAvg)} algorithm under random (and variably-sized) client availability, and rigorously establish its convergence for convex, possibly nonsmooth losses, achieving a standard rate of order $\mathcal{O}(1/\sqrt{T})$, where $T$ denotes the aggregation horizon. Our analysis provides the first convergence guarantees for agnostic FedAvg under general, non-uniform, stochastic client participation, without knowledge of the participation distribution. We also empirically demonstrate that agnostic FedAvg in fact outperforms common (and suboptimal) weighted aggregation FedAvg variants, even with server-side knowledge of participation weights.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10325v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>eess.SP</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator> Herlock (SeyedAbolfazl),  Rahimi, Dionysis Kalogerias</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>InstCache: A Predictive Cache for LLM Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13820</link>
   <description>The revolutionary capabilities of Large Language Models (LLMs) are attracting rapidly growing popularity and leading to soaring user requests to inference serving systems. Caching techniques, which leverage data reuse to reduce computation, offer opportunities to optimize the performance of LLM inference engines. On the one hand, the low-level key-value (KV) cache working at the token level is widely adopted, albeit it incurs significant overhead as request volume grows. On the other hand, instruction-level caching, which stores full instruction-response pairs, is expected to play an increasingly crucial role. However, the high variability in the content and length of instructions make it rare for identical instructions to recur within a short time window, presenting challenges for effective caching instruction-response pairs. To address this challenge, we propose InstCache, a predictive caching mechanism for LLM serving systems. Leveraging the capability of LLMs, we can effectively reorder the representation space of instruction texts and develop a sufficient level of spatial locality. Such spatial locality enables us to predict potential instructions located in a compact region in the space, resulting in an effective caching system at runtime. Experimental results demonstrate that InstCache achieves a 2.3x higher hit rate compared to the upper bound of traditional caching mechanisms on WildChat dataset and reduces the time per output token of vLLM by up to 42.0% and 50.0% on LMSys and Moss datasets, respectively.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2411.13820v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Longwei Zou, Yan Liu, Jiamu Kang, Tingfeng Liu, Jiangang Kong, Yangdong Deng</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>TimberStrike: Dataset Reconstruction Attack Revealing Privacy Leakage in Federated Tree-Based Systems</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.07605</link>
   <description>Federated Learning has emerged as a privacy-oriented alternative to centralized Machine Learning, enabling collaborative model training without direct data sharing. While extensively studied for neural networks, the security and privacy implications of tree-based models remain underexplored. This work introduces TimberStrike, an optimization-based dataset reconstruction attack targeting horizontally federated tree-based models. Our attack, carried out by a single client, exploits the discrete nature of decision trees by using split values and decision paths to infer sensitive training data from other clients. We evaluate TimberStrike on State-of-the-Art federated gradient boosting implementations across multiple frameworks, including Flower, NVFlare, and FedTree, demonstrating their vulnerability to privacy breaches. On a publicly available stroke prediction dataset, TimberStrike consistently reconstructs between 73.05% and 95.63% of the target dataset across all implementations. We further analyze Differential Privacy, showing that while it partially mitigates the attack, it also significantly degrades model performance. Our findings highlight the need for privacy-preserving mechanisms specifically designed for tree-based Federated Learning systems, and we provide preliminary insights into their design.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.07605v3</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Marco Di Gennaro, Giovanni De Lucia, Stefano Longari, Stefano Zanero, Michele Carminati</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Orchestration for Domain-specific Edge-Cloud Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09003</link>
   <description>The remarkable performance of Large Language Models (LLMs) has inspired many applications, which often necessitate edge-cloud collaboration due to connectivity, privacy, and cost considerations. Traditional methods primarily focus on selecting the best LLM model for optimizing performance, while neglecting the critical interplay between the components of the LLM serving pipeline (context retrieval, query preprocessing, etc.) or the changing latency and cost constraints. We introduce ECO-LLM (Edge-Cloud Orchestrator for LLMs), a novel system that reframes this problem as a joint optimization challenge and solves it by systematically exploring component configurations and dynamically selecting optimal strategies at the query level. ECO-LLM consists of two components: (1) the ECO-LLM Emulator, which efficiently explores the vast configuration space utilizing query clustering and pareto-optimal path selection, gathering domain-specific performance metrics without exhaustive evaluation; and (2) the ECO-LLM Runtime, which leverages these metrics to dynamically select optimal resolution strategies for user queries while meeting user-defined Service Level Objectives (SLOs). We evaluate ECO-LLM on a smart home and a smart car assistant scenarios. With an exhaustive exploration of all possible configurations for seen queries, ECO-LLM outperforms cloud-based models like GPT-4o in terms of accuracy (90% vs. 74% on average) while reducing costs by 90% and latency by 55%, demonstrating the value of its joint optimization at the query level. In practical deployment for previously unseen queries, ECO-LLM selects configurations that reduce costs by 62% or improve response times by 62% on average compared to state-of-the-art model routing approaches, while maintaining higher accuracy and consistently adhering to specified latency and cost constraints.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09003v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DB</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Prasoon Patidar (Carnegie Mellon University), Alex Crown (Microsoft Research), Kevin Hsieh (Microsoft Research), Yifei Xu (Microsoft Research), Tusher Chakraborty (Microsoft Research), Ranveer Chandra (Microsoft Research), Yuvraj Agarwal (Carnegie Mellon University)</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>HedraRAG: Coordinating LLM Generation and Database Retrieval in Heterogeneous RAG Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09138</link>
   <description>This paper addresses emerging system-level challenges in heterogeneous retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) serving, where complex multi-stage workflows and diverse request patterns complicate efficient execution. We present HedraRAG, a runtime system built on a graph-based abstraction that exposes optimization opportunities across stage-level parallelism, intra-request similarity, and inter-request skewness. These opportunities are realized through dynamic graph transformations, such as node splitting, reordering, edge addition, and dependency rewiring, applied to wavefronts of subgraphs spanning concurrent requests. The resulting execution plans are mapped onto hybrid CPU-GPU pipelines to improve resource utilization and reduce latency. Evaluations across a wide range of RAG workflows demonstrate speedups exceeding 1.5x and reaching up to 5x over existing frameworks, showcasing the effectiveness of coordinated generation and retrieval in serving environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09138v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DB</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhengding Hu, Vibha Murthy, Zaifeng Pan, Wanlu Li, Xiaoyi Fang, Yufei Ding, Yuke Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Tiny-Align: Bridging Automatic Speech Recognition and Large Language Model on the Edge</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13766</link>
   <description>The combination of Large Language Models (LLM) and Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR), when deployed on edge devices (called edge ASR-LLM), can serve as a powerful personalized assistant to enable audio-based interaction for users. Compared to text-based interaction, edge ASR-LLM allows accessible and natural audio interactions. Unfortunately, existing ASR-LLM models are mainly trained in high-performance computing environments and produce substantial model weights, making them difficult to deploy on edge devices. More importantly, to better serve users' personalized needs, the ASR-LLM must be able to learn from each distinct user, given that audio input often contains highly personalized characteristics that necessitate personalized on-device training. Since individually fine-tuning the ASR or LLM often leads to suboptimal results due to modality-specific limitations, end-to-end training ensures seamless integration of audio features and language understanding (cross-modal alignment), ultimately enabling a more personalized and efficient adaptation on edge devices. However, due to the complex training requirements and substantial computational demands of existing approaches, cross-modal alignment between ASR audio and LLM can be challenging on edge devices. In this work, we propose a resource-efficient cross-modal alignment framework that bridges ASR and LLMs on edge devices to handle personalized audio input. Our framework enables efficient ASR-LLM alignment on resource-constrained devices like NVIDIA Jetson Orin (8GB RAM), achieving 50x training time speedup while improving the alignment quality by more than 50\%. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first work to study efficient ASR-LLM alignment on resource-constrained edge devices.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2411.13766v4</guid>
   <category>cs.SD</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>eess.AS</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ruiyang Qin, Dancheng Liu, Gelei Xu, Zheyu Yan, Chenhui Xu, Yuting Hu, Shaocong Wang, X. Sharon Hu, Jinjun Xiong, Yiyu Shi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>MTF-Grasp: A Multi-tier Federated Learning Approach for Robotic Grasping</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10158</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) is a promising machine learning paradigm that enables participating devices to train privacy-preserved and collaborative models. FL has proven its benefits for robotic manipulation tasks. However, grasping tasks lack exploration in such settings where robots train a global model without moving data and ensuring data privacy. The main challenge is that each robot learns from data that is nonindependent and identically distributed (non-IID) and of low quantity. This exhibits performance degradation, particularly in robotic grasping. Thus, in this work, we propose MTF-Grasp, a multi-tier FL approach for robotic grasping, acknowledging the unique challenges posed by the non-IID data distribution across robots, including quantitative skewness. MTF-Grasp harnesses data quality and quantity across robots to select a set of &quot;top-level&quot; robots with better data distribution and higher sample count. It then utilizes top-level robots to train initial seed models and distribute them to the remaining &quot;low-level&quot; robots, reducing the risk of model performance degradation in low-level robots. Our approach outperforms the conventional FL setup by up to 8% on the quantity-skewed Cornell and Jacquard grasping datasets.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10158v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.RO</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Obaidullah Zaland, Erik Elmroth, Monowar Bhuyan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Privacy-Preserving Multi-Stage Fall Detection Framework with Semi-supervised Federated Learning and Robotic Vision Confirmation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10474</link>
   <description>The aging population is growing rapidly, and so is the danger of falls in older adults. A major cause of injury is falling, and detection in time can greatly save medical expenses and recovery time. However, to provide timely intervention and avoid unnecessary alarms, detection systems must be effective and reliable while addressing privacy concerns regarding the user. In this work, we propose a framework for detecting falls using several complementary systems: a semi-supervised federated learning-based fall detection system (SF2D), an indoor localization and navigation system, and a vision-based human fall recognition system. A wearable device and an edge device identify a fall scenario in the first system. On top of that, the second system uses an indoor localization technique first to localize the fall location and then navigate a robot to inspect the scenario. A vision-based detection system running on an edge device with a mounted camera on a robot is used to recognize fallen people. Each of the systems of this proposed framework achieves different accuracy rates. Specifically, the SF2D has a 0.81% failure rate equivalent to 99.19% accuracy, while the vision-based fallen people detection achieves 96.3% accuracy. However, when we combine the accuracy of these two systems with the accuracy of the navigation system (95% success rate), our proposed framework creates a highly reliable performance for fall detection, with an overall accuracy of 99.99%. Not only is the proposed framework safe for older adults, but it is also a privacy-preserving solution for detecting falls.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10474v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.RO</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Seyed Alireza Rahimi Azghadi, Truong-Thanh-Hung Nguyen, Helene Fournier, Monica Wachowicz, Rene Richard, Francis Palma, Hung Cao</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Can A Society of Generative Agents Simulate Human Behavior and Inform Public Health Policy? A Case Study on Vaccine Hesitancy</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09639</link>
   <description>Can we simulate a sandbox society with generative agents to model human behavior, thereby reducing the over-reliance on real human trials for assessing public policies? In this work, we investigate the feasibility of simulating health-related decision-making, using vaccine hesitancy, defined as the delay in acceptance or refusal of vaccines despite the availability of vaccination services (MacDonald, 2015), as a case study. To this end, we introduce the VacSim framework with 100 generative agents powered by Large Language Models (LLMs). VacSim simulates vaccine policy outcomes with the following steps: 1) instantiate a population of agents with demographics based on census data; 2) connect the agents via a social network and model vaccine attitudes as a function of social dynamics and disease-related information; 3) design and evaluate various public health interventions aimed at mitigating vaccine hesitancy. To align with real-world results, we also introduce simulation warmup and attitude modulation to adjust agents' attitudes. We propose a series of evaluations to assess the reliability of various LLM simulations. Experiments indicate that models like Llama and Qwen can simulate aspects of human behavior but also highlight real-world alignment challenges, such as inconsistent responses with demographic profiles. This early exploration of LLM-driven simulations is not meant to serve as definitive policy guidance; instead, it serves as a call for action to examine social simulation for policy development.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.09639v4</guid>
   <category>cs.MA</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Abe Bohan Hou, Hongru Du, Yichen Wang, Jingyu Zhang, Zixiao Wang, Paul Pu Liang, Daniel Khashabi, Lauren Gardner, Tianxing He</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>SLIM: A Heterogeneous Accelerator for Edge Inference of Sparse Large Language Model via Adaptive Thresholding</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09201</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated exceptional proficiency in understanding and generating human language, but efficient inference on resource-constrained embedded devices remains challenging due to large model sizes and memory-intensive operations in feedforward network (FFN) and multi-head attention (MHA) layers. While existing accelerators offload LLM inference to expensive heterogeneous computing systems, they fail to exploit the significant sparsity inherent in LLM operations, leaving hardware resources underutilized. We propose SLIM, an algorithm-hardware co-design optimized for sparse LLM serving on edge devices. SLIM exploits LLM sparsity through an adaptive thresholding algorithm that enables runtime-configurable sparsity with negligible accuracy loss, fetching only activated neurons to dramatically reduce data movement. Our heterogeneous hardware architecture strategically combines near-storage processing (NSP) and processing-in-memory (PIM): FFN weights are stored in high-density 3D NAND and computed using NSP units, while memory-intensive MHA operations are processed in PIM modules. This design significantly reduces memory footprint, data movement, and energy consumption. Our comprehensive evaluation demonstrates SLIM's effectiveness, achieving 13-18x throughput improvements over SSD-GPU systems and 9-10x better energy efficiency over DRAM-GPU systems while maintaining low latency, making cost-effective LLM deployment viable for edge computing environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09201v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Weihong Xu, Haein Choi, Po-kai Hsu, Shimeng Yu, Tajana Rosing</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Pimba: A Processing-in-Memory Acceleration for Post-Transformer Large Language Model Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10178</link>
   <description>Transformers are the driving force behind today's Large Language Models (LLMs), serving as the foundation for their performance and versatility. Yet, their compute and memory costs grow with sequence length, posing scalability challenges for long-context inferencing. In response, the algorithm community is exploring alternative architectures, such as state space models (SSMs), linear attention, and recurrent neural networks (RNNs), which we refer to as post-transformers. This shift presents a key challenge: building a serving system that efficiently supports both transformer and post-transformer LLMs within a unified framework. To address this challenge, we analyze the performance characteristics of transformer and post-transformer LLMs. Despite their algorithmic differences, both are fundamentally limited by memory bandwidth under batched inference due to attention in transformers and state updates in post-transformers. Further analyses suggest two additional insights: (1) state update operations, unlike attention, incur high hardware cost, making per-bank PIM acceleration inefficient, and (2) different low-precision arithmetic methods offer varying accuracy-area tradeoffs, while we identify Microsoft's MX as the Pareto-optimal choice. Building on these insights, we design Pimba as an array of State-update Processing Units (SPUs), each shared between two banks to enable interleaved access to PIM. Each SPU includes a State-update Processing Engine (SPE) that comprises element-wise multipliers and adders using MX-based quantized arithmetic, enabling efficient execution of state update and attention operations. Our evaluation shows that, compared to LLM-optimized GPU and GPU+PIM systems, Pimba achieves up to 3.2x and 2.1x higher token generation throughput, respectively.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10178v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Wonung Kim, Yubin Lee, Yoonsung Kim, Jinwoo Hwang, Seongryong Oh, Jiyong Jung, Aziz Huseynov, Woong Gyu Park, Chang Hyun Park, Divya Mahajan, Jongse Park</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Gradients as an Action: Towards Communication-Efficient Federated Recommender Systems via Adaptive Action Sharing</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08842</link>
   <description>As a promising privacy-aware collaborative model training paradigm, Federated Learning (FL) is becoming popular in the design of distributed recommender systems. However, Federated Recommender Systems (FedRecs) greatly suffer from two major problems: i) extremely high communication overhead due to massive item embeddings involved in recommendation systems, and ii) intolerably low training efficiency caused by the entanglement of both heterogeneous network environments and client devices. Although existing methods attempt to employ various compression techniques to reduce communication overhead, due to the parameter errors introduced by model compression, they inevitably suffer from model performance degradation. To simultaneously address the above problems, this paper presents a communication-efficient FedRec framework named FedRAS, which adopts an action-sharing strategy to cluster the gradients of item embedding into a specific number of model updating actions for communication rather than directly compressing the item embeddings. In this way, the cloud server can use the limited actions from clients to update all the items. Since gradient values are significantly smaller than item embeddings, constraining the directions of gradients (i.e., the action space) introduces smaller errors compared to compressing the entire item embedding matrix into a reduced space. To accommodate heterogeneous devices and network environments, FedRAS incorporates an adaptive clustering mechanism that dynamically adjusts the number of actions. Comprehensive experiments on well-known datasets demonstrate that FedRAS can reduce the size of communication payloads by up to 96.88%, while not sacrificing recommendation performance within various heterogeneous scenarios. We have open-sourced FedRAS at https://github.com/mastlab-T3S/FedRAS.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.08842v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhufeng Lu, Chentao Jia, Ming Hu, Xiaofei Xie, Mingsong Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Can We Predict Your Next Move Without Breaking Your Privacy?</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08843</link>
   <description>We propose FLLL3M--Federated Learning with Large Language Models for Mobility Modeling--a privacy-preserving framework for Next-Location Prediction (NxLP). By retaining user data locally and leveraging LLMs through an efficient outer product mechanism, FLLL3M ensures high accuracy with low resource demands. It achieves SOT results on Gowalla (Acc@1: 12.55, MRR: 0.1422), WeePlace (10.71, 0.1285), Brightkite (10.42, 0.1169), and FourSquare (8.71, 0.1023), while reducing parameters by up to 45.6% and memory usage by 52.7%.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.08843v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Arpita Soni, Sahil Tripathi, Gautam Siddharth Kashyap, Manaswi Kulahara, Mohammad Anas Azeez, Zohaib Hasan Siddiqui, Nipun Joshi, Jiechao Gao</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Towards Privacy-Preserving and Personalized Smart Homes via Tailored Small Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08878</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) have showcased remarkable generalizability in language comprehension and hold significant potential to revolutionize human-computer interaction in smart homes. Existing LLM-based smart home assistants typically transmit user commands, along with user profiles and home configurations, to remote servers to obtain personalized services. However, users are increasingly concerned about the potential privacy leaks to the remote servers. To address this issue, we develop HomeLLaMA, an on-device assistant for privacy-preserving and personalized smart home serving with a tailored small language model (SLM). HomeLLaMA learns from cloud LLMs to deliver satisfactory responses and enable user-friendly interactions. Once deployed, HomeLLaMA facilitates proactive interactions by continuously updating local SLMs and user profiles. To further enhance user experience while protecting their privacy, we develop PrivShield to offer an optional privacy-preserving LLM-based smart home serving for those users, who are unsatisfied with local responses and willing to send less-sensitive queries to remote servers. For evaluation, we build a comprehensive benchmark DevFinder to assess the service quality. Extensive experiments and user studies (M=100) demonstrate that HomeLLaMA can provide personalized services while significantly enhancing user privacy.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.08878v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xinyu Huang, Leming Shen, Zijing Ma, Yuanqing Zheng</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>On Evaluating Performance of LLM Inference Serving Systems</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09019</link>
   <description>The rapid evolution of Large Language Model (LLM) inference systems has yielded significant efficiency improvements. However, our systematic analysis reveals that current evaluation methodologies frequently exhibit fundamental flaws, often manifesting as common evaluation anti-patterns that obscure true performance characteristics and impede scientific progress. Through a comprehensive examination of recent systems, we identify recurring anti-patterns across three key dimensions: Baseline Fairness, Evaluation Setup, and Metric Design. These anti-patterns are uniquely problematic for LLM inference due to its dual-phase nature combining distinct prefill and decode operations, its handling of highly heterogeneous workloads, and its strict temporal requirements for interactive use. We demonstrate how common anti-patterns -- such as inadequate baseline comparisons that conflate engineering effort with algorithmic novelty, workload selections that fail to represent production scenarios, and metric normalizations that hide substantial performance variability like generation stalls-lead to misleading conclusions. To address these challenges, we provide a comprehensive checklist derived from our analysis, establishing a framework for recognizing and avoiding these anti-patterns in favor of robust LLM inference evaluation. To demonstrate the practical application of our framework, we present a case study analyzing speculative decoding, a technique whose bursty, non-uniform token generation is easily misinterpreted when evaluated using approaches characteristic of these anti-patterns. Our work establishes a rigorous foundation for evaluation methodology, enabling meaningful comparisons, ensuring reproducible results, and ultimately accelerating genuine progress in LLM inference systems by moving beyond common anti-patterns to align evaluation with real-world requirements.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09019v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Amey Agrawal, Nitin Kedia, Anmol Agarwal, Jayashree Mohan, Nipun Kwatra, Souvik Kundu, Ramachandran Ramjee, Alexey Tumanov</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Model Parallelism With Subnetwork Data Parallelism</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09029</link>
   <description>Distributed pre-training of large models at scale often imposes heavy memory demands on individual nodes and incurs significant intra-node communication costs. We propose a novel alternative approach that reduces the memory requirements by training small, structured subnetworks of the model on separate workers. Unlike pipelining, our method avoids inter-node activation communication and maintains bandwidth requirements that are comparable to or lower than standard data parallel communication schemes based on all-reduce. We evaluate two subnetwork construction strategies guided by the principle of ensuring uniform representation of each parameter across the distributed training setup. Our results show that the stochastic block dropping technique consistently outperforms the width-wise subnetwork construction previously explored in federated learning. We empirically attribute this superior performance to stronger gradient alignment in subnetworks that retain blocks having skip connections. Preliminary experiments highlight the promise of our approach, achieving a 20-40% reduction in memory usage without any loss in performance.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09029v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Vaibhav Singh, Zafir Khalid, Edouard Oyallon, Eugene Belilovsky</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Learning from Synthetic Labs: Language Models as Auction Participants</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09083</link>
   <description>This paper investigates the behavior of simulated AI agents (large language models, or LLMs) in auctions, introducing a novel synthetic data-generating process to help facilitate the study and design of auctions. We find that LLMs -- when endowed with chain of thought reasoning capacity -- agree with the experimental literature in auctions across a variety of classic auction formats. In particular, we find that LLM bidders produce results consistent with risk-averse human bidders; that they perform closer to theoretical predictions in obviously strategy-proof auctions; and, that they succumb to the winner's curse in common value settings. On prompting, we find that LLMs are not very sensitive to naive changes in prompts (e.g., language, currency) but can improve dramatically towards theoretical predictions with the right mental model (i.e., the language of Nash deviations). We run 1,000$+$ auctions for less than $\$$400 with GPT-4 models (three orders of magnitude cheaper than modern auction experiments) and develop a framework flexible enough to run auction experiments with any LLM model and a wide range of auction design specifications, facilitating further experimental study by decreasing costs and serving as a proof-of-concept for the use of LLM proxies.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09083v1</guid>
   <category>cs.GT</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Anand Shah, Kehang Zhu, Yanchen Jiang, Jeffrey G. Wang, Arif K. Dayi, John J. Horton, David C. Parkes</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>DRAGD: A Federated Unlearning Data Reconstruction Attack Based on Gradient Differences</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09602</link>
   <description>Federated learning enables collaborative machine learning while preserving data privacy. However, the rise of federated unlearning, designed to allow clients to erase their data from the global model, introduces new privacy concerns. Specifically, the gradient exchanges during the unlearning process can leak sensitive information about deleted data. In this paper, we introduce DRAGD, a novel attack that exploits gradient discrepancies before and after unlearning to reconstruct forgotten data. We also present DRAGDP, an enhanced version of DRAGD that leverages publicly available prior data to improve reconstruction accuracy, particularly for complex datasets like facial images. Extensive experiments across multiple datasets demonstrate that DRAGD and DRAGDP significantly outperform existing methods in data reconstruction.Our work highlights a critical privacy vulnerability in federated unlearning and offers a practical solution, advancing the security of federated unlearning systems in real-world applications.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09602v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Bocheng Ju, Junchao Fan, Jiaqi Liu, Xiaolin Chang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Learning with Graph-Based Aggregation for Traffic Forecasting</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09805</link>
   <description>In traffic prediction, the goal is to estimate traffic speed or flow in specific regions or road segments using historical data collected by devices deployed in each area. Each region or road segment can be viewed as an individual client that measures local traffic flow, making Federated Learning (FL) a suitable approach for collaboratively training models without sharing raw data. In centralized FL, a central server collects and aggregates model updates from multiple clients to build a shared model while preserving each client's data privacy. Standard FL methods, such as Federated Averaging (FedAvg), assume that clients are independent, which can limit performance in traffic prediction tasks where spatial relationships between clients are important. Federated Graph Learning methods can capture these dependencies during server-side aggregation, but they often introduce significant computational overhead. In this paper, we propose a lightweight graph-aware FL approach that blends the simplicity of FedAvg with key ideas from graph learning. Rather than training full models, our method applies basic neighbourhood aggregation principles to guide parameter updates, weighting client models based on graph connectivity. This approach captures spatial relationships effectively while remaining computationally efficient. We evaluate our method on two benchmark traffic datasets, METR-LA and PEMS-BAY, and show that it achieves competitive performance compared to standard baselines and recent graph-based federated learning techniques.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09805v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Audri Banik, Glaucio Haroldo Silva de Carvalho, Renata Dividino</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Feature Distillation is the Better Choice for Model-Heterogeneous Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10348</link>
   <description>Model-Heterogeneous Federated Learning (Hetero-FL) has attracted growing attention for its ability to aggregate knowledge from heterogeneous models while keeping private data locally. To better aggregate knowledge from clients, ensemble distillation, as a widely used and effective technique, is often employed after global aggregation to enhance the performance of the global model. However, simply combining Hetero-FL and ensemble distillation does not always yield promising results and can make the training process unstable. The reason is that existing methods primarily focus on logit distillation, which, while being model-agnostic with softmax predictions, fails to compensate for the knowledge bias arising from heterogeneous models. To tackle this challenge, we propose a stable and efficient Feature Distillation for model-heterogeneous Federated learning, dubbed FedFD, that can incorporate aligned feature information via orthogonal projection to integrate knowledge from heterogeneous models better. Specifically, a new feature-based ensemble federated knowledge distillation paradigm is proposed. The global model on the server needs to maintain a projection layer for each client-side model architecture to align the features separately. Orthogonal techniques are employed to re-parameterize the projection layer to mitigate knowledge bias from heterogeneous models and thus maximize the distilled knowledge. Extensive experiments show that FedFD achieves superior performance compared to state-of-the-art methods.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10348v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yichen Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Efficient Federated Learning with Heterogeneous Data and Adaptive Dropout</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10430</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) is a promising distributed machine learning approach that enables collaborative training of a global model using multiple edge devices. The data distributed among the edge devices is highly heterogeneous. Thus, FL faces the challenge of data distribution and heterogeneity, where non-Independent and Identically Distributed (non-IID) data across edge devices may yield in significant accuracy drop. Furthermore, the limited computation and communication capabilities of edge devices increase the likelihood of stragglers, thus leading to slow model convergence. In this paper, we propose the FedDHAD FL framework, which comes with two novel methods: Dynamic Heterogeneous model aggregation (FedDH) and Adaptive Dropout (FedAD). FedDH dynamically adjusts the weights of each local model within the model aggregation process based on the non-IID degree of heterogeneous data to deal with the statistical data heterogeneity. FedAD performs neuron-adaptive operations in response to heterogeneous devices to improve accuracy while achieving superb efficiency. The combination of these two methods makes FedDHAD significantly outperform state-of-the-art solutions in terms of accuracy (up to 6.7% higher), efficiency (up to 2.02 times faster), and computation cost (up to 15.0% smaller).</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10430v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ji Liu, Beichen Ma, Yang Zhou, Jingbo Zhou, Ruoming Jin, Dejing Dou, Huaiyu Dai, Haixun Wang, Patrick Valduriez</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Privacy-Preserving Multi-Stage Fall Detection Framework with Semi-supervised Federated Learning and Robotic Vision Confirmation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10474</link>
   <description>The aging population is growing rapidly, and so is the danger of falls in older adults. A major cause of injury is falling, and detection in time can greatly save medical expenses and recovery time. However, to provide timely intervention and avoid unnecessary alarms, detection systems must be effective and reliable while addressing privacy concerns regarding the user. In this work, we propose a framework for detecting falls using several complementary systems: a semi-supervised federated learning-based fall detection system (SF2D), an indoor localization and navigation system, and a vision-based human fall recognition system. A wearable device and an edge device identify a fall scenario in the first system. On top of that, the second system uses an indoor localization technique first to localize the fall location and then navigate a robot to inspect the scenario. A vision-based detection system running on an edge device with a mounted camera on a robot is used to recognize fallen people. Each of the systems of this proposed framework achieves different accuracy rates. Specifically, the SF2D has a 0.81% failure rate equivalent to 99.19% accuracy, while the vision-based fallen people detection achieves 96.3% accuracy. However, when we combine the accuracy of these two systems with the accuracy of the navigation system (95% success rate), our proposed framework creates a highly reliable performance for fall detection, with an overall accuracy of 99.99%. Not only is the proposed framework safe for older adults, but it is also a privacy-preserving solution for detecting falls.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10474v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.RO</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Seyed Alireza Rahimi Azghadi, Truong-Thanh-Hung Nguyen, Helene Fournier, Monica Wachowicz, Rene Richard, Francis Palma, Hung Cao</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>CodeJudgeBench: Benchmarking LLM-as-a-Judge for Coding Tasks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10535</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) have significantly advanced the state-of-the-art in various coding tasks. Beyond directly answering user queries, LLMs can also serve as judges, assessing and comparing the quality of responses generated by other models. Such an evaluation capability is crucial both for benchmarking different LLMs and for improving response quality through response ranking. However, despite the growing adoption of the LLM-as-a-Judge paradigm, its effectiveness in coding scenarios remains underexplored due to the absence of dedicated benchmarks. To address this gap, we introduce CodeJudgeBench, a benchmark explicitly designed to evaluate the performance of LLM-as-a-Judge models across three critical coding tasks: code generation, code repair, and unit test generation. Through comprehensive benchmarking of 26 LLM-as-a-Judge models, we find that recent thinking models significantly outperform non-thinking models on our carefully designed code judging tasks. Notably, even relatively small thinking models, such as Qwen3-8B, can outperform specially trained LLM-as-a-Judge models up to 70B in size. Nevertheless, all models still exhibit significant randomness in their judgment of coding tasks. For pairwise judging tasks, simply changing the order in which responses are presented can substantially impact accuracy. In addition, when judging code and unit tests written by different LLMs, LLM-as-a-Judge models also show variance in performance. This sensitivity raises concerns about the reliability and consistency of LLM-as-a-Judge in coding scenarios. Lastly, we study optimal prompting strategies for LLM-as-a-Judge. We find that using pair-wise comparison outperforms scalar point-wise judging. Furthermore, retaining comments and reasoning in the full, unprocessed LLM response leads to improved judge performance.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10535v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hongchao Jiang, Yiming Chen, Yushi Cao, Hung-yi Lee, Robby T. Tan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>GI-NAS: Boosting Gradient Inversion Attacks through Adaptive Neural Architecture Search</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20725</link>
   <description>Gradient Inversion Attacks invert the transmitted gradients in Federated Learning (FL) systems to reconstruct the sensitive data of local clients and have raised considerable privacy concerns. A majority of gradient inversion methods rely heavily on explicit prior knowledge (e.g., a well pre-trained generative model), which is often unavailable in realistic scenarios. This is because real-world client data distributions are often highly heterogeneous, domain-specific, and unavailable to attackers, making it impractical for attackers to obtain perfectly matched pre-trained models, which inevitably suffer from fundamental distribution shifts relative to target private data. To alleviate this issue, researchers have proposed to leverage the implicit prior knowledge of an over-parameterized network. However, they only utilize a fixed neural architecture for all the attack settings. This would hinder the adaptive use of implicit architectural priors and consequently limit the generalizability. In this paper, we further exploit such implicit prior knowledge by proposing Gradient Inversion via Neural Architecture Search (GI-NAS), which adaptively searches the network and captures the implicit priors behind neural architectures. Extensive experiments verify that our proposed GI-NAS can achieve superior attack performance compared to state-of-the-art gradient inversion methods, even under more practical settings with high-resolution images, large-sized batches, and advanced defense strategies. To the best of our knowledge, we are the first to successfully introduce NAS to the gradient inversion community. We believe that this work exposes critical vulnerabilities in real-world federated learning by demonstrating high-fidelity reconstruction of sensitive data without requiring domain-specific priors, forcing urgent reassessment of FL privacy safeguards.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2405.20725v3</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Wenbo Yu, Hao Fang, Bin Chen, Xiaohang Sui, Chuan Chen, Hao Wu, Shu-Tao Xia, Ke Xu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Dataset Distillation-based Hybrid Federated Learning on Non-IID Data</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17517</link>
   <description>With the development of edge computing, Federated Learning (FL) has emerged as a promising solution for the intelligent Internet of Things (IoT). However, applying FL in mobile edge-cloud networks is greatly challenged by statistical heterogeneity and high communication overhead. To address it, we propose a hybrid federated learning framework called HFLDD, which integrates dataset distillation to generate approximately independent and equally distributed (IID) data, thereby improving the performance of model training. In particular, we partition the clients into heterogeneous clusters, where the data labels among different clients within a cluster are unbalanced while the data labels among different clusters are balanced. The cluster heads collect distilled data from the corresponding cluster members, and conduct model training in collaboration with the server. This training process is like traditional federated learning on IID data, and hence effectively alleviates the impact of non-IID data on model training. We perform a comprehensive analysis of the convergence behavior, communication overhead, and computational complexity of the proposed HFLDD. Extensive experimental results based on multiple public datasets demonstrate that when data labels are severely imbalanced, the proposed HFLDD outperforms the baseline methods in terms of both test accuracy and communication cost.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2409.17517v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xiufang Shi, Wei Zhang, Mincheng Wu, Guangyi Liu, Zhenyu Wen, Shibo He, Tejal Shah, Rajiv Ranjan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Tiny-Align: Bridging Automatic Speech Recognition and Large Language Model on the Edge</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13766</link>
   <description>The combination of Large Language Models (LLM) and Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR), when deployed on edge devices (called edge ASR-LLM), can serve as a powerful personalized assistant to enable audio-based interaction for users. Compared to text-based interaction, edge ASR-LLM allows accessible and natural audio interactions. Unfortunately, existing ASR-LLM models are mainly trained in high-performance computing environments and produce substantial model weights, making them difficult to deploy on edge devices. More importantly, to better serve users' personalized needs, the ASR-LLM must be able to learn from each distinct user, given that audio input often contains highly personalized characteristics that necessitate personalized on-device training. Since individually fine-tuning the ASR or LLM often leads to suboptimal results due to modality-specific limitations, end-to-end training ensures seamless integration of audio features and language understanding (cross-modal alignment), ultimately enabling a more personalized and efficient adaptation on edge devices. However, due to the complex training requirements and substantial computational demands of existing approaches, cross-modal alignment between ASR audio and LLM can be challenging on edge devices. In this work, we propose a resource-efficient cross-modal alignment framework that bridges ASR and LLMs on edge devices to handle personalized audio input. Our framework enables efficient ASR-LLM alignment on resource-constrained devices like NVIDIA Jetson Orin (8GB RAM), achieving 50x training time speedup while improving the alignment quality by more than 50\%. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first work to study efficient ASR-LLM alignment on resource-constrained edge devices.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2411.13766v4</guid>
   <category>cs.SD</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>eess.AS</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ruiyang Qin, Dancheng Liu, Gelei Xu, Zheyu Yan, Chenhui Xu, Yuting Hu, Shaocong Wang, X. Sharon Hu, Jinjun Xiong, Yiyu Shi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Can A Society of Generative Agents Simulate Human Behavior and Inform Public Health Policy? A Case Study on Vaccine Hesitancy</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09639</link>
   <description>Can we simulate a sandbox society with generative agents to model human behavior, thereby reducing the over-reliance on real human trials for assessing public policies? In this work, we investigate the feasibility of simulating health-related decision-making, using vaccine hesitancy, defined as the delay in acceptance or refusal of vaccines despite the availability of vaccination services (MacDonald, 2015), as a case study. To this end, we introduce the VacSim framework with 100 generative agents powered by Large Language Models (LLMs). VacSim simulates vaccine policy outcomes with the following steps: 1) instantiate a population of agents with demographics based on census data; 2) connect the agents via a social network and model vaccine attitudes as a function of social dynamics and disease-related information; 3) design and evaluate various public health interventions aimed at mitigating vaccine hesitancy. To align with real-world results, we also introduce simulation warmup and attitude modulation to adjust agents' attitudes. We propose a series of evaluations to assess the reliability of various LLM simulations. Experiments indicate that models like Llama and Qwen can simulate aspects of human behavior but also highlight real-world alignment challenges, such as inconsistent responses with demographic profiles. This early exploration of LLM-driven simulations is not meant to serve as definitive policy guidance; instead, it serves as a call for action to examine social simulation for policy development.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.09639v4</guid>
   <category>cs.MA</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Abe Bohan Hou, Hongru Du, Yichen Wang, Jingyu Zhang, Zixiao Wang, Paul Pu Liang, Daniel Khashabi, Lauren Gardner, Tianxing He</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Learning from Synthetic Labs: Language Models as Auction Participants</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09083</link>
   <description>This paper investigates the behavior of simulated AI agents (large language models, or LLMs) in auctions, introducing a novel synthetic data-generating process to help facilitate the study and design of auctions. We find that LLMs -- when endowed with chain of thought reasoning capacity -- agree with the experimental literature in auctions across a variety of classic auction formats. In particular, we find that LLM bidders produce results consistent with risk-averse human bidders; that they perform closer to theoretical predictions in obviously strategy-proof auctions; and, that they succumb to the winner's curse in common value settings. On prompting, we find that LLMs are not very sensitive to naive changes in prompts (e.g., language, currency) but can improve dramatically towards theoretical predictions with the right mental model (i.e., the language of Nash deviations). We run 1,000$+$ auctions for less than $\$$400 with GPT-4 models (three orders of magnitude cheaper than modern auction experiments) and develop a framework flexible enough to run auction experiments with any LLM model and a wide range of auction design specifications, facilitating further experimental study by decreasing costs and serving as a proof-of-concept for the use of LLM proxies.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09083v1</guid>
   <category>cs.GT</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Anand Shah, Kehang Zhu, Yanchen Jiang, Jeffrey G. Wang, Arif K. Dayi, John J. Horton, David C. Parkes</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>PREAMBLE: Private and Efficient Aggregation via Block Sparse Vectors</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11897</link>
   <description>We revisit the problem of secure aggregation of high-dimensional vectors in a two-server system such as Prio. These systems are typically used to aggregate vectors such as gradients in private federated learning, where the aggregate itself is protected via noise addition to ensure differential privacy. Existing approaches require communication scaling with the dimensionality, and thus limit the dimensionality of vectors one can efficiently process in this setup.
  We propose PREAMBLE: {\bf Pr}ivate {\bf E}fficient {\bf A}ggregation {\bf M}echanism via {\bf BL}ock-sparse {\bf E}uclidean Vectors. PREAMBLE builds on an extension of distributed point functions that enables communication- and computation-efficient aggregation of {\em block-sparse vectors}, which are sparse vectors where the non-zero entries occur in a small number of clusters of consecutive coordinates. We show that these block-sparse DPFs can be combined with random sampling and privacy amplification by sampling results, to allow asymptotically optimal privacy-utility trade-offs for vector aggregation, at a fraction of the communication cost. When coupled with recent advances in numerical privacy accounting, our approach incurs a negligible overhead in noise variance, compared to the Gaussian mechanism used with Prio.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.11897v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DS</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hilal Asi, Vitaly Feldman, Hannah Keller, Guy N. Rothblum, Kunal Talwar</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>CodeJudgeBench: Benchmarking LLM-as-a-Judge for Coding Tasks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10535</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) have significantly advanced the state-of-the-art in various coding tasks. Beyond directly answering user queries, LLMs can also serve as judges, assessing and comparing the quality of responses generated by other models. Such an evaluation capability is crucial both for benchmarking different LLMs and for improving response quality through response ranking. However, despite the growing adoption of the LLM-as-a-Judge paradigm, its effectiveness in coding scenarios remains underexplored due to the absence of dedicated benchmarks. To address this gap, we introduce CodeJudgeBench, a benchmark explicitly designed to evaluate the performance of LLM-as-a-Judge models across three critical coding tasks: code generation, code repair, and unit test generation. Through comprehensive benchmarking of 26 LLM-as-a-Judge models, we find that recent thinking models significantly outperform non-thinking models on our carefully designed code judging tasks. Notably, even relatively small thinking models, such as Qwen3-8B, can outperform specially trained LLM-as-a-Judge models up to 70B in size. Nevertheless, all models still exhibit significant randomness in their judgment of coding tasks. For pairwise judging tasks, simply changing the order in which responses are presented can substantially impact accuracy. In addition, when judging code and unit tests written by different LLMs, LLM-as-a-Judge models also show variance in performance. This sensitivity raises concerns about the reliability and consistency of LLM-as-a-Judge in coding scenarios. Lastly, we study optimal prompting strategies for LLM-as-a-Judge. We find that using pair-wise comparison outperforms scalar point-wise judging. Furthermore, retaining comments and reasoning in the full, unprocessed LLM response leads to improved judge performance.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10535v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hongchao Jiang, Yiming Chen, Yushi Cao, Hung-yi Lee, Robby T. Tan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Can A Society of Generative Agents Simulate Human Behavior and Inform Public Health Policy? A Case Study on Vaccine Hesitancy</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09639</link>
   <description>Can we simulate a sandbox society with generative agents to model human behavior, thereby reducing the over-reliance on real human trials for assessing public policies? In this work, we investigate the feasibility of simulating health-related decision-making, using vaccine hesitancy, defined as the delay in acceptance or refusal of vaccines despite the availability of vaccination services (MacDonald, 2015), as a case study. To this end, we introduce the VacSim framework with 100 generative agents powered by Large Language Models (LLMs). VacSim simulates vaccine policy outcomes with the following steps: 1) instantiate a population of agents with demographics based on census data; 2) connect the agents via a social network and model vaccine attitudes as a function of social dynamics and disease-related information; 3) design and evaluate various public health interventions aimed at mitigating vaccine hesitancy. To align with real-world results, we also introduce simulation warmup and attitude modulation to adjust agents' attitudes. We propose a series of evaluations to assess the reliability of various LLM simulations. Experiments indicate that models like Llama and Qwen can simulate aspects of human behavior but also highlight real-world alignment challenges, such as inconsistent responses with demographic profiles. This early exploration of LLM-driven simulations is not meant to serve as definitive policy guidance; instead, it serves as a call for action to examine social simulation for policy development.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.09639v4</guid>
   <category>cs.MA</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Abe Bohan Hou, Hongru Du, Yichen Wang, Jingyu Zhang, Zixiao Wang, Paul Pu Liang, Daniel Khashabi, Lauren Gardner, Tianxing He</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Can A Society of Generative Agents Simulate Human Behavior and Inform Public Health Policy? A Case Study on Vaccine Hesitancy</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09639</link>
   <description>Can we simulate a sandbox society with generative agents to model human behavior, thereby reducing the over-reliance on real human trials for assessing public policies? In this work, we investigate the feasibility of simulating health-related decision-making, using vaccine hesitancy, defined as the delay in acceptance or refusal of vaccines despite the availability of vaccination services (MacDonald, 2015), as a case study. To this end, we introduce the VacSim framework with 100 generative agents powered by Large Language Models (LLMs). VacSim simulates vaccine policy outcomes with the following steps: 1) instantiate a population of agents with demographics based on census data; 2) connect the agents via a social network and model vaccine attitudes as a function of social dynamics and disease-related information; 3) design and evaluate various public health interventions aimed at mitigating vaccine hesitancy. To align with real-world results, we also introduce simulation warmup and attitude modulation to adjust agents' attitudes. We propose a series of evaluations to assess the reliability of various LLM simulations. Experiments indicate that models like Llama and Qwen can simulate aspects of human behavior but also highlight real-world alignment challenges, such as inconsistent responses with demographic profiles. This early exploration of LLM-driven simulations is not meant to serve as definitive policy guidance; instead, it serves as a call for action to examine social simulation for policy development.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.09639v4</guid>
   <category>cs.MA</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Abe Bohan Hou, Hongru Du, Yichen Wang, Jingyu Zhang, Zixiao Wang, Paul Pu Liang, Daniel Khashabi, Lauren Gardner, Tianxing He</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>MCEval: A Dynamic Framework for Fair Multilingual Cultural Evaluation of LLMs</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09701</link>
   <description>Large language models exhibit cultural biases and limited cross-cultural understanding capabilities, particularly when serving diverse global user populations. We propose MCEval, a novel multilingual evaluation framework that employs dynamic cultural question construction and enables causal analysis through Counterfactual Rephrasing and Confounder Rephrasing. Our comprehensive evaluation spans 13 cultures and 13 languages, systematically assessing both cultural awareness and cultural bias across different linguistic scenarios. The framework provides 39,897 cultural awareness instances and 17,940 cultural bias instances. Experimental results reveal performance disparities across different linguistic scenarios, demonstrating that optimal cultural performance is not only linked to training data distribution, but also is related to language-culture alignment. The evaluation results also expose the fairness issue, where approaches appearing successful in the English scenario create substantial disadvantages. MCEval represents the first comprehensive multilingual cultural evaluation framework that provides deeper insights into LLMs' cultural understanding.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.09701v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shulin Huang, Linyi Yang, Yue Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>CodeJudgeBench: Benchmarking LLM-as-a-Judge for Coding Tasks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10535</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) have significantly advanced the state-of-the-art in various coding tasks. Beyond directly answering user queries, LLMs can also serve as judges, assessing and comparing the quality of responses generated by other models. Such an evaluation capability is crucial both for benchmarking different LLMs and for improving response quality through response ranking. However, despite the growing adoption of the LLM-as-a-Judge paradigm, its effectiveness in coding scenarios remains underexplored due to the absence of dedicated benchmarks. To address this gap, we introduce CodeJudgeBench, a benchmark explicitly designed to evaluate the performance of LLM-as-a-Judge models across three critical coding tasks: code generation, code repair, and unit test generation. Through comprehensive benchmarking of 26 LLM-as-a-Judge models, we find that recent thinking models significantly outperform non-thinking models on our carefully designed code judging tasks. Notably, even relatively small thinking models, such as Qwen3-8B, can outperform specially trained LLM-as-a-Judge models up to 70B in size. Nevertheless, all models still exhibit significant randomness in their judgment of coding tasks. For pairwise judging tasks, simply changing the order in which responses are presented can substantially impact accuracy. In addition, when judging code and unit tests written by different LLMs, LLM-as-a-Judge models also show variance in performance. This sensitivity raises concerns about the reliability and consistency of LLM-as-a-Judge in coding scenarios. Lastly, we study optimal prompting strategies for LLM-as-a-Judge. We find that using pair-wise comparison outperforms scalar point-wise judging. Furthermore, retaining comments and reasoning in the full, unprocessed LLM response leads to improved judge performance.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10535v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hongchao Jiang, Yiming Chen, Yushi Cao, Hung-yi Lee, Robby T. Tan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Towards Pareto Optimal Throughput in Small Language Model Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03353</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) have revolutionized the state-of-the-art of many different natural language processing tasks. Although serving LLMs is computationally and memory demanding, the rise of Small Language Models (SLMs) offers new opportunities for resource-constrained users, who now are able to serve small models with cutting-edge performance. In this paper, we present a set of experiments designed to benchmark SLM inference at performance and energy levels. Our analysis provides a new perspective in serving, highlighting that the small memory footprint of SLMs allows for reaching the Pareto-optimal throughput within the resource capacity of a single accelerator. In this regard, we present an initial set of findings demonstrating how model replication can effectively improve resource utilization for serving SLMs.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2404.03353v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Pol G. Recasens, Yue Zhu, Chen Wang, Eun Kyung Lee, Olivier Tardieu, Alaa Youssef, Jordi Torres, Josep Ll. Berral</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Evaluation of Attribution Bias in Generator-Aware Retrieval-Augmented Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12380</link>
   <description>Attributing answers to source documents is an approach used to enhance the verifiability of a model's output in retrieval augmented generation (RAG). Prior work has mainly focused on improving and evaluating the attribution quality of large language models (LLMs) in RAG, but this may come at the expense of inducing biases in the attribution of answers. We define and examine two aspects in the evaluation of LLMs in RAG pipelines, namely attribution sensitivity and bias with respect to authorship information. We explicitly inform an LLM about the authors of source documents, instruct it to attribute its answers, and analyze (i) how sensitive the LLM's output is to the author of source documents, and (ii) whether the LLM exhibits a bias towards human-written or AI-generated source documents. We design an experimental setup in which we use counterfactual evaluation to study three LLMs in terms of their attribution sensitivity and bias in RAG pipelines. Our results show that adding authorship information to source documents can significantly change the attribution quality of LLMs by 3% to 18%. Moreover, we show that LLMs can have an attribution bias towards explicit human authorship, which can serve as a competing hypothesis for findings of prior work that shows that LLM-generated content may be preferred over human-written contents. Our findings indicate that metadata of source documents can influence LLMs' trust, and how they attribute their answers. Furthermore, our research highlights attribution bias and sensitivity as a novel aspect of brittleness in LLMs.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.12380v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Amin Abolghasemi, Leif Azzopardi, Seyyed Hadi Hashemi, Maarten de Rijke, Suzan Verberne</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>InstCache: A Predictive Cache for LLM Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13820</link>
   <description>The revolutionary capabilities of Large Language Models (LLMs) are attracting rapidly growing popularity and leading to soaring user requests to inference serving systems. Caching techniques, which leverage data reuse to reduce computation, offer opportunities to optimize the performance of LLM inference engines. On the one hand, the low-level key-value (KV) cache working at the token level is widely adopted, albeit it incurs significant overhead as request volume grows. On the other hand, instruction-level caching, which stores full instruction-response pairs, is expected to play an increasingly crucial role. However, the high variability in the content and length of instructions make it rare for identical instructions to recur within a short time window, presenting challenges for effective caching instruction-response pairs. To address this challenge, we propose InstCache, a predictive caching mechanism for LLM serving systems. Leveraging the capability of LLMs, we can effectively reorder the representation space of instruction texts and develop a sufficient level of spatial locality. Such spatial locality enables us to predict potential instructions located in a compact region in the space, resulting in an effective caching system at runtime. Experimental results demonstrate that InstCache achieves a 2.3x higher hit rate compared to the upper bound of traditional caching mechanisms on WildChat dataset and reduces the time per output token of vLLM by up to 42.0% and 50.0% on LMSys and Moss datasets, respectively.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2411.13820v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Longwei Zou, Yan Liu, Jiamu Kang, Tingfeng Liu, Jiangang Kong, Yangdong Deng</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>HYPEROFA: Expanding LLM Vocabulary to New Languages via Hypernetwork-Based Embedding Initialization</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21018</link>
   <description>Many pre-trained language models (PLMs) exhibit suboptimal performance on mid- and low-resource languages, largely due to limited exposure to these languages during pre-training. A common strategy to address this is to introduce new tokens specific to the target languages, initialize their embeddings, and apply continual pre-training on target-language data. Among such methods, OFA (Liu et al., 2024a) proposes a similarity-based subword embedding initialization heuristic that is both effective and efficient. However, OFA restricts target-language token embeddings to be convex combinations of a fixed number of source-language embeddings, which may limit expressiveness. To overcome this limitation, we propose HYPEROFA, a hypernetwork-based approach for more adaptive token embedding initialization. The hypernetwork is trained to map from an external multilingual word vector space to the PLMs token embedding space using source-language tokens. Once trained, it can generate flexible embeddings for target-language tokens, serving as a good starting point for continual pretraining. Experiments demonstrate that HYPEROFA consistently outperforms random initialization baseline and matches or exceeds the performance of OFA in both continual pre-training convergence and downstream task performance. We make the code publicly available.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.21018v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Enes \&quot;Ozeren, Yihong Liu, Hinrich Sch\&quot;utze</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>From Fragments to Facts: A Curriculum-Driven DPO Approach for Generating Hindi News Veracity Explanations</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05179</link>
   <description>In an era of rampant misinformation, generating reliable news explanations is vital, especially for under-represented languages like Hindi. Lacking robust automated tools, Hindi faces challenges in scaling misinformation detection. To bridge this gap, we propose a novel framework integrating Direct Preference Optimization (DPO) with curriculum learning to align machine-generated explanations with human reasoning. Fact-checked explanations from credible sources serve as preferred responses, while LLM outputs highlight system limitations and serve as non-preferred responses. To refine task-specific alignment, we introduce two key parameters -- Actuality and Finesse -- into the DPO loss function, enhancing explanation quality and consistency. Experiments with LLMs (Mistral, Llama, Gemma) and PLMs (mBART, mT5) confirm the framework's effectiveness in generating coherent, contextually relevant explanations. This scalable approach combats misinformation and extends automated explanation generation to low-resource languages.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.05179v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Pulkit Bansal, Raghvendra Kumar, Shakti Singh, Sriparna Saha, Adam Jatowt</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Can A Society of Generative Agents Simulate Human Behavior and Inform Public Health Policy? A Case Study on Vaccine Hesitancy</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09639</link>
   <description>Can we simulate a sandbox society with generative agents to model human behavior, thereby reducing the over-reliance on real human trials for assessing public policies? In this work, we investigate the feasibility of simulating health-related decision-making, using vaccine hesitancy, defined as the delay in acceptance or refusal of vaccines despite the availability of vaccination services (MacDonald, 2015), as a case study. To this end, we introduce the VacSim framework with 100 generative agents powered by Large Language Models (LLMs). VacSim simulates vaccine policy outcomes with the following steps: 1) instantiate a population of agents with demographics based on census data; 2) connect the agents via a social network and model vaccine attitudes as a function of social dynamics and disease-related information; 3) design and evaluate various public health interventions aimed at mitigating vaccine hesitancy. To align with real-world results, we also introduce simulation warmup and attitude modulation to adjust agents' attitudes. We propose a series of evaluations to assess the reliability of various LLM simulations. Experiments indicate that models like Llama and Qwen can simulate aspects of human behavior but also highlight real-world alignment challenges, such as inconsistent responses with demographic profiles. This early exploration of LLM-driven simulations is not meant to serve as definitive policy guidance; instead, it serves as a call for action to examine social simulation for policy development.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.09639v4</guid>
   <category>cs.MA</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Abe Bohan Hou, Hongru Du, Yichen Wang, Jingyu Zhang, Zixiao Wang, Paul Pu Liang, Daniel Khashabi, Lauren Gardner, Tianxing He</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
