<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 04:14:08 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 04:14:08 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Discrete Denoising Diffusion Model for Molecular Generation with OpenFL</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12523</link>
   <description>Generating unique molecules with biochemically desired properties to serve as viable drug candidates is a difficult task that requires specialized domain expertise. In recent years, diffusion models have shown promising results in accelerating the drug design process through AI-driven molecular generation. However, training these models requires massive amounts of data, which are often isolated in proprietary silos. OpenFL is a federated learning framework that enables privacy-preserving collaborative training across these decentralized data sites. In this work, we present a federated discrete denoising diffusion model that was trained using OpenFL. The federated model achieves comparable performance with a model trained on centralized data when evaluating the uniqueness and validity of the generated molecules. This demonstrates the utility of federated learning in the drug design process.
  OpenFL is available at: https://github.com/securefederatedai/openfl</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12523v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kevin Ta, Patrick Foley, Mattson Thieme, Abhishek Pandey, Prashant Shah</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedGrAINS: Personalized SubGraph Federated Learning with Adaptive Neighbor Sampling</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12592</link>
   <description>Graphs are crucial for modeling relational and biological data. As datasets grow larger in real-world scenarios, the risk of exposing sensitive information increases, making privacy-preserving training methods like federated learning (FL) essential to ensure data security and compliance with privacy regulations. Recently proposed personalized subgraph FL methods have become the de-facto standard for training personalized Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) in a federated manner while dealing with the missing links across clients' subgraphs due to privacy restrictions. However, personalized subgraph FL faces significant challenges due to the heterogeneity in client subgraphs, such as degree distributions among the nodes, which complicate federated training of graph models. To address these challenges, we propose \textit{FedGrAINS}, a novel data-adaptive and sampling-based regularization method for subgraph FL. FedGrAINS leverages generative flow networks (GFlowNets) to evaluate node importance concerning clients' tasks, dynamically adjusting the message-passing step in clients' GNNs. This adaptation reflects task-optimized sampling aligned with a trajectory balance objective. Experimental results demonstrate that the inclusion of \textit{FedGrAINS} as a regularizer consistently improves the FL performance compared to baselines that do not leverage such regularization.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12592v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Emir Ceyani, Han Xie, Baturalp Buyukates, Carl Yang, Salman Avestimehr</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>EchoLM: Accelerating LLM Serving with Real-time Knowledge Distillation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12689</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) have excelled in various applications, yet serving them at scale is challenging due to their substantial resource demands and high latency. Our real-world studies reveal that over 60% of user requests to LLMs have semantically similar counterparts, suggesting the potential for knowledge sharing among requests. However, naively caching and reusing past responses leads to large quality degradation. In this paper, we introduce EchoLM, an in-context caching system that leverages historical requests as examples to guide response generation, enabling selective offloading of requests to more efficient LLMs. However, enabling this real-time knowledge transfer leads to intricate tradeoffs between response quality, latency, and system throughput at scale. For a new request, EchoLM identifies similar, high-utility examples and efficiently prepends them to the input for better response. At scale, EchoLM adaptively routes requests to LLMs of varying capabilities, accounting for response quality and serving loads. EchoLM employs a cost-aware cache replay mechanism to improve example quality and coverage offline, maximizing cache utility and runtime efficiency. Evaluations on millions of open-source requests demonstrate that EchoLM has a throughput improvement of 1.4-5.9x while reducing latency by 28-71% without hurting response quality on average.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12689v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yifan Yu, Yu Gan, Lily Tasi, Nikhil Sarda, Jiaming Shen, Yanqi Zhou, Arvind Krishnamurthy, Fan Lai, Henry M. Levy, David Culler</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Anomaly Detection in Double-entry Bookkeeping Data by Federated Learning System with Non-model Sharing Approach</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12723</link>
   <description>Anomaly detection is crucial in financial auditing and effective detection often requires obtaining large volumes of data from multiple organizations. However, confidentiality concerns hinder data sharing among audit firms. Although the federated learning (FL)-based approach, FedAvg, has been proposed to address this challenge, its use of mutiple communication rounds increases its overhead, limiting its practicality. In this study, we propose a novel framework employing Data Collaboration (DC) analysis -- a non-model share-type FL method -- to streamline model training into a single communication round. Our method first encodes journal entry data via dimensionality reduction to obtain secure intermediate representations, then transforms them into collaboration representations for building an autoencoder that detects anomalies. We evaluate our approach on a synthetic dataset and real journal entry data from multiple organizations. The results show that our method not only outperforms single-organization baselines but also exceeds FedAvg in non-i.i.d. experiments on real journal entry data that closely mirror real-world conditions. By preserving data confidentiality and reducing iterative communication, this study addresses a key auditing challenge -- ensuring data confidentiality while integrating knowledge from multiple audit firms. Our findings represent a significant advance in artificial intelligence-driven auditing and underscore the potential of FL methods in high-security domains.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12723v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sota Mashiko, Yuji Kawamata, Tomoru Nakayama, Tetsuya Sakurai, Yukihiko Okada</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Bad-PFL: Exploring Backdoor Attacks against Personalized Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12736</link>
   <description>Data heterogeneity and backdoor attacks rank among the most significant challenges facing federated learning (FL). For data heterogeneity, personalized federated learning (PFL) enables each client to maintain a private personalized model to cater to client-specific knowledge. Meanwhile, vanilla FL has proven vulnerable to backdoor attacks. However, recent advancements in PFL community have demonstrated a potential immunity against such attacks. This paper explores this intersection further, revealing that existing federated backdoor attacks fail in PFL because backdoors about manually designed triggers struggle to survive in personalized models. To tackle this, we design Bad-PFL, which employs features from natural data as our trigger. As long as the model is trained on natural data, it inevitably embeds the backdoor associated with our trigger, ensuring its longevity in personalized models. Moreover, our trigger undergoes mutual reinforcement training with the model, further solidifying the backdoor's durability and enhancing attack effectiveness. The large-scale experiments across three benchmark datasets demonstrate the superior performance of our attack against various PFL methods, even when equipped with state-of-the-art defense mechanisms.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12736v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mingyuan Fan, Zhanyi Hu, Fuyi Wang, Cen Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>It's complicated. The relationship of algorithmic fairness and non-discrimination regulations in the EU AI Act</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12962</link>
   <description>What constitutes a fair decision? This question is not only difficult for humans but becomes more challenging when Artificial Intelligence (AI) models are used. In light of discriminatory algorithmic behaviors, the EU has recently passed the AI Act, which mandates specific rules for AI models, incorporating both traditional legal non-discrimination regulations and machine learning based algorithmic fairness concepts. This paper aims to bridge these two different concepts in the AI Act through: First a high-level introduction of both concepts targeting legal and computer science-oriented scholars, and second an in-depth analysis of the AI Act's relationship between legal non-discrimination regulations and algorithmic fairness. Our analysis reveals three key findings: (1.), most non-discrimination regulations target only high-risk AI systems. (2.), the regulation of high-risk systems encompasses both data input requirements and output monitoring, though these regulations are often inconsistent and raise questions of computational feasibility. (3.) Regulations for General Purpose AI Models, such as Large Language Models that are not simultaneously classified as high-risk systems, currently lack specificity compared to other regulations. Based on these findings, we recommend developing more specific auditing and testing methodologies for AI systems. This paper aims to serve as a foundation for future interdisciplinary collaboration between legal scholars and computer science-oriented machine learning researchers studying discrimination in AI systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12962v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kristof Meding</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Selective Homomorphic Encryption Approach for Faster Privacy-Preserving Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12911</link>
   <description>Federated learning is a machine learning method that supports training models on decentralized devices or servers, where each holds its local data, removing the need for data exchange. This approach is especially useful in healthcare, as it enables training on sensitive data without needing to share them. The nature of federated learning necessitates robust security precautions due to data leakage concerns during communication. To address this issue, we propose a new approach that employs selective encryption, homomorphic encryption, differential privacy, and bit-wise scrambling to minimize data leakage while achieving good execution performance. Our technique , FAS (fast and secure federated learning) is used to train deep learning models on medical imaging data. We implemented our technique using the Flower framework and compared with a state-of-the-art federated learning approach that also uses selective homomorphic encryption. Our experiments were run in a cluster of eleven physical machines to create a real-world federated learning scenario on different datasets. We observed that our approach is up to 90\% faster than applying fully homomorphic encryption on the model weights. In addition, we can avoid the pretraining step that is required by our competitor and can save up to 20\% in terms of total execution time. While our approach was faster, it obtained similar security results as the competitor.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12911v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Abdulkadir Korkmaz, Praveen Rao</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Refining Input Guardrails: Enhancing LLM-as-a-Judge Efficiency Through Chain-of-Thought Fine-Tuning and Alignment</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13080</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated powerful capabilities that render them valuable in different applications, including conversational AI products. It is paramount to ensure the security and reliability of these products by mitigating their vulnerabilities towards malicious user interactions, which can lead to the exposure of great risks and reputational repercussions. In this work, we present a comprehensive study on the efficacy of fine-tuning and aligning Chain-of-Thought (CoT) responses of different LLMs that serve as input moderation guardrails. We systematically explore various tuning methods by leveraging a small set of training data to adapt these models as proxy defense mechanisms to detect malicious inputs and provide a reasoning for their verdicts, thereby preventing the exploitation of conversational agents. We rigorously evaluate the efficacy and robustness of different tuning strategies to generalize across diverse adversarial and malicious query types. Our experimental results outline the potential of alignment processes tailored to a varied range of harmful input queries, even with constrained data resources. These techniques significantly enhance the safety of conversational AI systems and provide a feasible framework for deploying more secure and trustworthy AI-driven interactions.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.13080v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Melissa Kazemi Rad, Huy Nghiem, Andy Luo, Sahil Wadhwa, Mohammad Sorower, Stephen Rawls</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Yi-Lightning Technical Report</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01253</link>
   <description>This technical report presents Yi-Lightning, our latest flagship large language model (LLM). It achieves exceptional performance, ranking 6th overall on Chatbot Arena, with particularly strong results (2nd to 4th place) in specialized categories including Chinese, Math, Coding, and Hard Prompts. Yi-Lightning leverages an enhanced Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) architecture, featuring advanced expert segmentation and routing mechanisms coupled with optimized KV-caching techniques. Our development process encompasses comprehensive pre-training, supervised fine-tuning (SFT), and reinforcement learning from human feedback (RLHF), where we devise deliberate strategies for multi-stage training, synthetic data construction, and reward modeling. Furthermore, we implement RAISE (Responsible AI Safety Engine), a four-component framework to address safety issues across pre-training, post-training, and serving phases. Empowered by our scalable super-computing infrastructure, all these innovations substantially reduce training, deployment and inference costs while maintaining high-performance standards. With further evaluations on public academic benchmarks, Yi-Lightning demonstrates competitive performance against top-tier LLMs, while we observe a notable disparity between traditional, static benchmark results and real-world, dynamic human preferences. This observation prompts a critical reassessment of conventional benchmarks' utility in guiding the development of more intelligent and powerful AI systems for practical applications. Yi-Lightning is now available through our developer platform at https://platform.lingyiwanwu.com.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.01253v5</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Alan Wake, Bei Chen, C. X. Lv, Chao Li, Chengen Huang, Chenglin Cai, Chujie Zheng, Daniel Cooper, Fan Zhou, Feng Hu, Ge Zhang, Guoyin Wang, Heng Ji, Howard Qiu, Jiangcheng Zhu, Jun Tian, Katherine Su, Lihuan Zhang, Liying Li, Ming Song, Mou Li, Peng Liu, Qicheng Hu, Shawn Wang, Shijun Zhou, Shiming Yang, Shiyong Li, Tianhang Zhu, Wen Xie, Wenhao Huang, Xiang He, Xiaobo Chen, Xiaohui Hu, Xiaoyi Ren, Xinyao Niu, Yanpeng Li, Yongke Zhao, Yongzhen Luo, Yuchi Xu, Yuxuan Sha, Zhaodong Yan, Zhiyuan Liu, Zirui Zhang, Zonghong Dai</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Personalized Federated Learning for Cellular VR: Online Learning and Dynamic Caching</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11745</link>
   <description>Delivering an immersive experience to virtual reality (VR) users through wireless connectivity offers the freedom to engage from anywhere at any time. Nevertheless, it is challenging to ensure seamless wireless connectivity that delivers real-time and high-quality videos to the VR users. This paper proposes a field of view (FoV) aware caching for mobile edge computing (MEC)-enabled wireless VR network. In particular, the FoV of each VR user is cached/prefetched at the base stations (BSs) based on the caching strategies tailored to each BS. Specifically, decentralized and personalized federated learning (DP-FL) based caching strategies with guarantees are presented. Considering VR systems composed of multiple VR devices and BSs, a DP-FL caching algorithm is implemented at each BS to personalize content delivery for VR users. The utilized DP-FL algorithm guarantees a probably approximately correct (PAC) bound on the conditional average cache hit. Further, to reduce the cost of communicating gradients, one-bit quantization of the stochastic gradient descent (OBSGD) is proposed, and a convergence guarantee of $\mathcal{O}(1/\sqrt{T})$ is obtained for the proposed algorithm, where $T$ is the number of iterations. Additionally, to better account for the wireless channel dynamics, the FoVs are grouped into multicast or unicast groups based on the number of requesting VR users. The performance of the proposed DP-FL algorithm is validated through realistic VR head-tracking dataset, and the proposed algorithm is shown to have better performance in terms of average delay and cache hit as compared to baseline algorithms.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.11745v2</guid>
   <category>cs.IT</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>math.IT</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Krishnendu S. Tharakan, Hayssam Dahrouj, Nour Kouzayha, Hesham ElSawy, Tareq Y. Al-Naffouri</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedGrAINS: Personalized SubGraph Federated Learning with Adaptive Neighbor Sampling</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12592</link>
   <description>Graphs are crucial for modeling relational and biological data. As datasets grow larger in real-world scenarios, the risk of exposing sensitive information increases, making privacy-preserving training methods like federated learning (FL) essential to ensure data security and compliance with privacy regulations. Recently proposed personalized subgraph FL methods have become the de-facto standard for training personalized Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) in a federated manner while dealing with the missing links across clients' subgraphs due to privacy restrictions. However, personalized subgraph FL faces significant challenges due to the heterogeneity in client subgraphs, such as degree distributions among the nodes, which complicate federated training of graph models. To address these challenges, we propose \textit{FedGrAINS}, a novel data-adaptive and sampling-based regularization method for subgraph FL. FedGrAINS leverages generative flow networks (GFlowNets) to evaluate node importance concerning clients' tasks, dynamically adjusting the message-passing step in clients' GNNs. This adaptation reflects task-optimized sampling aligned with a trajectory balance objective. Experimental results demonstrate that the inclusion of \textit{FedGrAINS} as a regularizer consistently improves the FL performance compared to baselines that do not leverage such regularization.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12592v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Emir Ceyani, Han Xie, Baturalp Buyukates, Carl Yang, Salman Avestimehr</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Practical quantum federated learning and its experimental demonstration</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12709</link>
   <description>Federated learning is essential for decentralized, privacy-preserving model training in the data-driven era. Quantum-enhanced federated learning leverages quantum resources to address privacy and scalability challenges, offering security and efficiency advantages beyond classical methods. However, practical and scalable frameworks addressing privacy concerns in the quantum computing era remain undeveloped. Here, we propose a practical quantum federated learning framework on quantum networks, utilizing distributed quantum secret keys to protect local model updates and enable secure aggregation with information-theoretic security. We experimentally validate our framework on a 4-client quantum network with a scalable structure. Extensive numerical experiments on both quantum and classical datasets show that adding a quantum client significantly enhances the trained global model's ability to classify multipartite entangled and non-stabilizer quantum datasets. Simulations further demonstrate scalability to 200 clients with classical models trained on the MNIST dataset, reducing communication costs by $75\%$ through advanced model compression techniques and achieving rapid training convergence. Our work provides critical insights for building scalable, efficient, and quantum-secure machine learning systems for the coming quantum internet era.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12709v1</guid>
   <category>quant-ph</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhi-Ping Liu, Xiao-Yu Cao, Hao-Wen Liu, Xiao-Ran Sun, Yu Bao, Yu-Shuo Lu, Hua-Lei Yin, Zeng-Bing Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Selective Homomorphic Encryption Approach for Faster Privacy-Preserving Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12911</link>
   <description>Federated learning is a machine learning method that supports training models on decentralized devices or servers, where each holds its local data, removing the need for data exchange. This approach is especially useful in healthcare, as it enables training on sensitive data without needing to share them. The nature of federated learning necessitates robust security precautions due to data leakage concerns during communication. To address this issue, we propose a new approach that employs selective encryption, homomorphic encryption, differential privacy, and bit-wise scrambling to minimize data leakage while achieving good execution performance. Our technique , FAS (fast and secure federated learning) is used to train deep learning models on medical imaging data. We implemented our technique using the Flower framework and compared with a state-of-the-art federated learning approach that also uses selective homomorphic encryption. Our experiments were run in a cluster of eleven physical machines to create a real-world federated learning scenario on different datasets. We observed that our approach is up to 90\% faster than applying fully homomorphic encryption on the model weights. In addition, we can avoid the pretraining step that is required by our competitor and can save up to 20\% in terms of total execution time. While our approach was faster, it obtained similar security results as the competitor.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12911v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Abdulkadir Korkmaz, Praveen Rao</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>MicroPython Testbed for Federated Learning Algorithms</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09423</link>
   <description>Recently, Python Testbed for Federated Learning Algorithms emerged as a low code and generative large language models amenable framework for developing decentralized and distributed applications, primarily targeting edge systems, by nonprofessional programmers with the help of emerging artificial intelligence tools. This light framework is written in pure Python to be easy to install and to fit into a small IoT memory. It supports formally verified generic centralized and decentralized federated learning algorithms, as well as the peer-to-peer data exchange used in time division multiplexing communication, and its current main limitation is that all the application instances can run only on a single PC. This paper presents the MicroPyton Testbed for Federated Learning Algorithms, the new framework that overcomes its predecessor's limitation such that individual application instances may run on different network nodes like PCs and IoTs, primarily in edge systems. The new framework carries on the pure Python ideal, is based on asynchronous I/O abstractions, and runs on MicroPython, and therefore is a great match for IoTs and devices in edge systems. The new framework was experimentally validated on a wireless network comprising PCs and Raspberry Pi Pico W boards, by using application examples originally developed for the predecessor framework.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2405.09423v2</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Miroslav Popovic, Marko Popovic, Ivan Kastelan, Miodrag Djukic, Ilija Basicevic</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Towards Formal Verification of Federated Learning Orchestration Protocols on Satellites</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13429</link>
   <description>Python Testbed for Federated Learning Algorithms (PTB-FLA) is a simple FL framework targeting smart Internet of Things in edge systems that provides both generic centralized and decentralized FL algorithms, which implement the corresponding FL orchestration protocols that were formally verified using the process algebra CSP. This approach is appropriate for systems with stationary nodes but cannot be applied to systems with moving nodes. In this paper, we use celestial mechanics to model spacecraft movement, and timed automata (TA) to formalize and verify the centralized FL orchestration protocol, in two phases. In the first phase, we created a conventional TA model to prove traditional properties, namely deadlock freeness and termination. In the second phase, we created a stochastic TA model to prove timing correctness and to estimate termination probability.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.13429v2</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Miroslav Popovic, Marko Popovic, Miodrag Djukic, Ilija Basicevic</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Enhancing Privacy in the Early Detection of Sexual Predators Through Federated Learning and Differential Privacy</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12537</link>
   <description>The increased screen time and isolation caused by the COVID-19 pandemic have led to a significant surge in cases of online grooming, which is the use of strategies by predators to lure children into sexual exploitation. Previous efforts to detect grooming in industry and academia have involved accessing and monitoring private conversations through centrally-trained models or sending private conversations to a global server. In this work, we implement a privacy-preserving pipeline for the early detection of sexual predators. We leverage federated learning and differential privacy in order to create safer online spaces for children while respecting their privacy. We investigate various privacy-preserving implementations and discuss their benefits and shortcomings. Our extensive evaluation using real-world data proves that privacy and utility can coexist with only a slight reduction in utility.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12537v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Khaoula Chehbouni, Martine De Cock, Gilles Caporossi, Afaf Taik, Reihaneh Rabbany, Golnoosh Farnadi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Human-like conceptual representations emerge from language prediction</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12547</link>
   <description>Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) provide a new opportunity to address the long-standing question of how concepts are represented and organized in the mind, which is central to unravelling the nature of human cognition. Here, we reframed the classic reverse dictionary task to simulate human concept inference in context and investigated the emergence of human-like conceptual representations within LLMs. We found that LLMs were able to infer concepts from definitional descriptions and construct representation spaces that converge towards a shared, context-independent structure. These representations effectively predicted human behavioural judgments and aligned well with neural activity patterns in the human brain, offering evidence for biological plausibility. These findings demonstrate that human-like conceptual representations and organization can naturally emerge from language prediction, even without real-world grounding. Our work supports the view that LLMs serve as valuable tools for understanding complex human cognition and paves the way for better alignment between artificial and human intelligence.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12547v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ningyu Xu, Qi Zhang, Chao Du, Qiang Luo, Xipeng Qiu, Xuanjing Huang, Menghan Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Refining Input Guardrails: Enhancing LLM-as-a-Judge Efficiency Through Chain-of-Thought Fine-Tuning and Alignment</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13080</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated powerful capabilities that render them valuable in different applications, including conversational AI products. It is paramount to ensure the security and reliability of these products by mitigating their vulnerabilities towards malicious user interactions, which can lead to the exposure of great risks and reputational repercussions. In this work, we present a comprehensive study on the efficacy of fine-tuning and aligning Chain-of-Thought (CoT) responses of different LLMs that serve as input moderation guardrails. We systematically explore various tuning methods by leveraging a small set of training data to adapt these models as proxy defense mechanisms to detect malicious inputs and provide a reasoning for their verdicts, thereby preventing the exploitation of conversational agents. We rigorously evaluate the efficacy and robustness of different tuning strategies to generalize across diverse adversarial and malicious query types. Our experimental results outline the potential of alignment processes tailored to a varied range of harmful input queries, even with constrained data resources. These techniques significantly enhance the safety of conversational AI systems and provide a feasible framework for deploying more secure and trustworthy AI-driven interactions.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.13080v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Melissa Kazemi Rad, Huy Nghiem, Andy Luo, Sahil Wadhwa, Mohammad Sorower, Stephen Rawls</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Yi-Lightning Technical Report</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01253</link>
   <description>This technical report presents Yi-Lightning, our latest flagship large language model (LLM). It achieves exceptional performance, ranking 6th overall on Chatbot Arena, with particularly strong results (2nd to 4th place) in specialized categories including Chinese, Math, Coding, and Hard Prompts. Yi-Lightning leverages an enhanced Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) architecture, featuring advanced expert segmentation and routing mechanisms coupled with optimized KV-caching techniques. Our development process encompasses comprehensive pre-training, supervised fine-tuning (SFT), and reinforcement learning from human feedback (RLHF), where we devise deliberate strategies for multi-stage training, synthetic data construction, and reward modeling. Furthermore, we implement RAISE (Responsible AI Safety Engine), a four-component framework to address safety issues across pre-training, post-training, and serving phases. Empowered by our scalable super-computing infrastructure, all these innovations substantially reduce training, deployment and inference costs while maintaining high-performance standards. With further evaluations on public academic benchmarks, Yi-Lightning demonstrates competitive performance against top-tier LLMs, while we observe a notable disparity between traditional, static benchmark results and real-world, dynamic human preferences. This observation prompts a critical reassessment of conventional benchmarks' utility in guiding the development of more intelligent and powerful AI systems for practical applications. Yi-Lightning is now available through our developer platform at https://platform.lingyiwanwu.com.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.01253v5</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Alan Wake, Bei Chen, C. X. Lv, Chao Li, Chengen Huang, Chenglin Cai, Chujie Zheng, Daniel Cooper, Fan Zhou, Feng Hu, Ge Zhang, Guoyin Wang, Heng Ji, Howard Qiu, Jiangcheng Zhu, Jun Tian, Katherine Su, Lihuan Zhang, Liying Li, Ming Song, Mou Li, Peng Liu, Qicheng Hu, Shawn Wang, Shijun Zhou, Shiming Yang, Shiyong Li, Tianhang Zhu, Wen Xie, Wenhao Huang, Xiang He, Xiaobo Chen, Xiaohui Hu, Xiaoyi Ren, Xinyao Niu, Yanpeng Li, Yongke Zhao, Yongzhen Luo, Yuchi Xu, Yuxuan Sha, Zhaodong Yan, Zhiyuan Liu, Zirui Zhang, Zonghong Dai</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedGrAINS: Personalized SubGraph Federated Learning with Adaptive Neighbor Sampling</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12592</link>
   <description>Graphs are crucial for modeling relational and biological data. As datasets grow larger in real-world scenarios, the risk of exposing sensitive information increases, making privacy-preserving training methods like federated learning (FL) essential to ensure data security and compliance with privacy regulations. Recently proposed personalized subgraph FL methods have become the de-facto standard for training personalized Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) in a federated manner while dealing with the missing links across clients' subgraphs due to privacy restrictions. However, personalized subgraph FL faces significant challenges due to the heterogeneity in client subgraphs, such as degree distributions among the nodes, which complicate federated training of graph models. To address these challenges, we propose \textit{FedGrAINS}, a novel data-adaptive and sampling-based regularization method for subgraph FL. FedGrAINS leverages generative flow networks (GFlowNets) to evaluate node importance concerning clients' tasks, dynamically adjusting the message-passing step in clients' GNNs. This adaptation reflects task-optimized sampling aligned with a trajectory balance objective. Experimental results demonstrate that the inclusion of \textit{FedGrAINS} as a regularizer consistently improves the FL performance compared to baselines that do not leverage such regularization.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12592v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Emir Ceyani, Han Xie, Baturalp Buyukates, Carl Yang, Salman Avestimehr</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Bad-PFL: Exploring Backdoor Attacks against Personalized Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12736</link>
   <description>Data heterogeneity and backdoor attacks rank among the most significant challenges facing federated learning (FL). For data heterogeneity, personalized federated learning (PFL) enables each client to maintain a private personalized model to cater to client-specific knowledge. Meanwhile, vanilla FL has proven vulnerable to backdoor attacks. However, recent advancements in PFL community have demonstrated a potential immunity against such attacks. This paper explores this intersection further, revealing that existing federated backdoor attacks fail in PFL because backdoors about manually designed triggers struggle to survive in personalized models. To tackle this, we design Bad-PFL, which employs features from natural data as our trigger. As long as the model is trained on natural data, it inevitably embeds the backdoor associated with our trigger, ensuring its longevity in personalized models. Moreover, our trigger undergoes mutual reinforcement training with the model, further solidifying the backdoor's durability and enhancing attack effectiveness. The large-scale experiments across three benchmark datasets demonstrate the superior performance of our attack against various PFL methods, even when equipped with state-of-the-art defense mechanisms.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12736v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mingyuan Fan, Zhanyi Hu, Fuyi Wang, Cen Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Personalized Federated Learning for Cellular VR: Online Learning and Dynamic Caching</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11745</link>
   <description>Delivering an immersive experience to virtual reality (VR) users through wireless connectivity offers the freedom to engage from anywhere at any time. Nevertheless, it is challenging to ensure seamless wireless connectivity that delivers real-time and high-quality videos to the VR users. This paper proposes a field of view (FoV) aware caching for mobile edge computing (MEC)-enabled wireless VR network. In particular, the FoV of each VR user is cached/prefetched at the base stations (BSs) based on the caching strategies tailored to each BS. Specifically, decentralized and personalized federated learning (DP-FL) based caching strategies with guarantees are presented. Considering VR systems composed of multiple VR devices and BSs, a DP-FL caching algorithm is implemented at each BS to personalize content delivery for VR users. The utilized DP-FL algorithm guarantees a probably approximately correct (PAC) bound on the conditional average cache hit. Further, to reduce the cost of communicating gradients, one-bit quantization of the stochastic gradient descent (OBSGD) is proposed, and a convergence guarantee of $\mathcal{O}(1/\sqrt{T})$ is obtained for the proposed algorithm, where $T$ is the number of iterations. Additionally, to better account for the wireless channel dynamics, the FoVs are grouped into multicast or unicast groups based on the number of requesting VR users. The performance of the proposed DP-FL algorithm is validated through realistic VR head-tracking dataset, and the proposed algorithm is shown to have better performance in terms of average delay and cache hit as compared to baseline algorithms.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.11745v2</guid>
   <category>cs.IT</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>math.IT</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Krishnendu S. Tharakan, Hayssam Dahrouj, Nour Kouzayha, Hesham ElSawy, Tareq Y. Al-Naffouri</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Enhancing Privacy in the Early Detection of Sexual Predators Through Federated Learning and Differential Privacy</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12537</link>
   <description>The increased screen time and isolation caused by the COVID-19 pandemic have led to a significant surge in cases of online grooming, which is the use of strategies by predators to lure children into sexual exploitation. Previous efforts to detect grooming in industry and academia have involved accessing and monitoring private conversations through centrally-trained models or sending private conversations to a global server. In this work, we implement a privacy-preserving pipeline for the early detection of sexual predators. We leverage federated learning and differential privacy in order to create safer online spaces for children while respecting their privacy. We investigate various privacy-preserving implementations and discuss their benefits and shortcomings. Our extensive evaluation using real-world data proves that privacy and utility can coexist with only a slight reduction in utility.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12537v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Khaoula Chehbouni, Martine De Cock, Gilles Caporossi, Afaf Taik, Reihaneh Rabbany, Golnoosh Farnadi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>It's complicated. The relationship of algorithmic fairness and non-discrimination regulations in the EU AI Act</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12962</link>
   <description>What constitutes a fair decision? This question is not only difficult for humans but becomes more challenging when Artificial Intelligence (AI) models are used. In light of discriminatory algorithmic behaviors, the EU has recently passed the AI Act, which mandates specific rules for AI models, incorporating both traditional legal non-discrimination regulations and machine learning based algorithmic fairness concepts. This paper aims to bridge these two different concepts in the AI Act through: First a high-level introduction of both concepts targeting legal and computer science-oriented scholars, and second an in-depth analysis of the AI Act's relationship between legal non-discrimination regulations and algorithmic fairness. Our analysis reveals three key findings: (1.), most non-discrimination regulations target only high-risk AI systems. (2.), the regulation of high-risk systems encompasses both data input requirements and output monitoring, though these regulations are often inconsistent and raise questions of computational feasibility. (3.) Regulations for General Purpose AI Models, such as Large Language Models that are not simultaneously classified as high-risk systems, currently lack specificity compared to other regulations. Based on these findings, we recommend developing more specific auditing and testing methodologies for AI systems. This paper aims to serve as a foundation for future interdisciplinary collaboration between legal scholars and computer science-oriented machine learning researchers studying discrimination in AI systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12962v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kristof Meding</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Human-like conceptual representations emerge from language prediction</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12547</link>
   <description>Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) provide a new opportunity to address the long-standing question of how concepts are represented and organized in the mind, which is central to unravelling the nature of human cognition. Here, we reframed the classic reverse dictionary task to simulate human concept inference in context and investigated the emergence of human-like conceptual representations within LLMs. We found that LLMs were able to infer concepts from definitional descriptions and construct representation spaces that converge towards a shared, context-independent structure. These representations effectively predicted human behavioural judgments and aligned well with neural activity patterns in the human brain, offering evidence for biological plausibility. These findings demonstrate that human-like conceptual representations and organization can naturally emerge from language prediction, even without real-world grounding. Our work supports the view that LLMs serve as valuable tools for understanding complex human cognition and paves the way for better alignment between artificial and human intelligence.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12547v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ningyu Xu, Qi Zhang, Chao Du, Qiang Luo, Xipeng Qiu, Xuanjing Huang, Menghan Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedGrAINS: Personalized SubGraph Federated Learning with Adaptive Neighbor Sampling</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12592</link>
   <description>Graphs are crucial for modeling relational and biological data. As datasets grow larger in real-world scenarios, the risk of exposing sensitive information increases, making privacy-preserving training methods like federated learning (FL) essential to ensure data security and compliance with privacy regulations. Recently proposed personalized subgraph FL methods have become the de-facto standard for training personalized Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) in a federated manner while dealing with the missing links across clients' subgraphs due to privacy restrictions. However, personalized subgraph FL faces significant challenges due to the heterogeneity in client subgraphs, such as degree distributions among the nodes, which complicate federated training of graph models. To address these challenges, we propose \textit{FedGrAINS}, a novel data-adaptive and sampling-based regularization method for subgraph FL. FedGrAINS leverages generative flow networks (GFlowNets) to evaluate node importance concerning clients' tasks, dynamically adjusting the message-passing step in clients' GNNs. This adaptation reflects task-optimized sampling aligned with a trajectory balance objective. Experimental results demonstrate that the inclusion of \textit{FedGrAINS} as a regularizer consistently improves the FL performance compared to baselines that do not leverage such regularization.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12592v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Emir Ceyani, Han Xie, Baturalp Buyukates, Carl Yang, Salman Avestimehr</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Practical quantum federated learning and its experimental demonstration</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12709</link>
   <description>Federated learning is essential for decentralized, privacy-preserving model training in the data-driven era. Quantum-enhanced federated learning leverages quantum resources to address privacy and scalability challenges, offering security and efficiency advantages beyond classical methods. However, practical and scalable frameworks addressing privacy concerns in the quantum computing era remain undeveloped. Here, we propose a practical quantum federated learning framework on quantum networks, utilizing distributed quantum secret keys to protect local model updates and enable secure aggregation with information-theoretic security. We experimentally validate our framework on a 4-client quantum network with a scalable structure. Extensive numerical experiments on both quantum and classical datasets show that adding a quantum client significantly enhances the trained global model's ability to classify multipartite entangled and non-stabilizer quantum datasets. Simulations further demonstrate scalability to 200 clients with classical models trained on the MNIST dataset, reducing communication costs by $75\%$ through advanced model compression techniques and achieving rapid training convergence. Our work provides critical insights for building scalable, efficient, and quantum-secure machine learning systems for the coming quantum internet era.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12709v1</guid>
   <category>quant-ph</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhi-Ping Liu, Xiao-Yu Cao, Hao-Wen Liu, Xiao-Ran Sun, Yu Bao, Yu-Shuo Lu, Hua-Lei Yin, Zeng-Bing Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>It's complicated. The relationship of algorithmic fairness and non-discrimination regulations in the EU AI Act</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12962</link>
   <description>What constitutes a fair decision? This question is not only difficult for humans but becomes more challenging when Artificial Intelligence (AI) models are used. In light of discriminatory algorithmic behaviors, the EU has recently passed the AI Act, which mandates specific rules for AI models, incorporating both traditional legal non-discrimination regulations and machine learning based algorithmic fairness concepts. This paper aims to bridge these two different concepts in the AI Act through: First a high-level introduction of both concepts targeting legal and computer science-oriented scholars, and second an in-depth analysis of the AI Act's relationship between legal non-discrimination regulations and algorithmic fairness. Our analysis reveals three key findings: (1.), most non-discrimination regulations target only high-risk AI systems. (2.), the regulation of high-risk systems encompasses both data input requirements and output monitoring, though these regulations are often inconsistent and raise questions of computational feasibility. (3.) Regulations for General Purpose AI Models, such as Large Language Models that are not simultaneously classified as high-risk systems, currently lack specificity compared to other regulations. Based on these findings, we recommend developing more specific auditing and testing methodologies for AI systems. This paper aims to serve as a foundation for future interdisciplinary collaboration between legal scholars and computer science-oriented machine learning researchers studying discrimination in AI systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12962v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kristof Meding</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Yi-Lightning Technical Report</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01253</link>
   <description>This technical report presents Yi-Lightning, our latest flagship large language model (LLM). It achieves exceptional performance, ranking 6th overall on Chatbot Arena, with particularly strong results (2nd to 4th place) in specialized categories including Chinese, Math, Coding, and Hard Prompts. Yi-Lightning leverages an enhanced Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) architecture, featuring advanced expert segmentation and routing mechanisms coupled with optimized KV-caching techniques. Our development process encompasses comprehensive pre-training, supervised fine-tuning (SFT), and reinforcement learning from human feedback (RLHF), where we devise deliberate strategies for multi-stage training, synthetic data construction, and reward modeling. Furthermore, we implement RAISE (Responsible AI Safety Engine), a four-component framework to address safety issues across pre-training, post-training, and serving phases. Empowered by our scalable super-computing infrastructure, all these innovations substantially reduce training, deployment and inference costs while maintaining high-performance standards. With further evaluations on public academic benchmarks, Yi-Lightning demonstrates competitive performance against top-tier LLMs, while we observe a notable disparity between traditional, static benchmark results and real-world, dynamic human preferences. This observation prompts a critical reassessment of conventional benchmarks' utility in guiding the development of more intelligent and powerful AI systems for practical applications. Yi-Lightning is now available through our developer platform at https://platform.lingyiwanwu.com.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.01253v5</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Alan Wake, Bei Chen, C. X. Lv, Chao Li, Chengen Huang, Chenglin Cai, Chujie Zheng, Daniel Cooper, Fan Zhou, Feng Hu, Ge Zhang, Guoyin Wang, Heng Ji, Howard Qiu, Jiangcheng Zhu, Jun Tian, Katherine Su, Lihuan Zhang, Liying Li, Ming Song, Mou Li, Peng Liu, Qicheng Hu, Shawn Wang, Shijun Zhou, Shiming Yang, Shiyong Li, Tianhang Zhu, Wen Xie, Wenhao Huang, Xiang He, Xiaobo Chen, Xiaohui Hu, Xiaoyi Ren, Xinyao Niu, Yanpeng Li, Yongke Zhao, Yongzhen Luo, Yuchi Xu, Yuxuan Sha, Zhaodong Yan, Zhiyuan Liu, Zirui Zhang, Zonghong Dai</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
