<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 03:30:11 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 03:30:11 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>Multi-Modal Multi-Task Federated Foundation Models for Next-Generation Extended Reality Systems: Towards Privacy-Preserving Distributed Intelligence in AR/VR/MR</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05683</link>
   <description>Extended reality (XR) systems, which consist of virtual reality (VR), augmented reality (AR), and mixed reality (XR), offer a transformative interface for immersive, multi-modal, and embodied human-computer interaction. In this paper, we envision that multi-modal multi-task (M3T) federated foundation models (FedFMs) can offer transformative capabilities for XR systems through integrating the representational strength of M3T foundation models (FMs) with the privacy-preserving model training principles of federated learning (FL). We present a modular architecture for FedFMs, which entails different coordination paradigms for model training and aggregations. Central to our vision is the codification of XR challenges that affect the implementation of FedFMs under the SHIFT dimensions: (1) Sensor and modality diversity, (2) Hardware heterogeneity and system-level constraints, (3) Interactivity and embodied personalization, (4) Functional/task variability, and (5) Temporality and environmental variability. We illustrate the manifestation of these dimensions across a set of emerging and anticipated applications of XR systems. Finally, we propose evaluation metrics, dataset requirements, and design tradeoffs necessary for the development of resource-aware FedFMs in XR. This perspective aims to chart the technical and conceptual foundations for context-aware privacy-preserving intelligence in the next generation of XR systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.05683v4</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.MM</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Fardis Nadimi, Payam Abdisarabshali, Kasra Borazjani, Jacob Chakareski, Seyyedali Hosseinalipour</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>TURA: Tool-Augmented Unified Retrieval Agent for AI Search</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04604</link>
   <description>The advent of Large Language Models (LLMs) is transforming search engines into conversational AI search products, primarily using Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) on web corpora. However, this paradigm has significant industrial limitations. Traditional RAG approaches struggle with real-time needs and structured queries that require accessing dynamically generated content like ticket availability or inventory. Limited to indexing static pages, search engines cannot perform the interactive queries needed for such time-sensitive data. Academic research has focused on optimizing RAG for static content, overlooking complex intents and the need for dynamic sources like databases and real-time APIs. To bridge this gap, we introduce TURA (Tool-Augmented Unified Retrieval Agent for AI Search), a novel three-stage framework that combines RAG with agentic tool-use to access both static content and dynamic, real-time information. TURA has three key components: an Intent-Aware Retrieval module to decompose queries and retrieve information sources encapsulated as Model Context Protocol (MCP) Servers, a DAG-based Task Planner that models task dependencies as a Directed Acyclic Graph (DAG) for optimal parallel execution, and a lightweight Distilled Agent Executor for efficient tool calling. TURA is the first architecture to systematically bridge the gap between static RAG and dynamic information sources for a world-class AI search product. Serving tens of millions of users, it leverages an agentic framework to deliver robust, real-time answers while meeting the low-latency demands of a large-scale industrial system.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.04604v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhejun Zhao, Yuehu Dong, Alley Liu, Lixue Zheng, Pingsheng Liu, Dongdong Shen, Long Xia, Jiashu Zhao, Dawei Yin</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FLAT: Latent-Driven Arbitrary-Target Backdoor Attacks in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04064</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) is vulnerable to backdoor attacks, yet most existing methods are limited by fixed-pattern or single-target triggers, making them inflexible and easier to detect. We propose FLAT (FL Arbitrary-Target Attack), a novel backdoor attack that leverages a latent-driven conditional autoencoder to generate diverse, target-specific triggers as needed. By introducing a latent code, FLAT enables the creation of visually adaptive and highly variable triggers, allowing attackers to select arbitrary targets without retraining and to evade conventional detection mechanisms. Our approach unifies attack success, stealth, and diversity within a single framework, introducing a new level of flexibility and sophistication to backdoor attacks in FL. Extensive experiments show that FLAT achieves high attack success and remains robust against advanced FL defenses. These results highlight the urgent need for new defense strategies to address latent-driven, multi-target backdoor threats in federated settings.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.04064v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Tuan Nguyen, Khoa D Doan, Kok-Seng Wong</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Decoupled Contrastive Learning for Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04005</link>
   <description>Federated learning is a distributed machine learning paradigm that allows multiple participants to train a shared model by exchanging model updates instead of their raw data. However, its performance is degraded compared to centralized approaches due to data heterogeneity across clients. While contrastive learning has emerged as a promising approach to mitigate this, our theoretical analysis reveals a fundamental conflict: its asymptotic assumptions of an infinite number of negative samples are violated in finite-sample regime of federated learning. To address this issue, we introduce Decoupled Contrastive Learning for Federated Learning (DCFL), a novel framework that decouples the existing contrastive loss into two objectives. Decoupling the loss into its alignment and uniformity components enables the independent calibration of the attraction and repulsion forces without relying on the asymptotic assumptions. This strategy provides a contrastive learning method suitable for federated learning environments where each client has a small amount of data. Our experimental results show that DCFL achieves stronger alignment between positive samples and greater uniformity between negative samples compared to existing contrastive learning methods. Furthermore, experimental results on standard benchmarks, including CIFAR-10, CIFAR-100, and Tiny-ImageNet, demonstrate that DCFL consistently outperforms state-of-the-art federated learning methods.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.04005v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hyungbin Kim, Incheol Baek, Yon Dohn Chung</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FeDaL: Federated Dataset Learning for Time Series Foundation Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04045</link>
   <description>Dataset-wise heterogeneity introduces significant domain biases that fundamentally degrade generalization on Time Series Foundation Models (TSFMs), yet this challenge remains underexplored. This paper rethink the development of TSFMs using the paradigm of federated learning. We propose a novel Federated Dataset Learning (FeDaL) approach to tackle heterogeneous time series by learning dataset-agnostic temporal representations. Specifically, the distributed architecture of federated learning is a nature solution to decompose heterogeneous TS datasets into shared generalized knowledge and preserved personalized knowledge. Moreover, based on the TSFM architecture, FeDaL explicitly mitigates both local and global biases by adding two complementary mechanisms: Domain Bias Elimination (DBE) and Global Bias Elimination (GBE). FeDaL`s cross-dataset generalization has been extensively evaluated in real-world datasets spanning eight tasks, including both representation learning and downstream time series analysis, against 54 baselines. We further analyze federated scaling behavior, showing how data volume, client count, and join rate affect model performance under decentralization.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.04045v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shengchao Chen, Guodong Long, Jing Jiang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FLAT: Latent-Driven Arbitrary-Target Backdoor Attacks in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04064</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) is vulnerable to backdoor attacks, yet most existing methods are limited by fixed-pattern or single-target triggers, making them inflexible and easier to detect. We propose FLAT (FL Arbitrary-Target Attack), a novel backdoor attack that leverages a latent-driven conditional autoencoder to generate diverse, target-specific triggers as needed. By introducing a latent code, FLAT enables the creation of visually adaptive and highly variable triggers, allowing attackers to select arbitrary targets without retraining and to evade conventional detection mechanisms. Our approach unifies attack success, stealth, and diversity within a single framework, introducing a new level of flexibility and sophistication to backdoor attacks in FL. Extensive experiments show that FLAT achieves high attack success and remains robust against advanced FL defenses. These results highlight the urgent need for new defense strategies to address latent-driven, multi-target backdoor threats in federated settings.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.04064v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Tuan Nguyen, Khoa D Doan, Kok-Seng Wong</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FlexQ: Efficient Post-training INT6 Quantization for LLM Serving via Algorithm-System Co-Design</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04405</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) demonstrate exceptional performance but entail significant memory and computational costs, restricting their practical deployment. While existing INT4/INT8 quantization reduces these costs, they often degrade accuracy or lack optimal efficiency. INT6 quantization offers a superior trade-off between model accuracy and inference efficiency, but lacks hardware support in modern GPUs, forcing emulation via higher-precision arithmetic units that limit acceleration.
  In this paper, we propose FlexQ, a novel post-training INT6 quantization framework combining algorithmic innovation with system-level optimizations. FlexQ employs uniform 6-bit weight quantization across all layers, with adaptive retention of 8-bit activations in layers identified through layer-wise sensitivity analysis. To maximize hardware efficiency, we develop a specialized high-performance GPU kernel supporting matrix multiplication for W6A6 and W6A8 representations via Binary Tensor Core (BTC) equivalents, effectively bypassing the lack of native INT6 tensor cores. Evaluations on LLaMA models show FlexQ maintains near-FP16 accuracy, with perplexity increases of no more than 0.05. The proposed kernel achieves an average 1.39$\times$ speedup over ABQ-LLM on LLaMA-2-70B linear layers. End-to-end, FlexQ delivers 1.33$\times$ inference acceleration and 1.21$\times$ memory savings over SmoothQuant. Code is released at https://github.com/FlyFoxPlayer/FlexQ.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.04405v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hao Zhang, Aining Jia, Weifeng Bu, Yushu Cai, Kai Sheng, Hao Chen, Xin He</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedHiP: Heterogeneity-Invariant Personalized Federated Learning Through Closed-Form Solutions</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04470</link>
   <description>Lately, Personalized Federated Learning (PFL) has emerged as a prevalent paradigm to deliver personalized models by collaboratively training while simultaneously adapting to each client's local applications. Existing PFL methods typically face a significant challenge due to the ubiquitous data heterogeneity (i.e., non-IID data) across clients, which severely hinders convergence and degrades performance. We identify that the root issue lies in the long-standing reliance on gradient-based updates, which are inherently sensitive to non-IID data. To fundamentally address this issue and bridge the research gap, in this paper, we propose a Heterogeneity-invariant Personalized Federated learning scheme, named FedHiP, through analytical (i.e., closed-form) solutions to avoid gradient-based updates. Specifically, we exploit the trend of self-supervised pre-training, leveraging a foundation model as a frozen backbone for gradient-free feature extraction. Following the feature extractor, we further develop an analytic classifier for gradient-free training. To support both collective generalization and individual personalization, our FedHiP scheme incorporates three phases: analytic local training, analytic global aggregation, and analytic local personalization. The closed-form solutions of our FedHiP scheme enable its ideal property of heterogeneity invariance, meaning that each personalized model remains identical regardless of how non-IID the data are distributed across all other clients. Extensive experiments on benchmark datasets validate the superiority of our FedHiP scheme, outperforming the state-of-the-art baselines by at least 5.79%-20.97% in accuracy.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.04470v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jianheng Tang, Zhirui Yang, Jingchao Wang, Kejia Fan, Jinfeng Xu, Huiping Zhuang, Anfeng Liu, Houbing Herbert Song, Leye Wang, Yunhuai Liu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Channel-Independent Federated Traffic Prediction</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04517</link>
   <description>In recent years, traffic prediction has achieved remarkable success and has become an integral component of intelligent transportation systems. However, traffic data is typically distributed among multiple data owners, and privacy constraints prevent the direct utilization of these isolated datasets for traffic prediction. Most existing federated traffic prediction methods focus on designing communication mechanisms that allow models to leverage information from other clients in order to improve prediction accuracy. Unfortunately, such approaches often incur substantial communication overhead, and the resulting transmission delays significantly slow down the training process. As the volume of traffic data continues to grow, this issue becomes increasingly critical, making the resource consumption of current methods unsustainable. To address this challenge, we propose a novel variable relationship modeling paradigm for federated traffic prediction, termed the Channel-Independent Paradigm(CIP). Unlike traditional approaches, CIP eliminates the need for inter-client communication by enabling each node to perform efficient and accurate predictions using only local information. Based on the CIP, we further develop Fed-CI, an efficient federated learning framework, allowing each client to process its own data independently while effectively mitigating the information loss caused by the lack of direct data sharing among clients. Fed-CI significantly reduces communication overhead, accelerates the training process, and achieves state-of-the-art performance while complying with privacy regulations. Extensive experiments on multiple real-world datasets demonstrate that Fed-CI consistently outperforms existing methods across all datasets and federated settings. It achieves improvements of 8%, 14%, and 16% in RMSE, MAE, and MAPE, respectively, while also substantially reducing communication costs.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.04517v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mo Zhang, Xiaoyu Li, Bin Xu, Meng Chen, Yongshun Gong</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Evaluating Selective Encryption Against Gradient Inversion Attacks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04155</link>
   <description>Gradient inversion attacks pose significant privacy threats to distributed training frameworks such as federated learning, enabling malicious parties to reconstruct sensitive local training data from gradient communications between clients and an aggregation server during the aggregation process. While traditional encryption-based defenses, such as homomorphic encryption, offer strong privacy guarantees without compromising model utility, they often incur prohibitive computational overheads. To mitigate this, selective encryption has emerged as a promising approach, encrypting only a subset of gradient data based on the data's significance under a certain metric. However, there have been few systematic studies on how to specify this metric in practice. This paper systematically evaluates selective encryption methods with different significance metrics against state-of-the-art attacks. Our findings demonstrate the feasibility of selective encryption in reducing computational overhead while maintaining resilience against attacks. We propose a distance-based significance analysis framework that provides theoretical foundations for selecting critical gradient elements for encryption. Through extensive experiments on different model architectures (LeNet, CNN, BERT, GPT-2) and attack types, we identify gradient magnitude as a generally effective metric for protection against optimization-based gradient inversions. However, we also observe that no single selective encryption strategy is universally optimal across all attack scenarios, and we provide guidelines for choosing appropriate strategies for different model architectures and privacy requirements.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.04155v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jiajun Gu, Yuhang Yao, Shuaiqi Wang, Carlee Joe-Wong</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Multi-Modal Multi-Task Federated Foundation Models for Next-Generation Extended Reality Systems: Towards Privacy-Preserving Distributed Intelligence in AR/VR/MR</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05683</link>
   <description>Extended reality (XR) systems, which consist of virtual reality (VR), augmented reality (AR), and mixed reality (XR), offer a transformative interface for immersive, multi-modal, and embodied human-computer interaction. In this paper, we envision that multi-modal multi-task (M3T) federated foundation models (FedFMs) can offer transformative capabilities for XR systems through integrating the representational strength of M3T foundation models (FMs) with the privacy-preserving model training principles of federated learning (FL). We present a modular architecture for FedFMs, which entails different coordination paradigms for model training and aggregations. Central to our vision is the codification of XR challenges that affect the implementation of FedFMs under the SHIFT dimensions: (1) Sensor and modality diversity, (2) Hardware heterogeneity and system-level constraints, (3) Interactivity and embodied personalization, (4) Functional/task variability, and (5) Temporality and environmental variability. We illustrate the manifestation of these dimensions across a set of emerging and anticipated applications of XR systems. Finally, we propose evaluation metrics, dataset requirements, and design tradeoffs necessary for the development of resource-aware FedFMs in XR. This perspective aims to chart the technical and conceptual foundations for context-aware privacy-preserving intelligence in the next generation of XR systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.05683v4</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.MM</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Fardis Nadimi, Payam Abdisarabshali, Kasra Borazjani, Jacob Chakareski, Seyyedali Hosseinalipour</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Heterogeneity-Oblivious Robust Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03579</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) remains highly vulnerable to poisoning attacks, especially under real-world hyper-heterogeneity, where clients differ significantly in data distributions, communication capabilities, and model architectures. Such heterogeneity not only undermines the effectiveness of aggregation strategies but also makes attacks more difficult to detect. Furthermore, high-dimensional models expand the attack surface. To address these challenges, we propose Horus, a heterogeneity-oblivious robust FL framework centered on low-rank adaptations (LoRAs). Rather than aggregating full model parameters, Horus inserts LoRAs into empirically stable layers and aggregates only LoRAs to reduce the attack uncover a key empirical observation that the input projection (LoRA-A) is markedly more stable than the output projection (LoRA-B) under heterogeneity and poisoning. Leveraging this, we design a Heterogeneity-Oblivious Poisoning Score using the features from LoRA-A to filter poisoned clients. For the remaining benign clients, we propose projection-aware aggregation mechanism to preserve collaborative signals while suppressing drifts, which reweights client updates by consistency with the global directions. Extensive experiments across diverse datasets, model architectures, and attacks demonstrate that Horus consistently outperforms state-of-the-art baselines in both robustness and accuracy.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.03579v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.NI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Weiyao Zhang, Jinyang Li, Qi Song, Miao Wang, Chungang Lin, Haitong Luo, Xuying Meng, Yujun Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Adaptive Coded Federated Learning: Privacy Preservation and Straggler Mitigation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14905</link>
   <description>In this article, we address the problem of federated learning in the presence of stragglers. For this problem, a coded federated learning framework has been proposed, where the central server aggregates gradients received from the non-stragglers and gradient computed from a privacy-preservation global coded dataset to mitigate the negative impact of the stragglers. However, when aggregating these gradients, fixed weights are consistently applied across iterations, neglecting the generation process of the global coded dataset and the dynamic nature of the trained model over iterations. This oversight may result in diminished learning performance. To overcome this drawback, we propose a new method named adaptive coded federated learning (ACFL). In ACFL, before the training, each device uploads a coded local dataset with additive noise to the central server to generate a global coded dataset under privacy preservation requirements. During each iteration of the training, the central server aggregates the gradients received from the non-stragglers and the gradient computed from the global coded dataset, where an adaptive policy for varying the aggregation weights is designed. Under this policy, we optimize the performance in terms of privacy and learning, where the learning performance is analyzed through convergence analysis and the privacy performance is characterized via mutual information differential privacy. Finally, we perform simulations to demonstrate the superiority of ACFL compared with the non-adaptive methods.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2403.14905v2</guid>
   <category>eess.SP</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chengxi Li, Ming Xiao, Mikael Skoglund</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Traceable Black-box Watermarks for Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13651</link>
   <description>Due to the distributed nature of Federated Learning (FL) systems, each local client has access to the global model, posing a critical risk of model leakage. Existing works have explored injecting watermarks into local models to enable intellectual property protection. However, these methods either focus on non-traceable watermarks or traceable but white-box watermarks. We identify a gap in the literature regarding the formal definition of traceable black-box watermarking and the formulation of the problem of injecting such watermarks into FL systems. In this work, we first formalize the problem of injecting traceable black-box watermarks into FL. Based on the problem, we propose a novel server-side watermarking method, $\mathbf{TraMark}$, which creates a traceable watermarked model for each client, enabling verification of model leakage in black-box settings. To achieve this, $\mathbf{TraMark}$ partitions the model parameter space into two distinct regions: the main task region and the watermarking region. Subsequently, a personalized global model is constructed for each client by aggregating only the main task region while preserving the watermarking region. Each model then learns a unique watermark exclusively within the watermarking region using a distinct watermark dataset before being sent back to the local client. Extensive results across various FL systems demonstrate that $\mathbf{TraMark}$ ensures the traceability of all watermarked models while preserving their main task performance.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.13651v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jiahao Xu, Rui Hu, Olivera Kotevska, Zikai Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>SelectiveShield: Lightweight Hybrid Defense Against Gradient Leakage in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04265</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) enables collaborative model training on decentralized data but remains vulnerable to gradient leakage attacks that can reconstruct sensitive user information. Existing defense mechanisms, such as differential privacy (DP) and homomorphic encryption (HE), often introduce a trade-off between privacy, model utility, and system overhead, a challenge that is exacerbated in heterogeneous environments with non-IID data and varying client capabilities. To address these limitations, we propose SelectiveShield, a lightweight hybrid defense framework that adaptively integrates selective homomorphic encryption and differential privacy. SelectiveShield leverages Fisher information to quantify parameter sensitivity, allowing clients to identify critical parameters locally. Through a collaborative negotiation protocol, clients agree on a shared set of the most sensitive parameters for protection via homomorphic encryption. Parameters that are uniquely important to individual clients are retained locally, fostering personalization, while non-critical parameters are protected with adaptive differential privacy noise. Extensive experiments demonstrate that SelectiveShield maintains strong model utility while significantly mitigating gradient leakage risks, offering a practical and scalable defense mechanism for real-world federated learning deployments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.04265v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Borui Li, Li Yan, Jianmin Liu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>SenseCrypt: Sensitivity-guided Selective Homomorphic Encryption for Joint Federated Learning in Cross-Device Scenarios</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04100</link>
   <description>Homomorphic Encryption (HE) prevails in securing Federated Learning (FL), but suffers from high overhead and adaptation cost. Selective HE methods, which partially encrypt model parameters by a global mask, are expected to protect privacy with reduced overhead and easy adaptation. However, in cross-device scenarios with heterogeneous data and system capabilities, traditional Selective HE methods deteriorate client straggling, and suffer from degraded HE overhead reduction performance. Accordingly, we propose SenseCrypt, a Sensitivity-guided selective Homomorphic EnCryption framework, to adaptively balance security and HE overhead per cross-device FL client. Given the observation that model parameter sensitivity is effective for measuring clients' data distribution similarity, we first design a privacy-preserving method to respectively cluster the clients with similar data distributions. Then, we develop a scoring mechanism to deduce the straggler-free ratio of model parameters that can be encrypted by each client per cluster. Finally, for each client, we formulate and solve a multi-objective model parameter selection optimization problem, which minimizes HE overhead while maximizing model security without causing straggling. Experiments demonstrate that SenseCrypt ensures security against the state-of-the-art inversion attacks, while achieving normal model accuracy as on IID data, and reducing training time by 58.4%-88.7% as compared to traditional HE methods.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.04100v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Borui Li, Li Yan, Junhao Han, Jianmin Liu, Lei Yu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>xDeepServe: Model-as-a-Service on Huawei CloudMatrix384</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02520</link>
   <description>The rise of scaled-out LLMs and scaled-up SuperPods signals a new era in large-scale AI infrastructure. LLMs continue to scale out via MoE, as seen in recent models like DeepSeek, Kimi, and Qwen. In parallel, AI hardware is scaling up, with Huawei's CloudMatrix384 SuperPod offering hundreds of GB/s high-speed interconnects. Running large MoE models on SuperPod-scale hardware brings new challenges. It requires new execution models, scalable scheduling, efficient expert load balancing, and elimination of single points of failure. This paper presents xDeepServe, Huawei Cloud's LLM serving system designed for SuperPod-scale infrastructure. At its core is Transformerless, a disaggregated architecture that decomposes transformer models into modular units--attention, feedforward, and MoE--executed independently on NPUs connected via high-speed fabric. We implement this design in two forms: disaggregated prefill-decode and disaggregated MoE-attention. This fully disaggregated setup enables independent scaling of compute and memory without sacrificing performance. To support this architecture, we propose XCCL, a communication library that leverages CloudMatrix384's global shared memory to implement efficient point-to-point and all-to-all primitives. We also extend our serving engine FlowServe with system-level techniques, enabling scalable inference across hundreds of NPUs.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.02520v4</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ao Xiao, Bangzheng He, Baoquan Zhang, Baoxing Huai, Bingji Wang, Bo Wang, Bo Xu, Boyi Hou, Chan Yang, Changhong Liu, Cheng Cui, Chenyu Zhu, Cong Feng, Daohui Wang, Dayun Lin, Duo Zhao, Fengshao Zou, Fu Wang, Gangqiang Zhang, Gengyuan Dan, Guanjie Chen, Guodong Guan, Guodong Yang, Haifeng Li, Haipei Zhu, Hao Feng, Hao Huang, Hao Xu, Hengrui Ma, Hengtao Fan, Hui Liu, Jia Li, Jiang Liu, Jiang Xu, Jie Meng, Jinhan Xin, Junhao Hu, Juwei Chen, Lan Yu, Lanxin Miao, Liang Liu, Linan Jing, Lu Zhou, Meina Han, Mingkun Deng, Mingyu Deng, Naitian Deng, Nizhong Lin, Peihan Zhao, Peng Pan, Pengfei Shen, Ping Li, Qi Zhang, Qin Zhang, Qingrong Xia, Qingyi Zhang, Qunchao Fu, Ren Guo, Ruimin Gao, Shaochun Li, Sheng Long, Shentian Li, Shining Wan, Shuai Shen, Shuangfu Zeng, Shuming Jing, Siqi Yang, Song Zhang, Tao Xu, Tianlin Du, Ting Chen, Wanxu Wu, Wei Jiang, Weinan Tong, Weiwei Chen, Wen Peng, Wenli Zhou, Wenquan Yang, Wenxin Liang, Xiang Liu, Xiaoli Zhou, Xin Jin, Xinyu Duan, Xu Li, Xu Zhang, Xusheng Chen, Yalong Shan, Yang Gan, Yao Lu, Yi Deng, Yi Zheng, Yingfei Zheng, Yiyun Zheng, Yizhou Shan, Yong Gao, Yongqiang Yang, Yuanjin Gong, Yue Yu, Yuetao Chen, Yukun Zhu, Yulong He, Yusu Zhao, Yuyan Wu, Zenan Zhang, Zhaojin Zhuo, Zhaoyang Ji, Zhefeng Wang, Zheng Wang, Zhenhua Yang, Zhenli Sheng, Zhibin Yu, Zhigang Ji, Zhihao Ren, Zhipeng Bian, Zhixia Liu, Zhiyu Dong, Zhonghua Li, Zhou Yu, Zhuoming Shen, Zhuwei Peng, Zi Ye, Zihao Xiang, Zimin Fu, Zixuan Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FLAT: Latent-Driven Arbitrary-Target Backdoor Attacks in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04064</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) is vulnerable to backdoor attacks, yet most existing methods are limited by fixed-pattern or single-target triggers, making them inflexible and easier to detect. We propose FLAT (FL Arbitrary-Target Attack), a novel backdoor attack that leverages a latent-driven conditional autoencoder to generate diverse, target-specific triggers as needed. By introducing a latent code, FLAT enables the creation of visually adaptive and highly variable triggers, allowing attackers to select arbitrary targets without retraining and to evade conventional detection mechanisms. Our approach unifies attack success, stealth, and diversity within a single framework, introducing a new level of flexibility and sophistication to backdoor attacks in FL. Extensive experiments show that FLAT achieves high attack success and remains robust against advanced FL defenses. These results highlight the urgent need for new defense strategies to address latent-driven, multi-target backdoor threats in federated settings.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.04064v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Tuan Nguyen, Khoa D Doan, Kok-Seng Wong</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>SenseCrypt: Sensitivity-guided Selective Homomorphic Encryption for Joint Federated Learning in Cross-Device Scenarios</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04100</link>
   <description>Homomorphic Encryption (HE) prevails in securing Federated Learning (FL), but suffers from high overhead and adaptation cost. Selective HE methods, which partially encrypt model parameters by a global mask, are expected to protect privacy with reduced overhead and easy adaptation. However, in cross-device scenarios with heterogeneous data and system capabilities, traditional Selective HE methods deteriorate client straggling, and suffer from degraded HE overhead reduction performance. Accordingly, we propose SenseCrypt, a Sensitivity-guided selective Homomorphic EnCryption framework, to adaptively balance security and HE overhead per cross-device FL client. Given the observation that model parameter sensitivity is effective for measuring clients' data distribution similarity, we first design a privacy-preserving method to respectively cluster the clients with similar data distributions. Then, we develop a scoring mechanism to deduce the straggler-free ratio of model parameters that can be encrypted by each client per cluster. Finally, for each client, we formulate and solve a multi-objective model parameter selection optimization problem, which minimizes HE overhead while maximizing model security without causing straggling. Experiments demonstrate that SenseCrypt ensures security against the state-of-the-art inversion attacks, while achieving normal model accuracy as on IID data, and reducing training time by 58.4%-88.7% as compared to traditional HE methods.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.04100v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Borui Li, Li Yan, Junhao Han, Jianmin Liu, Lei Yu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>SelectiveShield: Lightweight Hybrid Defense Against Gradient Leakage in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04265</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) enables collaborative model training on decentralized data but remains vulnerable to gradient leakage attacks that can reconstruct sensitive user information. Existing defense mechanisms, such as differential privacy (DP) and homomorphic encryption (HE), often introduce a trade-off between privacy, model utility, and system overhead, a challenge that is exacerbated in heterogeneous environments with non-IID data and varying client capabilities. To address these limitations, we propose SelectiveShield, a lightweight hybrid defense framework that adaptively integrates selective homomorphic encryption and differential privacy. SelectiveShield leverages Fisher information to quantify parameter sensitivity, allowing clients to identify critical parameters locally. Through a collaborative negotiation protocol, clients agree on a shared set of the most sensitive parameters for protection via homomorphic encryption. Parameters that are uniquely important to individual clients are retained locally, fostering personalization, while non-critical parameters are protected with adaptive differential privacy noise. Extensive experiments demonstrate that SelectiveShield maintains strong model utility while significantly mitigating gradient leakage risks, offering a practical and scalable defense mechanism for real-world federated learning deployments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.04265v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Borui Li, Li Yan, Jianmin Liu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>TURA: Tool-Augmented Unified Retrieval Agent for AI Search</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04604</link>
   <description>The advent of Large Language Models (LLMs) is transforming search engines into conversational AI search products, primarily using Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) on web corpora. However, this paradigm has significant industrial limitations. Traditional RAG approaches struggle with real-time needs and structured queries that require accessing dynamically generated content like ticket availability or inventory. Limited to indexing static pages, search engines cannot perform the interactive queries needed for such time-sensitive data. Academic research has focused on optimizing RAG for static content, overlooking complex intents and the need for dynamic sources like databases and real-time APIs. To bridge this gap, we introduce TURA (Tool-Augmented Unified Retrieval Agent for AI Search), a novel three-stage framework that combines RAG with agentic tool-use to access both static content and dynamic, real-time information. TURA has three key components: an Intent-Aware Retrieval module to decompose queries and retrieve information sources encapsulated as Model Context Protocol (MCP) Servers, a DAG-based Task Planner that models task dependencies as a Directed Acyclic Graph (DAG) for optimal parallel execution, and a lightweight Distilled Agent Executor for efficient tool calling. TURA is the first architecture to systematically bridge the gap between static RAG and dynamic information sources for a world-class AI search product. Serving tens of millions of users, it leverages an agentic framework to deliver robust, real-time answers while meeting the low-latency demands of a large-scale industrial system.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.04604v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhejun Zhao, Yuehu Dong, Alley Liu, Lixue Zheng, Pingsheng Liu, Dongdong Shen, Long Xia, Jiashu Zhao, Dawei Yin</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Multi-Modal Multi-Task Federated Foundation Models for Next-Generation Extended Reality Systems: Towards Privacy-Preserving Distributed Intelligence in AR/VR/MR</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05683</link>
   <description>Extended reality (XR) systems, which consist of virtual reality (VR), augmented reality (AR), and mixed reality (XR), offer a transformative interface for immersive, multi-modal, and embodied human-computer interaction. In this paper, we envision that multi-modal multi-task (M3T) federated foundation models (FedFMs) can offer transformative capabilities for XR systems through integrating the representational strength of M3T foundation models (FMs) with the privacy-preserving model training principles of federated learning (FL). We present a modular architecture for FedFMs, which entails different coordination paradigms for model training and aggregations. Central to our vision is the codification of XR challenges that affect the implementation of FedFMs under the SHIFT dimensions: (1) Sensor and modality diversity, (2) Hardware heterogeneity and system-level constraints, (3) Interactivity and embodied personalization, (4) Functional/task variability, and (5) Temporality and environmental variability. We illustrate the manifestation of these dimensions across a set of emerging and anticipated applications of XR systems. Finally, we propose evaluation metrics, dataset requirements, and design tradeoffs necessary for the development of resource-aware FedFMs in XR. This perspective aims to chart the technical and conceptual foundations for context-aware privacy-preserving intelligence in the next generation of XR systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.05683v4</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.MM</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Fardis Nadimi, Payam Abdisarabshali, Kasra Borazjani, Jacob Chakareski, Seyyedali Hosseinalipour</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Heterogeneity-Oblivious Robust Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03579</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) remains highly vulnerable to poisoning attacks, especially under real-world hyper-heterogeneity, where clients differ significantly in data distributions, communication capabilities, and model architectures. Such heterogeneity not only undermines the effectiveness of aggregation strategies but also makes attacks more difficult to detect. Furthermore, high-dimensional models expand the attack surface. To address these challenges, we propose Horus, a heterogeneity-oblivious robust FL framework centered on low-rank adaptations (LoRAs). Rather than aggregating full model parameters, Horus inserts LoRAs into empirically stable layers and aggregates only LoRAs to reduce the attack uncover a key empirical observation that the input projection (LoRA-A) is markedly more stable than the output projection (LoRA-B) under heterogeneity and poisoning. Leveraging this, we design a Heterogeneity-Oblivious Poisoning Score using the features from LoRA-A to filter poisoned clients. For the remaining benign clients, we propose projection-aware aggregation mechanism to preserve collaborative signals while suppressing drifts, which reweights client updates by consistency with the global directions. Extensive experiments across diverse datasets, model architectures, and attacks demonstrate that Horus consistently outperforms state-of-the-art baselines in both robustness and accuracy.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.03579v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.NI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Weiyao Zhang, Jinyang Li, Qi Song, Miao Wang, Chungang Lin, Haitong Luo, Xuying Meng, Yujun Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>TURA: Tool-Augmented Unified Retrieval Agent for AI Search</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04604</link>
   <description>The advent of Large Language Models (LLMs) is transforming search engines into conversational AI search products, primarily using Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) on web corpora. However, this paradigm has significant industrial limitations. Traditional RAG approaches struggle with real-time needs and structured queries that require accessing dynamically generated content like ticket availability or inventory. Limited to indexing static pages, search engines cannot perform the interactive queries needed for such time-sensitive data. Academic research has focused on optimizing RAG for static content, overlooking complex intents and the need for dynamic sources like databases and real-time APIs. To bridge this gap, we introduce TURA (Tool-Augmented Unified Retrieval Agent for AI Search), a novel three-stage framework that combines RAG with agentic tool-use to access both static content and dynamic, real-time information. TURA has three key components: an Intent-Aware Retrieval module to decompose queries and retrieve information sources encapsulated as Model Context Protocol (MCP) Servers, a DAG-based Task Planner that models task dependencies as a Directed Acyclic Graph (DAG) for optimal parallel execution, and a lightweight Distilled Agent Executor for efficient tool calling. TURA is the first architecture to systematically bridge the gap between static RAG and dynamic information sources for a world-class AI search product. Serving tens of millions of users, it leverages an agentic framework to deliver robust, real-time answers while meeting the low-latency demands of a large-scale industrial system.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2508.04604v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhejun Zhao, Yuehu Dong, Alley Liu, Lixue Zheng, Pingsheng Liu, Dongdong Shen, Long Xia, Jiashu Zhao, Dawei Yin</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
