<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 04:15:24 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 04:15:24 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>From Binary to Bilingual: How the National Weather Service is Using Artificial Intelligence to Develop a Comprehensive Translation Program</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14369</link>
   <description>To advance a Weather-Ready Nation, the National Weather Service (NWS) is developing a systematic translation program to better serve the 68.8 million people in the U.S. who do not speak English at home. This article outlines the foundation of an automated translation tool for NWS products, powered by artificial intelligence. The NWS has partnered with LILT, whose patented training process enables large language models (LLMs) to adapt neural machine translation (NMT) tools for weather terminology and messaging. Designed for scalability across Weather Forecast Offices (WFOs) and National Centers, the system is currently being developed in Spanish, Simplified Chinese, Vietnamese, and other widely spoken non-English languages. Rooted in best practices for multilingual risk communication, the system provides accurate, timely, and culturally relevant translations, significantly reducing manual translation time and easing operational workloads across the NWS. To guide the distribution of these products, GIS mapping was used to identify language needs across different NWS regions, helping prioritize resources for the communities that need them most. We also integrated ethical AI practices throughout the program's design, ensuring that transparency, fairness, and human oversight guide how automated translations are created, evaluated, and shared with the public. This work has culminated into a website featuring experimental multilingual NWS products, including translated warnings, 7-day forecasts, and educational campaigns, bringing the country one step closer to a national warning system that reaches all Americans.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14369v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Joseph E. Trujillo-Falcon, Monica L. Bozeman, Liam E. Llewellyn, Samuel T. Halvorson, Meryl Mizell, Stuti Deshpande, Bob Manning, Todd Fagin</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Leveraging Multimodal LLM Descriptions of Activity for Explainable Semi-Supervised Video Anomaly Detection</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14896</link>
   <description>Existing semi-supervised video anomaly detection (VAD) methods often struggle with detecting complex anomalies involving object interactions and generally lack explainability. To overcome these limitations, we propose a novel VAD framework leveraging Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs). Unlike previous MLLM-based approaches that make direct anomaly judgments at the frame level, our method focuses on extracting and interpreting object activity and interactions over time. By querying an MLLM with visual inputs of object pairs at different moments, we generate textual descriptions of the activity and interactions from nominal videos. These textual descriptions serve as a high-level representation of the activity and interactions of objects in a video. They are used to detect anomalies during test time by comparing them to textual descriptions found in nominal training videos. Our approach inherently provides explainability and can be combined with many traditional VAD methods to further enhance their interpretability. Extensive experiments on benchmark datasets demonstrate that our method not only detects complex interaction-based anomalies effectively but also achieves state-of-the-art performance on datasets without interaction anomalies.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14896v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Furkan Mumcu, Michael J. Jones, Anoop Cherian, Yasin Yilmaz</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>GOPLA: Generalizable Object Placement Learning via Synthetic Augmentation of Human Arrangement</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14627</link>
   <description>Robots are expected to serve as intelligent assistants, helping humans with everyday household organization. A central challenge in this setting is the task of object placement, which requires reasoning about both semantic preferences (e.g., common-sense object relations) and geometric feasibility (e.g., collision avoidance). We present GOPLA, a hierarchical framework that learns generalizable object placement from augmented human demonstrations. A multi-modal large language model translates human instructions and visual inputs into structured plans that specify pairwise object relationships. These plans are then converted into 3D affordance maps with geometric common sense by a spatial mapper, while a diffusion-based planner generates placement poses guided by test-time costs, considering multi-plan distributions and collision avoidance. To overcome data scarcity, we introduce a scalable pipeline that expands human placement demonstrations into diverse synthetic training data. Extensive experiments show that our approach improves placement success rates by 30.04 percentage points over the runner-up, evaluated on positioning accuracy and physical plausibility, demonstrating strong generalization across a wide range of real-world robotic placement scenarios.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14627v1</guid>
   <category>cs.RO</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yao Zhong, Hanzhi Chen, Simon Schaefer, Anran Zhang, Stefan Leutenegger</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>MX+: Pushing the Limits of Microscaling Formats for Efficient Large Language Model Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14557</link>
   <description>Reduced-precision data formats are crucial for cost-effective serving of large language models (LLMs). While numerous reduced-precision formats have been introduced thus far, they often require intrusive modifications to the software frameworks or are rather unconventional for widespread adoption across hardware vendors. In this paper, we instead focus on recent industry-driven variants of block floating-point (BFP) formats and conduct a comprehensive analysis to push their limits for efficient LLM serving. Our analysis shows that existing ultra low-bit BFP variants struggle to provide reasonable language model performance due to outlier values in blocks. To address the outliers with BFPs, we propose MX+, a cost-effective and non-intrusive extension designed for seamless integration into the microscaling (MX) formats. MX+ builds on the key insight that the outlier does not need to use its exponent field in the element data type, which allows us to repurpose the exponent field as an extended mantissa to increase the precision of the outlier element. Our evaluation shows that MX+ achieves significantly higher model performance compared to the 4-bit MX format (MXFP4) with negligible storage overhead and slowdown, thus offering a compelling alternative to MXFP4 or MXFP6 for efficient LLM inference.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14557v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AR</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jungi Lee, Junyong Park, Soohyun Cha, Jaehoon Cho, Jaewoong Sim</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>GOPLA: Generalizable Object Placement Learning via Synthetic Augmentation of Human Arrangement</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14627</link>
   <description>Robots are expected to serve as intelligent assistants, helping humans with everyday household organization. A central challenge in this setting is the task of object placement, which requires reasoning about both semantic preferences (e.g., common-sense object relations) and geometric feasibility (e.g., collision avoidance). We present GOPLA, a hierarchical framework that learns generalizable object placement from augmented human demonstrations. A multi-modal large language model translates human instructions and visual inputs into structured plans that specify pairwise object relationships. These plans are then converted into 3D affordance maps with geometric common sense by a spatial mapper, while a diffusion-based planner generates placement poses guided by test-time costs, considering multi-plan distributions and collision avoidance. To overcome data scarcity, we introduce a scalable pipeline that expands human placement demonstrations into diverse synthetic training data. Extensive experiments show that our approach improves placement success rates by 30.04 percentage points over the runner-up, evaluated on positioning accuracy and physical plausibility, demonstrating strong generalization across a wide range of real-world robotic placement scenarios.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14627v1</guid>
   <category>cs.RO</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yao Zhong, Hanzhi Chen, Simon Schaefer, Anran Zhang, Stefan Leutenegger</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedHFT: Efficient Federated Finetuning with Heterogeneous Edge Clients</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14054</link>
   <description>Fine-tuning pre-trained large language models (LLMs) has become a common practice for personalized natural language understanding (NLU) applications on downstream tasks and domain-specific datasets. However, there are two main challenges: (i) limited and/or heterogeneous data for fine-tuning due to proprietary data confidentiality or privacy requirements, and (ii) varying computation resources available across participating clients such as edge devices. This paper presents FedHFT - an efficient and personalized federated fine-tuning framework to address both challenges. First, we introduce a mixture of masked adapters to handle resource heterogeneity across participating clients, enabling high-performance collaborative fine-tuning of pre-trained language model(s) across multiple clients in a distributed setting, while keeping proprietary data local. Second, we introduce a bi-level optimization approach to handle non-iid data distribution based on masked personalization and client clustering. Extensive experiments demonstrate significant performance and efficiency improvements over various natural language understanding tasks under data and resource heterogeneity compared to representative heterogeneous federated learning methods.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14054v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Fatih Ilhan, Selim Furkan Tekin, Tiansheng Huang, Gaowen Liu, Ramana Kompella, Greg Eisenhauer, Yingyan Celine Lin, Calton Pu, Ling Liu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Incentive-Based Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14208</link>
   <description>Federated learning promises to revolutionize machine learning by enabling collaborative model training without compromising data privacy. However, practical adaptability can be limited by critical factors, such as the participation dilemma. Participating entities are often unwilling to contribute to a learning system unless they receive some benefits, or they may pretend to participate and free-ride on others. This chapter identifies the fundamental challenges in designing incentive mechanisms for federated learning systems. It examines how foundational concepts from economics and game theory can be applied to federated learning, alongside technology-driven solutions such as blockchain and deep reinforcement learning. This work presents a comprehensive taxonomy that thoroughly covers both centralized and decentralized architectures based on the aforementioned theoretical concepts. Furthermore, the concepts described are presented from an application perspective, covering emerging industrial applications, including healthcare, smart infrastructure, vehicular networks, and blockchain-based decentralized systems. Through this exploration, this chapter demonstrates that well-designed incentive mechanisms are not merely optional features but essential components for the practical success of federated learning. This analysis reveals both the promising solutions that have emerged and the significant challenges that remain in building truly sustainable, fair, and robust federated learning ecosystems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14208v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chanuka A. S. Hewa Kaluannakkage, Rajkumar Buyya</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>MX+: Pushing the Limits of Microscaling Formats for Efficient Large Language Model Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14557</link>
   <description>Reduced-precision data formats are crucial for cost-effective serving of large language models (LLMs). While numerous reduced-precision formats have been introduced thus far, they often require intrusive modifications to the software frameworks or are rather unconventional for widespread adoption across hardware vendors. In this paper, we instead focus on recent industry-driven variants of block floating-point (BFP) formats and conduct a comprehensive analysis to push their limits for efficient LLM serving. Our analysis shows that existing ultra low-bit BFP variants struggle to provide reasonable language model performance due to outlier values in blocks. To address the outliers with BFPs, we propose MX+, a cost-effective and non-intrusive extension designed for seamless integration into the microscaling (MX) formats. MX+ builds on the key insight that the outlier does not need to use its exponent field in the element data type, which allows us to repurpose the exponent field as an extended mantissa to increase the precision of the outlier element. Our evaluation shows that MX+ achieves significantly higher model performance compared to the 4-bit MX format (MXFP4) with negligible storage overhead and slowdown, thus offering a compelling alternative to MXFP4 or MXFP6 for efficient LLM inference.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14557v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AR</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jungi Lee, Junyong Park, Soohyun Cha, Jaehoon Cho, Jaewoong Sim</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedPPA: Progressive Parameter Alignment for Personalized Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14698</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) is designed as a decentralized, privacy-preserving machine learning paradigm that enables multiple clients to collaboratively train a model without sharing their data. In real-world scenarios, however, clients often have heterogeneous computational resources and hold non-independent and identically distributed data (non-IID), which poses significant challenges during training. Personalized Federated Learning (PFL) has emerged to address these issues by customizing models for each client based on their unique data distribution. Despite its potential, existing PFL approaches typically overlook the coexistence of model and data heterogeneity arising from clients with diverse computational capabilities. To overcome this limitation, we propose a novel method, called Progressive Parameter Alignment (FedPPA), which progressively aligns the weights of common layers across clients with the global model's weights. Our approach not only mitigates inconsistencies between global and local models during client updates, but also preserves client's local knowledge, thereby enhancing personalization robustness in non-IID settings. To further enhance the global model performance while retaining strong personalization, we also integrate entropy-based weighted averaging into the FedPPA framework. Experiments on three image classification datasets, including MNIST, FMNIST, and CIFAR-10, demonstrate that FedPPA consistently outperforms existing FL algorithms, achieving superior performance in personalized adaptation.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14698v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Maulidi Adi Prasetia, Muhamad Risqi U. Saputra, Guntur Dharma Putra</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Personalized federated learning, Row-wise fusion regularization, Multivariate modeling, Sparse estimation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14413</link>
   <description>We study personalized federated learning for multivariate responses where client models are heterogeneous yet share variable-level structure. Existing entry-wise penalties ignore cross-response dependence, while matrix-wise fusion over-couples clients. We propose a Sparse Row-wise Fusion (SROF) regularizer that clusters row vectors across clients and induces within-row sparsity, and we develop RowFed, a communication-efficient federated algorithm that embeds SROF into a linearized ADMM framework with privacy-preserving partial participation. Theoretically, we establish an oracle property for SROF-achieving correct variable-level group recovery with asymptotic normality-and prove convergence of RowFed to a stationary solution. Under random client participation, the iterate gap contracts at a rate that improves with participation probability. Empirically, simulations in heterogeneous regimes show that RowFed consistently lowers estimation and prediction error and strengthens variable-level cluster recovery over NonFed, FedAvg, and a personalized matrix-fusion baseline. A real-data study further corroborates these gains while preserving interpretability. Together, our results position row-wise fusion as an effective and transparent paradigm for large-scale personalized federated multivariate learning, bridging the gap between entry-wise and matrix-wise formulations.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14413v1</guid>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Runlin Zhou, Letian Li, Zemin Zheng</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedRTS: Federated Robust Pruning via Combinatorial Thompson Sampling</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19122</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) enables collaborative model training across distributed clients without data sharing, but its high computational and communication demands strain resource-constrained devices. While existing methods use dynamic pruning to improve efficiency by periodically adjusting sparse model topologies while maintaining sparsity, these approaches suffer from issues such as greedy adjustments, unstable topologies, and communication inefficiency, resulting in less robust models and suboptimal performance under data heterogeneity and partial client availability. To address these challenges, we propose Federated Robust pruning via combinatorial Thompson Sampling (FedRTS), a novel framework designed to develop robust sparse models. FedRTS enhances robustness and performance through its Thompson Sampling-based Adjustment (TSAdj) mechanism, which uses probabilistic decisions informed by stable, farsighted information instead of deterministic decisions reliant on unstable and myopic information in previous methods. Extensive experiments demonstrate that FedRTS achieves state-of-the-art performance in computer vision and natural language processing tasks while reducing communication costs, particularly excelling in scenarios with heterogeneous data distributions and partial client participation. Our codes are available at: https://github.com/Little0o0/FedRTS</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.19122v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hong Huang, Hai Yang, Yuan Chen, Jiaxun Ye, Dapeng Wu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Absolute Zero: Reinforced Self-play Reasoning with Zero Data</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03335</link>
   <description>Reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards (RLVR) has shown promise in enhancing the reasoning capabilities of large language models by learning directly from outcome-based rewards. Recent RLVR works that operate under the zero setting avoid supervision in labeling the reasoning process, but still depend on manually curated collections of questions and answers for training. The scarcity of high-quality, human-produced examples raises concerns about the long-term scalability of relying on human supervision, a challenge already evident in the domain of language model pretraining. Furthermore, in a hypothetical future where AI surpasses human intelligence, tasks provided by humans may offer limited learning potential for a superintelligent system. To address these concerns, we propose a new RLVR paradigm called Absolute Zero, in which a single model learns to propose tasks that maximize its own learning progress and improves reasoning by solving them, without relying on any external data. Under this paradigm, we introduce the Absolute Zero Reasoner (AZR), a system that self-evolves its training curriculum and reasoning ability by using a code executor to both validate proposed code reasoning tasks and verify answers, serving as an unified source of verifiable reward to guide open-ended yet grounded learning. Despite being trained entirely without external data, AZR achieves overall SOTA performance on coding and mathematical reasoning tasks, outperforming existing zero-setting models that rely on tens of thousands of in-domain human-curated examples. Furthermore, we demonstrate that AZR can be effectively applied across different model scales and is compatible with various model classes.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.03335v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Andrew Zhao, Yiran Wu, Yang Yue, Tong Wu, Quentin Xu, Yang Yue, Matthieu Lin, Shenzhi Wang, Qingyun Wu, Zilong Zheng, Gao Huang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Role-Aware Multi-modal federated learning system for detecting phishing webpages</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22369</link>
   <description>We present a federated, multi-modal phishing website detector that supports URL, HTML, and IMAGE inputs without binding clients to a fixed modality at inference: any client can invoke any modality head trained elsewhere. Methodologically, we propose role-aware bucket aggregation on top of FedProx, inspired by Mixture-of-Experts and FedMM. We drop learnable routing and use hard gating (selecting the IMAGE/HTML/URL expert by sample modality), enabling separate aggregation of modality-specific parameters to isolate cross-embedding conflicts and stabilize convergence. On TR-OP, the Fusion head reaches Acc 97.5% with FPR 2.4% across two data types; on the image subset (ablation) it attains Acc 95.5% with FPR 5.9%. For text, we use GraphCodeBERT for URLs and an early three-way embedding for raw, noisy HTML. On WebPhish (HTML) we obtain Acc 96.5% / FPR 1.8%; on TR-OP (raw HTML) we obtain Acc 95.1% / FPR 4.6%. Results indicate that bucket aggregation with hard-gated experts enables stable federated training under strict privacy, while improving the usability and flexibility of multi-modal phishing detection.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.22369v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Bo Wang, Imran Khan, Martin White, Natalia Beloff</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Technical and legal aspects of federated learning in bioinformatics: applications, challenges and opportunities</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09649</link>
   <description>Federated learning leverages data across institutions to improve clinical discovery while complying with data-sharing restrictions and protecting patient privacy. This paper provides a gentle introduction to this approach in bioinformatics, and is the first to review key applications in proteomics, genome-wide association studies (GWAS), single-cell and multi-omics studies in their legal as well as methodological and infrastructural challenges. As the evolution of biobanks in genetics and systems biology has proved, accessing more extensive and varied data pools leads to a faster and more robust exploration and translation of results. More widespread use of federated learning may have a similar impact in bioinformatics, allowing academic and clinical institutions to access many combinations of genotypic, phenotypic and environmental information that are undercovered or not included in existing biobanks.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.09649v3</guid>
   <category>q-bio.OT</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Daniele Malpetti, Marco Scutari, Francesco Gualdi, Jessica van Setten, Sander van der Laan, Saskia Haitjema, Aaron Mark Lee, Isabelle Hering, Francesca Mangili</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Helmsman: Autonomous Synthesis of Federated Learning Systems via Multi-Agent Collaboration</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14512</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) offers a powerful paradigm for training models on decentralized data, but its promise is often undermined by the immense complexity of designing and deploying robust systems. The need to select, combine, and tune strategies for multifaceted challenges like data heterogeneity and system constraints has become a critical bottleneck, resulting in brittle, bespoke solutions. To address this, we introduce Helmsman, a novel multi-agent system that automates the end-to-end synthesis of federated learning systems from high-level user specifications. It emulates a principled research and development workflow through three collaborative phases: (1) interactive human-in-the-loop planning to formulate a sound research plan, (2) modular code generation by supervised agent teams, and (3) a closed-loop of autonomous evaluation and refinement in a sandboxed simulation environment. To facilitate rigorous evaluation, we also introduce AgentFL-Bench, a new benchmark comprising 16 diverse tasks designed to assess the system-level generation capabilities of agentic systems in FL. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our approach generates solutions competitive with, and often superior to, established hand-crafted baselines. Our work represents a significant step towards the automated engineering of complex decentralized AI systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14512v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Haoyuan Li, Mathias Funk, Aaqib Saeed</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>ToolPRM: Fine-Grained Inference Scaling of Structured Outputs for Function Calling</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14703</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) are increasingly demonstrating strong capabilities as autonomous agents, with function calling serving as a core mechanism for interaction with the environment. Meanwhile, inference scaling has become a cutting-edge technique to enhance LLM performance by allocating more computational resources during the inference process. However, current research on inference scaling primarily focuses on unstructured output generation tasks, leaving its application in structured outputs, like function calling, largely underexplored. To bridge this gap, we propose an inference scaling framework that combines fine-grained beam search with a process reward model, ToolPRM, which scores the internal steps of each single function call. To train ToolPRM, we construct the first fine-grained intra-call process supervision dataset, automatically annotated with function-masking techniques to provide step-level rewards for structured tool-use reasoning. Extensive experiments demonstrate that ToolPRM beats the coarse-grained and outcome reward models in terms of predictive accuracy, indicating its stronger capability in supervising the function calling inference process. Inference scaling technique equipped with ToolPRM also significantly improves the backbone model performance across various function calling tasks and benchmarks. More importantly, we reveal a key principle for applying inference scaling techniques to structured outputs: &quot;explore more but retain less&quot; due to the unrecoverability characteristics of structured function calling generation.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14703v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jianghao Lin, Yuanyuan Shi, Xin Peng, Renjie Ding, Hairui Wang, Yuxuan Peng, Bizhe Bai, Weixi Song, Fengshuo Bai, Huacan Chai, Weinan Zhang, Fei Huang, Ying Wen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>From Binary to Bilingual: How the National Weather Service is Using Artificial Intelligence to Develop a Comprehensive Translation Program</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14369</link>
   <description>To advance a Weather-Ready Nation, the National Weather Service (NWS) is developing a systematic translation program to better serve the 68.8 million people in the U.S. who do not speak English at home. This article outlines the foundation of an automated translation tool for NWS products, powered by artificial intelligence. The NWS has partnered with LILT, whose patented training process enables large language models (LLMs) to adapt neural machine translation (NMT) tools for weather terminology and messaging. Designed for scalability across Weather Forecast Offices (WFOs) and National Centers, the system is currently being developed in Spanish, Simplified Chinese, Vietnamese, and other widely spoken non-English languages. Rooted in best practices for multilingual risk communication, the system provides accurate, timely, and culturally relevant translations, significantly reducing manual translation time and easing operational workloads across the NWS. To guide the distribution of these products, GIS mapping was used to identify language needs across different NWS regions, helping prioritize resources for the communities that need them most. We also integrated ethical AI practices throughout the program's design, ensuring that transparency, fairness, and human oversight guide how automated translations are created, evaluated, and shared with the public. This work has culminated into a website featuring experimental multilingual NWS products, including translated warnings, 7-day forecasts, and educational campaigns, bringing the country one step closer to a national warning system that reaches all Americans.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14369v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Joseph E. Trujillo-Falcon, Monica L. Bozeman, Liam E. Llewellyn, Samuel T. Halvorson, Meryl Mizell, Stuti Deshpande, Bob Manning, Todd Fagin</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FairBatching: Fairness-Aware Batch Formation for LLM Inference</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14392</link>
   <description>Large language model (LLM) inference systems face a fundamental tension between minimizing Time-to-First-Token (TTFT) latency for new requests and maintaining a high, steady token generation rate (low Time-Per-Output-Token, or TPOT) for ongoing requests. Existing stall-free batching schedulers proposed by Sarathi, while effective at preventing decode stalls, introduce significant computational unfairness. They prioritize decode tasks excessively, simultaneously leading to underutilized decode slack and unnecessary prefill queuing delays, which collectively degrade the system's overall quality of service (QoS).
  This work identifies the root cause of this unfairness: the non-monotonic nature of Time-Between-Tokens (TBT) as a scheduling metric and the rigid decode-prioritizing policy that fails to adapt to dynamic workload bursts. We therefore propose FairBatching, a novel LLM inference scheduler that enforces fair resource allocation between prefill and decode tasks. It features an adaptive batch capacity determination mechanism, which dynamically adjusts the computational budget to improve the GPU utilization without triggering SLO violations. Its fair and dynamic batch formation algorithm breaks away from the decode-prioritizing paradigm, allowing computation resources to be reclaimed from bursting decode tasks to serve prefill surges, achieving global fairness. Furthermore, FairBatching provides a novel load estimation method, enabling more effective coordination with upper-level schedulers. Implemented and evaluated on realistic traces, FairBatching significantly reduces TTFT tail latency by up to 2.29x while robustly maintaining TPOT SLOs, achieving overall 20.0% improvement in single-node capacity and 54.3% improvement in cluster-level capacity.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14392v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hongtao Lyu, Boyue Liu, Mingyu Wu, Haibo Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>xLLM Technical Report</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14686</link>
   <description>We introduce xLLM, an intelligent and efficient Large Language Model (LLM) inference framework designed for high-performance, large-scale enterprise-grade serving, with deep optimizations for diverse AI accelerators. To address these challenges, xLLM builds a novel decoupled service-engine architecture. At the service layer, xLLM-Service features an intelligent scheduling module that efficiently processes multimodal requests and co-locates online and offline tasks through unified elastic scheduling to maximize cluster utilization. This module also relies on a workload-adaptive dynamic Prefill-Decode (PD) disaggregation policy and a novel Encode-Prefill-Decode (EPD) disaggregation policy designed for multimodal inputs. Furthermore, it incorporates a distributed architecture to provide global KV Cache management and robust fault-tolerant capabilities for high availability. At the engine layer, xLLM-Engine co-optimizes system and algorithm designs to fully saturate computing resources. This is achieved through comprehensive multi-layer execution pipeline optimizations, an adaptive graph mode and an xTensor memory management. xLLM-Engine also further integrates algorithmic enhancements such as optimized speculative decoding and dynamic EPLB, collectively serving to substantially boost throughput and inference efficiency. Extensive evaluations demonstrate that xLLM delivers significantly superior performance and resource efficiency. Under identical TPOT constraints, xLLM achieves throughput up to 1.7x that of MindIE and 2.2x that of vLLM-Ascend with Qwen-series models, while maintaining an average throughput of 1.7x that of MindIE with Deepseek-series models. xLLM framework is publicly available at https://github.com/jd-opensource/xllm and https://github.com/jd-opensource/xllm-service.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14686v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Tongxuan Liu, Tao Peng, Peijun Yang, Xiaoyang Zhao, Xiusheng Lu, Weizhe Huang, Zirui Liu, Xiaoyu Chen, Zhiwei Liang, Jun Xiong, Donghe Jin, Minchao Zhang, Jinrong Guo, Yingxu Deng, Xu Zhang, Xianzhe Dong, Siqi Wang, Siyu Wu, Yu Wu, Zihan Tang, Yuting Zeng, Yanshu Wang, Jinguang Liu, Meng Kang, Menxin Li, Yunlong Wang, Yiming Liu, Xiaolong Ma, Yifan Wang, Yichen Zhang, Jinrun Yin, Keyang Zheng, Jiawei Yin, Jun Zhang, Ziyue Wang, Xiaobo Lin, Liangyu Liu, Liwei Lan, Yang Liu, Chunhua Peng, Han Liu, Songcheng Ren, Xuezhu Wang, Yunheng Shen, Yi Wang, Guyue Liu, Hui Chen, Tong Yang, Hailong Yang, Jing Li, Guiguang Ding, Ke Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedPPA: Progressive Parameter Alignment for Personalized Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14698</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) is designed as a decentralized, privacy-preserving machine learning paradigm that enables multiple clients to collaboratively train a model without sharing their data. In real-world scenarios, however, clients often have heterogeneous computational resources and hold non-independent and identically distributed data (non-IID), which poses significant challenges during training. Personalized Federated Learning (PFL) has emerged to address these issues by customizing models for each client based on their unique data distribution. Despite its potential, existing PFL approaches typically overlook the coexistence of model and data heterogeneity arising from clients with diverse computational capabilities. To overcome this limitation, we propose a novel method, called Progressive Parameter Alignment (FedPPA), which progressively aligns the weights of common layers across clients with the global model's weights. Our approach not only mitigates inconsistencies between global and local models during client updates, but also preserves client's local knowledge, thereby enhancing personalization robustness in non-IID settings. To further enhance the global model performance while retaining strong personalization, we also integrate entropy-based weighted averaging into the FedPPA framework. Experiments on three image classification datasets, including MNIST, FMNIST, and CIFAR-10, demonstrate that FedPPA consistently outperforms existing FL algorithms, achieving superior performance in personalized adaptation.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14698v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Maulidi Adi Prasetia, Muhamad Risqi U. Saputra, Guntur Dharma Putra</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedRTS: Federated Robust Pruning via Combinatorial Thompson Sampling</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19122</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) enables collaborative model training across distributed clients without data sharing, but its high computational and communication demands strain resource-constrained devices. While existing methods use dynamic pruning to improve efficiency by periodically adjusting sparse model topologies while maintaining sparsity, these approaches suffer from issues such as greedy adjustments, unstable topologies, and communication inefficiency, resulting in less robust models and suboptimal performance under data heterogeneity and partial client availability. To address these challenges, we propose Federated Robust pruning via combinatorial Thompson Sampling (FedRTS), a novel framework designed to develop robust sparse models. FedRTS enhances robustness and performance through its Thompson Sampling-based Adjustment (TSAdj) mechanism, which uses probabilistic decisions informed by stable, farsighted information instead of deterministic decisions reliant on unstable and myopic information in previous methods. Extensive experiments demonstrate that FedRTS achieves state-of-the-art performance in computer vision and natural language processing tasks while reducing communication costs, particularly excelling in scenarios with heterogeneous data distributions and partial client participation. Our codes are available at: https://github.com/Little0o0/FedRTS</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.19122v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hong Huang, Hai Yang, Yuan Chen, Jiaxun Ye, Dapeng Wu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Absolute Zero: Reinforced Self-play Reasoning with Zero Data</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03335</link>
   <description>Reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards (RLVR) has shown promise in enhancing the reasoning capabilities of large language models by learning directly from outcome-based rewards. Recent RLVR works that operate under the zero setting avoid supervision in labeling the reasoning process, but still depend on manually curated collections of questions and answers for training. The scarcity of high-quality, human-produced examples raises concerns about the long-term scalability of relying on human supervision, a challenge already evident in the domain of language model pretraining. Furthermore, in a hypothetical future where AI surpasses human intelligence, tasks provided by humans may offer limited learning potential for a superintelligent system. To address these concerns, we propose a new RLVR paradigm called Absolute Zero, in which a single model learns to propose tasks that maximize its own learning progress and improves reasoning by solving them, without relying on any external data. Under this paradigm, we introduce the Absolute Zero Reasoner (AZR), a system that self-evolves its training curriculum and reasoning ability by using a code executor to both validate proposed code reasoning tasks and verify answers, serving as an unified source of verifiable reward to guide open-ended yet grounded learning. Despite being trained entirely without external data, AZR achieves overall SOTA performance on coding and mathematical reasoning tasks, outperforming existing zero-setting models that rely on tens of thousands of in-domain human-curated examples. Furthermore, we demonstrate that AZR can be effectively applied across different model scales and is compatible with various model classes.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.03335v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Andrew Zhao, Yiran Wu, Yang Yue, Tong Wu, Quentin Xu, Yang Yue, Matthieu Lin, Shenzhi Wang, Qingyun Wu, Zilong Zheng, Gao Huang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FairBatching: Fairness-Aware Batch Formation for LLM Inference</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14392</link>
   <description>Large language model (LLM) inference systems face a fundamental tension between minimizing Time-to-First-Token (TTFT) latency for new requests and maintaining a high, steady token generation rate (low Time-Per-Output-Token, or TPOT) for ongoing requests. Existing stall-free batching schedulers proposed by Sarathi, while effective at preventing decode stalls, introduce significant computational unfairness. They prioritize decode tasks excessively, simultaneously leading to underutilized decode slack and unnecessary prefill queuing delays, which collectively degrade the system's overall quality of service (QoS).
  This work identifies the root cause of this unfairness: the non-monotonic nature of Time-Between-Tokens (TBT) as a scheduling metric and the rigid decode-prioritizing policy that fails to adapt to dynamic workload bursts. We therefore propose FairBatching, a novel LLM inference scheduler that enforces fair resource allocation between prefill and decode tasks. It features an adaptive batch capacity determination mechanism, which dynamically adjusts the computational budget to improve the GPU utilization without triggering SLO violations. Its fair and dynamic batch formation algorithm breaks away from the decode-prioritizing paradigm, allowing computation resources to be reclaimed from bursting decode tasks to serve prefill surges, achieving global fairness. Furthermore, FairBatching provides a novel load estimation method, enabling more effective coordination with upper-level schedulers. Implemented and evaluated on realistic traces, FairBatching significantly reduces TTFT tail latency by up to 2.29x while robustly maintaining TPOT SLOs, achieving overall 20.0% improvement in single-node capacity and 54.3% improvement in cluster-level capacity.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14392v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hongtao Lyu, Boyue Liu, Mingyu Wu, Haibo Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>xLLM Technical Report</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14686</link>
   <description>We introduce xLLM, an intelligent and efficient Large Language Model (LLM) inference framework designed for high-performance, large-scale enterprise-grade serving, with deep optimizations for diverse AI accelerators. To address these challenges, xLLM builds a novel decoupled service-engine architecture. At the service layer, xLLM-Service features an intelligent scheduling module that efficiently processes multimodal requests and co-locates online and offline tasks through unified elastic scheduling to maximize cluster utilization. This module also relies on a workload-adaptive dynamic Prefill-Decode (PD) disaggregation policy and a novel Encode-Prefill-Decode (EPD) disaggregation policy designed for multimodal inputs. Furthermore, it incorporates a distributed architecture to provide global KV Cache management and robust fault-tolerant capabilities for high availability. At the engine layer, xLLM-Engine co-optimizes system and algorithm designs to fully saturate computing resources. This is achieved through comprehensive multi-layer execution pipeline optimizations, an adaptive graph mode and an xTensor memory management. xLLM-Engine also further integrates algorithmic enhancements such as optimized speculative decoding and dynamic EPLB, collectively serving to substantially boost throughput and inference efficiency. Extensive evaluations demonstrate that xLLM delivers significantly superior performance and resource efficiency. Under identical TPOT constraints, xLLM achieves throughput up to 1.7x that of MindIE and 2.2x that of vLLM-Ascend with Qwen-series models, while maintaining an average throughput of 1.7x that of MindIE with Deepseek-series models. xLLM framework is publicly available at https://github.com/jd-opensource/xllm and https://github.com/jd-opensource/xllm-service.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14686v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Tongxuan Liu, Tao Peng, Peijun Yang, Xiaoyang Zhao, Xiusheng Lu, Weizhe Huang, Zirui Liu, Xiaoyu Chen, Zhiwei Liang, Jun Xiong, Donghe Jin, Minchao Zhang, Jinrong Guo, Yingxu Deng, Xu Zhang, Xianzhe Dong, Siqi Wang, Siyu Wu, Yu Wu, Zihan Tang, Yuting Zeng, Yanshu Wang, Jinguang Liu, Meng Kang, Menxin Li, Yunlong Wang, Yiming Liu, Xiaolong Ma, Yifan Wang, Yichen Zhang, Jinrun Yin, Keyang Zheng, Jiawei Yin, Jun Zhang, Ziyue Wang, Xiaobo Lin, Liangyu Liu, Liwei Lan, Yang Liu, Chunhua Peng, Han Liu, Songcheng Ren, Xuezhu Wang, Yunheng Shen, Yi Wang, Guyue Liu, Hui Chen, Tong Yang, Hailong Yang, Jing Li, Guiguang Ding, Ke Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedHFT: Efficient Federated Finetuning with Heterogeneous Edge Clients</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14054</link>
   <description>Fine-tuning pre-trained large language models (LLMs) has become a common practice for personalized natural language understanding (NLU) applications on downstream tasks and domain-specific datasets. However, there are two main challenges: (i) limited and/or heterogeneous data for fine-tuning due to proprietary data confidentiality or privacy requirements, and (ii) varying computation resources available across participating clients such as edge devices. This paper presents FedHFT - an efficient and personalized federated fine-tuning framework to address both challenges. First, we introduce a mixture of masked adapters to handle resource heterogeneity across participating clients, enabling high-performance collaborative fine-tuning of pre-trained language model(s) across multiple clients in a distributed setting, while keeping proprietary data local. Second, we introduce a bi-level optimization approach to handle non-iid data distribution based on masked personalization and client clustering. Extensive experiments demonstrate significant performance and efficiency improvements over various natural language understanding tasks under data and resource heterogeneity compared to representative heterogeneous federated learning methods.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14054v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Fatih Ilhan, Selim Furkan Tekin, Tiansheng Huang, Gaowen Liu, Ramana Kompella, Greg Eisenhauer, Yingyan Celine Lin, Calton Pu, Ling Liu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Incentive-Based Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14208</link>
   <description>Federated learning promises to revolutionize machine learning by enabling collaborative model training without compromising data privacy. However, practical adaptability can be limited by critical factors, such as the participation dilemma. Participating entities are often unwilling to contribute to a learning system unless they receive some benefits, or they may pretend to participate and free-ride on others. This chapter identifies the fundamental challenges in designing incentive mechanisms for federated learning systems. It examines how foundational concepts from economics and game theory can be applied to federated learning, alongside technology-driven solutions such as blockchain and deep reinforcement learning. This work presents a comprehensive taxonomy that thoroughly covers both centralized and decentralized architectures based on the aforementioned theoretical concepts. Furthermore, the concepts described are presented from an application perspective, covering emerging industrial applications, including healthcare, smart infrastructure, vehicular networks, and blockchain-based decentralized systems. Through this exploration, this chapter demonstrates that well-designed incentive mechanisms are not merely optional features but essential components for the practical success of federated learning. This analysis reveals both the promising solutions that have emerged and the significant challenges that remain in building truly sustainable, fair, and robust federated learning ecosystems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14208v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chanuka A. S. Hewa Kaluannakkage, Rajkumar Buyya</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>MoLink: Distributed and Efficient Serving Framework for Large Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05043</link>
   <description>Large language models represent a groundbreaking shift in generative AI. Yet, these advances come with a significant challenge: the high cost of model serving. To mitigate these costs, consumer-grade GPUs emerge as a more affordable alternative. This presents an opportunity for more cost-efficient LLM serving by leveraging these GPUs.
  However, it is non-trivial to achieve high-efficiency LLM serving on consumer-grade GPUs, mainly due to two challenges: 1) these GPUs are often deployed in limited network conditions; 2) these GPUs often exhibit heterogeneity in host systems. To address these challenges, we present MoLink, a distributed LLM serving system for large models. It incorporates several key techniques, enabling efficient LLM serving on heterogeneous and weakly connected consumer-grade GPUs. Our experiments demonstrate that it achieves throughput improvements of up to 458\% and cost-profit margin improvements of up to 151\%, compared to state-of-the-art systems. MoLink allows users on Windows, Linux, and containerized VMs to seamlessly integrate GPUs with just a few lines of code over Ethernet or public networks. Currently, it supports 18 mainstream architectures of open-source large language models. The source code is publicly available https://github.com/oldcpple/MoLink.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.05043v2</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Lewei Jin, Yongqi Chen, Kui Zhang, Yifan Zhuo, Yi Gao, Bowei Yang, Zhengong Cai, Wei Dong</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Role-Aware Multi-modal federated learning system for detecting phishing webpages</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22369</link>
   <description>We present a federated, multi-modal phishing website detector that supports URL, HTML, and IMAGE inputs without binding clients to a fixed modality at inference: any client can invoke any modality head trained elsewhere. Methodologically, we propose role-aware bucket aggregation on top of FedProx, inspired by Mixture-of-Experts and FedMM. We drop learnable routing and use hard gating (selecting the IMAGE/HTML/URL expert by sample modality), enabling separate aggregation of modality-specific parameters to isolate cross-embedding conflicts and stabilize convergence. On TR-OP, the Fusion head reaches Acc 97.5% with FPR 2.4% across two data types; on the image subset (ablation) it attains Acc 95.5% with FPR 5.9%. For text, we use GraphCodeBERT for URLs and an early three-way embedding for raw, noisy HTML. On WebPhish (HTML) we obtain Acc 96.5% / FPR 1.8%; on TR-OP (raw HTML) we obtain Acc 95.1% / FPR 4.6%. Results indicate that bucket aggregation with hard-gated experts enables stable federated training under strict privacy, while improving the usability and flexibility of multi-modal phishing detection.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.22369v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Bo Wang, Imran Khan, Martin White, Natalia Beloff</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>From Binary to Bilingual: How the National Weather Service is Using Artificial Intelligence to Develop a Comprehensive Translation Program</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14369</link>
   <description>To advance a Weather-Ready Nation, the National Weather Service (NWS) is developing a systematic translation program to better serve the 68.8 million people in the U.S. who do not speak English at home. This article outlines the foundation of an automated translation tool for NWS products, powered by artificial intelligence. The NWS has partnered with LILT, whose patented training process enables large language models (LLMs) to adapt neural machine translation (NMT) tools for weather terminology and messaging. Designed for scalability across Weather Forecast Offices (WFOs) and National Centers, the system is currently being developed in Spanish, Simplified Chinese, Vietnamese, and other widely spoken non-English languages. Rooted in best practices for multilingual risk communication, the system provides accurate, timely, and culturally relevant translations, significantly reducing manual translation time and easing operational workloads across the NWS. To guide the distribution of these products, GIS mapping was used to identify language needs across different NWS regions, helping prioritize resources for the communities that need them most. We also integrated ethical AI practices throughout the program's design, ensuring that transparency, fairness, and human oversight guide how automated translations are created, evaluated, and shared with the public. This work has culminated into a website featuring experimental multilingual NWS products, including translated warnings, 7-day forecasts, and educational campaigns, bringing the country one step closer to a national warning system that reaches all Americans.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14369v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Joseph E. Trujillo-Falcon, Monica L. Bozeman, Liam E. Llewellyn, Samuel T. Halvorson, Meryl Mizell, Stuti Deshpande, Bob Manning, Todd Fagin</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Absolute Zero: Reinforced Self-play Reasoning with Zero Data</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03335</link>
   <description>Reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards (RLVR) has shown promise in enhancing the reasoning capabilities of large language models by learning directly from outcome-based rewards. Recent RLVR works that operate under the zero setting avoid supervision in labeling the reasoning process, but still depend on manually curated collections of questions and answers for training. The scarcity of high-quality, human-produced examples raises concerns about the long-term scalability of relying on human supervision, a challenge already evident in the domain of language model pretraining. Furthermore, in a hypothetical future where AI surpasses human intelligence, tasks provided by humans may offer limited learning potential for a superintelligent system. To address these concerns, we propose a new RLVR paradigm called Absolute Zero, in which a single model learns to propose tasks that maximize its own learning progress and improves reasoning by solving them, without relying on any external data. Under this paradigm, we introduce the Absolute Zero Reasoner (AZR), a system that self-evolves its training curriculum and reasoning ability by using a code executor to both validate proposed code reasoning tasks and verify answers, serving as an unified source of verifiable reward to guide open-ended yet grounded learning. Despite being trained entirely without external data, AZR achieves overall SOTA performance on coding and mathematical reasoning tasks, outperforming existing zero-setting models that rely on tens of thousands of in-domain human-curated examples. Furthermore, we demonstrate that AZR can be effectively applied across different model scales and is compatible with various model classes.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.03335v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Andrew Zhao, Yiran Wu, Yang Yue, Tong Wu, Quentin Xu, Yang Yue, Matthieu Lin, Shenzhi Wang, Qingyun Wu, Zilong Zheng, Gao Huang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>From Binary to Bilingual: How the National Weather Service is Using Artificial Intelligence to Develop a Comprehensive Translation Program</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14369</link>
   <description>To advance a Weather-Ready Nation, the National Weather Service (NWS) is developing a systematic translation program to better serve the 68.8 million people in the U.S. who do not speak English at home. This article outlines the foundation of an automated translation tool for NWS products, powered by artificial intelligence. The NWS has partnered with LILT, whose patented training process enables large language models (LLMs) to adapt neural machine translation (NMT) tools for weather terminology and messaging. Designed for scalability across Weather Forecast Offices (WFOs) and National Centers, the system is currently being developed in Spanish, Simplified Chinese, Vietnamese, and other widely spoken non-English languages. Rooted in best practices for multilingual risk communication, the system provides accurate, timely, and culturally relevant translations, significantly reducing manual translation time and easing operational workloads across the NWS. To guide the distribution of these products, GIS mapping was used to identify language needs across different NWS regions, helping prioritize resources for the communities that need them most. We also integrated ethical AI practices throughout the program's design, ensuring that transparency, fairness, and human oversight guide how automated translations are created, evaluated, and shared with the public. This work has culminated into a website featuring experimental multilingual NWS products, including translated warnings, 7-day forecasts, and educational campaigns, bringing the country one step closer to a national warning system that reaches all Americans.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2510.14369v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Joseph E. Trujillo-Falcon, Monica L. Bozeman, Liam E. Llewellyn, Samuel T. Halvorson, Meryl Mizell, Stuti Deshpande, Bob Manning, Todd Fagin</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
