<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2025 03:21:26 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2025 03:21:26 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>Not Just What, But When: Integrating Irregular Intervals to LLM for Sequential Recommendation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23209</link>
   <description>Time intervals between purchasing items are a crucial factor in sequential recommendation tasks, whereas existing approaches focus on item sequences and often overlook by assuming the intervals between items are static. However, dynamic intervals serve as a dimension that describes user profiling on not only the history within a user but also different users with the same item history. In this work, we propose IntervalLLM, a novel framework that integrates interval information into LLM and incorporates the novel interval-infused attention to jointly consider information of items and intervals. Furthermore, unlike prior studies that address the cold-start scenario only from the perspectives of users and items, we introduce a new viewpoint: the interval perspective to serve as an additional metric for evaluating recommendation methods on the warm and cold scenarios. Extensive experiments on 3 benchmarks with both traditional- and LLM-based baselines demonstrate that our IntervalLLM achieves not only 4.4% improvements in average but also the best-performing warm and cold scenarios across all users, items, and the proposed interval perspectives. In addition, we observe that the cold scenario from the interval perspective experiences the most significant performance drop among all recommendation methods. This finding underscores the necessity of further research on interval-based cold challenges and our integration of interval information in the realm of sequential recommendation tasks. Our code is available here: https://github.com/sony/ds-research-code/tree/master/recsys25-IntervalLLM.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.23209v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Wei-Wei Du, Takuma Udagawa, Kei Tateno</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>RecGPT Technical Report</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22879</link>
   <description>Recommender systems are among the most impactful applications of artificial intelligence, serving as critical infrastructure connecting users, merchants, and platforms. However, most current industrial systems remain heavily reliant on historical co-occurrence patterns and log-fitting objectives, i.e., optimizing for past user interactions without explicitly modeling user intent. This log-fitting approach often leads to overfitting to narrow historical preferences, failing to capture users' evolving and latent interests. As a result, it reinforces filter bubbles and long-tail phenomena, ultimately harming user experience and threatening the sustainability of the whole recommendation ecosystem.
  To address these challenges, we rethink the overall design paradigm of recommender systems and propose RecGPT, a next-generation framework that places user intent at the center of the recommendation pipeline. By integrating large language models (LLMs) into key stages of user interest mining, item retrieval, and explanation generation, RecGPT transforms log-fitting recommendation into an intent-centric process. To effectively align general-purpose LLMs to the above domain-specific recommendation tasks at scale, RecGPT incorporates a multi-stage training paradigm, which integrates reasoning-enhanced pre-alignment and self-training evolution, guided by a Human-LLM cooperative judge system. Currently, RecGPT has been fully deployed on the Taobao App. Online experiments demonstrate that RecGPT achieves consistent performance gains across stakeholders: users benefit from increased content diversity and satisfaction, merchants and the platform gain greater exposure and conversions. These comprehensive improvement results across all stakeholders validates that LLM-driven, intent-centric design can foster a more sustainable and mutually beneficial recommendation ecosystem.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.22879v2</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chao Yi, Dian Chen, Gaoyang Guo, Jiakai Tang, Jian Wu, Jing Yu, Mao Zhang, Sunhao Dai, Wen Chen, Wenjun Yang, Yuning Jiang, Zhujin Gao, Bo Zheng, Chi Li, Dimin Wang, Dixuan Wang, Fan Li, Fan Zhang, Haibin Chen, Haozhuang Liu, Jialin Zhu, Jiamang Wang, Jiawei Wu, Jin Cui, Ju Huang, Kai Zhang, Kan Liu, Lang Tian, Liang Rao, Longbin Li, Lulu Zhao, Na He, Peiyang Wang, Qiqi Huang, Tao Luo, Wenbo Su, Xiaoxiao He, Xin Tong, Xu Chen, Xunke Xi, Yang Li, Yaxuan Wu, Yeqiu Yang, Yi Hu, Yinnan Song, Yuchen Li, Yujie Luo, Yujin Yuan, Yuliang Yan, Zhengyang Wang, Zhibo Xiao, Zhixin Ma, Zile Zhou, Ziqi Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Mitigating Resolution-Drift in Federated Learning: Case of Keypoint Detection</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23461</link>
   <description>The Federated Learning (FL) approach enables effective learning across distributed systems, while preserving user data privacy. To date, research has primarily focused on addressing statistical heterogeneity and communication efficiency, through which FL has achieved success in classification tasks. However, its application to non-classification tasks, such as human pose estimation, remains underexplored. This paper identifies and investigates a critical issue termed ``resolution-drift,'' where performance degrades significantly due to resolution variability across clients. Unlike class-level heterogeneity, resolution drift highlights the importance of resolution as another axis of not independent or identically distributed (non-IID) data. To address this issue, we present resolution-adaptive federated learning (RAF), a method that leverages heatmap-based knowledge distillation. Through multi-resolution knowledge distillation between higher-resolution outputs (teachers) and lower-resolution outputs (students), our approach enhances resolution robustness without overfitting. Extensive experiments and theoretical analysis demonstrate that RAF not only effectively mitigates resolution drift and achieves significant performance improvements, but also can be integrated seamlessly into existing FL frameworks. Furthermore, although this paper focuses on human pose estimation, our t-SNE analysis reveals distinct characteristics between classification and high-resolution representation tasks, supporting the generalizability of RAF to other tasks that rely on preserving spatial detail.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.23461v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Taeheon Lim, Joohyung Lee, Kyungjae Lee, Jungchan Cho</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Automated Label Placement on Maps via Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22952</link>
   <description>Label placement is a critical aspect of map design, serving as a form of spatial annotation that directly impacts clarity and interpretability. Despite its importance, label placement remains largely manual and difficult to scale, as existing automated systems struggle to integrate cartographic conventions, adapt to context, or interpret labeling instructions. In this work, we introduce a new paradigm for automatic label placement (ALP) that formulates the task as a data editing problem and leverages large language models (LLMs) for context-aware spatial annotation. To support this direction, we curate MAPLE, the first known benchmarking dataset for evaluating ALP on real-world maps, encompassing diverse landmark types and label placement annotations from open-source data. Our method retrieves labeling guidelines relevant to each landmark type leveraging retrieval-augmented generation (RAG), integrates them into prompts, and employs instruction-tuned LLMs to generate ideal label coordinates. We evaluate four open-source LLMs on MAPLE, analyzing both overall performance and generalization across different types of landmarks. This includes both zero-shot and instruction-tuned performance. Our results demonstrate that LLMs, when guided by structured prompts and domain-specific retrieval, can learn to perform accurate spatial edits, aligning the generated outputs with expert cartographic standards. Overall, our work presents a scalable framework for AI-assisted map finishing and demonstrates the potential of foundation models in structured data editing tasks. The code and data can be found at https://github.com/HarryShomer/MAPLE.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.22952v1</guid>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Harry Shomer, Jiejun Xu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>VisNumBench: Evaluating Number Sense of Multimodal Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14939</link>
   <description>Can Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) develop an intuitive number sense similar to humans? Targeting this problem, we introduce Visual Number Benchmark (VisNumBench) to evaluate the number sense abilities of MLLMs across a wide range of visual numerical tasks. VisNumBench consists of about 1,900 multiple-choice question-answer pairs derived from both synthetic and real-world visual data, covering seven visual numerical attributes and four types of visual numerical estimation tasks. Our experiments on VisNumBench led to the following key findings: (i) The 17 MLLMs we tested, including open-source models such as Qwen2.5-VL and InternVL2.5, as well as proprietary models like GPT-4o and Gemini 2.0 Flash, perform significantly below human levels in number sense-related tasks. (ii) Multimodal mathematical models and multimodal chain-of-thought (CoT) models did not exhibit significant improvements in number sense abilities. (iii) Stronger MLLMs with larger parameter sizes and broader general abilities demonstrate modest gains in number sense abilities. We believe VisNumBench will serve as a valuable resource for the research community, encouraging further advancements in enhancing MLLMs' number sense abilities. Code and dataset are available at https://wwwtttjjj.github.io/VisNumBench/.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.14939v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Tengjin Weng, Jingyi Wang, Wenhao Jiang, Zhong Ming</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedCVD++: Communication-Efficient Federated Learning for Cardiovascular Risk Prediction with Parametric and Non-Parametric Model Optimization</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22963</link>
   <description>Cardiovascular diseases (CVD) cause over 17 million deaths annually worldwide, highlighting the urgent need for privacy-preserving predictive systems. We introduce FedCVD++, an enhanced federated learning (FL) framework that integrates both parametric models (logistic regression, SVM, neural networks) and non-parametric models (Random Forest, XGBoost) for coronary heart disease risk prediction. To address key FL challenges, we propose: (1) tree-subset sampling that reduces Random Forest communication overhead by 70%, (2) XGBoost-based feature extraction enabling lightweight federated ensembles, and (3) federated SMOTE synchronization for resolving cross-institutional class imbalance.
  Evaluated on the Framingham dataset (4,238 records), FedCVD++ achieves state-of-the-art results: federated XGBoost (F1 = 0.80) surpasses its centralized counterpart (F1 = 0.78), and federated Random Forest (F1 = 0.81) matches non-federated performance. Additionally, our communication-efficient strategies reduce bandwidth consumption by 3.2X while preserving 95% accuracy.
  Compared to existing FL frameworks, FedCVD++ delivers up to 15% higher F1-scores and superior scalability for multi-institutional deployment. This work represents the first practical integration of non-parametric models into federated healthcare systems, providing a privacy-preserving solution validated under real-world clinical constraints.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.22963v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>q-bio.OT</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Abdelrhman Gaber, Hassan Abd-Eltawab, John Elgallab, Youssif Abuzied, Dineo Mpanya, Turgay Celik, Swarun Kumar, Tamer ElBatt</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FLOSS: Federated Learning with Opt-Out and Straggler Support</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23115</link>
   <description>Previous work on data privacy in federated learning systems focuses on privacy-preserving operations for data from users who have agreed to share their data for training. However, modern data privacy agreements also empower users to use the system while opting out of sharing their data as desired. When combined with stragglers that arise from heterogeneous device capabilities, the result is missing data from a variety of sources that introduces bias and degrades model performance. In this paper, we present FLOSS, a system that mitigates the impacts of such missing data on federated learning in the presence of stragglers and user opt-out, and empirically demonstrate its performance in simulations.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.23115v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>David J Goetze, Dahlia J Felten, Jeannie R Albrecht, Rohit Bhattacharya</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>OptiGradTrust: Byzantine-Robust Federated Learning with Multi-Feature Gradient Analysis and Reinforcement Learning-Based Trust Weighting</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23638</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) enables collaborative model training across distributed medical institutions while preserving patient privacy, but remains vulnerable to Byzantine attacks and statistical heterogeneity. We present OptiGradTrust, a comprehensive defense framework that evaluates gradient updates through a novel six-dimensional fingerprint including VAE reconstruction error, cosine similarity metrics, $L_2$ norm, sign-consistency ratio, and Monte Carlo Shapley value, which drive a hybrid RL-attention module for adaptive trust scoring. To address convergence challenges under data heterogeneity, we develop FedBN-Prox (FedBN-P), combining Federated Batch Normalization with proximal regularization for optimal accuracy-convergence trade-offs. Extensive evaluation across MNIST, CIFAR-10, and Alzheimer's MRI datasets under various Byzantine attack scenarios demonstrates significant improvements over state-of-the-art defenses, achieving up to +1.6 percentage points over FLGuard under non-IID conditions while maintaining robust performance against diverse attack patterns through our adaptive learning approach.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.23638v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mohammad Karami, Fatemeh Ghassemi, Hamed Kebriaei, Hamid Azadegan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Privacy-Preserving Federated Framework with Hybrid Quantum-Enhanced Learning for Financial Fraud Detection</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22908</link>
   <description>Rapid growth of digital transactions has led to a surge in fraudulent activities, challenging traditional detection methods in the financial sector. To tackle this problem, we introduce a specialised federated learning framework that uniquely combines a quantum-enhanced Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) model with advanced privacy preserving techniques. By integrating quantum layers into the LSTM architecture, our approach adeptly captures complex cross-transactional patters, resulting in an approximate 5% performance improvement across key evaluation metrics compared to conventional models. Central to our framework is &quot;FedRansel&quot;, a novel method designed to defend against poisoning and inference attacks, thereby reducing model degradation and inference accuracy by 4-8%, compared to standard differential privacy mechanisms. This pseudo-centralised setup with a Quantum LSTM model, enhances fraud detection accuracy and reinforces the security and confidentiality of sensitive financial data.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.22908v1</guid>
   <category>q-fin.CP</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Abhishek Sawaika, Swetang Krishna, Tushar Tomar, Durga Pritam Suggisetti, Aditi Lal, Tanmaya Shrivastav, Nouhaila Innan, Muhammad Shafique</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Automated Label Placement on Maps via Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22952</link>
   <description>Label placement is a critical aspect of map design, serving as a form of spatial annotation that directly impacts clarity and interpretability. Despite its importance, label placement remains largely manual and difficult to scale, as existing automated systems struggle to integrate cartographic conventions, adapt to context, or interpret labeling instructions. In this work, we introduce a new paradigm for automatic label placement (ALP) that formulates the task as a data editing problem and leverages large language models (LLMs) for context-aware spatial annotation. To support this direction, we curate MAPLE, the first known benchmarking dataset for evaluating ALP on real-world maps, encompassing diverse landmark types and label placement annotations from open-source data. Our method retrieves labeling guidelines relevant to each landmark type leveraging retrieval-augmented generation (RAG), integrates them into prompts, and employs instruction-tuned LLMs to generate ideal label coordinates. We evaluate four open-source LLMs on MAPLE, analyzing both overall performance and generalization across different types of landmarks. This includes both zero-shot and instruction-tuned performance. Our results demonstrate that LLMs, when guided by structured prompts and domain-specific retrieval, can learn to perform accurate spatial edits, aligning the generated outputs with expert cartographic standards. Overall, our work presents a scalable framework for AI-assisted map finishing and demonstrates the potential of foundation models in structured data editing tasks. The code and data can be found at https://github.com/HarryShomer/MAPLE.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.22952v1</guid>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Harry Shomer, Jiejun Xu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Not Just What, But When: Integrating Irregular Intervals to LLM for Sequential Recommendation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23209</link>
   <description>Time intervals between purchasing items are a crucial factor in sequential recommendation tasks, whereas existing approaches focus on item sequences and often overlook by assuming the intervals between items are static. However, dynamic intervals serve as a dimension that describes user profiling on not only the history within a user but also different users with the same item history. In this work, we propose IntervalLLM, a novel framework that integrates interval information into LLM and incorporates the novel interval-infused attention to jointly consider information of items and intervals. Furthermore, unlike prior studies that address the cold-start scenario only from the perspectives of users and items, we introduce a new viewpoint: the interval perspective to serve as an additional metric for evaluating recommendation methods on the warm and cold scenarios. Extensive experiments on 3 benchmarks with both traditional- and LLM-based baselines demonstrate that our IntervalLLM achieves not only 4.4% improvements in average but also the best-performing warm and cold scenarios across all users, items, and the proposed interval perspectives. In addition, we observe that the cold scenario from the interval perspective experiences the most significant performance drop among all recommendation methods. This finding underscores the necessity of further research on interval-based cold challenges and our integration of interval information in the realm of sequential recommendation tasks. Our code is available here: https://github.com/sony/ds-research-code/tree/master/recsys25-IntervalLLM.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.23209v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Wei-Wei Du, Takuma Udagawa, Kei Tateno</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Satellite Federated Fine-Tuning for Foundation Models in Space Computing Power Networks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10403</link>
   <description>Advancements in artificial intelligence (AI) and low-earth orbit (LEO) satellites have promoted the application of large remote sensing foundation models for various downstream tasks. However, direct downloading of these models for fine-tuning on the ground is impeded by privacy concerns and limited bandwidth. Satellite federated learning (FL) offers a solution by enabling model fine-tuning directly on-board satellites and aggregating model updates without data downloading. Nevertheless, for large foundation models, the computational capacity of satellites is insufficient to support effective on-board fine-tuning in traditional satellite FL frameworks. To address these challenges, we propose a satellite-ground collaborative federated fine-tuning framework. The key of the framework lies in how to reasonably decompose and allocate model components to alleviate insufficient on-board computation capabilities. During fine-tuning, satellites exchange intermediate results with ground stations or other satellites for forward propagation and back propagation, which brings communication challenges due to the special communication topology of space transmission networks, such as intermittent satellite-ground communication, short duration of satellite-ground communication windows, and unstable inter-orbit inter-satellite links (ISLs). To reduce transmission delays, we further introduce tailored communication strategies that integrate both communication and computing resources. Specifically, we propose a parallel intra-orbit communication strategy, a topology-aware satellite-ground communication strategy, and a latency-minimalization inter-orbit communication strategy to reduce space communication costs. Simulation results demonstrate significant reductions in training time with improvements of approximately 33%.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.10403v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.NI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yan Zhu, Jingyang Zhu, Ting Wang, Yuanming Shi, Chunxiao Jiang, Khaled Ben Letaief</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>G-Core: A Simple, Scalable and Balanced RLHF Trainer</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22789</link>
   <description>Reinforcement Learning from Human Feedback (RLHF) has become an increasingly popular paradigm for training large language models (LLMs) and diffusion models. While existing RLHF training systems have enabled significant progress, they often face challenges in scaling to multi-modal and diffusion workflows and adapting to dynamic workloads. In particular, current approaches may encounter limitations in controller scalability, flexible resource placement, and efficient orchestration when handling complex RLHF pipelines, especially in scenarios involving dynamic sampling or generative reward modeling. In this paper, we present \textbf{G-Core}, a simple, scalable, and balanced RLHF training framework designed to address these challenges. G-Core introduces a parallel controller programming model, enabling flexible and efficient orchestration of complex RLHF workflows without the bottlenecks of a single centralized controller. Furthermore, we propose a dynamic placement schema that adaptively partitions resources and schedules workloads, significantly reducing hardware idle time and improving utilization, even under highly variable training conditions. G-Core has successfully trained models that support WeChat product features serving a large-scale user base, demonstrating its effectiveness and robustness in real-world scenarios. Our results show that G-Core advances the state of the art in RLHF training, providing a solid foundation for future research and deployment of large-scale, human-aligned models.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.22789v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Junyu Wu, Weiming Chang, Xiaotao Liu, Guanyou He, Haoqiang Hong, Boqi Liu, Hongtao Tian, Tao Yang, Yunsheng Shi, Feng Lin, Ting Yao</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Satellite Federated Fine-Tuning for Foundation Models in Space Computing Power Networks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10403</link>
   <description>Advancements in artificial intelligence (AI) and low-earth orbit (LEO) satellites have promoted the application of large remote sensing foundation models for various downstream tasks. However, direct downloading of these models for fine-tuning on the ground is impeded by privacy concerns and limited bandwidth. Satellite federated learning (FL) offers a solution by enabling model fine-tuning directly on-board satellites and aggregating model updates without data downloading. Nevertheless, for large foundation models, the computational capacity of satellites is insufficient to support effective on-board fine-tuning in traditional satellite FL frameworks. To address these challenges, we propose a satellite-ground collaborative federated fine-tuning framework. The key of the framework lies in how to reasonably decompose and allocate model components to alleviate insufficient on-board computation capabilities. During fine-tuning, satellites exchange intermediate results with ground stations or other satellites for forward propagation and back propagation, which brings communication challenges due to the special communication topology of space transmission networks, such as intermittent satellite-ground communication, short duration of satellite-ground communication windows, and unstable inter-orbit inter-satellite links (ISLs). To reduce transmission delays, we further introduce tailored communication strategies that integrate both communication and computing resources. Specifically, we propose a parallel intra-orbit communication strategy, a topology-aware satellite-ground communication strategy, and a latency-minimalization inter-orbit communication strategy to reduce space communication costs. Simulation results demonstrate significant reductions in training time with improvements of approximately 33%.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.10403v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.NI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yan Zhu, Jingyang Zhu, Ting Wang, Yuanming Shi, Chunxiao Jiang, Khaled Ben Letaief</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>TextQuests: How Good are LLMs at Text-Based Video Games?</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23701</link>
   <description>Evaluating AI agents within complex, interactive environments that mirror real-world challenges is critical for understanding their practical capabilities. While existing agent benchmarks effectively assess skills like tool use or performance on structured tasks, they often do not fully capture an agent's ability to operate autonomously in exploratory environments that demand sustained, self-directed reasoning over a long and growing context. To spur the development of agents capable of more robust intrinsic reasoning over long horizons, we introduce TextQuests, a benchmark based on the Infocom suite of interactive fiction games. These text-based adventures, which can take human players over 30 hours and require hundreds of precise actions to solve, serve as an effective proxy for evaluating AI agents on focused, stateful tasks. The benchmark is specifically designed to assess an LLM agent's capacity for self-contained problem-solving by precluding the use of external tools, thereby focusing on intrinsic long-context reasoning capabilities in an exploratory environment characterized by the need for trial-and-error learning and sustained problem-solving within a single interactive session. We release TextQuests at https://textquests.ai.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.23701v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Long Phan, Mantas Mazeika, Andy Zou, Dan Hendrycks</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Privacy-Preserving Federated Framework with Hybrid Quantum-Enhanced Learning for Financial Fraud Detection</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22908</link>
   <description>Rapid growth of digital transactions has led to a surge in fraudulent activities, challenging traditional detection methods in the financial sector. To tackle this problem, we introduce a specialised federated learning framework that uniquely combines a quantum-enhanced Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) model with advanced privacy preserving techniques. By integrating quantum layers into the LSTM architecture, our approach adeptly captures complex cross-transactional patters, resulting in an approximate 5% performance improvement across key evaluation metrics compared to conventional models. Central to our framework is &quot;FedRansel&quot;, a novel method designed to defend against poisoning and inference attacks, thereby reducing model degradation and inference accuracy by 4-8%, compared to standard differential privacy mechanisms. This pseudo-centralised setup with a Quantum LSTM model, enhances fraud detection accuracy and reinforces the security and confidentiality of sensitive financial data.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.22908v1</guid>
   <category>q-fin.CP</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Abhishek Sawaika, Swetang Krishna, Tushar Tomar, Durga Pritam Suggisetti, Aditi Lal, Tanmaya Shrivastav, Nouhaila Innan, Muhammad Shafique</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Discrete Tokenization for Multimodal LLMs: A Comprehensive Survey</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22920</link>
   <description>The rapid advancement of large language models (LLMs) has intensified the need for effective mechanisms to transform continuous multimodal data into discrete representations suitable for language-based processing. Discrete tokenization, with vector quantization (VQ) as a central approach, offers both computational efficiency and compatibility with LLM architectures. Despite its growing importance, there is a lack of a comprehensive survey that systematically examines VQ techniques in the context of LLM-based systems. This work fills this gap by presenting the first structured taxonomy and analysis of discrete tokenization methods designed for LLMs. We categorize 8 representative VQ variants that span classical and modern paradigms and analyze their algorithmic principles, training dynamics, and integration challenges with LLM pipelines. Beyond algorithm-level investigation, we discuss existing research in terms of classical applications without LLMs, LLM-based single-modality systems, and LLM-based multimodal systems, highlighting how quantization strategies influence alignment, reasoning, and generation performance. In addition, we identify key challenges including codebook collapse, unstable gradient estimation, and modality-specific encoding constraints. Finally, we discuss emerging research directions such as dynamic and task-adaptive quantization, unified tokenization frameworks, and biologically inspired codebook learning. This survey bridges the gap between traditional vector quantization and modern LLM applications, serving as a foundational reference for the development of efficient and generalizable multimodal systems. A continuously updated version is available at: https://github.com/jindongli-Ai/LLM-Discrete-Tokenization-Survey.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.22920v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jindong Li, Yali Fu, Jiahong Liu, Linxiao Cao, Wei Ji, Menglin Yang, Irwin King, Ming-Hsuan Yang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>On LLM-Assisted Generation of Smart Contracts from Business Processes</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23087</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) have changed the reality of how software is produced. Within the wider software engineering community, among many other purposes, they are explored for code generation use cases from different types of input. In this work, we present an exploratory study to investigate the use of LLMs for generating smart contract code from business process descriptions, an idea that has emerged in recent literature to overcome the limitations of traditional rule-based code generation approaches. However, current LLM-based work evaluates generated code on small samples, relying on manual inspection, or testing whether code compiles but ignoring correct execution. With this work, we introduce an automated evaluation framework and provide empirical data from larger data sets of process models. We test LLMs of different types and sizes in their capabilities of achieving important properties of process execution, including enforcing process flow, resource allocation, and data-based conditions. Our results show that LLM performance falls short of the perfect reliability required for smart contract development. We suggest future work to explore responsible LLM integrations in existing tools for code generation to ensure more reliable output. Our benchmarking framework can serve as a foundation for developing and evaluating such integrations.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.23087v1</guid>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Fabian Stiehle, Hans Weytjens, Ingo Weber</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FLOSS: Federated Learning with Opt-Out and Straggler Support</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23115</link>
   <description>Previous work on data privacy in federated learning systems focuses on privacy-preserving operations for data from users who have agreed to share their data for training. However, modern data privacy agreements also empower users to use the system while opting out of sharing their data as desired. When combined with stragglers that arise from heterogeneous device capabilities, the result is missing data from a variety of sources that introduces bias and degrades model performance. In this paper, we present FLOSS, a system that mitigates the impacts of such missing data on federated learning in the presence of stragglers and user opt-out, and empirically demonstrate its performance in simulations.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.23115v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>David J Goetze, Dahlia J Felten, Jeannie R Albrecht, Rohit Bhattacharya</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Mitigating Resolution-Drift in Federated Learning: Case of Keypoint Detection</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23461</link>
   <description>The Federated Learning (FL) approach enables effective learning across distributed systems, while preserving user data privacy. To date, research has primarily focused on addressing statistical heterogeneity and communication efficiency, through which FL has achieved success in classification tasks. However, its application to non-classification tasks, such as human pose estimation, remains underexplored. This paper identifies and investigates a critical issue termed ``resolution-drift,'' where performance degrades significantly due to resolution variability across clients. Unlike class-level heterogeneity, resolution drift highlights the importance of resolution as another axis of not independent or identically distributed (non-IID) data. To address this issue, we present resolution-adaptive federated learning (RAF), a method that leverages heatmap-based knowledge distillation. Through multi-resolution knowledge distillation between higher-resolution outputs (teachers) and lower-resolution outputs (students), our approach enhances resolution robustness without overfitting. Extensive experiments and theoretical analysis demonstrate that RAF not only effectively mitigates resolution drift and achieves significant performance improvements, but also can be integrated seamlessly into existing FL frameworks. Furthermore, although this paper focuses on human pose estimation, our t-SNE analysis reveals distinct characteristics between classification and high-resolution representation tasks, supporting the generalizability of RAF to other tasks that rely on preserving spatial detail.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.23461v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Taeheon Lim, Joohyung Lee, Kyungjae Lee, Jungchan Cho</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>OptiGradTrust: Byzantine-Robust Federated Learning with Multi-Feature Gradient Analysis and Reinforcement Learning-Based Trust Weighting</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23638</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) enables collaborative model training across distributed medical institutions while preserving patient privacy, but remains vulnerable to Byzantine attacks and statistical heterogeneity. We present OptiGradTrust, a comprehensive defense framework that evaluates gradient updates through a novel six-dimensional fingerprint including VAE reconstruction error, cosine similarity metrics, $L_2$ norm, sign-consistency ratio, and Monte Carlo Shapley value, which drive a hybrid RL-attention module for adaptive trust scoring. To address convergence challenges under data heterogeneity, we develop FedBN-Prox (FedBN-P), combining Federated Batch Normalization with proximal regularization for optimal accuracy-convergence trade-offs. Extensive evaluation across MNIST, CIFAR-10, and Alzheimer's MRI datasets under various Byzantine attack scenarios demonstrates significant improvements over state-of-the-art defenses, achieving up to +1.6 percentage points over FLGuard under non-IID conditions while maintaining robust performance against diverse attack patterns through our adaptive learning approach.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.23638v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mohammad Karami, Fatemeh Ghassemi, Hamed Kebriaei, Hamid Azadegan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>EducationQ: Evaluating LLMs' Teaching Capabilities Through Multi-Agent Dialogue Framework</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14928</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) increasingly serve as educational tools, yet evaluating their teaching capabilities remains challenging due to the resource-intensive, context-dependent, and methodologically complex nature of teacher-student interactions. We introduce EducationQ, a multi-agent dialogue framework that efficiently assesses teaching capabilities through simulated dynamic educational scenarios, featuring specialized agents for teaching, learning, and evaluation. Testing 14 LLMs across major AI Organizations (OpenAI, Meta, Google, Anthropic, and others) on 1,498 questions spanning 13 disciplines and 10 difficulty levels reveals that teaching effectiveness does not correlate linearly with model scale or general reasoning capabilities - with some smaller open-source models outperforming larger commercial counterparts in teaching contexts. This finding highlights a critical gap in current evaluations that prioritize knowledge recall over interactive pedagogy. Our mixed-methods evaluation, combining quantitative metrics with qualitative analysis and expert case studies, identifies distinct pedagogical strengths employed by top-performing models (e.g., sophisticated questioning strategies, adaptive feedback mechanisms). Human expert evaluations show 78% agreement with our automated qualitative analysis of effective teaching behaviors, validating our methodology. EducationQ demonstrates that LLMs-as-teachers require specialized optimization beyond simple scaling, suggesting next-generation educational AI prioritize targeted enhancement of specific pedagogical effectiveness.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.14928v3</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CE</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yao Shi, Rongkeng Liang, Yong Xu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Compute-Matched Re-Evaluation of TroVE on MATH</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22069</link>
   <description>Reusing established theorems and formulas is central to mathematical problem solving, serving as essential building blocks for tackling increasingly complex challenges. Recent work, TroVE, argues that code-generating Large Language Models (LLMs) can benefit similarly on the MATH benchmark by inducing and reusing higher-level toolboxes. By allocating computational budget across an ensemble of three modes -- directly generating code, creating tools, and reusing tools -- TroVE claims to outperform a PRIMITIVE baseline that only performs direct generation. However, recent analysis (Berlot-Attwell et al., 2024) casts doubt on these gains, noting that the tools created are often trivial or rarely reused, suggesting that improvements may stem from self-consistency or self-correction. In this work, we re-evaluate TroVE on MATH, analyze the impact of each of its modes, and show that its benefit does not come from these mechanisms, but simply from a higher computational budget spent for TroVE compared to PRIMITIVE. To this end, we also perform a small correction in the original implementation of TroVE's selection mechanism, boosting TroVE's performance on MATH by 3\% in accuracy. After matching for compute, the benefit of TroVE reduces to a marginal improvement of 1\%, suggesting that this toolbox approach does not provide a significant benefit on MATH.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.22069v2</guid>
   <category>cs.PL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Tobias Sesterhenn, Ian Berlot-Attwell, Janis Zenkner, Christian Bartelt</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>G-Core: A Simple, Scalable and Balanced RLHF Trainer</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22789</link>
   <description>Reinforcement Learning from Human Feedback (RLHF) has become an increasingly popular paradigm for training large language models (LLMs) and diffusion models. While existing RLHF training systems have enabled significant progress, they often face challenges in scaling to multi-modal and diffusion workflows and adapting to dynamic workloads. In particular, current approaches may encounter limitations in controller scalability, flexible resource placement, and efficient orchestration when handling complex RLHF pipelines, especially in scenarios involving dynamic sampling or generative reward modeling. In this paper, we present \textbf{G-Core}, a simple, scalable, and balanced RLHF training framework designed to address these challenges. G-Core introduces a parallel controller programming model, enabling flexible and efficient orchestration of complex RLHF workflows without the bottlenecks of a single centralized controller. Furthermore, we propose a dynamic placement schema that adaptively partitions resources and schedules workloads, significantly reducing hardware idle time and improving utilization, even under highly variable training conditions. G-Core has successfully trained models that support WeChat product features serving a large-scale user base, demonstrating its effectiveness and robustness in real-world scenarios. Our results show that G-Core advances the state of the art in RLHF training, providing a solid foundation for future research and deployment of large-scale, human-aligned models.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.22789v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Junyu Wu, Weiming Chang, Xiaotao Liu, Guanyou He, Haoqiang Hong, Boqi Liu, Hongtao Tian, Tao Yang, Yunsheng Shi, Feng Lin, Ting Yao</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Compute-Matched Re-Evaluation of TroVE on MATH</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22069</link>
   <description>Reusing established theorems and formulas is central to mathematical problem solving, serving as essential building blocks for tackling increasingly complex challenges. Recent work, TroVE, argues that code-generating Large Language Models (LLMs) can benefit similarly on the MATH benchmark by inducing and reusing higher-level toolboxes. By allocating computational budget across an ensemble of three modes -- directly generating code, creating tools, and reusing tools -- TroVE claims to outperform a PRIMITIVE baseline that only performs direct generation. However, recent analysis (Berlot-Attwell et al., 2024) casts doubt on these gains, noting that the tools created are often trivial or rarely reused, suggesting that improvements may stem from self-consistency or self-correction. In this work, we re-evaluate TroVE on MATH, analyze the impact of each of its modes, and show that its benefit does not come from these mechanisms, but simply from a higher computational budget spent for TroVE compared to PRIMITIVE. To this end, we also perform a small correction in the original implementation of TroVE's selection mechanism, boosting TroVE's performance on MATH by 3\% in accuracy. After matching for compute, the benefit of TroVE reduces to a marginal improvement of 1\%, suggesting that this toolbox approach does not provide a significant benefit on MATH.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.22069v2</guid>
   <category>cs.PL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Tobias Sesterhenn, Ian Berlot-Attwell, Janis Zenkner, Christian Bartelt</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>MindVote: When AI Meets the Wild West of Social Media Opinion</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14422</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) are increasingly used as scalable tools for pilot testing, predicting public opinion distributions before deploying costly surveys. To serve as effective pilot testing tools, the performance of these LLMs is typically benchmarked against their ability to reproduce the outcomes of past structured surveys. This evaluation paradigm, however, is misaligned with the dynamic, context-rich social media environments where public opinion is increasingly formed and expressed. By design, surveys strip away the social, cultural, and temporal context that shapes public opinion, and LLM benchmarks built on this paradigm inherit these critical limitations. To bridge this gap, we introduce MindVote, the first benchmark for public opinion distribution prediction grounded in authentic social media discourse. MindVote is constructed from 3,918 naturalistic polls sourced from Reddit and Weibo, spanning 23 topics and enriched with detailed annotations for platform, topical, and temporal context. Using this benchmark, we conduct a comprehensive evaluation of 15 LLMs. MindVote provides a robust, ecologically valid framework to move beyond survey-based evaluations and advance the development of more socially intelligent AI systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.14422v3</guid>
   <category>cs.SI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xutao Mao, Ezra Xuanru Tao, Leyao Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Satellite Federated Fine-Tuning for Foundation Models in Space Computing Power Networks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10403</link>
   <description>Advancements in artificial intelligence (AI) and low-earth orbit (LEO) satellites have promoted the application of large remote sensing foundation models for various downstream tasks. However, direct downloading of these models for fine-tuning on the ground is impeded by privacy concerns and limited bandwidth. Satellite federated learning (FL) offers a solution by enabling model fine-tuning directly on-board satellites and aggregating model updates without data downloading. Nevertheless, for large foundation models, the computational capacity of satellites is insufficient to support effective on-board fine-tuning in traditional satellite FL frameworks. To address these challenges, we propose a satellite-ground collaborative federated fine-tuning framework. The key of the framework lies in how to reasonably decompose and allocate model components to alleviate insufficient on-board computation capabilities. During fine-tuning, satellites exchange intermediate results with ground stations or other satellites for forward propagation and back propagation, which brings communication challenges due to the special communication topology of space transmission networks, such as intermittent satellite-ground communication, short duration of satellite-ground communication windows, and unstable inter-orbit inter-satellite links (ISLs). To reduce transmission delays, we further introduce tailored communication strategies that integrate both communication and computing resources. Specifically, we propose a parallel intra-orbit communication strategy, a topology-aware satellite-ground communication strategy, and a latency-minimalization inter-orbit communication strategy to reduce space communication costs. Simulation results demonstrate significant reductions in training time with improvements of approximately 33%.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.10403v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.NI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yan Zhu, Jingyang Zhu, Ting Wang, Yuanming Shi, Chunxiao Jiang, Khaled Ben Letaief</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>EducationQ: Evaluating LLMs' Teaching Capabilities Through Multi-Agent Dialogue Framework</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14928</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) increasingly serve as educational tools, yet evaluating their teaching capabilities remains challenging due to the resource-intensive, context-dependent, and methodologically complex nature of teacher-student interactions. We introduce EducationQ, a multi-agent dialogue framework that efficiently assesses teaching capabilities through simulated dynamic educational scenarios, featuring specialized agents for teaching, learning, and evaluation. Testing 14 LLMs across major AI Organizations (OpenAI, Meta, Google, Anthropic, and others) on 1,498 questions spanning 13 disciplines and 10 difficulty levels reveals that teaching effectiveness does not correlate linearly with model scale or general reasoning capabilities - with some smaller open-source models outperforming larger commercial counterparts in teaching contexts. This finding highlights a critical gap in current evaluations that prioritize knowledge recall over interactive pedagogy. Our mixed-methods evaluation, combining quantitative metrics with qualitative analysis and expert case studies, identifies distinct pedagogical strengths employed by top-performing models (e.g., sophisticated questioning strategies, adaptive feedback mechanisms). Human expert evaluations show 78% agreement with our automated qualitative analysis of effective teaching behaviors, validating our methodology. EducationQ demonstrates that LLMs-as-teachers require specialized optimization beyond simple scaling, suggesting next-generation educational AI prioritize targeted enhancement of specific pedagogical effectiveness.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.14928v3</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CE</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yao Shi, Rongkeng Liang, Yong Xu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>On LLM-Assisted Generation of Smart Contracts from Business Processes</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23087</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) have changed the reality of how software is produced. Within the wider software engineering community, among many other purposes, they are explored for code generation use cases from different types of input. In this work, we present an exploratory study to investigate the use of LLMs for generating smart contract code from business process descriptions, an idea that has emerged in recent literature to overcome the limitations of traditional rule-based code generation approaches. However, current LLM-based work evaluates generated code on small samples, relying on manual inspection, or testing whether code compiles but ignoring correct execution. With this work, we introduce an automated evaluation framework and provide empirical data from larger data sets of process models. We test LLMs of different types and sizes in their capabilities of achieving important properties of process execution, including enforcing process flow, resource allocation, and data-based conditions. Our results show that LLM performance falls short of the perfect reliability required for smart contract development. We suggest future work to explore responsible LLM integrations in existing tools for code generation to ensure more reliable output. Our benchmarking framework can serve as a foundation for developing and evaluating such integrations.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.23087v1</guid>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Fabian Stiehle, Hans Weytjens, Ingo Weber</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Automated Label Placement on Maps via Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22952</link>
   <description>Label placement is a critical aspect of map design, serving as a form of spatial annotation that directly impacts clarity and interpretability. Despite its importance, label placement remains largely manual and difficult to scale, as existing automated systems struggle to integrate cartographic conventions, adapt to context, or interpret labeling instructions. In this work, we introduce a new paradigm for automatic label placement (ALP) that formulates the task as a data editing problem and leverages large language models (LLMs) for context-aware spatial annotation. To support this direction, we curate MAPLE, the first known benchmarking dataset for evaluating ALP on real-world maps, encompassing diverse landmark types and label placement annotations from open-source data. Our method retrieves labeling guidelines relevant to each landmark type leveraging retrieval-augmented generation (RAG), integrates them into prompts, and employs instruction-tuned LLMs to generate ideal label coordinates. We evaluate four open-source LLMs on MAPLE, analyzing both overall performance and generalization across different types of landmarks. This includes both zero-shot and instruction-tuned performance. Our results demonstrate that LLMs, when guided by structured prompts and domain-specific retrieval, can learn to perform accurate spatial edits, aligning the generated outputs with expert cartographic standards. Overall, our work presents a scalable framework for AI-assisted map finishing and demonstrates the potential of foundation models in structured data editing tasks. The code and data can be found at https://github.com/HarryShomer/MAPLE.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.22952v1</guid>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Harry Shomer, Jiejun Xu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>EducationQ: Evaluating LLMs' Teaching Capabilities Through Multi-Agent Dialogue Framework</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14928</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) increasingly serve as educational tools, yet evaluating their teaching capabilities remains challenging due to the resource-intensive, context-dependent, and methodologically complex nature of teacher-student interactions. We introduce EducationQ, a multi-agent dialogue framework that efficiently assesses teaching capabilities through simulated dynamic educational scenarios, featuring specialized agents for teaching, learning, and evaluation. Testing 14 LLMs across major AI Organizations (OpenAI, Meta, Google, Anthropic, and others) on 1,498 questions spanning 13 disciplines and 10 difficulty levels reveals that teaching effectiveness does not correlate linearly with model scale or general reasoning capabilities - with some smaller open-source models outperforming larger commercial counterparts in teaching contexts. This finding highlights a critical gap in current evaluations that prioritize knowledge recall over interactive pedagogy. Our mixed-methods evaluation, combining quantitative metrics with qualitative analysis and expert case studies, identifies distinct pedagogical strengths employed by top-performing models (e.g., sophisticated questioning strategies, adaptive feedback mechanisms). Human expert evaluations show 78% agreement with our automated qualitative analysis of effective teaching behaviors, validating our methodology. EducationQ demonstrates that LLMs-as-teachers require specialized optimization beyond simple scaling, suggesting next-generation educational AI prioritize targeted enhancement of specific pedagogical effectiveness.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.14928v3</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CE</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yao Shi, Rongkeng Liang, Yong Xu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>EducationQ: Evaluating LLMs' Teaching Capabilities Through Multi-Agent Dialogue Framework</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14928</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) increasingly serve as educational tools, yet evaluating their teaching capabilities remains challenging due to the resource-intensive, context-dependent, and methodologically complex nature of teacher-student interactions. We introduce EducationQ, a multi-agent dialogue framework that efficiently assesses teaching capabilities through simulated dynamic educational scenarios, featuring specialized agents for teaching, learning, and evaluation. Testing 14 LLMs across major AI Organizations (OpenAI, Meta, Google, Anthropic, and others) on 1,498 questions spanning 13 disciplines and 10 difficulty levels reveals that teaching effectiveness does not correlate linearly with model scale or general reasoning capabilities - with some smaller open-source models outperforming larger commercial counterparts in teaching contexts. This finding highlights a critical gap in current evaluations that prioritize knowledge recall over interactive pedagogy. Our mixed-methods evaluation, combining quantitative metrics with qualitative analysis and expert case studies, identifies distinct pedagogical strengths employed by top-performing models (e.g., sophisticated questioning strategies, adaptive feedback mechanisms). Human expert evaluations show 78% agreement with our automated qualitative analysis of effective teaching behaviors, validating our methodology. EducationQ demonstrates that LLMs-as-teachers require specialized optimization beyond simple scaling, suggesting next-generation educational AI prioritize targeted enhancement of specific pedagogical effectiveness.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.14928v3</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CE</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yao Shi, Rongkeng Liang, Yong Xu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Discrete Tokenization for Multimodal LLMs: A Comprehensive Survey</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22920</link>
   <description>The rapid advancement of large language models (LLMs) has intensified the need for effective mechanisms to transform continuous multimodal data into discrete representations suitable for language-based processing. Discrete tokenization, with vector quantization (VQ) as a central approach, offers both computational efficiency and compatibility with LLM architectures. Despite its growing importance, there is a lack of a comprehensive survey that systematically examines VQ techniques in the context of LLM-based systems. This work fills this gap by presenting the first structured taxonomy and analysis of discrete tokenization methods designed for LLMs. We categorize 8 representative VQ variants that span classical and modern paradigms and analyze their algorithmic principles, training dynamics, and integration challenges with LLM pipelines. Beyond algorithm-level investigation, we discuss existing research in terms of classical applications without LLMs, LLM-based single-modality systems, and LLM-based multimodal systems, highlighting how quantization strategies influence alignment, reasoning, and generation performance. In addition, we identify key challenges including codebook collapse, unstable gradient estimation, and modality-specific encoding constraints. Finally, we discuss emerging research directions such as dynamic and task-adaptive quantization, unified tokenization frameworks, and biologically inspired codebook learning. This survey bridges the gap between traditional vector quantization and modern LLM applications, serving as a foundational reference for the development of efficient and generalizable multimodal systems. A continuously updated version is available at: https://github.com/jindongli-Ai/LLM-Discrete-Tokenization-Survey.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.22920v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jindong Li, Yali Fu, Jiahong Liu, Linxiao Cao, Wei Ji, Menglin Yang, Irwin King, Ming-Hsuan Yang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Failures Are the Stepping Stones to Success: Enhancing Few-Shot In-Context Learning by Leveraging Negative Samples</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23211</link>
   <description>Large Language Models exhibit powerful few-shot in-context learning (ICL) capabilities, but the performance is highly sensitive to provided examples.
  Recent research has focused on retrieving corresponding examples for each input query, not only enhancing the efficiency and scalability of the learning process but also mitigating inherent biases in manual example selection.
  However, these studies have primarily emphasized leveraging Positive samples while overlooking the additional information within Negative samples for contextual learning.
  We propose a novel method that utilizes Negative samples to better select Positive sample examples, thereby enhancing the performance of few-shot ICL. Initially, we construct Positive and Negative sample corpora based on Zero-Shot-Cot. Then, during inference, we employ a semantic similarity-based approach to select the most similar examples from both the Positive and Negative corpora for a given query. Subsequently, we further retrieve Positive examples from the Positive sample corpus based on semantic similarity to the Negative examples, then concatenating them with the previously selected Positive examples to serve as ICL demonstrations. Experimental results demonstrate that our approach surpasses methods solely relying on the most similar positive examples for context, validating that the additional information in negative samples aids in enhancing ICL performance through improved Positive sample selection.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.23211v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yunhao Liang, Ruixuan Ying, Takuya Taniguchi, Zhe Cui</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>TextQuests: How Good are LLMs at Text-Based Video Games?</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23701</link>
   <description>Evaluating AI agents within complex, interactive environments that mirror real-world challenges is critical for understanding their practical capabilities. While existing agent benchmarks effectively assess skills like tool use or performance on structured tasks, they often do not fully capture an agent's ability to operate autonomously in exploratory environments that demand sustained, self-directed reasoning over a long and growing context. To spur the development of agents capable of more robust intrinsic reasoning over long horizons, we introduce TextQuests, a benchmark based on the Infocom suite of interactive fiction games. These text-based adventures, which can take human players over 30 hours and require hundreds of precise actions to solve, serve as an effective proxy for evaluating AI agents on focused, stateful tasks. The benchmark is specifically designed to assess an LLM agent's capacity for self-contained problem-solving by precluding the use of external tools, thereby focusing on intrinsic long-context reasoning capabilities in an exploratory environment characterized by the need for trial-and-error learning and sustained problem-solving within a single interactive session. We release TextQuests at https://textquests.ai.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.23701v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Long Phan, Mantas Mazeika, Andy Zou, Dan Hendrycks</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>EducationQ: Evaluating LLMs' Teaching Capabilities Through Multi-Agent Dialogue Framework</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14928</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) increasingly serve as educational tools, yet evaluating their teaching capabilities remains challenging due to the resource-intensive, context-dependent, and methodologically complex nature of teacher-student interactions. We introduce EducationQ, a multi-agent dialogue framework that efficiently assesses teaching capabilities through simulated dynamic educational scenarios, featuring specialized agents for teaching, learning, and evaluation. Testing 14 LLMs across major AI Organizations (OpenAI, Meta, Google, Anthropic, and others) on 1,498 questions spanning 13 disciplines and 10 difficulty levels reveals that teaching effectiveness does not correlate linearly with model scale or general reasoning capabilities - with some smaller open-source models outperforming larger commercial counterparts in teaching contexts. This finding highlights a critical gap in current evaluations that prioritize knowledge recall over interactive pedagogy. Our mixed-methods evaluation, combining quantitative metrics with qualitative analysis and expert case studies, identifies distinct pedagogical strengths employed by top-performing models (e.g., sophisticated questioning strategies, adaptive feedback mechanisms). Human expert evaluations show 78% agreement with our automated qualitative analysis of effective teaching behaviors, validating our methodology. EducationQ demonstrates that LLMs-as-teachers require specialized optimization beyond simple scaling, suggesting next-generation educational AI prioritize targeted enhancement of specific pedagogical effectiveness.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.14928v3</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CE</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yao Shi, Rongkeng Liang, Yong Xu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>RecGPT Technical Report</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22879</link>
   <description>Recommender systems are among the most impactful applications of artificial intelligence, serving as critical infrastructure connecting users, merchants, and platforms. However, most current industrial systems remain heavily reliant on historical co-occurrence patterns and log-fitting objectives, i.e., optimizing for past user interactions without explicitly modeling user intent. This log-fitting approach often leads to overfitting to narrow historical preferences, failing to capture users' evolving and latent interests. As a result, it reinforces filter bubbles and long-tail phenomena, ultimately harming user experience and threatening the sustainability of the whole recommendation ecosystem.
  To address these challenges, we rethink the overall design paradigm of recommender systems and propose RecGPT, a next-generation framework that places user intent at the center of the recommendation pipeline. By integrating large language models (LLMs) into key stages of user interest mining, item retrieval, and explanation generation, RecGPT transforms log-fitting recommendation into an intent-centric process. To effectively align general-purpose LLMs to the above domain-specific recommendation tasks at scale, RecGPT incorporates a multi-stage training paradigm, which integrates reasoning-enhanced pre-alignment and self-training evolution, guided by a Human-LLM cooperative judge system. Currently, RecGPT has been fully deployed on the Taobao App. Online experiments demonstrate that RecGPT achieves consistent performance gains across stakeholders: users benefit from increased content diversity and satisfaction, merchants and the platform gain greater exposure and conversions. These comprehensive improvement results across all stakeholders validates that LLM-driven, intent-centric design can foster a more sustainable and mutually beneficial recommendation ecosystem.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.22879v2</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chao Yi, Dian Chen, Gaoyang Guo, Jiakai Tang, Jian Wu, Jing Yu, Mao Zhang, Sunhao Dai, Wen Chen, Wenjun Yang, Yuning Jiang, Zhujin Gao, Bo Zheng, Chi Li, Dimin Wang, Dixuan Wang, Fan Li, Fan Zhang, Haibin Chen, Haozhuang Liu, Jialin Zhu, Jiamang Wang, Jiawei Wu, Jin Cui, Ju Huang, Kai Zhang, Kan Liu, Lang Tian, Liang Rao, Longbin Li, Lulu Zhao, Na He, Peiyang Wang, Qiqi Huang, Tao Luo, Wenbo Su, Xiaoxiao He, Xin Tong, Xu Chen, Xunke Xi, Yang Li, Yaxuan Wu, Yeqiu Yang, Yi Hu, Yinnan Song, Yuchen Li, Yujie Luo, Yujin Yuan, Yuliang Yan, Zhengyang Wang, Zhibo Xiao, Zhixin Ma, Zile Zhou, Ziqi Zhang</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
