<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 04:33:32 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 04:33:32 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>Can Large Language Models Predict Audio Effects Parameters from Natural Language?</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20770</link>
   <description>In music production, manipulating audio effects (Fx) parameters through natural language has the potential to reduce technical barriers for non-experts. We present LLM2Fx, a framework leveraging Large Language Models (LLMs) to predict Fx parameters directly from textual descriptions without requiring task-specific training or fine-tuning. Our approach address the text-to-effect parameter prediction (Text2Fx) task by mapping natural language descriptions to the corresponding Fx parameters for equalization and reverberation. We demonstrate that LLMs can generate Fx parameters in a zero-shot manner that elucidates the relationship between timbre semantics and audio effects in music production. To enhance performance, we introduce three types of in-context examples: audio Digital Signal Processing (DSP) features, DSP function code, and few-shot examples. Our results demonstrate that LLM-based Fx parameter generation outperforms previous optimization approaches, offering competitive performance in translating natural language descriptions to appropriate Fx settings. Furthermore, LLMs can serve as text-driven interfaces for audio production, paving the way for more intuitive and accessible music production tools.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.20770v2</guid>
   <category>cs.SD</category>
   <category>cs.MM</category>
   <category>eess.AS</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Seungheon Doh, Junghyun Koo, Marco A. Mart\'inez-Ram\'irez, Wei-Hsiang Liao, Juhan Nam, Yuki Mitsufuji</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Multi-task retriever fine-tuning for domain-specific and efficient RAG</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04652</link>
   <description>Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) has become ubiquitous when deploying Large Language Models (LLMs), as it can address typical limitations such as generating hallucinated or outdated information. However, when building real-world RAG applications, practical issues arise. First, the retrieved information is generally domain-specific. Since it is computationally expensive to fine-tune LLMs, it is more feasible to fine-tune the retriever to improve the quality of the data included in the LLM input. Second, as more applications are deployed in the same real-world system, one cannot afford to deploy separate retrievers. Moreover, these RAG applications normally retrieve different kinds of data. Our solution is to instruction fine-tune a small retriever encoder on a variety of domain-specific tasks to allow us to deploy one encoder that can serve many use cases, thereby achieving low-cost, scalability, and speed. We show how this encoder generalizes to out-of-domain settings as well as to an unseen retrieval task on real-world enterprise use cases.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.04652v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Patrice B\'echard, Orlando Marquez Ayala</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Learning for Commercial Image Sources</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12903</link>
   <description>Federated Learning is a collaborative machine learning paradigm that enables multiple clients to learn a global model without exposing their data to each other. Consequently, it provides a secure learning platform with privacy-preserving capabilities. This paper introduces a new dataset containing 23,326 images collected from eight different commercial sources and classified into 31 categories, similar to the Office-31 dataset. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first image classification dataset specifically designed for Federated Learning. We also propose two new Federated Learning algorithms, namely Fed-Cyclic and Fed-Star. In Fed-Cyclic, a client receives weights from its previous client, updates them through local training, and passes them to the next client, thus forming a cyclic topology. In Fed-Star, a client receives weights from all other clients, updates its local weights through pre-aggregation (to address statistical heterogeneity) and local training, and sends its updated local weights to all other clients, thus forming a star-like topology. Our experiments reveal that both algorithms perform better than existing baselines on our newly introduced dataset.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.12903v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>eess.IV</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shreyansh Jain, Koteswar Rao Jerripothula</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Site-Level Fine-Tuning with Progressive Layer Freezing: Towards Robust Prediction of Bronchopulmonary Dysplasia from Day-1 Chest Radiographs in Extremely Preterm Infants</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12269</link>
   <description>Bronchopulmonary dysplasia (BPD) is a chronic lung disease affecting 35% of extremely low birth weight infants. Defined by oxygen dependence at 36 weeks postmenstrual age, it causes lifelong respiratory complications. However, preventive interventions carry severe risks, including neurodevelopmental impairment, ventilator-induced lung injury, and systemic complications. Therefore, early BPD prognosis and prediction of BPD outcome is crucial to avoid unnecessary toxicity in low risk infants. Admission radiographs of extremely preterm infants are routinely acquired within 24h of life and could serve as a non-invasive prognostic tool. In this work, we developed and investigated a deep learning approach using chest X-rays from 163 extremely low-birth-weight infants ($\leq$32 weeks gestation, 401-999g) obtained within 24 hours of birth. We fine-tuned a ResNet-50 pretrained specifically on adult chest radiographs, employing progressive layer freezing with discriminative learning rates to prevent overfitting and evaluated a CutMix augmentation and linear probing. For moderate/severe BPD outcome prediction, our best performing model with progressive freezing, linear probing and CutMix achieved an AUROC of 0.78 $\pm$ 0.10, balanced accuracy of 0.69 $\pm$ 0.10, and an F1-score of 0.67 $\pm$ 0.11. In-domain pre-training significantly outperformed ImageNet initialization (p = 0.031) which confirms domain-specific pretraining to be important for BPD outcome prediction. Routine IRDS grades showed limited prognostic value (AUROC 0.57 $\pm$ 0.11), confirming the need of learned markers. Our approach demonstrates that domain-specific pretraining enables accurate BPD prediction from routine day-1 radiographs. Through progressive freezing and linear probing, the method remains computationally feasible for site-level implementation and future federated learning deployments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.12269v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sybelle Goedicke-Fritz (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Michelle Bous (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Annika Engel (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany), Matthias Flotho (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany, Helmholtz Institute for Pharmaceutical Research Saarland), Pascal Hirsch (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany), Hannah Wittig (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Dino Milanovic (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany), Dominik Mohr (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Mathias Kaspar (Digital Medicine, University Hospital of Augsburg, Augsburg, Germany), Sogand Nemat (Department of Radiology, and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital of Saarland, Homburg, Germany), Dorothea Kerner (Department of Radiology, and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital of Saarland, Homburg, Germany), Arno B\&quot;ucker (Department of Radiology, and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital of Saarland, Homburg, Germany), Andreas Keller (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany, Helmholtz Institute for Pharmaceutical Research Saarland, Pharma Science Hub), Sascha Meyer (Clinical Centre Karlsruhe, Franz-Lust Clinic for Paediatrics, Karlsruhe, Germany), Michael Zemlin (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Philipp Flotho (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany, Helmholtz Institute for Pharmaceutical Research Saarland)</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Learning in Open- and Closed-Loop EMG Decoding: A Privacy and Performance Perspective</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12652</link>
   <description>Invasive and non-invasive neural interfaces hold promise as high-bandwidth input devices for next-generation technologies. However, neural signals inherently encode sensitive information about an individual's identity and health, making data sharing for decoder training a critical privacy challenge. Federated learning (FL), a distributed, privacy-preserving learning framework, presents a promising solution, but it remains unexplored in closed-loop adaptive neural interfaces. Here, we introduce FL-based neural decoding and systematically evaluate its performance and privacy using high-dimensional electromyography signals in both open- and closed-loop scenarios. In open-loop simulations, FL significantly outperformed local learning baselines, demonstrating its potential for high-performance, privacy-conscious neural decoding. In contrast, closed-loop user studies required adapting FL methods to accommodate single-user, real-time interactions, a scenario not supported by standard FL. This modification resulted in local learning decoders surpassing the adapted FL approach in closed-loop performance, yet local learning still carried higher privacy risks. Our findings highlight a critical performance-privacy tradeoff in real-time adaptive applications and indicate the need for FL methods specifically designed for co-adaptive, single-user applications.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.12652v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kai Malcolm, C\'esar Uribe, Momona Yamagami</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Distributed Generative AI Approach for Heterogeneous Multi-Domain Environments under Data Sharing constraints</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12979</link>
   <description>Federated Learning has gained increasing attention for its ability to enable multiple nodes to collaboratively train machine learning models without sharing their raw data. At the same time, Generative AI -- particularly Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs) -- have achieved remarkable success across a wide range of domains, such as healthcare, security, and Image Generation. However, training generative models typically requires large datasets and significant computational resources, which are often unavailable in real-world settings. Acquiring such resources can be costly and inefficient, especially when many underutilized devices -- such as IoT devices and edge devices -- with varying capabilities remain idle. Moreover, obtaining large datasets is challenging due to privacy concerns and copyright restrictions, as most devices are unwilling to share their data. To address these challenges, we propose a novel approach for decentralized GAN training that enables the utilization of distributed data and underutilized, low-capability devices while not sharing data in its raw form. Our approach is designed to tackle key challenges in decentralized environments, combining KLD-weighted Clustered Federated Learning to address the issues of data heterogeneity and multi-domain datasets, with Heterogeneous U-Shaped split learning to tackle the challenge of device heterogeneity under strict data sharing constraints -- ensuring that no labels or raw data, whether real or synthetic, are ever shared between nodes. Experimental results shows that our approach demonstrates consistent and significant improvements across key performance metrics, where it achieves 1.1x -- 2.2x higher image generation scores, an average 10% boost in classification metrics (up to 50% in multi-domain non-IID settings), in much lower latency compared to several benchmarks. Find our code at https://github.com/youssefga28/HuSCF-GAN.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.12979v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Youssef Tawfilis, Hossam Amer, Minar El-Aasser, Tallal Elshabrawy</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedGA: A Fair Federated Learning Framework Based on the Gini Coefficient</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12983</link>
   <description>Fairness has emerged as one of the key challenges in federated learning. In horizontal federated settings, data heterogeneity often leads to substantial performance disparities across clients, raising concerns about equitable model behavior. To address this issue, we propose FedGA, a fairness-aware federated learning algorithm. We first employ the Gini coefficient to measure the performance disparity among clients. Based on this, we establish a relationship between the Gini coefficient $G$ and the update scale of the global model ${U_s}$, and use this relationship to adaptively determine the timing of fairness intervention. Subsequently, we dynamically adjust the aggregation weights according to the system's real-time fairness status, enabling the global model to better incorporate information from clients with relatively poor performance.We conduct extensive experiments on the Office-Caltech-10, CIFAR-10, and Synthetic datasets. The results show that FedGA effectively improves fairness metrics such as variance and the Gini coefficient, while maintaining strong overall performance, demonstrating the effectiveness of our approach.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.12983v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>ShanBin Liu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Sporadic Federated Learning Approach in Quantum Environment to Tackle Quantum Noise</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12492</link>
   <description>Quantum Federated Learning (QFL) is an emerging paradigm that combines quantum computing and federated learning (FL) to enable decentralized model training while maintaining data privacy over quantum networks. However, quantum noise remains a significant barrier in QFL, since modern quantum devices experience heterogeneous noise levels due to variances in hardware quality and sensitivity to quantum decoherence, resulting in inadequate training performance. To address this issue, we propose SpoQFL, a novel QFL framework that leverages sporadic learning to mitigate quantum noise heterogeneity in distributed quantum systems. SpoQFL dynamically adjusts training strategies based on noise fluctuations, enhancing model robustness, convergence stability, and overall learning efficiency. Extensive experiments on real-world datasets demonstrate that SpoQFL significantly outperforms conventional QFL approaches, achieving superior training performance and more stable convergence.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.12492v1</guid>
   <category>quant-ph</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ratun Rahman, Atit Pokharel, Dinh C. Nguyen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Learning: A Survey on Privacy-Preserving Collaborative Intelligence</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17703</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) has emerged as a transformative paradigm in the field of distributed machine learning, enabling multiple clients such as mobile devices, edge nodes, or organizations to collaboratively train a shared global model without the need to centralize sensitive data. This decentralized approach addresses growing concerns around data privacy, security, and regulatory compliance, making it particularly attractive in domains such as healthcare, finance, and smart IoT systems. This survey provides a concise yet comprehensive overview of Federated Learning, beginning with its core architecture and communication protocol. We discuss the standard FL lifecycle, including local training, model aggregation, and global updates. A particular emphasis is placed on key technical challenges such as handling non-IID (non-independent and identically distributed) data, mitigating system and hardware heterogeneity, reducing communication overhead, and ensuring privacy through mechanisms like differential privacy and secure aggregation. Furthermore, we examine emerging trends in FL research, including personalized FL, cross-device versus cross-silo settings, and integration with other paradigms such as reinforcement learning and quantum computing. We also highlight real-world applications and summarize benchmark datasets and evaluation metrics commonly used in FL research. Finally, we outline open research problems and future directions to guide the development of scalable, efficient, and trustworthy FL systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.17703v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Nusrat Jahan, Ratun Rahman, Michel Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Multi-task retriever fine-tuning for domain-specific and efficient RAG</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04652</link>
   <description>Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) has become ubiquitous when deploying Large Language Models (LLMs), as it can address typical limitations such as generating hallucinated or outdated information. However, when building real-world RAG applications, practical issues arise. First, the retrieved information is generally domain-specific. Since it is computationally expensive to fine-tune LLMs, it is more feasible to fine-tune the retriever to improve the quality of the data included in the LLM input. Second, as more applications are deployed in the same real-world system, one cannot afford to deploy separate retrievers. Moreover, these RAG applications normally retrieve different kinds of data. Our solution is to instruction fine-tune a small retriever encoder on a variety of domain-specific tasks to allow us to deploy one encoder that can serve many use cases, thereby achieving low-cost, scalability, and speed. We show how this encoder generalizes to out-of-domain settings as well as to an unseen retrieval task on real-world enterprise use cases.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.04652v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Patrice B\'echard, Orlando Marquez Ayala</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Site-Level Fine-Tuning with Progressive Layer Freezing: Towards Robust Prediction of Bronchopulmonary Dysplasia from Day-1 Chest Radiographs in Extremely Preterm Infants</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12269</link>
   <description>Bronchopulmonary dysplasia (BPD) is a chronic lung disease affecting 35% of extremely low birth weight infants. Defined by oxygen dependence at 36 weeks postmenstrual age, it causes lifelong respiratory complications. However, preventive interventions carry severe risks, including neurodevelopmental impairment, ventilator-induced lung injury, and systemic complications. Therefore, early BPD prognosis and prediction of BPD outcome is crucial to avoid unnecessary toxicity in low risk infants. Admission radiographs of extremely preterm infants are routinely acquired within 24h of life and could serve as a non-invasive prognostic tool. In this work, we developed and investigated a deep learning approach using chest X-rays from 163 extremely low-birth-weight infants ($\leq$32 weeks gestation, 401-999g) obtained within 24 hours of birth. We fine-tuned a ResNet-50 pretrained specifically on adult chest radiographs, employing progressive layer freezing with discriminative learning rates to prevent overfitting and evaluated a CutMix augmentation and linear probing. For moderate/severe BPD outcome prediction, our best performing model with progressive freezing, linear probing and CutMix achieved an AUROC of 0.78 $\pm$ 0.10, balanced accuracy of 0.69 $\pm$ 0.10, and an F1-score of 0.67 $\pm$ 0.11. In-domain pre-training significantly outperformed ImageNet initialization (p = 0.031) which confirms domain-specific pretraining to be important for BPD outcome prediction. Routine IRDS grades showed limited prognostic value (AUROC 0.57 $\pm$ 0.11), confirming the need of learned markers. Our approach demonstrates that domain-specific pretraining enables accurate BPD prediction from routine day-1 radiographs. Through progressive freezing and linear probing, the method remains computationally feasible for site-level implementation and future federated learning deployments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.12269v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sybelle Goedicke-Fritz (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Michelle Bous (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Annika Engel (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany), Matthias Flotho (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany, Helmholtz Institute for Pharmaceutical Research Saarland), Pascal Hirsch (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany), Hannah Wittig (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Dino Milanovic (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany), Dominik Mohr (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Mathias Kaspar (Digital Medicine, University Hospital of Augsburg, Augsburg, Germany), Sogand Nemat (Department of Radiology, and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital of Saarland, Homburg, Germany), Dorothea Kerner (Department of Radiology, and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital of Saarland, Homburg, Germany), Arno B\&quot;ucker (Department of Radiology, and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital of Saarland, Homburg, Germany), Andreas Keller (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany, Helmholtz Institute for Pharmaceutical Research Saarland, Pharma Science Hub), Sascha Meyer (Clinical Centre Karlsruhe, Franz-Lust Clinic for Paediatrics, Karlsruhe, Germany), Michael Zemlin (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Philipp Flotho (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany, Helmholtz Institute for Pharmaceutical Research Saarland)</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedGA: A Fair Federated Learning Framework Based on the Gini Coefficient</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12983</link>
   <description>Fairness has emerged as one of the key challenges in federated learning. In horizontal federated settings, data heterogeneity often leads to substantial performance disparities across clients, raising concerns about equitable model behavior. To address this issue, we propose FedGA, a fairness-aware federated learning algorithm. We first employ the Gini coefficient to measure the performance disparity among clients. Based on this, we establish a relationship between the Gini coefficient $G$ and the update scale of the global model ${U_s}$, and use this relationship to adaptively determine the timing of fairness intervention. Subsequently, we dynamically adjust the aggregation weights according to the system's real-time fairness status, enabling the global model to better incorporate information from clients with relatively poor performance.We conduct extensive experiments on the Office-Caltech-10, CIFAR-10, and Synthetic datasets. The results show that FedGA effectively improves fairness metrics such as variance and the Gini coefficient, while maintaining strong overall performance, demonstrating the effectiveness of our approach.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.12983v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>ShanBin Liu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Can Large Language Models Predict Audio Effects Parameters from Natural Language?</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20770</link>
   <description>In music production, manipulating audio effects (Fx) parameters through natural language has the potential to reduce technical barriers for non-experts. We present LLM2Fx, a framework leveraging Large Language Models (LLMs) to predict Fx parameters directly from textual descriptions without requiring task-specific training or fine-tuning. Our approach address the text-to-effect parameter prediction (Text2Fx) task by mapping natural language descriptions to the corresponding Fx parameters for equalization and reverberation. We demonstrate that LLMs can generate Fx parameters in a zero-shot manner that elucidates the relationship between timbre semantics and audio effects in music production. To enhance performance, we introduce three types of in-context examples: audio Digital Signal Processing (DSP) features, DSP function code, and few-shot examples. Our results demonstrate that LLM-based Fx parameter generation outperforms previous optimization approaches, offering competitive performance in translating natural language descriptions to appropriate Fx settings. Furthermore, LLMs can serve as text-driven interfaces for audio production, paving the way for more intuitive and accessible music production tools.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.20770v2</guid>
   <category>cs.SD</category>
   <category>cs.MM</category>
   <category>eess.AS</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Seungheon Doh, Junghyun Koo, Marco A. Mart\'inez-Ram\'irez, Wei-Hsiang Liao, Juhan Nam, Yuki Mitsufuji</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Sporadic Federated Learning Approach in Quantum Environment to Tackle Quantum Noise</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12492</link>
   <description>Quantum Federated Learning (QFL) is an emerging paradigm that combines quantum computing and federated learning (FL) to enable decentralized model training while maintaining data privacy over quantum networks. However, quantum noise remains a significant barrier in QFL, since modern quantum devices experience heterogeneous noise levels due to variances in hardware quality and sensitivity to quantum decoherence, resulting in inadequate training performance. To address this issue, we propose SpoQFL, a novel QFL framework that leverages sporadic learning to mitigate quantum noise heterogeneity in distributed quantum systems. SpoQFL dynamically adjusts training strategies based on noise fluctuations, enhancing model robustness, convergence stability, and overall learning efficiency. Extensive experiments on real-world datasets demonstrate that SpoQFL significantly outperforms conventional QFL approaches, achieving superior training performance and more stable convergence.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.12492v1</guid>
   <category>quant-ph</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ratun Rahman, Atit Pokharel, Dinh C. Nguyen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Safeguarding Federated Learning-based Road Condition Classification</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12568</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) has emerged as a promising solution for privacy-preserving autonomous driving, specifically camera-based Road Condition Classification (RCC) systems, harnessing distributed sensing, computing, and communication resources on board vehicles without sharing sensitive image data. However, the collaborative nature of FL-RCC frameworks introduces new vulnerabilities: Targeted Label Flipping Attacks (TLFAs), in which malicious clients (vehicles) deliberately alter their training data labels to compromise the learned model inference performance. Such attacks can, e.g., cause a vehicle to mis-classify slippery, dangerous road conditions as pristine and exceed recommended speed. However, TLFAs for FL-based RCC systems are largely missing. We address this challenge with a threefold contribution: 1) we disclose the vulnerability of existing FL-RCC systems to TLFAs; 2) we introduce a novel label-distance-based metric to precisely quantify the safety risks posed by TLFAs; and 3) we propose FLARE, a defensive mechanism leveraging neuron-wise analysis of the output layer to mitigate TLFA effects. Extensive experiments across three RCC tasks, four evaluation metrics, six baselines, and three deep learning models demonstrate both the severity of TLFAs on FL-RCC systems and the effectiveness of FLARE in mitigating the attack impact.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.12568v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sheng Liu, Panos Papadimitratos</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Distributed Generative AI Approach for Heterogeneous Multi-Domain Environments under Data Sharing constraints</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12979</link>
   <description>Federated Learning has gained increasing attention for its ability to enable multiple nodes to collaboratively train machine learning models without sharing their raw data. At the same time, Generative AI -- particularly Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs) -- have achieved remarkable success across a wide range of domains, such as healthcare, security, and Image Generation. However, training generative models typically requires large datasets and significant computational resources, which are often unavailable in real-world settings. Acquiring such resources can be costly and inefficient, especially when many underutilized devices -- such as IoT devices and edge devices -- with varying capabilities remain idle. Moreover, obtaining large datasets is challenging due to privacy concerns and copyright restrictions, as most devices are unwilling to share their data. To address these challenges, we propose a novel approach for decentralized GAN training that enables the utilization of distributed data and underutilized, low-capability devices while not sharing data in its raw form. Our approach is designed to tackle key challenges in decentralized environments, combining KLD-weighted Clustered Federated Learning to address the issues of data heterogeneity and multi-domain datasets, with Heterogeneous U-Shaped split learning to tackle the challenge of device heterogeneity under strict data sharing constraints -- ensuring that no labels or raw data, whether real or synthetic, are ever shared between nodes. Experimental results shows that our approach demonstrates consistent and significant improvements across key performance metrics, where it achieves 1.1x -- 2.2x higher image generation scores, an average 10% boost in classification metrics (up to 50% in multi-domain non-IID settings), in much lower latency compared to several benchmarks. Find our code at https://github.com/youssefga28/HuSCF-GAN.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.12979v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Youssef Tawfilis, Hossam Amer, Minar El-Aasser, Tallal Elshabrawy</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Learning: A Survey on Privacy-Preserving Collaborative Intelligence</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17703</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) has emerged as a transformative paradigm in the field of distributed machine learning, enabling multiple clients such as mobile devices, edge nodes, or organizations to collaboratively train a shared global model without the need to centralize sensitive data. This decentralized approach addresses growing concerns around data privacy, security, and regulatory compliance, making it particularly attractive in domains such as healthcare, finance, and smart IoT systems. This survey provides a concise yet comprehensive overview of Federated Learning, beginning with its core architecture and communication protocol. We discuss the standard FL lifecycle, including local training, model aggregation, and global updates. A particular emphasis is placed on key technical challenges such as handling non-IID (non-independent and identically distributed) data, mitigating system and hardware heterogeneity, reducing communication overhead, and ensuring privacy through mechanisms like differential privacy and secure aggregation. Furthermore, we examine emerging trends in FL research, including personalized FL, cross-device versus cross-silo settings, and integration with other paradigms such as reinforcement learning and quantum computing. We also highlight real-world applications and summarize benchmark datasets and evaluation metrics commonly used in FL research. Finally, we outline open research problems and future directions to guide the development of scalable, efficient, and trustworthy FL systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.17703v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Nusrat Jahan, Ratun Rahman, Michel Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Site-Level Fine-Tuning with Progressive Layer Freezing: Towards Robust Prediction of Bronchopulmonary Dysplasia from Day-1 Chest Radiographs in Extremely Preterm Infants</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12269</link>
   <description>Bronchopulmonary dysplasia (BPD) is a chronic lung disease affecting 35% of extremely low birth weight infants. Defined by oxygen dependence at 36 weeks postmenstrual age, it causes lifelong respiratory complications. However, preventive interventions carry severe risks, including neurodevelopmental impairment, ventilator-induced lung injury, and systemic complications. Therefore, early BPD prognosis and prediction of BPD outcome is crucial to avoid unnecessary toxicity in low risk infants. Admission radiographs of extremely preterm infants are routinely acquired within 24h of life and could serve as a non-invasive prognostic tool. In this work, we developed and investigated a deep learning approach using chest X-rays from 163 extremely low-birth-weight infants ($\leq$32 weeks gestation, 401-999g) obtained within 24 hours of birth. We fine-tuned a ResNet-50 pretrained specifically on adult chest radiographs, employing progressive layer freezing with discriminative learning rates to prevent overfitting and evaluated a CutMix augmentation and linear probing. For moderate/severe BPD outcome prediction, our best performing model with progressive freezing, linear probing and CutMix achieved an AUROC of 0.78 $\pm$ 0.10, balanced accuracy of 0.69 $\pm$ 0.10, and an F1-score of 0.67 $\pm$ 0.11. In-domain pre-training significantly outperformed ImageNet initialization (p = 0.031) which confirms domain-specific pretraining to be important for BPD outcome prediction. Routine IRDS grades showed limited prognostic value (AUROC 0.57 $\pm$ 0.11), confirming the need of learned markers. Our approach demonstrates that domain-specific pretraining enables accurate BPD prediction from routine day-1 radiographs. Through progressive freezing and linear probing, the method remains computationally feasible for site-level implementation and future federated learning deployments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.12269v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sybelle Goedicke-Fritz (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Michelle Bous (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Annika Engel (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany), Matthias Flotho (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany, Helmholtz Institute for Pharmaceutical Research Saarland), Pascal Hirsch (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany), Hannah Wittig (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Dino Milanovic (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany), Dominik Mohr (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Mathias Kaspar (Digital Medicine, University Hospital of Augsburg, Augsburg, Germany), Sogand Nemat (Department of Radiology, and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital of Saarland, Homburg, Germany), Dorothea Kerner (Department of Radiology, and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital of Saarland, Homburg, Germany), Arno B\&quot;ucker (Department of Radiology, and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital of Saarland, Homburg, Germany), Andreas Keller (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany, Helmholtz Institute for Pharmaceutical Research Saarland, Pharma Science Hub), Sascha Meyer (Clinical Centre Karlsruhe, Franz-Lust Clinic for Paediatrics, Karlsruhe, Germany), Michael Zemlin (Department of General Pediatrics and Neonatology, Saarland University, Campus Homburg, Homburg/Saar, Germany), Philipp Flotho (Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland Informatics Campus, Saarland University, Saarbr\&quot;ucken, Germany, Helmholtz Institute for Pharmaceutical Research Saarland)</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Learning in Open- and Closed-Loop EMG Decoding: A Privacy and Performance Perspective</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12652</link>
   <description>Invasive and non-invasive neural interfaces hold promise as high-bandwidth input devices for next-generation technologies. However, neural signals inherently encode sensitive information about an individual's identity and health, making data sharing for decoder training a critical privacy challenge. Federated learning (FL), a distributed, privacy-preserving learning framework, presents a promising solution, but it remains unexplored in closed-loop adaptive neural interfaces. Here, we introduce FL-based neural decoding and systematically evaluate its performance and privacy using high-dimensional electromyography signals in both open- and closed-loop scenarios. In open-loop simulations, FL significantly outperformed local learning baselines, demonstrating its potential for high-performance, privacy-conscious neural decoding. In contrast, closed-loop user studies required adapting FL methods to accommodate single-user, real-time interactions, a scenario not supported by standard FL. This modification resulted in local learning decoders surpassing the adapted FL approach in closed-loop performance, yet local learning still carried higher privacy risks. Our findings highlight a critical performance-privacy tradeoff in real-time adaptive applications and indicate the need for FL methods specifically designed for co-adaptive, single-user applications.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.12652v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kai Malcolm, C\'esar Uribe, Momona Yamagami</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Multi-task retriever fine-tuning for domain-specific and efficient RAG</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04652</link>
   <description>Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) has become ubiquitous when deploying Large Language Models (LLMs), as it can address typical limitations such as generating hallucinated or outdated information. However, when building real-world RAG applications, practical issues arise. First, the retrieved information is generally domain-specific. Since it is computationally expensive to fine-tune LLMs, it is more feasible to fine-tune the retriever to improve the quality of the data included in the LLM input. Second, as more applications are deployed in the same real-world system, one cannot afford to deploy separate retrievers. Moreover, these RAG applications normally retrieve different kinds of data. Our solution is to instruction fine-tune a small retriever encoder on a variety of domain-specific tasks to allow us to deploy one encoder that can serve many use cases, thereby achieving low-cost, scalability, and speed. We show how this encoder generalizes to out-of-domain settings as well as to an unseen retrieval task on real-world enterprise use cases.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.04652v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Patrice B\'echard, Orlando Marquez Ayala</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>What Factors Affect LLMs and RLLMs in Financial Question Answering?</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08339</link>
   <description>Recently, the development of large language models (LLMs) and reasoning large language models (RLLMs) have gained considerable attention from many researchers. RLLMs enhance the reasoning capabilities of LLMs through Long Chain-of-Thought (Long CoT) processes, significantly improving the performance of LLMs in addressing complex problems. However, there are few works that systematically explore what methods can fully unlock the performance of LLMs and RLLMs within the financial domain. To investigate the impact of various methods on LLMs and RLLMs, we utilize five LLMs and three RLLMs to assess the effects of prompting methods, agentic frameworks, and multilingual alignment methods on financial question-answering tasks. Our research findings indicate: (1) Current prompting methods and agent frameworks enhance the performance of LLMs in financial question answering by simulating Long CoT; (2) RLLMs possess inherent Long CoT capabilities, which limits the effectiveness of conventional methods in further enhancing their performance; (3) Current advanced multilingual alignment methods primarily improve the multilingual performance of LLMs by extending the reasoning length, which yields minimal benefits for RLLMs. We hope that this study can serve as an important reference for LLMs and RLLMs in the field of financial question answering.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.08339v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Peng Wang, Xuesi Hu, Jiageng Wu, Yuntao Zou, Qiancheng Zhang, Dagang Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>ToDMA: Large Model-Driven Token-Domain Multiple Access for Semantic Communications</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10946</link>
   <description>Token communications (TokCom) is an emerging generative semantic communication concept that reduces transmission rates by using context and multimodal large language model (MLLM)-based token processing, with tokens serving as universal semantic units across modalities. In this paper, we propose a semantic multiple access scheme in the token domain, referred to as token domain multiple access (ToDMA), where a large number of devices share a token codebook and a modulation codebook for source and channel coding, respectively. Specifically, each transmitter first tokenizes its source signal and modulate each token to a codeword. At the receiver, compressed sensing is employed first to detect active tokens and the corresponding channel state information (CSI) from the superposed signals. Then, the source token sequences are reconstructed by clustering the token-associated CSI across multiple time slots. In case of token collisions, some active tokens cannot be assigned and some positions in the reconstructed token sequences are empty. We propose to use pre-trained MLLMs to leverage the context, predict masked tokens, and thus mitigate token collisions. Simulation results demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed ToDMA framework for both text and image transmission tasks, achieving significantly lower latency compared to context-unaware orthogonal communication schemes, while also delivering superior distortion and perceptual quality compared to state-of-the-art context-unaware non-orthogonal communication methods.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.10946v2</guid>
   <category>cs.IT</category>
   <category>eess.SP</category>
   <category>math.IT</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Li Qiao, Mahdi Boloursaz Mashhadi, Zhen Gao, Robert Schober, Deniz G\&quot;und\&quot;uz</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
