<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 04:15:01 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 04:15:01 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>TinyServe: Query-Aware Cache Selection for Efficient LLM Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12211</link>
   <description>Serving large language models (LLMs) efficiently remains challenging due to the high memory and latency overhead of key-value (KV) cache access during autoregressive decoding. We present \textbf{TinyServe}, a lightweight and extensible serving system for deploying tiny LLMs (e.g., TinyLLaMA, GPT2-345M) with support for structured KV sparsity, plugin-based token selection, and hardware-efficient attention kernels. Unlike prior simulation frameworks, TinyServe executes real-time decoding with configurable sparsity strategies and fine-grained instrumentation.
  To reduce decoding cost, we introduce a \textit{query-aware page selection} mechanism that leverages bounding-box metadata to estimate attention relevance between the query and KV cache blocks. This enables selective KV loading with minimal overhead and no model modifications. Our fused CUDA kernel integrates page scoring, sparse memory access, and masked attention in a single pass.
  Experiments show that TinyServe achieves up to \textbf{3.4x} speedup and over \textbf{2x} memory savings with negligible accuracy drop. Additional analysis of cache reuse, page hit rate, and multi-GPU scaling confirms its practicality as an efficient system-level design for LLM training and inference research on resource-constrained hardware.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.12211v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Dong Liu, Yanxuan Yu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Analysis and Optimization of Wireless Multimodal Federated Learning on Modal Heterogeneity</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12930</link>
   <description>Multimodal federated learning (MFL) is a distributed framework for training multimodal models without uploading local multimodal data of clients, thereby effectively protecting client privacy. However, multimodal data is commonly heterogeneous across diverse clients, where each client possesses only a subset of all modalities, renders conventional analysis results and optimization methods in unimodal federated learning inapplicable. In addition, fixed latency demand and limited communication bandwidth pose significant challenges for deploying MFL in wireless scenarios. To optimize the wireless MFL performance on modal heterogeneity, this paper proposes a joint client scheduling and bandwidth allocation (JCSBA) algorithm based on a decision-level fusion architecture with adding a unimodal loss function. Specifically, with the decision results, the unimodal loss functions are added to both the training objective and local update loss functions to accelerate multimodal convergence and improve unimodal performance. To characterize MFL performance, we derive a closed-form upper bound related to client and modality scheduling and minimize the derived bound under the latency, energy, and bandwidth constraints through JCSBA. Experimental results on multimodal datasets demonstrate that the JCSBA algorithm improves the multimodal accuracy and the unimodal accuracy by 4.06% and 2.73%, respectively, compared to conventional algorithms.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.12930v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xuefeng Han, Wen Chen, Jun Li, Ming Ding, Qingqing Wu, Kang Wei, Xiumei Deng, Yumeng Shao, Qiong Wu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Accelerating Privacy-Preserving Federated Learning in Large-Scale LEO Satellite Systems</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12222</link>
   <description>Large-scale low-Earth-orbit (LEO) satellite systems are increasingly valued for their ability to enable rapid and wide-area data exchange, thereby facilitating the collaborative training of artificial intelligence (AI) models across geographically distributed regions. Due to privacy concerns and regulatory constraints, raw data collected at remote clients cannot be centrally aggregated, posing a major obstacle to traditional AI training methods. Federated learning offers a privacy-preserving alternative by training local models on distributed devices and exchanging only model parameters. However, the dynamic topology and limited bandwidth of satellite systems will hinder timely parameter aggregation and distribution, resulting in prolonged training times. To address this challenge, we investigate the problem of scheduling federated learning over satellite networks and identify key bottlenecks that impact the overall duration of each training round. We propose a discrete temporal graph-based on-demand scheduling framework that dynamically allocates communication resources to accelerate federated learning. Simulation results demonstrate that the proposed approach achieves significant performance gains over traditional statistical multiplexing-based model exchange strategies, reducing overall round times by 14.20% to 41.48%. Moreover, the acceleration effect becomes more pronounced for larger models and higher numbers of clients, highlighting the scalability of the proposed approach.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.12222v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Binquan Guo, Junteng Cao, Marie Siew, Binbin Chen, Tony Q. S. Quek, Zhu Han</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Ratio1 -- AI meta-OS</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12223</link>
   <description>We propose the Ratio1 AI meta-operating system (meta-OS), a decentralized MLOps protocol that unifies AI model development, deployment, and inference across heterogeneous edge devices. Its key innovation is an integrated blockchain-based framework that transforms idle computing resources (laptops, smartphones, cloud VMs) into a trustless global supercomputer. The architecture includes novel components: a decentralized authentication layer (dAuth), an in-memory state database (CSTORE), a distributed storage system (R1FS), homomorphic encrypted federated learning (EDIL), decentralized container orchestration (Deeploy) and an oracle network (OracleSync), which collectively ensure secure, resilient execution of AI pipelines and other container based apps at scale. The protocol enforces a formal circular token-economic model combining Proof-of-Availability (PoA) and Proof-of-AI (PoAI) consensus. Compared to centralized heterogeneous cloud MLOps and existing decentralized compute platforms, which often lack integrated AI toolchains or trusted Ratio1 node operators (R1OP) mechanics, Ratio1's holistic design lowers barriers for AI deployment and improves cost-efficiency. We provide mathematical formulations of its secure licensing and reward protocols, and include descriptive information for the system architecture and protocol flow. We argue that our proposed fully functional ecosystem proposes and demonstrates significant improvements in accessibility, scalability, and security over existing alternatives.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.12223v1</guid>
   <category>cs.OS</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Andrei Damian, Petrica Butusina, Alessandro De Franceschi, Vitalii Toderian, Marius Grigoras, Cristian Bleotiu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Energy-Efficient Quantized Federated Learning for Resource-constrained IoT devices</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12814</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) has emerged as a promising paradigm for enabling collaborative machine learning while preserving data privacy, making it particularly suitable for Internet of Things (IoT) environments. However, resource-constrained IoT devices face significant challenges due to limited energy,unreliable communication channels, and the impracticality of assuming infinite blocklength transmission. This paper proposes a federated learning framework for IoT networks that integrates finite blocklength transmission, model quantization, and an error-aware aggregation mechanism to enhance energy efficiency and communication reliability. The framework also optimizes uplink transmission power to balance energy savings and model performance. Simulation results demonstrate that the proposed approach significantly reduces energy consumption by up to 75\% compared to a standard FL model, while maintaining robust model accuracy, making it a viable solution for FL in real-world IoT scenarios with constrained resources. This work paves the way for efficient and reliable FL implementations in practical IoT deployments. Index Terms: Federated learning, IoT, finite blocklength, quantization, energy efficiency.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.12814v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Wilfrid Sougrinoma Compaor\'e, Yaya Etiabi, El Mehdi Amhoud, Mohamad Assaad</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>InferLog: Accelerating LLM Inference for Online Log Parsing via ICL-oriented Prefix Caching</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08523</link>
   <description>Modern software systems generate massive volumes of runtime logs, necessitating efficient and accurate log parsing to enable critical downstream tasks such as anomaly detection and root cause analysis. Recently, large language models (LLMs) have achieved advanced accuracy on log parsing, but their deployment in production environments faces two major limitations: (1) the privacy risks associated with commercial LLMs, driving the adoption of local deployment, and (2) the stringent latency and throughput requirements imposed by high-volume log streams, which existing LLM-based parsers fail to meet. Although recent efforts have reduced the number of LLM queries, they overlook the high latency of the LLM invocations, where concurrent log parsing requests can cause serve performance degradation of LLM inference system.
  In this study, we present InferLog, the first LLM inference optimization method for online log parsing. Our key insight is that the inference efficiency emerges as the vital bottleneck in LLM-based online log parsing, rather than parsing accuracy. InferLog accelerates inference by designing (1) A Prefix-aware ICL Refinement policy to refine the examples and permutation of in-context learning to improve the prefix caching efficiency. (2) A rapid and task-specific configuration tuning pipeline based on meta-learning to find the optimal LLM scheduling-related configuration for dynamic log parsing workloads. The experimental results based on Loghub dataset and vLLM demonstrate that InferLog significantly outperforms existing inference optimization methods and markedly accelerates the state-of-the-art LLM-based log parser without compromising parsing accuracy.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.08523v3</guid>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yilun Wang, Pengfei Chen, Haiyu Huang, Zilong He, Gou Tan, Chuanfu Zhang, Jingkai He, Zibin Zheng</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LLM-as-a-Judge: Rapid Evaluation of Legal Document Recommendation for Retrieval-Augmented Generation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12382</link>
   <description>The evaluation bottleneck in recommendation systems has become particularly acute with the rise of Generative AI, where traditional metrics fall short of capturing nuanced quality dimensions that matter in specialized domains like legal research. Can we trust Large Language Models to serve as reliable judges of their own kind? This paper investigates LLM-as-a-Judge as a principled approach to evaluating Retrieval-Augmented Generation systems in legal contexts, where the stakes of recommendation quality are exceptionally high.
  We tackle two fundamental questions that determine practical viability: which inter-rater reliability metrics best capture the alignment between LLM and human assessments, and how do we conduct statistically sound comparisons between competing systems? Through systematic experimentation, we discover that traditional agreement metrics like Krippendorff's alpha can be misleading in the skewed distributions typical of AI system evaluations. Instead, Gwet's AC2 and rank correlation coefficients emerge as more robust indicators for judge selection, while the Wilcoxon Signed-Rank Test with Benjamini-Hochberg corrections provides the statistical rigor needed for reliable system comparisons.
  Our findings suggest a path toward scalable, cost-effective evaluation that maintains the precision demanded by legal applications, transforming what was once a human-intensive bottleneck into an automated, yet statistically principled, evaluation framework.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.12382v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Anu Pradhan, Alexandra Ortan, Apurv Verma, Madhavan Seshadri</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Neural Collapse-Inspired Multi-Label Federated Learning under Label-Distribution Skew</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12544</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) enables collaborative model training across distributed clients while preserving data privacy. However, the performance of deep learning often deteriorates in FL due to decentralized and heterogeneous data. This challenge is further amplified in multi-label scenarios, where data exhibit complex characteristics such as label co-occurrence, inter-label dependency, and discrepancies between local and global label relationships. While most existing FL research primarily focuses on single-label classification, many real-world applications, particularly in domains such as medical imaging, often involve multi-label settings. In this paper, we address this important yet underexplored scenario in FL, where clients hold multi-label data with skewed label distributions. Neural Collapse (NC) describes a geometric structure in the latent feature space where features of each class collapse to their class mean with vanishing intra-class variance, and the class means form a maximally separated configuration. Motivated by this theory, we propose a method to align feature distributions across clients and to learn high-quality, well-clustered representations. To make the NC-structure applicable to multi-label settings, where image-level features may contain multiple semantic concepts, we introduce a feature disentanglement module that extracts semantically specific features. The clustering of these disentangled class-wise features is guided by a predefined shared NC structure, which mitigates potential conflicts between client models due to diverse local data distributions. In addition, we design regularisation losses to encourage compact clustering in the latent feature space. Experiments conducted on four benchmark datasets across eight diverse settings demonstrate that our approach outperforms existing methods, validating its effectiveness in this challenging FL scenario.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.12544v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Can Peng, Yuyuan Liu, Yingyu Yang, Pramit Saha, Qianye Yang, J. Alison Noble</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Simulating Clinical AI Assistance using Multimodal LLMs: A Case Study in Diabetic Retinopathy</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13234</link>
   <description>Diabetic retinopathy (DR) is a leading cause of blindness worldwide, and AI systems can expand access to fundus photography screening. Current FDA-cleared systems primarily provide binary referral outputs, where this minimal output may limit clinical trust and utility. Yet, determining the most effective output format to enhance clinician-AI performance is an empirical challenge that is difficult to assess at scale. We evaluated multimodal large language models (MLLMs) for DR detection and their ability to simulate clinical AI assistance across different output types. Two models were tested on IDRiD and Messidor-2: GPT-4o, a general-purpose MLLM, and MedGemma, an open-source medical model. Experiments included: (1) baseline evaluation, (2) simulated AI assistance with synthetic predictions, and (3) actual AI-to-AI collaboration where GPT-4o incorporated MedGemma outputs. MedGemma outperformed GPT-4o at baseline, achieving higher sensitivity and AUROC, while GPT-4o showed near-perfect specificity but low sensitivity. Both models adjusted predictions based on simulated AI inputs, but GPT-4o's performance collapsed with incorrect ones, whereas MedGemma remained more stable. In actual collaboration, GPT-4o achieved strong results when guided by MedGemma's descriptive outputs, even without direct image access (AUROC up to 0.96). These findings suggest MLLMs may improve DR screening pipelines and serve as scalable simulators for studying clinical AI assistance across varying output configurations. Open, lightweight models such as MedGemma may be especially valuable in low-resource settings, while descriptive outputs could enhance explainability and clinician trust in clinical workflows.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.13234v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Nadim Barakat, William Lotter</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Accelerating Privacy-Preserving Federated Learning in Large-Scale LEO Satellite Systems</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12222</link>
   <description>Large-scale low-Earth-orbit (LEO) satellite systems are increasingly valued for their ability to enable rapid and wide-area data exchange, thereby facilitating the collaborative training of artificial intelligence (AI) models across geographically distributed regions. Due to privacy concerns and regulatory constraints, raw data collected at remote clients cannot be centrally aggregated, posing a major obstacle to traditional AI training methods. Federated learning offers a privacy-preserving alternative by training local models on distributed devices and exchanging only model parameters. However, the dynamic topology and limited bandwidth of satellite systems will hinder timely parameter aggregation and distribution, resulting in prolonged training times. To address this challenge, we investigate the problem of scheduling federated learning over satellite networks and identify key bottlenecks that impact the overall duration of each training round. We propose a discrete temporal graph-based on-demand scheduling framework that dynamically allocates communication resources to accelerate federated learning. Simulation results demonstrate that the proposed approach achieves significant performance gains over traditional statistical multiplexing-based model exchange strategies, reducing overall round times by 14.20% to 41.48%. Moreover, the acceleration effect becomes more pronounced for larger models and higher numbers of clients, highlighting the scalability of the proposed approach.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.12222v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Binquan Guo, Junteng Cao, Marie Siew, Binbin Chen, Tony Q. S. Quek, Zhu Han</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Enhancing Smart Farming Through Federated Learning: A Secure, Scalable, and Efficient Approach for AI-Driven Agriculture</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12363</link>
   <description>The agricultural sector is undergoing a transformation with the integration of advanced technologies, particularly in data-driven decision-making. This work proposes a federated learning framework for smart farming, aiming to develop a scalable, efficient, and secure solution for crop disease detection tailored to the environmental and operational conditions of Minnesota farms. By maintaining sensitive farm data locally and enabling collaborative model updates, our proposed framework seeks to achieve high accuracy in crop disease classification without compromising data privacy. We outline a methodology involving data collection from Minnesota farms, application of local deep learning algorithms, transfer learning, and a central aggregation server for model refinement, aiming to achieve improved accuracy in disease detection, good generalization across agricultural scenarios, lower costs in communication and training time, and earlier identification and intervention against diseases in future implementations. We outline a methodology and anticipated outcomes, setting the stage for empirical validation in subsequent studies. This work comes in a context where more and more demand for data-driven interpretations in agriculture has to be weighed with concerns about privacy from farms that are hesitant to share their operational data. This will be important to provide a secure and efficient disease detection method that can finally revolutionize smart farming systems and solve local agricultural problems with data confidentiality. In doing so, this paper bridges the gap between advanced machine learning techniques and the practical, privacy-sensitive needs of farmers in Minnesota and beyond, leveraging the benefits of federated learning.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.12363v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ritesh Janga, Rushit Dave</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>High-Energy Concentration for Federated Learning in Frequency Domain</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12630</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) presents significant potential for collaborative optimization without data sharing. Since synthetic data is sent to the server, leveraging the popular concept of dataset distillation, this FL framework protects real data privacy while alleviating data heterogeneity. However, such methods are still challenged by the redundant information and noise in entire spatial-domain designs, which inevitably increases the communication burden. In this paper, we propose a novel Frequency-Domain aware FL method with high-energy concentration (FedFD) to address this problem. Our FedFD is inspired by the discovery that the discrete cosine transform predominantly distributes energy to specific regions, referred to as high-energy concentration. The principle behind FedFD is that low-energy like high-frequency components usually contain redundant information and noise, thus filtering them helps reduce communication costs and optimize performance. Our FedFD is mathematically formulated to preserve the low-frequency components using a binary mask, facilitating an optimal solution through frequency-domain distribution alignment. In particular, real data-driven synthetic classification is imposed into the loss to enhance the quality of the low-frequency components. On five image and speech datasets, FedFD achieves superior performance than state-of-the-art methods while reducing communication costs. For example, on the CIFAR-10 dataset with Dirichlet coefficient $\alpha = 0.01$, FedFD achieves a minimum reduction of 37.78\% in the communication cost, while attaining a 10.88\% performance gain.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.12630v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Haozhi Shi, Weiying Xie, Hangyu Ye, Daixun Li, Jitao Ma, Leyuan Fang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Energy-Efficient Quantized Federated Learning for Resource-constrained IoT devices</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12814</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) has emerged as a promising paradigm for enabling collaborative machine learning while preserving data privacy, making it particularly suitable for Internet of Things (IoT) environments. However, resource-constrained IoT devices face significant challenges due to limited energy,unreliable communication channels, and the impracticality of assuming infinite blocklength transmission. This paper proposes a federated learning framework for IoT networks that integrates finite blocklength transmission, model quantization, and an error-aware aggregation mechanism to enhance energy efficiency and communication reliability. The framework also optimizes uplink transmission power to balance energy savings and model performance. Simulation results demonstrate that the proposed approach significantly reduces energy consumption by up to 75\% compared to a standard FL model, while maintaining robust model accuracy, making it a viable solution for FL in real-world IoT scenarios with constrained resources. This work paves the way for efficient and reliable FL implementations in practical IoT deployments. Index Terms: Federated learning, IoT, finite blocklength, quantization, energy efficiency.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.12814v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Wilfrid Sougrinoma Compaor\'e, Yaya Etiabi, El Mehdi Amhoud, Mohamad Assaad</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>BAPFL: Exploring Backdoor Attacks Against Prototype-based Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12964</link>
   <description>Prototype-based federated learning (PFL) has emerged as a promising paradigm to address data heterogeneity problems in federated learning, as it leverages mean feature vectors as prototypes to enhance model generalization. However, its robustness against backdoor attacks remains largely unexplored. In this paper, we identify that PFL is inherently resistant to existing backdoor attacks due to its unique prototype learning mechanism and local data heterogeneity. To further explore the security of PFL, we propose BAPFL, the first backdoor attack method specifically designed for PFL frameworks. BAPFL integrates a prototype poisoning strategy with a trigger optimization mechanism. The prototype poisoning strategy manipulates the trajectories of global prototypes to mislead the prototype training of benign clients, pushing their local prototypes of clean samples away from the prototypes of trigger-embedded samples. Meanwhile, the trigger optimization mechanism learns a unique and stealthy trigger for each potential target label, and guides the prototypes of trigger-embedded samples to align closely with the global prototype of the target label. Experimental results across multiple datasets and PFL variants demonstrate that BAPFL achieves a 35\%-75\% improvement in attack success rate compared to traditional backdoor attacks, while preserving main task accuracy. These results highlight the effectiveness, stealthiness, and adaptability of BAPFL in PFL.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.12964v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Honghong Zeng, Jiong Lou, Zhe Wang, Hefeng Zhou, Chentao Wu, Wei Zhao, Jie Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>On the Out-of-Distribution Backdoor Attack for Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13219</link>
   <description>Traditional backdoor attacks in federated learning (FL) operate within constrained attack scenarios, as they depend on visible triggers and require physical modifications to the target object, which limits their practicality. To address this limitation, we introduce a novel backdoor attack prototype for FL called the out-of-distribution (OOD) backdoor attack ($\mathtt{OBA}$), which uses OOD data as both poisoned samples and triggers simultaneously. Our approach significantly broadens the scope of backdoor attack scenarios in FL. To improve the stealthiness of $\mathtt{OBA}$, we propose $\mathtt{SoDa}$, which regularizes both the magnitude and direction of malicious local models during local training, aligning them closely with their benign versions to evade detection. Empirical results demonstrate that $\mathtt{OBA}$ effectively circumvents state-of-the-art defenses while maintaining high accuracy on the main task.
  To address this security vulnerability in the FL system, we introduce $\mathtt{BNGuard}$, a new server-side defense method tailored against $\mathtt{SoDa}$. $\mathtt{BNGuard}$ leverages the observation that OOD data causes significant deviations in the running statistics of batch normalization layers. This allows $\mathtt{BNGuard}$ to identify malicious model updates and exclude them from aggregation, thereby enhancing the backdoor robustness of FL. Extensive experiments across various settings show the effectiveness of $\mathtt{BNGuard}$ on defending against $\mathtt{SoDa}$. The code is available at https://github.com/JiiahaoXU/SoDa-BNGuard.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.13219v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jiahao Xu, Zikai Zhang, Rui Hu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Statistical Analysis of Deep Federated Learning for Intrinsically Low-dimensional Data</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.20659</link>
   <description>Despite significant research on the optimization aspects of federated learning, the exploration of generalization error, especially in the realm of heterogeneous federated learning, remains an area that has been insufficiently investigated, primarily limited to developments in the parametric regime. This paper delves into the generalization properties of deep federated regression within a two-stage sampling model. Our findings reveal that the intrinsic dimension, characterized by the entropic dimension, plays a pivotal role in determining the convergence rates for deep learners when appropriately chosen network sizes are employed. Specifically, when the true relationship between the response and explanatory variables is described by a $\beta$-H\&quot;older function and one has access to $n$ independent and identically distributed (i.i.d.) samples from $m$ participating clients, for participating clients, the error rate scales at most as $\Tilde{O}((mn)^{-2\beta/(2\beta + \bar{d}_{2\beta}(\lambda))})$, whereas for non-participating clients, it scales as $\Tilde{O}(\Delta \cdot m^{-2\beta/(2\beta + \bar{d}_{2\beta}(\lambda))} + (mn)^{-2\beta/(2\beta + \bar{d}_{2\beta}(\lambda))})$. Here $\bar{d}_{2\beta}(\lambda)$ denotes the corresponding $2\beta$-entropic dimension of $\lambda$, the marginal distribution of the explanatory variables. The dependence between the two stages of the sampling scheme is characterized by $\Delta$. Consequently, our findings not only explicitly incorporate the ``heterogeneity&quot; of the clients, but also highlight that the convergence rates of errors of deep federated learners are not contingent on the nominal high dimensionality of the data but rather on its intrinsic dimension.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.20659v2</guid>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>math.ST</category>
   <category>stat.TH</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Saptarshi Chakraborty, Peter L. Bartlett</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Pimba: A Processing-in-Memory Acceleration for Post-Transformer Large Language Model Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10178</link>
   <description>Transformers are the driving force behind today's Large Language Models (LLMs), serving as the foundation for their performance and versatility. Yet, their compute and memory costs grow with sequence length, posing scalability challenges for long-context inferencing. In response, the algorithm community is exploring alternative architectures, such as state space models (SSMs), linear attention, and recurrent neural networks (RNNs), which we refer to as post-transformers. This shift presents a key challenge: building a serving system that efficiently supports both transformer and post-transformer LLMs within a unified framework. To address this challenge, we analyze the performance characteristics of transformer and post-transformer LLMs. Despite their algorithmic differences, both are fundamentally limited by memory bandwidth under batched inference due to attention in transformers and state updates in post-transformers. Further analyses suggest two additional insights: (1) state update operations, unlike attention, incur high hardware cost, making per-bank PIM acceleration inefficient, and (2) different low-precision arithmetic methods offer varying accuracy-area tradeoffs, while we identify Microsoft's MX as the Pareto-optimal choice. Building on these insights, we design Pimba as an array of State-update Processing Units (SPUs), each shared between two banks to enable interleaved access to PIM. Each SPU includes a State-update Processing Engine (SPE) that comprises element-wise multipliers and adders using MX-based quantized arithmetic, enabling efficient execution of state update and attention operations. Our evaluation shows that, compared to LLM-optimized GPU and GPU+PIM systems, Pimba achieves up to 4.1x and 2.1x higher token generation throughput, respectively.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10178v3</guid>
   <category>cs.AR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Wonung Kim, Yubin Lee, Yoonsung Kim, Jinwoo Hwang, Seongryong Oh, Jiyong Jung, Aziz Huseynov, Woong Gyu Park, Chang Hyun Park, Divya Mahajan, Jongse Park</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Pimba: A Processing-in-Memory Acceleration for Post-Transformer Large Language Model Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10178</link>
   <description>Transformers are the driving force behind today's Large Language Models (LLMs), serving as the foundation for their performance and versatility. Yet, their compute and memory costs grow with sequence length, posing scalability challenges for long-context inferencing. In response, the algorithm community is exploring alternative architectures, such as state space models (SSMs), linear attention, and recurrent neural networks (RNNs), which we refer to as post-transformers. This shift presents a key challenge: building a serving system that efficiently supports both transformer and post-transformer LLMs within a unified framework. To address this challenge, we analyze the performance characteristics of transformer and post-transformer LLMs. Despite their algorithmic differences, both are fundamentally limited by memory bandwidth under batched inference due to attention in transformers and state updates in post-transformers. Further analyses suggest two additional insights: (1) state update operations, unlike attention, incur high hardware cost, making per-bank PIM acceleration inefficient, and (2) different low-precision arithmetic methods offer varying accuracy-area tradeoffs, while we identify Microsoft's MX as the Pareto-optimal choice. Building on these insights, we design Pimba as an array of State-update Processing Units (SPUs), each shared between two banks to enable interleaved access to PIM. Each SPU includes a State-update Processing Engine (SPE) that comprises element-wise multipliers and adders using MX-based quantized arithmetic, enabling efficient execution of state update and attention operations. Our evaluation shows that, compared to LLM-optimized GPU and GPU+PIM systems, Pimba achieves up to 4.1x and 2.1x higher token generation throughput, respectively.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.10178v3</guid>
   <category>cs.AR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Wonung Kim, Yubin Lee, Yoonsung Kim, Jinwoo Hwang, Seongryong Oh, Jiyong Jung, Aziz Huseynov, Woong Gyu Park, Chang Hyun Park, Divya Mahajan, Jongse Park</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Ratio1 -- AI meta-OS</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12223</link>
   <description>We propose the Ratio1 AI meta-operating system (meta-OS), a decentralized MLOps protocol that unifies AI model development, deployment, and inference across heterogeneous edge devices. Its key innovation is an integrated blockchain-based framework that transforms idle computing resources (laptops, smartphones, cloud VMs) into a trustless global supercomputer. The architecture includes novel components: a decentralized authentication layer (dAuth), an in-memory state database (CSTORE), a distributed storage system (R1FS), homomorphic encrypted federated learning (EDIL), decentralized container orchestration (Deeploy) and an oracle network (OracleSync), which collectively ensure secure, resilient execution of AI pipelines and other container based apps at scale. The protocol enforces a formal circular token-economic model combining Proof-of-Availability (PoA) and Proof-of-AI (PoAI) consensus. Compared to centralized heterogeneous cloud MLOps and existing decentralized compute platforms, which often lack integrated AI toolchains or trusted Ratio1 node operators (R1OP) mechanics, Ratio1's holistic design lowers barriers for AI deployment and improves cost-efficiency. We provide mathematical formulations of its secure licensing and reward protocols, and include descriptive information for the system architecture and protocol flow. We argue that our proposed fully functional ecosystem proposes and demonstrates significant improvements in accessibility, scalability, and security over existing alternatives.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.12223v1</guid>
   <category>cs.OS</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Andrei Damian, Petrica Butusina, Alessandro De Franceschi, Vitalii Toderian, Marius Grigoras, Cristian Bleotiu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>TrojanRobot: Physical-world Backdoor Attacks Against VLM-based Robotic Manipulation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11683</link>
   <description>Robotic manipulation in the physical world is increasingly empowered by \textit{large language models} (LLMs) and \textit{vision-language models} (VLMs), leveraging their understanding and perception capabilities. Recently, various attacks against such robotic policies have been proposed, with backdoor attacks drawing considerable attention for their high stealth and strong persistence capabilities. However, existing backdoor efforts are limited to simulators and suffer from physical-world realization. To address this, we propose \textit{TrojanRobot}, a highly stealthy and broadly effective robotic backdoor attack in the physical world. Specifically, we introduce a module-poisoning approach by embedding a backdoor module into the modular robotic policy, enabling backdoor control over the policy's visual perception module thereby backdooring the entire robotic policy. Our vanilla implementation leverages a backdoor-finetuned VLM to serve as the backdoor module. To enhance its generalization in physical environments, we propose a prime implementation, leveraging the LVLM-as-a-backdoor paradigm and developing three types of prime attacks, \ie, \textit{permutation}, \textit{stagnation}, and \textit{intentional} attacks, thus achieving finer-grained backdoors. Extensive experiments on the UR3e manipulator with 18 task instructions using robotic policies based on four VLMs demonstrate the broad effectiveness and physical-world stealth of TrojanRobot. Our attack's video demonstrations are available via a github link https://trojanrobot.github.io.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2411.11683v5</guid>
   <category>cs.RO</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xianlong Wang, Hewen Pan, Hangtao Zhang, Minghui Li, Shengshan Hu, Ziqi Zhou, Lulu Xue, Aishan Liu, Yunpeng Jiang, Leo Yu Zhang, Xiaohua Jia</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Simulating Clinical AI Assistance using Multimodal LLMs: A Case Study in Diabetic Retinopathy</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13234</link>
   <description>Diabetic retinopathy (DR) is a leading cause of blindness worldwide, and AI systems can expand access to fundus photography screening. Current FDA-cleared systems primarily provide binary referral outputs, where this minimal output may limit clinical trust and utility. Yet, determining the most effective output format to enhance clinician-AI performance is an empirical challenge that is difficult to assess at scale. We evaluated multimodal large language models (MLLMs) for DR detection and their ability to simulate clinical AI assistance across different output types. Two models were tested on IDRiD and Messidor-2: GPT-4o, a general-purpose MLLM, and MedGemma, an open-source medical model. Experiments included: (1) baseline evaluation, (2) simulated AI assistance with synthetic predictions, and (3) actual AI-to-AI collaboration where GPT-4o incorporated MedGemma outputs. MedGemma outperformed GPT-4o at baseline, achieving higher sensitivity and AUROC, while GPT-4o showed near-perfect specificity but low sensitivity. Both models adjusted predictions based on simulated AI inputs, but GPT-4o's performance collapsed with incorrect ones, whereas MedGemma remained more stable. In actual collaboration, GPT-4o achieved strong results when guided by MedGemma's descriptive outputs, even without direct image access (AUROC up to 0.96). These findings suggest MLLMs may improve DR screening pipelines and serve as scalable simulators for studying clinical AI assistance across varying output configurations. Open, lightweight models such as MedGemma may be especially valuable in low-resource settings, while descriptive outputs could enhance explainability and clinician trust in clinical workflows.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.13234v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Nadim Barakat, William Lotter</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Simulating Clinical AI Assistance using Multimodal LLMs: A Case Study in Diabetic Retinopathy</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13234</link>
   <description>Diabetic retinopathy (DR) is a leading cause of blindness worldwide, and AI systems can expand access to fundus photography screening. Current FDA-cleared systems primarily provide binary referral outputs, where this minimal output may limit clinical trust and utility. Yet, determining the most effective output format to enhance clinician-AI performance is an empirical challenge that is difficult to assess at scale. We evaluated multimodal large language models (MLLMs) for DR detection and their ability to simulate clinical AI assistance across different output types. Two models were tested on IDRiD and Messidor-2: GPT-4o, a general-purpose MLLM, and MedGemma, an open-source medical model. Experiments included: (1) baseline evaluation, (2) simulated AI assistance with synthetic predictions, and (3) actual AI-to-AI collaboration where GPT-4o incorporated MedGemma outputs. MedGemma outperformed GPT-4o at baseline, achieving higher sensitivity and AUROC, while GPT-4o showed near-perfect specificity but low sensitivity. Both models adjusted predictions based on simulated AI inputs, but GPT-4o's performance collapsed with incorrect ones, whereas MedGemma remained more stable. In actual collaboration, GPT-4o achieved strong results when guided by MedGemma's descriptive outputs, even without direct image access (AUROC up to 0.96). These findings suggest MLLMs may improve DR screening pipelines and serve as scalable simulators for studying clinical AI assistance across varying output configurations. Open, lightweight models such as MedGemma may be especially valuable in low-resource settings, while descriptive outputs could enhance explainability and clinician trust in clinical workflows.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.13234v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.HC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Nadim Barakat, William Lotter</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>TinyServe: Query-Aware Cache Selection for Efficient LLM Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12211</link>
   <description>Serving large language models (LLMs) efficiently remains challenging due to the high memory and latency overhead of key-value (KV) cache access during autoregressive decoding. We present \textbf{TinyServe}, a lightweight and extensible serving system for deploying tiny LLMs (e.g., TinyLLaMA, GPT2-345M) with support for structured KV sparsity, plugin-based token selection, and hardware-efficient attention kernels. Unlike prior simulation frameworks, TinyServe executes real-time decoding with configurable sparsity strategies and fine-grained instrumentation.
  To reduce decoding cost, we introduce a \textit{query-aware page selection} mechanism that leverages bounding-box metadata to estimate attention relevance between the query and KV cache blocks. This enables selective KV loading with minimal overhead and no model modifications. Our fused CUDA kernel integrates page scoring, sparse memory access, and masked attention in a single pass.
  Experiments show that TinyServe achieves up to \textbf{3.4x} speedup and over \textbf{2x} memory savings with negligible accuracy drop. Additional analysis of cache reuse, page hit rate, and multi-GPU scaling confirms its practicality as an efficient system-level design for LLM training and inference research on resource-constrained hardware.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.12211v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Dong Liu, Yanxuan Yu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Accelerating Privacy-Preserving Federated Learning in Large-Scale LEO Satellite Systems</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12222</link>
   <description>Large-scale low-Earth-orbit (LEO) satellite systems are increasingly valued for their ability to enable rapid and wide-area data exchange, thereby facilitating the collaborative training of artificial intelligence (AI) models across geographically distributed regions. Due to privacy concerns and regulatory constraints, raw data collected at remote clients cannot be centrally aggregated, posing a major obstacle to traditional AI training methods. Federated learning offers a privacy-preserving alternative by training local models on distributed devices and exchanging only model parameters. However, the dynamic topology and limited bandwidth of satellite systems will hinder timely parameter aggregation and distribution, resulting in prolonged training times. To address this challenge, we investigate the problem of scheduling federated learning over satellite networks and identify key bottlenecks that impact the overall duration of each training round. We propose a discrete temporal graph-based on-demand scheduling framework that dynamically allocates communication resources to accelerate federated learning. Simulation results demonstrate that the proposed approach achieves significant performance gains over traditional statistical multiplexing-based model exchange strategies, reducing overall round times by 14.20% to 41.48%. Moreover, the acceleration effect becomes more pronounced for larger models and higher numbers of clients, highlighting the scalability of the proposed approach.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.12222v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Binquan Guo, Junteng Cao, Marie Siew, Binbin Chen, Tony Q. S. Quek, Zhu Han</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Ratio1 -- AI meta-OS</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12223</link>
   <description>We propose the Ratio1 AI meta-operating system (meta-OS), a decentralized MLOps protocol that unifies AI model development, deployment, and inference across heterogeneous edge devices. Its key innovation is an integrated blockchain-based framework that transforms idle computing resources (laptops, smartphones, cloud VMs) into a trustless global supercomputer. The architecture includes novel components: a decentralized authentication layer (dAuth), an in-memory state database (CSTORE), a distributed storage system (R1FS), homomorphic encrypted federated learning (EDIL), decentralized container orchestration (Deeploy) and an oracle network (OracleSync), which collectively ensure secure, resilient execution of AI pipelines and other container based apps at scale. The protocol enforces a formal circular token-economic model combining Proof-of-Availability (PoA) and Proof-of-AI (PoAI) consensus. Compared to centralized heterogeneous cloud MLOps and existing decentralized compute platforms, which often lack integrated AI toolchains or trusted Ratio1 node operators (R1OP) mechanics, Ratio1's holistic design lowers barriers for AI deployment and improves cost-efficiency. We provide mathematical formulations of its secure licensing and reward protocols, and include descriptive information for the system architecture and protocol flow. We argue that our proposed fully functional ecosystem proposes and demonstrates significant improvements in accessibility, scalability, and security over existing alternatives.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.12223v1</guid>
   <category>cs.OS</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Andrei Damian, Petrica Butusina, Alessandro De Franceschi, Vitalii Toderian, Marius Grigoras, Cristian Bleotiu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Enhancing Smart Farming Through Federated Learning: A Secure, Scalable, and Efficient Approach for AI-Driven Agriculture</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12363</link>
   <description>The agricultural sector is undergoing a transformation with the integration of advanced technologies, particularly in data-driven decision-making. This work proposes a federated learning framework for smart farming, aiming to develop a scalable, efficient, and secure solution for crop disease detection tailored to the environmental and operational conditions of Minnesota farms. By maintaining sensitive farm data locally and enabling collaborative model updates, our proposed framework seeks to achieve high accuracy in crop disease classification without compromising data privacy. We outline a methodology involving data collection from Minnesota farms, application of local deep learning algorithms, transfer learning, and a central aggregation server for model refinement, aiming to achieve improved accuracy in disease detection, good generalization across agricultural scenarios, lower costs in communication and training time, and earlier identification and intervention against diseases in future implementations. We outline a methodology and anticipated outcomes, setting the stage for empirical validation in subsequent studies. This work comes in a context where more and more demand for data-driven interpretations in agriculture has to be weighed with concerns about privacy from farms that are hesitant to share their operational data. This will be important to provide a secure and efficient disease detection method that can finally revolutionize smart farming systems and solve local agricultural problems with data confidentiality. In doing so, this paper bridges the gap between advanced machine learning techniques and the practical, privacy-sensitive needs of farmers in Minnesota and beyond, leveraging the benefits of federated learning.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.12363v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ritesh Janga, Rushit Dave</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Cross-Training Learners for Robust Generalization under Data Heterogeneity</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20046</link>
   <description>Federated learning benefits from cross-training strategies, which enables models to train on data from distinct sources to improve generalization capability. However, due to inherent differences in data distributions, the optimization goals of local models remain misaligned, and this mismatch continues to manifest as feature space heterogeneity even after cross-training. We argue that knowledge distillation from the personalized view preserves client-specific characteristics and expands the local knowledge base, while distillation from the global view provides consistent semantic anchors that facilitate feature alignment across clients. To achieve this goal, this paper presents a cross-training scheme, termed FedCT, includes three main modules, where the consistency-aware knowledge broadcasting module aims to optimize model assignment strategies, which enhances collaborative advantages between clients and achieves an efficient federated learning process. The multi-view knowledge-guided representation learning module leverages fused prototypical knowledge from both global and local views to enhance the preservation of local knowledge before and after model exchange, as well as to ensure consistency between local and global knowledge. The mixup-based feature augmentation module aggregates rich information to further increase the diversity of feature spaces, which enables the model to better discriminate complex samples. Extensive experiments were conducted on four datasets in terms of performance comparison, ablation study, in-depth analysis and case study. The results demonstrated that FedCT alleviates knowledge forgetting from both local and global views, which enables it outperform state-of-the-art methods.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2405.20046v4</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhuang Qi, Lei Meng, Ruohan Zhang, Yu Wang, Xin Qi, Xiangxu Meng, Han Yu, Qiang Yang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Statistical Analysis of Deep Federated Learning for Intrinsically Low-dimensional Data</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.20659</link>
   <description>Despite significant research on the optimization aspects of federated learning, the exploration of generalization error, especially in the realm of heterogeneous federated learning, remains an area that has been insufficiently investigated, primarily limited to developments in the parametric regime. This paper delves into the generalization properties of deep federated regression within a two-stage sampling model. Our findings reveal that the intrinsic dimension, characterized by the entropic dimension, plays a pivotal role in determining the convergence rates for deep learners when appropriately chosen network sizes are employed. Specifically, when the true relationship between the response and explanatory variables is described by a $\beta$-H\&quot;older function and one has access to $n$ independent and identically distributed (i.i.d.) samples from $m$ participating clients, for participating clients, the error rate scales at most as $\Tilde{O}((mn)^{-2\beta/(2\beta + \bar{d}_{2\beta}(\lambda))})$, whereas for non-participating clients, it scales as $\Tilde{O}(\Delta \cdot m^{-2\beta/(2\beta + \bar{d}_{2\beta}(\lambda))} + (mn)^{-2\beta/(2\beta + \bar{d}_{2\beta}(\lambda))})$. Here $\bar{d}_{2\beta}(\lambda)$ denotes the corresponding $2\beta$-entropic dimension of $\lambda$, the marginal distribution of the explanatory variables. The dependence between the two stages of the sampling scheme is characterized by $\Delta$. Consequently, our findings not only explicitly incorporate the ``heterogeneity&quot; of the clients, but also highlight that the convergence rates of errors of deep federated learners are not contingent on the nominal high dimensionality of the data but rather on its intrinsic dimension.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.20659v2</guid>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>math.ST</category>
   <category>stat.TH</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Saptarshi Chakraborty, Peter L. Bartlett</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>TrojanRobot: Physical-world Backdoor Attacks Against VLM-based Robotic Manipulation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11683</link>
   <description>Robotic manipulation in the physical world is increasingly empowered by \textit{large language models} (LLMs) and \textit{vision-language models} (VLMs), leveraging their understanding and perception capabilities. Recently, various attacks against such robotic policies have been proposed, with backdoor attacks drawing considerable attention for their high stealth and strong persistence capabilities. However, existing backdoor efforts are limited to simulators and suffer from physical-world realization. To address this, we propose \textit{TrojanRobot}, a highly stealthy and broadly effective robotic backdoor attack in the physical world. Specifically, we introduce a module-poisoning approach by embedding a backdoor module into the modular robotic policy, enabling backdoor control over the policy's visual perception module thereby backdooring the entire robotic policy. Our vanilla implementation leverages a backdoor-finetuned VLM to serve as the backdoor module. To enhance its generalization in physical environments, we propose a prime implementation, leveraging the LVLM-as-a-backdoor paradigm and developing three types of prime attacks, \ie, \textit{permutation}, \textit{stagnation}, and \textit{intentional} attacks, thus achieving finer-grained backdoors. Extensive experiments on the UR3e manipulator with 18 task instructions using robotic policies based on four VLMs demonstrate the broad effectiveness and physical-world stealth of TrojanRobot. Our attack's video demonstrations are available via a github link https://trojanrobot.github.io.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2411.11683v5</guid>
   <category>cs.RO</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xianlong Wang, Hewen Pan, Hangtao Zhang, Minghui Li, Shengshan Hu, Ziqi Zhou, Lulu Xue, Aishan Liu, Yunpeng Jiang, Leo Yu Zhang, Xiaohua Jia</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Foundation Models in Harsh Wireless Environments: Prospects, Challenges, and Future Directions</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01957</link>
   <description>Foundation models (FMs) have shown remarkable capabilities in generalized intelligence, multimodal understanding, and adaptive learning across a wide range of domains. However, their deployment in harsh or austere environments -- characterized by intermittent connectivity, limited computation, noisy data, and dynamically changing network topologies -- remains an open challenge. Existing distributed learning methods such as federated learning (FL) struggle to adapt in such settings due to their reliance on stable infrastructure, synchronized updates, and resource-intensive training. In this work, we explore the potential of Federated Foundation Models (FFMs) as a promising paradigm to address these limitations. By integrating the scalability and generalization power of FMs with novel decentralized, communication-aware FL frameworks, we aim to enable robust, energy-efficient, and adaptive intelligence in extreme and adversarial conditions. We present a detailed breakdown of system-level constraints in harsh environments, and discuss the open research challenges in communication design, model robustness, and energy-efficient personalization for these unique settings.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2509.01957v2</guid>
   <category>cs.NI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Evan Chen, Seyyedali Hosseinalipour, Christopher G. Brinton, David J. Love</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
