<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 03:07:48 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 03:07:48 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>Using Reinforcement Learning to Train Large Language Models to Explain Human Decisions</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11614</link>
   <description>A central goal of cognitive modeling is to develop models that not only predict human behavior but also provide insight into the underlying cognitive mechanisms. While neural network models trained on large-scale behavioral data often achieve strong predictive performance, they typically fall short in offering interpretable explanations of the cognitive processes they capture. In this work, we explore the potential of pretrained large language models (LLMs) to serve as dual-purpose cognitive models--capable of both accurate prediction and interpretable explanation in natural language. Specifically, we employ reinforcement learning with outcome-based rewards to guide LLMs toward generating explicit reasoning traces for explaining human risky choices. Our findings demonstrate that this approach produces high-quality explanations alongside strong quantitative predictions of human decisions.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.11614v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jian-Qiao Zhu, Hanbo Xie, Dilip Arumugam, Robert C. Wilson, Thomas L. Griffiths</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>mCLM: A Function-Infused and Synthesis-Friendly Modular Chemical Language Model</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12565</link>
   <description>Despite their ability to understand chemical knowledge and accurately generate sequential representations, large language models (LLMs) remain limited in their capacity to propose novel molecules with drug-like properties. In addition, the molecules that LLMs propose can often be challenging to make in the lab. To more effectively enable the discovery of functional small molecules, LLMs need to learn a molecular language. However, LLMs are currently limited by encoding molecules from atoms. In this paper, we argue that just like tokenizing texts into (sub-)word tokens instead of characters, molecules should be decomposed and reassembled at the level of functional building blocks, i.e., parts of molecules that bring unique functions and serve as effective building blocks for real-world automated laboratory synthesis. This motivates us to propose mCLM, a modular Chemical-Language Model tokenizing molecules into building blocks and learning a bilingual language model of both natural language descriptions of functions and molecule building blocks. By reasoning on such functional building blocks, mCLM guarantees to generate efficiently synthesizable molecules thanks to recent progress in block-based chemistry, while also improving the functions of molecules in a principled manner. In experiments on 430 FDA-approved drugs, we find mCLM capable of significantly improving 5 out of 6 chemical functions critical to determining drug potentials. More importantly, mCLM can reason on multiple functions and improve the FDA-rejected drugs (``fallen angels'') over multiple iterations to greatly improve their shortcomings.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.12565v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>q-bio.QM</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Carl Edwards, Chi Han, Gawon Lee, Thao Nguyen, Bowen Jin, Chetan Kumar Prasad, Sara Szymku\'c, Bartosz A. Grzybowski, Ying Diao, Jiawei Han, Ge Liu, Hao Peng, Martin D. Burke, Heng Ji</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>RealMath: A Continuous Benchmark for Evaluating Language Models on Research-Level Mathematics</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12575</link>
   <description>Existing benchmarks for evaluating mathematical reasoning in large language models (LLMs) rely primarily on competition problems, formal proofs, or artificially challenging questions -- failing to capture the nature of mathematics encountered in actual research environments. We introduce RealMath, a novel benchmark derived directly from research papers and mathematical forums that assesses LLMs' abilities on authentic mathematical tasks. Our approach addresses three critical challenges: sourcing diverse research-level content, enabling reliable automated evaluation through verifiable statements, and designing a continually refreshable dataset to mitigate contamination risks. Experimental results across multiple LLMs reveal surprising capabilities in handling research mathematics compared to competition problems, suggesting current models may already serve as valuable assistants for working mathematicians despite limitations on highly challenging problems. The code and dataset for RealMath are publicly available.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.12575v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jie Zhang, Cezara Petrui, Kristina Nikoli\'c, Florian Tram\`er</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Tool-Aided Evolutionary LLM for Generative Policy Toward Efficient Resource Management in Wireless Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11570</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) enables distributed model training across edge devices in a privacy-friendly manner. However, its efficiency heavily depends on effective device selection and high-dimensional resource allocation in dynamic and heterogeneous wireless environments. Conventional methods demand a confluence of domain-specific expertise, extensive hyperparameter tuning, and/or heavy interaction cost. This paper proposes a Tool-aided Evolutionary Large Language Model (T-ELLM) framework to generate a qualified policy for device selection in a wireless FL environment. Unlike conventional optimization methods, T-ELLM leverages natural language-based scenario prompts to enhance generalization across varying network conditions. The framework decouples the joint optimization problem mathematically, enabling tractable learning of device selection policies while delegating resource allocation to convex optimization tools. To improve adaptability, T-ELLM integrates a sample-efficient, model-based virtual learning environment that captures the relationship between device selection and learning performance, facilitating subsequent group relative policy optimization. This concerted approach reduces reliance on real-world interactions, minimizing communication overhead while maintaining high-fidelity decision-making. Theoretical analysis proves that the discrepancy between virtual and real environments is bounded, ensuring the advantage function learned in the virtual environment maintains a provably small deviation from real-world conditions. Experimental results demonstrate that T-ELLM outperforms benchmark methods in energy efficiency and exhibits robust adaptability to environmental changes.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.11570v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chongyang Tan, Ruoqi Wen, Rongpeng Li, Zhifeng Zhao, Ekram Hossain, Honggang Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Attribution Projection Calculus: A Novel Framework for Causal Inference in Bayesian Networks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12094</link>
   <description>This paper introduces Attribution Projection Calculus (AP-Calculus), a novel mathematical framework for determining causal relationships in structured Bayesian networks. We investigate a specific network architecture with source nodes connected to destination nodes through intermediate nodes, where each input maps to a single label with maximum marginal probability. We prove that for each label, exactly one intermediate node acts as a deconfounder while others serve as confounders, enabling optimal attribution of features to their corresponding labels. The framework formalizes the dual nature of intermediate nodes as both confounders and deconfounders depending on the context, and establishes separation functions that maximize distinctions between intermediate representations. We demonstrate that the proposed network architecture is optimal for causal inference compared to alternative structures, including those based on Pearl's causal framework. AP-Calculus provides a comprehensive mathematical foundation for analyzing feature-label attributions, managing spurious correlations, quantifying information gain, ensuring fairness, and evaluating uncertainty in prediction models, including large language models. Theoretical verification shows that AP-Calculus not only extends but can also subsume traditional do-calculus for many practical applications, offering a more direct approach to causal inference in supervised learning contexts.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.12094v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.IT</category>
   <category>math.IT</category>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>M Ruhul Amin</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LightRetriever: A LLM-based Hybrid Retrieval Architecture with 1000x Faster Query Inference</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12260</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs)-based hybrid retrieval uses LLMs to encode queries and documents into low-dimensional dense or high-dimensional sparse vectors. It retrieves documents relevant to search queries based on vector similarities. Documents are pre-encoded offline, while queries arrive in real-time, necessitating an efficient online query encoder. Although LLMs significantly enhance retrieval capabilities, serving deeply parameterized LLMs slows down query inference throughput and increases demands for online deployment resources. In this paper, we propose LightRetriever, a novel LLM-based hybrid retriever with extremely lightweight query encoders. Our method retains a full-sized LLM for document encoding, but reduces the workload of query encoding to no more than an embedding lookup. Compared to serving a full-sized LLM on an H800 GPU, our approach achieves over a 1000x speedup for query inference with GPU acceleration, and even a 20x speedup without GPU. Experiments on large-scale retrieval benchmarks demonstrate that our method generalizes well across diverse retrieval tasks, retaining an average of 95% full-sized performance.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.12260v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Guangyuan Ma, Yongliang Ma, Xuanrui Gou, Zhenpeng Su, Ming Zhou, Songlin Hu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedSVD: Adaptive Orthogonalization for Private Federated Learning with LoRA</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12805</link>
   <description>Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA), which introduces a product of two trainable low-rank matrices into frozen pre-trained weights, is widely used for efficient fine-tuning of language models in federated learning (FL). However, when combined with differentially private stochastic gradient descent (DP-SGD), LoRA faces substantial noise amplification: DP-SGD perturbs per-sample gradients, and the matrix multiplication of the LoRA update ($BA$) intensifies this effect. Freezing one matrix (e.g., $A$) reduces the noise but restricts model expressiveness, often resulting in suboptimal adaptation. To address this, we propose FedSVD, a simple yet effective method that introduces a global reparameterization based on singular value decomposition (SVD). In our approach, each client optimizes only the $B$ matrix and transmits it to the server. The server aggregates the $B$ matrices, computes the product $BA$ using the previous $A$, and refactorizes the result via SVD. This yields a new adaptive $A$ composed of the orthonormal right singular vectors of $BA$, and an updated $B$ containing the remaining SVD components. This reparameterization avoids quadratic noise amplification, while allowing $A$ to better capture the principal directions of the aggregate updates. Moreover, the orthonormal structure of $A$ bounds the gradient norms of $B$ and preserves more signal under DP-SGD, as confirmed by our theoretical analysis. As a result, FedSVD consistently improves stability and performance across a variety of privacy settings and benchmarks, outperforming relevant baselines under both private and non-private regimes.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.12805v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Seanie Lee, Sangwoo Park, Dong Bok Lee, Dominik Wagner, Haebin Seong, Tobias Bocklet, Juho Lee, Sung Ju Hwang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FLTG: Byzantine-Robust Federated Learning via Angle-Based Defense and Non-IID-Aware Weighting</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12851</link>
   <description>Byzantine attacks during model aggregation in Federated Learning (FL) threaten training integrity by manipulating malicious clients' updates. Existing methods struggle with limited robustness under high malicious client ratios and sensitivity to non-i.i.d. data, leading to degraded accuracy. To address this, we propose FLTG, a novel aggregation algorithm integrating angle-based defense and dynamic reference selection. FLTG first filters clients via ReLU-clipped cosine similarity, leveraging a server-side clean dataset to exclude misaligned updates. It then dynamically selects a reference client based on the prior global model to mitigate non-i.i.d. bias, assigns aggregation weights inversely proportional to angular deviations, and normalizes update magnitudes to suppress malicious scaling. Evaluations across datasets of varying complexity under five classic attacks demonstrate FLTG's superiority over state-of-the-art methods under extreme bias scenarios and sustains robustness with a higher proportion(over 50%) of malicious clients.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.12851v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yanhua Wen, Lu Ai, Gang Liu, Chuang Li, Jianhao Wei</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Cross-Cloud Data Privacy Protection: Optimizing Collaborative Mechanisms of AI Systems by Integrating Federated Learning and LLMs</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13292</link>
   <description>In the age of cloud computing, data privacy protection has become a major challenge, especially when sharing sensitive data across cloud environments. However, how to optimize collaboration across cloud environments remains an unresolved problem. In this paper, we combine federated learning with large-scale language models to optimize the collaborative mechanism of AI systems. Based on the existing federated learning framework, we introduce a cross-cloud architecture in which federated learning works by aggregating model updates from decentralized nodes without exposing the original data. At the same time, combined with large-scale language models, its powerful context and semantic understanding capabilities are used to improve model training efficiency and decision-making ability. We've further innovated by introducing a secure communication layer to ensure the privacy and integrity of model updates and training data. The model enables continuous model adaptation and fine-tuning across different cloud environments while protecting sensitive data. Experimental results show that the proposed method is significantly better than the traditional federated learning model in terms of accuracy, convergence speed and data privacy protection.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.13292v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Huaiying Luo, Cheng Ji</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Kick Bad Guys Out! Conditionally Activated Anomaly Detection in Federated Learning with Zero-Knowledge Proof Verification</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.04055</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) systems are vulnerable to adversarial attacks, such as model poisoning and backdoor attacks. However, existing defense mechanisms often fall short in real-world settings due to key limitations: they may rely on impractical assumptions, introduce distortions by modifying aggregation functions, or degrade model performance even in benign scenarios. To address these issues, we propose a novel anomaly detection method designed specifically for practical FL scenarios. Our approach employs a two-stage, conditionally activated detection mechanism: cross-round check first detects whether suspicious activity has occurred, and, if warranted, a cross-client check filters out malicious participants. This mechanism preserves utility while avoiding unrealistic assumptions. Moreover, to ensure the transparency and integrity of the defense mechanism, we incorporate zero-knowledge proofs, enabling clients to verify the detection without relying solely on the server's goodwill. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first method to bridge the gap between theoretical advances in FL security and the demands of real-world deployment. Extensive experiments across diverse tasks and real-world edge devices demonstrate the effectiveness of our method over state-of-the-art defenses.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2310.04055v5</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shanshan Han, Wenxuan Wu, Baturalp Buyukates, Weizhao Jin, Qifan Zhang, Yuhang Yao, Salman Avestimehr, Chaoyang He</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Fair Concurrent Training of Multiple Models in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.13841</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) enables collaborative learning across multiple clients. In most FL work, all clients train a single learning task. However, the recent proliferation of FL applications may increasingly require multiple FL tasks to be trained simultaneously, sharing clients' computing and communication resources, which we call Multiple-Model Federated Learning (MMFL). Current MMFL algorithms use naive average-based client-task allocation schemes that can lead to unfair performance when FL tasks have heterogeneous difficulty levels, e.g., tasks with larger models may need more rounds and data to train. Just as naively allocating resources to generic computing jobs with heterogeneous resource needs can lead to unfair outcomes, naive allocation of clients to FL tasks can lead to unfairness, with some tasks having excessively long training times, or lower converged accuracies. Furthermore, in the FL setting, since clients are typically not paid for their training effort, we face a further challenge that some clients may not even be willing to train some tasks, e.g., due to high computational costs, which may exacerbate unfairness in training outcomes across tasks. We address both challenges by firstly designing FedFairMMFL, a difficulty-aware algorithm that dynamically allocates clients to tasks in each training round. We provide guarantees on airness and FedFairMMFL's convergence rate. We then propose a novel auction design that incentivizes clients to train multiple tasks, so as to fairly distribute clients' training efforts across the tasks. We show how our fairness-based learning and incentive mechanisms impact training convergence and finally evaluate our algorithm with multiple sets of learning tasks on real world datasets.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2404.13841v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Marie Siew, Haoran Zhang, Jong-Ik Park, Yuezhou Liu, Yichen Ruan, Lili Su, Stratis Ioannidis, Edmund Yeh, Carlee Joe-Wong</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>CodeGRAG: Bridging the Gap between Natural Language and Programming Language via Graphical Retrieval Augmented Generation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02355</link>
   <description>Utilizing large language models to generate codes has shown promising meaning in software development revolution. Despite the intelligence shown by the large language models, their specificity in code generation can still be improved due to the syntactic gap and mismatched vocabulary existing between natural language and programming languages. In this paper, we propose CodeGRAG, a Graphical Retrieval Augmented Code Generation framework that bridges the gap between NL and PL to enhance the performance of LLMs. CodeGRAG builds the graphical view of code blocks based on the control flow and data flow of them to better interpret the programming domain knowledge, which can facilitate natural language based LLMs for better understanding of code syntax and serve as a bridge among different programming languages. To take the extracted structural knowledge into the foundation models, we propose 1) a hard meta-graph prompt template to transform the challenging syntax graph into informative graphical view for tuning-free models and 2) a soft prompting technique that injects the domain knowledge of programming languages into model parameters via finetuning the models with the soft signals encoded by GNN expert model. Specifically, two constraints are designed to improve the alignment and structure expressiveness, contributing to the informativeness of the single-token-sized external &lt;GraphEmb&gt; for enhanced code generation. CodeGRAG significantly improves the code generation ability of LLMs and can even offer performance gain for cross-lingual code generation. Implementation is available at https://anonymous.4open.science/r/Code-5970/ .</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2405.02355v4</guid>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kounianhua Du, Jizheng Chen, Renting Rui, Huacan Chai, Lingyue Fu, Wei Xia, Yasheng Wang, Ruiming Tang, Yong Yu, Weinan Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>ClinicRealm: Re-evaluating Large Language Models with Conventional Machine Learning for Non-Generative Clinical Prediction Tasks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18525</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) are increasingly deployed in medicine. However, their utility in non-generative clinical prediction, often presumed inferior to specialized models, remains under-evaluated, leading to ongoing debate within the field and potential for misuse, misunderstanding, or over-reliance due to a lack of systematic benchmarking. Our ClinicRealm study addresses this by benchmarking 9 GPT-based LLMs, 5 BERT-based models, and 7 traditional methods on unstructured clinical notes and structured Electronic Health Records (EHR). Key findings reveal a significant shift: for clinical note predictions, leading LLMs (e.g., DeepSeek R1/V3, GPT o3-mini-high) in zero-shot settings now decisively outperform finetuned BERT models. On structured EHRs, while specialized models excel with ample data, advanced LLMs (e.g., GPT-4o, DeepSeek R1/V3) show potent zero-shot capabilities, often surpassing conventional models in data-scarce settings. Notably, leading open-source LLMs can match or exceed proprietary counterparts. These results establish modern LLMs as powerful non-generative clinical prediction tools, particularly with unstructured text and offering data-efficient structured data options, thus necessitating a re-evaluation of model selection strategies. This research should serve as an important insight for medical informaticists, AI developers, and clinical researchers, potentially prompting a reassessment of current assumptions and inspiring new approaches to LLM application in predictive healthcare.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2407.18525v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yinghao Zhu, Junyi Gao, Zixiang Wang, Weibin Liao, Xiaochen Zheng, Lifang Liang, Miguel O. Bernabeu, Yasha Wang, Lequan Yu, Chengwei Pan, Ewen M. Harrison, Liantao Ma</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>KunServe: Efficient Parameter-centric Memory Management for LLM Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18169</link>
   <description>Serving LLMs with a cluster of GPUs is common nowadays, where the serving system must meet strict latency SLOs required by applications. However, the stateful nature of LLM serving requires maintaining huge states (i.e., KVCache) in limited GPU memory. Under spikes in real-world workloads, GPU memory can be easily throttled, leading to orders of magnitude higher response latency due to queuing introduced by waiting for KVCache to be reclaimed. Prior KVCache-centric approaches handle load throttling by dropping, migrating, or swapping KVCache. These methods fail to release sufficient memory quickly with requests still queued.
  This paper proposes the first parameter-centric approach to handling throttling by selectively dropping replicated parameters to instantly free memory for requests, based on an unnoticed observation that model parameters are commonly replicated across GPUs for serving LLMs. With additional memory, all requests can be served with a larger batch without queuing. To make the parameter-centric approach correct and efficient, we cooperatively execute requests on GPUs with a complete copy of parameters using pipeline parallelism, and derive an appropriate drop plan without unnecessary cooperation. We also design techniques to minimize the performance overhead due to pipeline parallelism with the execution patterns of requests under drop. Evaluations show that {\sys} reduces the tail TTFT of requests under throttling by up to 72.2 times compared to the state-of-the-art systems including Llumnix, vLLM and InferCept.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18169v4</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Rongxin Cheng, Yuxin Lai, Xingda Wei, Rong Chen, Haibo Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>GeFL: Model-Agnostic Federated Learning with Generative Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18460</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) is a distributed training paradigm that enables collaborative learning across clients without sharing local data, thereby preserving privacy. However, the increasing scale and complexity of modern deep models often exceed the computational or memory capabilities of edge devices. Furthermore, clients may be constrained to use heterogeneous model architectures due to hardware variability (e.g., ASICs, FPGAs) or proprietary requirements that prevent the disclosure or modification of local model structures. These practical considerations motivate the need for model-heterogeneous FL, where clients participate using distinct model architectures. In this work, we propose Generative Model-Aided Federated Learning (GeFL), a framework that enables cross-client knowledge sharing via a generative model trained in a federated manner. This generative model captures global data semantics and facilitates local training without requiring model homogeneity across clients. While GeFL achieves strong performance, empirical analysis reveals limitations in scalability and potential privacy leakage due to generative sample memorization. To address these concerns, we propose GeFL-F, which utilizes feature-level generative modeling. This approach enhances scalability to large client populations and mitigates privacy risks. Extensive experiments across image classification tasks demonstrate that both GeFL and GeFL-F offer competitive performance in heterogeneous settings. Code is available at [1].</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18460v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Honggu Kang, Seohyeon Cha, Joonhyuk Kang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>AdaServe: Accelerating Multi-SLO LLM Serving with SLO-Customized Speculative Decoding</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12162</link>
   <description>Modern large language model (LLM) applications exhibit diverse service-level objectives (SLOs), from low-latency requirements in interactive coding assistants to more relaxed constraints in data wrangling tasks. Existing LLM serving systems, which rely on uniform batching and scheduling strategies, often fail to meet these heterogeneous SLOs concurrently. We present AdaServe, the first LLM serving system designed to support efficient multi-SLO serving through SLO-customized speculative decoding. AdaServe formulates multi-SLO serving as a constrained optimization problem and introduces a hardware-aware algorithm that constructs a speculation tree tailored to each request's latency target. It features a speculate-select-verify pipeline that enables fine-grained control over decoding speed while maximizing system throughput. AdaServe further adapts to workload variation by dynamically adjusting speculation parameters. Evaluations across diverse workloads show that AdaServe reduces SLO violations by up to 4.3$\times$ and improves goodput by up to 1.9$\times$ compared to the best performing baselines, highlighting its effectiveness in multi-SLO serving.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12162v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zikun Li, Zhuofu Chen, Remi Delacourt, Gabriele Oliaro, Zeyu Wang, Qinghan Chen, Shuhuai Lin, April Yang, Zhihao Zhang, Zhuoming Chen, Sean Lai, Xinhao Cheng, Xupeng Miao, Zhihao Jia</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Jailbreaking LLMs' Safeguard with Universal Magic Words for Text Embedding Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18280</link>
   <description>The security issue of large language models (LLMs) has gained wide attention recently, with various defense mechanisms developed to prevent harmful output, among which safeguards based on text embedding models serve as a fundamental defense. Through testing, we discover that the output distribution of text embedding models is severely biased with a large mean. Inspired by this observation, we propose novel, efficient methods to search for **universal magic words** that attack text embedding models. Universal magic words as suffixes can shift the embedding of any text towards the bias direction, thus manipulating the similarity of any text pair and misleading safeguards. Attackers can jailbreak the safeguards by appending magic words to user prompts and requiring LLMs to end answers with magic words. Experiments show that magic word attacks significantly degrade safeguard performance on JailbreakBench, cause real-world chatbots to produce harmful outputs in full-pipeline attacks, and generalize across input/output texts, models, and languages. To eradicate this security risk, we also propose defense methods against such attacks, which can correct the bias of text embeddings and improve downstream performance in a train-free manner.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.18280v3</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.NE</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Haoyu Liang, Youran Sun, Yunfeng Cai, Jun Zhu, Bo Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedRTS: Federated Robust Pruning via Combinatorial Thompson Sampling</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19122</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) enables collaborative model training across distributed clients without data sharing, but its high computational and communication demands strain resource-constrained devices. While existing methods use dynamic pruning to improve efficiency by periodically adjusting sparse model topologies while maintaining sparsity, these approaches suffer from issues such as greedy adjustments, unstable topologies, and communication inefficiency, resulting in less robust models and suboptimal performance under data heterogeneity and partial client availability. To address these challenges, we propose Federated Robust pruning via combinatorial Thompson Sampling (FedRTS), a novel framework designed to develop robust sparse models. FedRTS enhances robustness and performance through its Thompson Sampling-based Adjustment (TSAdj) mechanism, which uses probabilistic decisions informed by stable, farsighted information instead of deterministic decisions reliant on unstable and myopic information in previous methods. Extensive experiments demonstrate that FedRTS achieves state-of-the-art performance in computer vision and natural language processing tasks while reducing communication costs, particularly excelling in scenarios with heterogeneous data distributions and partial client participation. Our codes are available at: https://github.com/Little0o0/FedRTS</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.19122v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hong Huang, Hai Yang, Yuan Chen, Jiaxun Ye, Dapeng Wu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Gradient Correction in Federated Learning with Adaptive Optimization</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02727</link>
   <description>In federated learning (FL), model training performance is strongly impacted by data heterogeneity across clients. Client-drift compensation methods have recently emerged as a solution to this issue, introducing correction terms into local model updates. To date, these methods have only been considered under stochastic gradient descent (SGD)-based model training, while modern FL frameworks also employ adaptive optimizers (e.g., Adam) for improved convergence. However, due to the complex interplay between first and second moments found in most adaptive optimization methods, naively injecting correction terms can lead to performance degradation in heterogeneous settings. In this work, we propose {\tt FAdamGC}, the first algorithm to integrate drift compensation into adaptive federated optimization. The key idea of {\tt FAdamGC} is injecting a pre-estimation correction term that aligns with the moment structure of adaptive methods. We provide a rigorous convergence analysis of our algorithm under non-convex settings, showing that {\tt FAdamGC} results in better rate and milder assumptions than naively porting SGD-based correction algorithms into adaptive optimizers. Our experimental results demonstrate that {\tt FAdamGC} consistently outperform existing methods in total communication and computation cost across varying levels of data heterogeneity, showing the efficacy of correcting gradient information in federated adaptive optimization.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.02727v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Evan Chen, Shiqiang Wang, Jianing Zhang, Dong-Jun Han, Chaoyue Liu, Christopher Brinton</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>DPZV: Elevating the Tradeoff between Privacy and Utility in Zeroth-Order Vertical Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20565</link>
   <description>Vertical Federated Learning (VFL) enables collaborative training with feature-partitioned data, yet remains vulnerable to privacy leakage through gradient transmissions. Standard differential privacy (DP) techniques such as DP-SGD are difficult to apply in this setting due to VFL's distributed nature and the high variance incurred by vector-valued noise. On the other hand, zeroth-order (ZO) optimization techniques can avoid explicit gradient exposure but lack formal privacy guarantees. In this work, we propose DPZV, the first ZO optimization framework for VFL that achieves tunable DP with performance guarantees. DPZV overcomes these limitations by injecting low-variance scalar noise at the server, enabling controllable privacy with reduced memory overhead. We conduct a comprehensive theoretical analysis showing that DPZV matches the convergence rate of first-order optimization methods while satisfying formal ($\epsilon, \delta$)-DP guarantees. Experiments on image and language benchmarks demonstrate that DPZV outperforms several baselines in terms of accuracy under a wide range of privacy constraints ($\epsilon \le 10$), thereby elevating the privacy-utility tradeoff in VFL.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.20565v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jianing Zhang, Evan Chen, Chaoyue Liu, Christopher G. Brinton</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>dFLMoE: Decentralized Federated Learning via Mixture of Experts for Medical Data Analysis</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10412</link>
   <description>Federated learning has wide applications in the medical field. It enables knowledge sharing among different healthcare institutes while protecting patients' privacy. However, existing federated learning systems are typically centralized, requiring clients to upload client-specific knowledge to a central server for aggregation. This centralized approach would integrate the knowledge from each client into a centralized server, and the knowledge would be already undermined during the centralized integration before it reaches back to each client. Besides, the centralized approach also creates a dependency on the central server, which may affect training stability if the server malfunctions or connections are unstable. To address these issues, we propose a decentralized federated learning framework named dFLMoE. In our framework, clients directly exchange lightweight head models with each other. After exchanging, each client treats both local and received head models as individual experts, and utilizes a client-specific Mixture of Experts (MoE) approach to make collective decisions. This design not only reduces the knowledge damage with client-specific aggregations but also removes the dependency on the central server to enhance the robustness of the framework. We validate our framework on multiple medical tasks, demonstrating that our method evidently outperforms state-of-the-art approaches under both model homogeneity and heterogeneity settings.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.10412v4</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Luyuan Xie, Tianyu Luan, Wenyuan Cai, Guochen Yan, Zhaoyu Chen, Nan Xi, Yuejian Fang, Qingni Shen, Zhonghai Wu, Junsong Yuan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Low-hallucination Synthetic Captions for Large-Scale Vision-Language Model Pre-training</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13123</link>
   <description>In recent years, the field of vision-language model pre-training has experienced rapid advancements, driven primarily by the continuous enhancement of textual capabilities in large language models. However, existing training paradigms for multimodal large language models heavily rely on high-quality image-text pairs. As models and data scales grow exponentially, the availability of such meticulously curated data has become increasingly scarce and saturated, thereby severely limiting further advancements in this domain. This study investigates scalable caption generation techniques for vision-language model pre-training and demonstrates that large-scale low-hallucination synthetic captions can serve dual purposes: 1) acting as a viable alternative to real-world data for pre-training paradigms and 2) achieving superior performance enhancement when integrated into vision-language models through empirical validation. This paper presents following key contributions: 1) a novel pipeline for generating high-quality, low-hallucination, and knowledge-rich synthetic captions. Our continuous DPO methodology yields remarkable results in reducing hallucinations. Specifically, the non-hallucination caption rate on a held-out test set increases from 48.3% to 77.9% for a 7B-size model. 2) Comprehensive empirical validation reveals that our synthetic captions confer superior pre-training advantages over their counterparts. Across 15 vision language tasks, the model trained with our data achieves a significant performance gain of at least 6.2% compared to identical images with alt-text. In 20 common cognitive domains, the model trained with our data outperforms the alt-text data by at least 7.5%. Meanwhile, it also offers considerable support in the text-to-image domain. With our dataset, the FID score is reduced by 17.1 on a real-world validation benchmark and 13.3 on the MSCOCO validation benchmark.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.13123v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xinsong Zhang, Yarong Zeng, Xinting Huang, Hu Hu, Runquan Xie, Han Hu, Zhanhui Kang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>REI-Bench: Can Embodied Agents Understand Vague Human Instructions in Task Planning?</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10872</link>
   <description>Robot task planning decomposes human instructions into executable action sequences that enable robots to complete a series of complex tasks. Although recent large language model (LLM)-based task planners achieve amazing performance, they assume that human instructions are clear and straightforward. However, real-world users are not experts, and their instructions to robots often contain significant vagueness. Linguists suggest that such vagueness frequently arises from referring expressions (REs), whose meanings depend heavily on dialogue context and environment. This vagueness is even more prevalent among the elderly and children, who robots should serve more. This paper studies how such vagueness in REs within human instructions affects LLM-based robot task planning and how to overcome this issue. To this end, we propose the first robot task planning benchmark with vague REs (REI-Bench), where we discover that the vagueness of REs can severely degrade robot planning performance, leading to success rate drops of up to 77.9%. We also observe that most failure cases stem from missing objects in planners. To mitigate the REs issue, we propose a simple yet effective approach: task-oriented context cognition, which generates clear instructions for robots, achieving state-of-the-art performance compared to aware prompt and chains of thought. This work contributes to the research community of human-robot interaction (HRI) by making robot task planning more practical, particularly for non-expert users, e.g., the elderly and children.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.10872v2</guid>
   <category>cs.RO</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chenxi Jiang, Chuhao Zhou, Jianfei Yang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Tool-Aided Evolutionary LLM for Generative Policy Toward Efficient Resource Management in Wireless Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11570</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) enables distributed model training across edge devices in a privacy-friendly manner. However, its efficiency heavily depends on effective device selection and high-dimensional resource allocation in dynamic and heterogeneous wireless environments. Conventional methods demand a confluence of domain-specific expertise, extensive hyperparameter tuning, and/or heavy interaction cost. This paper proposes a Tool-aided Evolutionary Large Language Model (T-ELLM) framework to generate a qualified policy for device selection in a wireless FL environment. Unlike conventional optimization methods, T-ELLM leverages natural language-based scenario prompts to enhance generalization across varying network conditions. The framework decouples the joint optimization problem mathematically, enabling tractable learning of device selection policies while delegating resource allocation to convex optimization tools. To improve adaptability, T-ELLM integrates a sample-efficient, model-based virtual learning environment that captures the relationship between device selection and learning performance, facilitating subsequent group relative policy optimization. This concerted approach reduces reliance on real-world interactions, minimizing communication overhead while maintaining high-fidelity decision-making. Theoretical analysis proves that the discrepancy between virtual and real environments is bounded, ensuring the advantage function learned in the virtual environment maintains a provably small deviation from real-world conditions. Experimental results demonstrate that T-ELLM outperforms benchmark methods in energy efficiency and exhibits robust adaptability to environmental changes.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.11570v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chongyang Tan, Ruoqi Wen, Rongpeng Li, Zhifeng Zhao, Ekram Hossain, Honggang Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Joint Graph Estimation and Signal Restoration for Robust Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11648</link>
   <description>We propose a robust aggregation method for model parameters in federated learning (FL) under noisy communications. FL is a distributed machine learning paradigm in which a central server aggregates local model parameters from multiple clients. These parameters are often noisy and/or have missing values during data collection, training, and communication between the clients and server. This may cause a considerable drop in model accuracy. To address this issue, we learn a graph that represents pairwise relationships between model parameters of the clients during aggregation. We realize it with a joint problem of graph learning and signal (i.e., model parameters) restoration. The problem is formulated as a difference-of-convex (DC) optimization, which is efficiently solved via a proximal DC algorithm. Experimental results on MNIST and CIFAR-10 datasets show that the proposed method outperforms existing approaches by up to $2$--$5\%$ in classification accuracy under biased data distributions and noisy conditions.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.11648v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>eess.SP</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Tsutahiro Fukuhara, Junya Hara, Hiroshi Higashi, Yuichi Tanaka</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedHQ: Hybrid Runtime Quantization for Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11982</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) is a decentralized model training approach that preserves data privacy but struggles with low efficiency. Quantization, a powerful training optimization technique, has been widely explored for integration into FL. However, many studies fail to consider the distinct performance attribution between particular quantization strategies, such as post-training quantization (PTQ) or quantization-aware training (QAT). As a result, existing FL quantization methods rely solely on either PTQ or QAT, optimizing for speed or accuracy while compromising the other. To efficiently accelerate FL and maintain distributed convergence accuracy across various FL settings, this paper proposes a hybrid quantitation approach combining PTQ and QAT for FL systems. We conduct case studies to validate the effectiveness of using hybrid quantization in FL. To solve the difficulty of modeling speed and accuracy caused by device and data heterogeneity, we propose a hardware-related analysis and data-distribution-related analysis to help identify the trade-off boundaries for strategy selection. Based on these, we proposed a novel framework named FedHQ to automatically adopt optimal hybrid strategy allocation for FL systems. Specifically, FedHQ develops a coarse-grained global initialization and fine-grained ML-based adjustment to ensure efficiency and robustness. Experiments show that FedHQ achieves up to 2.47x times training acceleration and up to 11.15% accuracy improvement and negligible extra overhead.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.11982v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zihao Zheng (Eric), Ziyao Wang (Eric), Xiuping Cui (Eric), Maoliang Li (Eric), Jiayu Chen (Eric),  Yun (Eric),  Liang, Ang Li, Xiang Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Attribution Projection Calculus: A Novel Framework for Causal Inference in Bayesian Networks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12094</link>
   <description>This paper introduces Attribution Projection Calculus (AP-Calculus), a novel mathematical framework for determining causal relationships in structured Bayesian networks. We investigate a specific network architecture with source nodes connected to destination nodes through intermediate nodes, where each input maps to a single label with maximum marginal probability. We prove that for each label, exactly one intermediate node acts as a deconfounder while others serve as confounders, enabling optimal attribution of features to their corresponding labels. The framework formalizes the dual nature of intermediate nodes as both confounders and deconfounders depending on the context, and establishes separation functions that maximize distinctions between intermediate representations. We demonstrate that the proposed network architecture is optimal for causal inference compared to alternative structures, including those based on Pearl's causal framework. AP-Calculus provides a comprehensive mathematical foundation for analyzing feature-label attributions, managing spurious correlations, quantifying information gain, ensuring fairness, and evaluating uncertainty in prediction models, including large language models. Theoretical verification shows that AP-Calculus not only extends but can also subsume traditional do-calculus for many practical applications, offering a more direct approach to causal inference in supervised learning contexts.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.12094v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.IT</category>
   <category>math.IT</category>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>M Ruhul Amin</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>$\gamma$-FedHT: Stepsize-Aware Hard-Threshold Gradient Compression in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12479</link>
   <description>Gradient compression can effectively alleviate communication bottlenecks in Federated Learning (FL). Contemporary state-of-the-art sparse compressors, such as Top-$k$, exhibit high computational complexity, up to $\mathcal{O}(d\log_2{k})$, where $d$ is the number of model parameters. The hard-threshold compressor, which simply transmits elements with absolute values higher than a fixed threshold, is thus proposed to reduce the complexity to $\mathcal{O}(d)$. However, the hard-threshold compression causes accuracy degradation in FL, where the datasets are non-IID and the stepsize $\gamma$ is decreasing for model convergence. The decaying stepsize reduces the updates and causes the compression ratio of the hard-threshold compression to drop rapidly to an aggressive ratio. At or below this ratio, the model accuracy has been observed to degrade severely. To address this, we propose $\gamma$-FedHT, a stepsize-aware low-cost compressor with Error-Feedback to guarantee convergence. Given that the traditional theoretical framework of FL does not consider Error-Feedback, we introduce the fundamental conversation of Error-Feedback. We prove that $\gamma$-FedHT has the convergence rate of $\mathcal{O}(\frac{1}{T})$ ($T$ representing total training iterations) under $\mu$-strongly convex cases and $\mathcal{O}(\frac{1}{\sqrt{T}})$ under non-convex cases, \textit{same as FedAVG}. Extensive experiments demonstrate that $\gamma$-FedHT improves accuracy by up to $7.42\%$ over Top-$k$ under equal communication traffic on various non-IID image datasets.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.12479v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Rongwei Lu, Yutong Jiang, Jinrui Zhang, Chunyang Li, Yifei Zhu, Bin Chen, Zhi Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedSVD: Adaptive Orthogonalization for Private Federated Learning with LoRA</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12805</link>
   <description>Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA), which introduces a product of two trainable low-rank matrices into frozen pre-trained weights, is widely used for efficient fine-tuning of language models in federated learning (FL). However, when combined with differentially private stochastic gradient descent (DP-SGD), LoRA faces substantial noise amplification: DP-SGD perturbs per-sample gradients, and the matrix multiplication of the LoRA update ($BA$) intensifies this effect. Freezing one matrix (e.g., $A$) reduces the noise but restricts model expressiveness, often resulting in suboptimal adaptation. To address this, we propose FedSVD, a simple yet effective method that introduces a global reparameterization based on singular value decomposition (SVD). In our approach, each client optimizes only the $B$ matrix and transmits it to the server. The server aggregates the $B$ matrices, computes the product $BA$ using the previous $A$, and refactorizes the result via SVD. This yields a new adaptive $A$ composed of the orthonormal right singular vectors of $BA$, and an updated $B$ containing the remaining SVD components. This reparameterization avoids quadratic noise amplification, while allowing $A$ to better capture the principal directions of the aggregate updates. Moreover, the orthonormal structure of $A$ bounds the gradient norms of $B$ and preserves more signal under DP-SGD, as confirmed by our theoretical analysis. As a result, FedSVD consistently improves stability and performance across a variety of privacy settings and benchmarks, outperforming relevant baselines under both private and non-private regimes.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.12805v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Seanie Lee, Sangwoo Park, Dong Bok Lee, Dominik Wagner, Haebin Seong, Tobias Bocklet, Juho Lee, Sung Ju Hwang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>RIFLES: Resource-effIcient Federated LEarning via Scheduling</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13169</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) is a privacy-preserving machine learning technique that allows decentralized collaborative model training across a set of distributed clients, by avoiding raw data exchange. A fundamental component of FL is the selection of a subset of clients in each round for model training by a central server. Current selection strategies are myopic in nature in that they are based on past or current interactions, often leading to inefficiency issues such as straggling clients. In this paper, we address this serious shortcoming by proposing the RIFLES approach that builds a novel availability forecasting layer to support the client selection process. We make the following contributions: (i) we formalise the sequential selection problem and reduce it to a scheduling problem and show that the problem is NP-complete, (ii) leveraging heartbeat messages from clients, RIFLES build an availability prediction layer to support (long term) selection decisions, (iii) we propose a novel adaptive selection strategy to support efficient learning and resource usage. To circumvent the inherent exponential complexity, we present RIFLES, a heuristic that leverages clients' historical availability data by using a CNN-LSTM time series forecasting model, allowing the server to predict the optimal participation times of clients, thereby enabling informed selection decisions. By comparing against other FL techniques, we show that RIFLES provide significant improvement by between 10%-50% on a variety of metrics such as accuracy and test loss. To the best of our knowledge, it is the first work to investigate FL as a scheduling problem.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.13169v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sara Alosaime (University of Warwick), Arshad Jhumka (University of Leeds)</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Thinking Short and Right Over Thinking Long: Serving LLM Reasoning Efficiently and Accurately</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13326</link>
   <description>Recent advances in test-time scaling suggest that Large Language Models (LLMs) can gain better capabilities by generating Chain-of-Thought reasoning (analogous to human thinking) to respond a given request, and meanwhile exploring more reasoning branches (i.e., generating multiple responses and ensembling them) can improve the final output quality. However, when incorporating the two scaling dimensions, we find that the system efficiency is dampened significantly for two reasons. Firstly, the time cost to generate the final output increases substantially as many reasoning branches would be trapped in the over-thinking dilemma, producing excessively long responses. Secondly, generating multiple reasoning branches for each request increases memory consumption, which is unsuitable for LLM serving since we can only batch a limited number of requests to process simultaneously. To address this, we present SART, a serving framework for efficient and accurate LLM reasoning. The essential idea is to manage the thinking to be short and right, rather than long. For one thing, we devise a redundant sampling with early stopping approach based on empirical observations and theoretic analysis, which increases the likelihood of obtaining short-thinking responses when sampling reasoning branches. For another, we propose to dynamically prune low-quality branches so that only right-thinking branches are maintained, reducing the memory consumption and allowing us to batch more requests. Experimental results demonstrate that SART not only improves the accuracy of LLM reasoning but also enhances the serving efficiency, outperforming existing methods by up to 28.2 times and on average 15.7 times in terms of efficiency when achieving the same level of accuracy.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.13326v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yuhang Wang, Youhe Jiang, Bin Cui, Fangcheng Fu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Survey of Learning-Based Intrusion Detection Systems for In-Vehicle Network</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11551</link>
   <description>Connected and Autonomous Vehicles (CAVs) enhance mobility but face cybersecurity threats, particularly through the insecure Controller Area Network (CAN) bus. Cyberattacks can have devastating consequences in connected vehicles, including the loss of control over critical systems, necessitating robust security solutions. In-vehicle Intrusion Detection Systems (IDSs) offer a promising approach by detecting malicious activities in real time. This survey provides a comprehensive review of state-of-the-art research on learning-based in-vehicle IDSs, focusing on Machine Learning (ML), Deep Learning (DL), and Federated Learning (FL) approaches. Based on the reviewed studies, we critically examine existing IDS approaches, categorising them by the types of attacks they detect - known, unknown, and combined known-unknown attacks - while identifying their limitations. We also review the evaluation metrics used in research, emphasising the need to consider multiple criteria to meet the requirements of safety-critical systems. Additionally, we analyse FL-based IDSs and highlight their limitations. By doing so, this survey helps identify effective security measures, address existing limitations, and guide future research toward more resilient and adaptive protection mechanisms, ensuring the safety and reliability of CAVs.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.11551v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Muzun Althunayyan, Amir Javed, Omer Rana</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Incentivize Contribution and Learn Parameters Too: Federated Learning with Strategic Data Owners</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12010</link>
   <description>Classical federated learning (FL) assumes that the clients have a limited amount of noisy data with which they voluntarily participate and contribute towards learning a global, more accurate model in a principled manner. The learning happens in a distributed fashion without sharing the data with the center. However, these methods do not consider the incentive of an agent for participating and contributing to the process, given that data collection and running a distributed algorithm is costly for the clients. The question of rationality of contribution has been asked recently in the literature and some results exist that consider this problem. This paper addresses the question of simultaneous parameter learning and incentivizing contribution, which distinguishes it from the extant literature. Our first mechanism incentivizes each client to contribute to the FL process at a Nash equilibrium and simultaneously learn the model parameters. However, this equilibrium outcome can be away from the optimal, where clients contribute with their full data and the algorithm learns the optimal parameters. We propose a second mechanism with monetary transfers that is budget balanced and enables the full data contribution along with optimal parameter learning. Large scale experiments with real (federated) datasets (CIFAR-10, FeMNIST, and Twitter) show that these algorithms converge quite fast in practice, yield good welfare guarantees, and better model performance for all agents.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.12010v1</guid>
   <category>cs.GT</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.MA</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Drashthi Doshi, Aditya Vema Reddy Kesari, Swaprava Nath, Avishek Ghosh, Suhas S Kowshik</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FL-PLAS: Federated Learning with Partial Layer Aggregation for Backdoor Defense Against High-Ratio Malicious Clients</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12019</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) is gaining increasing attention as an emerging collaborative machine learning approach, particularly in the context of large-scale computing and data systems. However, the fundamental algorithm of FL, Federated Averaging (FedAvg), is susceptible to backdoor attacks. Although researchers have proposed numerous defense algorithms, two significant challenges remain. The attack is becoming more stealthy and harder to detect, and current defense methods are unable to handle 50\% or more malicious users or assume an auxiliary server dataset.
  To address these challenges, we propose a novel defense algorithm, FL-PLAS, \textbf{F}ederated \textbf{L}earning based on \textbf{P}artial\textbf{ L}ayer \textbf{A}ggregation \textbf{S}trategy. In particular, we divide the local model into a feature extractor and a classifier. In each iteration, the clients only upload the parameters of a feature extractor after local training. The server then aggregates these local parameters and returns the results to the clients.
  Each client retains its own classifier layer, ensuring that the backdoor labels do not impact other clients. We assess the effectiveness of FL-PLAS against state-of-the-art (SOTA) backdoor attacks on three image datasets and compare our approach to six defense strategies. The results of the experiment demonstrate that our methods can effectively protect local models from backdoor attacks. Without requiring any auxiliary dataset for the server, our method achieves a high main-task accuracy with a lower backdoor accuracy even under the condition of 90\% malicious users with the attacks of trigger, semantic and edge-case.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.12019v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jianyi Zhang, Ziyin Zhou, Yilong Li, Qichao Jin</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>mCLM: A Function-Infused and Synthesis-Friendly Modular Chemical Language Model</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12565</link>
   <description>Despite their ability to understand chemical knowledge and accurately generate sequential representations, large language models (LLMs) remain limited in their capacity to propose novel molecules with drug-like properties. In addition, the molecules that LLMs propose can often be challenging to make in the lab. To more effectively enable the discovery of functional small molecules, LLMs need to learn a molecular language. However, LLMs are currently limited by encoding molecules from atoms. In this paper, we argue that just like tokenizing texts into (sub-)word tokens instead of characters, molecules should be decomposed and reassembled at the level of functional building blocks, i.e., parts of molecules that bring unique functions and serve as effective building blocks for real-world automated laboratory synthesis. This motivates us to propose mCLM, a modular Chemical-Language Model tokenizing molecules into building blocks and learning a bilingual language model of both natural language descriptions of functions and molecule building blocks. By reasoning on such functional building blocks, mCLM guarantees to generate efficiently synthesizable molecules thanks to recent progress in block-based chemistry, while also improving the functions of molecules in a principled manner. In experiments on 430 FDA-approved drugs, we find mCLM capable of significantly improving 5 out of 6 chemical functions critical to determining drug potentials. More importantly, mCLM can reason on multiple functions and improve the FDA-rejected drugs (``fallen angels'') over multiple iterations to greatly improve their shortcomings.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.12565v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>q-bio.QM</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Carl Edwards, Chi Han, Gawon Lee, Thao Nguyen, Bowen Jin, Chetan Kumar Prasad, Sara Szymku\'c, Bartosz A. Grzybowski, Ying Diao, Jiawei Han, Ge Liu, Hao Peng, Martin D. Burke, Heng Ji</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>EcoLearn: Optimizing the Carbon Footprint of Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.17972</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) distributes machine learning (ML) training across edge devices to reduce data transfer overhead and protect data privacy. Since FL model training may span hundreds of devices and is thus resource- and energy-intensive, it has a significant carbon footprint. Importantly, since energy's carbon-intensity differs substantially (by up to 60$\times$) across locations, training on the same device using the same amount of energy, but at different locations, can incur widely different carbon emissions. While prior work has focused on improving FL's resource- and energy-efficiency by optimizing time-to-accuracy, it implicitly assumes all energy has the same carbon intensity and thus does not optimize carbon efficiency, i.e., work done per unit of carbon emitted.
  To address the problem, we design EcoLearn, which minimizes FL's carbon footprint without significantly affecting model accuracy or training time. EcoLearn achieves a favorable tradeoff by integrating carbon awareness into multiple aspects of FL training, including i) selecting clients with high data utility and low carbon, ii) provisioning more clients during the initial training rounds, and iii) mitigating stragglers by dynamically adjusting client over-provisioning based on carbon. We implement EcoLearn and its carbon-aware FL training policies in the Flower framework and show that it reduces the carbon footprint of training (by up to $10.8$$\times$) while maintaining model accuracy and training time (within $\sim$$1$\%) compared to state-of-the-art approaches.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2310.17972v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Talha Mehboob, Noman Bashir, Jesus Omana Iglesias, Michael Zink, David Irwin</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Fair Concurrent Training of Multiple Models in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.13841</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) enables collaborative learning across multiple clients. In most FL work, all clients train a single learning task. However, the recent proliferation of FL applications may increasingly require multiple FL tasks to be trained simultaneously, sharing clients' computing and communication resources, which we call Multiple-Model Federated Learning (MMFL). Current MMFL algorithms use naive average-based client-task allocation schemes that can lead to unfair performance when FL tasks have heterogeneous difficulty levels, e.g., tasks with larger models may need more rounds and data to train. Just as naively allocating resources to generic computing jobs with heterogeneous resource needs can lead to unfair outcomes, naive allocation of clients to FL tasks can lead to unfairness, with some tasks having excessively long training times, or lower converged accuracies. Furthermore, in the FL setting, since clients are typically not paid for their training effort, we face a further challenge that some clients may not even be willing to train some tasks, e.g., due to high computational costs, which may exacerbate unfairness in training outcomes across tasks. We address both challenges by firstly designing FedFairMMFL, a difficulty-aware algorithm that dynamically allocates clients to tasks in each training round. We provide guarantees on airness and FedFairMMFL's convergence rate. We then propose a novel auction design that incentivizes clients to train multiple tasks, so as to fairly distribute clients' training efforts across the tasks. We show how our fairness-based learning and incentive mechanisms impact training convergence and finally evaluate our algorithm with multiple sets of learning tasks on real world datasets.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2404.13841v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Marie Siew, Haoran Zhang, Jong-Ik Park, Yuezhou Liu, Yichen Ruan, Lili Su, Stratis Ioannidis, Edmund Yeh, Carlee Joe-Wong</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Securing Federated Learning against Backdoor Threats with Foundation Model Integration</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17573</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) enables decentralized model training while preserving privacy. Recently, the integration of Foundation Models (FMs) into FL has enhanced performance but introduced a novel backdoor attack mechanism. Attackers can exploit FM vulnerabilities to embed backdoors into synthetic data generated by FMs. During global model fusion, these backdoors are transferred to the global model through compromised synthetic data, subsequently infecting all client models. Existing FL backdoor defenses are ineffective against this novel attack due to its fundamentally different mechanism compared to classic ones. In this work, we propose a novel data-free defense strategy that addresses both classic and novel backdoor attacks in FL. The shared attack pattern lies in the abnormal activations within the hidden feature space during model aggregation. Hence, we propose to constrain internal activations to remain within reasonable ranges, effectively mitigating attacks while preserving model functionality. The activation constraints are optimized using synthetic data alongside FL training. Extensive experiments demonstrate its effectiveness against both novel and classic backdoor attacks, outperforming existing defenses.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.17573v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xiaohuan Bi, Xi Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Personalized Federated Fine-Tuning for LLMs via Data-Driven Heterogeneous Model Architectures</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19128</link>
   <description>Large-scale instruction data is essential for aligning pretrained Large Language Models (LLMs) with human instructions, but may contain sensitive information that hinders its public sharing. Federated Learning (FL) enables collaborative fine-tuning of LLMs without accessing raw data. However, existing approaches to federated LLM fine-tuning usually adopt a uniform model architecture, making it hard to fit highly heterogeneous client-side data in varying domains and formats. To address this, we propose FedAMoLE, a lightweight personalized FL framework that enables data-driven heterogeneous model architectures. This framework features a heterogeneous mixture of LoRA experts module for aggregating architecturally heterogeneous models and a reverse selection-based expert assignment strategy that optimizes model architectures based on data distributions. Experiments across five scenarios show that FedAMoLE improves client-side performance by an average of 5.14% compared to existing approaches while maintaining scalability.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2411.19128v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yicheng Zhang, Zhen Qin, Zhaomin Wu, Jian Hou, Shuiguang Deng</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>GeFL: Model-Agnostic Federated Learning with Generative Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18460</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) is a distributed training paradigm that enables collaborative learning across clients without sharing local data, thereby preserving privacy. However, the increasing scale and complexity of modern deep models often exceed the computational or memory capabilities of edge devices. Furthermore, clients may be constrained to use heterogeneous model architectures due to hardware variability (e.g., ASICs, FPGAs) or proprietary requirements that prevent the disclosure or modification of local model structures. These practical considerations motivate the need for model-heterogeneous FL, where clients participate using distinct model architectures. In this work, we propose Generative Model-Aided Federated Learning (GeFL), a framework that enables cross-client knowledge sharing via a generative model trained in a federated manner. This generative model captures global data semantics and facilitates local training without requiring model homogeneity across clients. While GeFL achieves strong performance, empirical analysis reveals limitations in scalability and potential privacy leakage due to generative sample memorization. To address these concerns, we propose GeFL-F, which utilizes feature-level generative modeling. This approach enhances scalability to large client populations and mitigates privacy risks. Extensive experiments across image classification tasks demonstrate that both GeFL and GeFL-F offer competitive performance in heterogeneous settings. Code is available at [1].</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18460v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Honggu Kang, Seohyeon Cha, Joonhyuk Kang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedRTS: Federated Robust Pruning via Combinatorial Thompson Sampling</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19122</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) enables collaborative model training across distributed clients without data sharing, but its high computational and communication demands strain resource-constrained devices. While existing methods use dynamic pruning to improve efficiency by periodically adjusting sparse model topologies while maintaining sparsity, these approaches suffer from issues such as greedy adjustments, unstable topologies, and communication inefficiency, resulting in less robust models and suboptimal performance under data heterogeneity and partial client availability. To address these challenges, we propose Federated Robust pruning via combinatorial Thompson Sampling (FedRTS), a novel framework designed to develop robust sparse models. FedRTS enhances robustness and performance through its Thompson Sampling-based Adjustment (TSAdj) mechanism, which uses probabilistic decisions informed by stable, farsighted information instead of deterministic decisions reliant on unstable and myopic information in previous methods. Extensive experiments demonstrate that FedRTS achieves state-of-the-art performance in computer vision and natural language processing tasks while reducing communication costs, particularly excelling in scenarios with heterogeneous data distributions and partial client participation. Our codes are available at: https://github.com/Little0o0/FedRTS</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.19122v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hong Huang, Hai Yang, Yuan Chen, Jiaxun Ye, Dapeng Wu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Gradient Correction in Federated Learning with Adaptive Optimization</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02727</link>
   <description>In federated learning (FL), model training performance is strongly impacted by data heterogeneity across clients. Client-drift compensation methods have recently emerged as a solution to this issue, introducing correction terms into local model updates. To date, these methods have only been considered under stochastic gradient descent (SGD)-based model training, while modern FL frameworks also employ adaptive optimizers (e.g., Adam) for improved convergence. However, due to the complex interplay between first and second moments found in most adaptive optimization methods, naively injecting correction terms can lead to performance degradation in heterogeneous settings. In this work, we propose {\tt FAdamGC}, the first algorithm to integrate drift compensation into adaptive federated optimization. The key idea of {\tt FAdamGC} is injecting a pre-estimation correction term that aligns with the moment structure of adaptive methods. We provide a rigorous convergence analysis of our algorithm under non-convex settings, showing that {\tt FAdamGC} results in better rate and milder assumptions than naively porting SGD-based correction algorithms into adaptive optimizers. Our experimental results demonstrate that {\tt FAdamGC} consistently outperform existing methods in total communication and computation cost across varying levels of data heterogeneity, showing the efficacy of correcting gradient information in federated adaptive optimization.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.02727v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Evan Chen, Shiqiang Wang, Jianing Zhang, Dong-Jun Han, Chaoyue Liu, Christopher Brinton</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>DPZV: Elevating the Tradeoff between Privacy and Utility in Zeroth-Order Vertical Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20565</link>
   <description>Vertical Federated Learning (VFL) enables collaborative training with feature-partitioned data, yet remains vulnerable to privacy leakage through gradient transmissions. Standard differential privacy (DP) techniques such as DP-SGD are difficult to apply in this setting due to VFL's distributed nature and the high variance incurred by vector-valued noise. On the other hand, zeroth-order (ZO) optimization techniques can avoid explicit gradient exposure but lack formal privacy guarantees. In this work, we propose DPZV, the first ZO optimization framework for VFL that achieves tunable DP with performance guarantees. DPZV overcomes these limitations by injecting low-variance scalar noise at the server, enabling controllable privacy with reduced memory overhead. We conduct a comprehensive theoretical analysis showing that DPZV matches the convergence rate of first-order optimization methods while satisfying formal ($\epsilon, \delta$)-DP guarantees. Experiments on image and language benchmarks demonstrate that DPZV outperforms several baselines in terms of accuracy under a wide range of privacy constraints ($\epsilon \le 10$), thereby elevating the privacy-utility tradeoff in VFL.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.20565v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jianing Zhang, Evan Chen, Chaoyue Liu, Christopher G. Brinton</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>dFLMoE: Decentralized Federated Learning via Mixture of Experts for Medical Data Analysis</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10412</link>
   <description>Federated learning has wide applications in the medical field. It enables knowledge sharing among different healthcare institutes while protecting patients' privacy. However, existing federated learning systems are typically centralized, requiring clients to upload client-specific knowledge to a central server for aggregation. This centralized approach would integrate the knowledge from each client into a centralized server, and the knowledge would be already undermined during the centralized integration before it reaches back to each client. Besides, the centralized approach also creates a dependency on the central server, which may affect training stability if the server malfunctions or connections are unstable. To address these issues, we propose a decentralized federated learning framework named dFLMoE. In our framework, clients directly exchange lightweight head models with each other. After exchanging, each client treats both local and received head models as individual experts, and utilizes a client-specific Mixture of Experts (MoE) approach to make collective decisions. This design not only reduces the knowledge damage with client-specific aggregations but also removes the dependency on the central server to enhance the robustness of the framework. We validate our framework on multiple medical tasks, demonstrating that our method evidently outperforms state-of-the-art approaches under both model homogeneity and heterogeneity settings.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.10412v4</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Luyuan Xie, Tianyu Luan, Wenyuan Cai, Guochen Yan, Zhaoyu Chen, Nan Xi, Yuejian Fang, Qingni Shen, Zhonghai Wu, Junsong Yuan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Self-Generated In-Context Examples Improve LLM Agents for Sequential Decision-Making Tasks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00234</link>
   <description>Improving Large Language Model (LLM) agents for sequential decision-making tasks typically requires extensive task-specific knowledge engineering--custom prompts, curated examples, and specialized observation/action spaces. We investigate a different approach where agents automatically improve by learning from their own successful experiences without human intervention. Our method constructs and refines a database of self-generated trajectories that serve as in-context examples for future tasks. Even naive accumulation of successful trajectories yields substantial performance gains across three diverse benchmarks: ALFWorld (73% to 89%), Wordcraft (55% to 64%), and InterCode-SQL (75% to 79%). These improvements exceed those achieved by upgrading from gpt-4o-mini to gpt-4o and match the performance of allowing multiple attempts per task. We further enhance this approach with two innovations: database-level curation using population-based training to propagate high-performing example collections, and exemplar-level curation that selectively retains trajectories based on their empirical utility as in-context examples. With these enhancements, our method achieves 93% success on ALFWorld--surpassing approaches that use more powerful LLMs and hand-crafted components. Our trajectory bootstrapping technique demonstrates that agents can autonomously improve through experience, offering a scalable alternative to labor-intensive knowledge engineering.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.00234v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Vishnu Sarukkai, Zhiqiang Xie, Kayvon Fatahalian</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Enhancing the Performance of Global Model by Improving the Adaptability of Local Models in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10125</link>
   <description>Federated learning enables the clients to collaboratively train a global model, which is aggregated from local models. Due to the heterogeneous data distributions over clients and data privacy in federated learning, it is difficult to train local models to achieve a well-performed global model. In this paper, we introduce the adaptability of local models, i.e., the average performance of local models on data distributions over clients, and enhance the performance of the global model by improving the adaptability of local models. Since each client does not know the data distributions over other clients, the adaptability of the local model cannot be directly optimized. First, we provide the property of an appropriate local model which has good adaptability on the data distributions over clients. Then, we formalize the property into the local training objective with a constraint and propose a feasible solution to train the local model. Extensive experiments on federated learning benchmarks demonstrate that our method significantly improves the adaptability of local models and achieves a well-performed global model that consistently outperforms the baseline methods.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.10125v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Wujun Zhou, Shu Ding, ZeLin Li, Wei Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>ClinicRealm: Re-evaluating Large Language Models with Conventional Machine Learning for Non-Generative Clinical Prediction Tasks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18525</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) are increasingly deployed in medicine. However, their utility in non-generative clinical prediction, often presumed inferior to specialized models, remains under-evaluated, leading to ongoing debate within the field and potential for misuse, misunderstanding, or over-reliance due to a lack of systematic benchmarking. Our ClinicRealm study addresses this by benchmarking 9 GPT-based LLMs, 5 BERT-based models, and 7 traditional methods on unstructured clinical notes and structured Electronic Health Records (EHR). Key findings reveal a significant shift: for clinical note predictions, leading LLMs (e.g., DeepSeek R1/V3, GPT o3-mini-high) in zero-shot settings now decisively outperform finetuned BERT models. On structured EHRs, while specialized models excel with ample data, advanced LLMs (e.g., GPT-4o, DeepSeek R1/V3) show potent zero-shot capabilities, often surpassing conventional models in data-scarce settings. Notably, leading open-source LLMs can match or exceed proprietary counterparts. These results establish modern LLMs as powerful non-generative clinical prediction tools, particularly with unstructured text and offering data-efficient structured data options, thus necessitating a re-evaluation of model selection strategies. This research should serve as an important insight for medical informaticists, AI developers, and clinical researchers, potentially prompting a reassessment of current assumptions and inspiring new approaches to LLM application in predictive healthcare.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2407.18525v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yinghao Zhu, Junyi Gao, Zixiang Wang, Weibin Liao, Xiaochen Zheng, Lifang Liang, Miguel O. Bernabeu, Yasha Wang, Lequan Yu, Chengwei Pan, Ewen M. Harrison, Liantao Ma</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>AdaServe: Accelerating Multi-SLO LLM Serving with SLO-Customized Speculative Decoding</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12162</link>
   <description>Modern large language model (LLM) applications exhibit diverse service-level objectives (SLOs), from low-latency requirements in interactive coding assistants to more relaxed constraints in data wrangling tasks. Existing LLM serving systems, which rely on uniform batching and scheduling strategies, often fail to meet these heterogeneous SLOs concurrently. We present AdaServe, the first LLM serving system designed to support efficient multi-SLO serving through SLO-customized speculative decoding. AdaServe formulates multi-SLO serving as a constrained optimization problem and introduces a hardware-aware algorithm that constructs a speculation tree tailored to each request's latency target. It features a speculate-select-verify pipeline that enables fine-grained control over decoding speed while maximizing system throughput. AdaServe further adapts to workload variation by dynamically adjusting speculation parameters. Evaluations across diverse workloads show that AdaServe reduces SLO violations by up to 4.3$\times$ and improves goodput by up to 1.9$\times$ compared to the best performing baselines, highlighting its effectiveness in multi-SLO serving.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12162v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zikun Li, Zhuofu Chen, Remi Delacourt, Gabriele Oliaro, Zeyu Wang, Qinghan Chen, Shuhuai Lin, April Yang, Zhihao Zhang, Zhuoming Chen, Sean Lai, Xinhao Cheng, Xupeng Miao, Zhihao Jia</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Jailbreaking LLMs' Safeguard with Universal Magic Words for Text Embedding Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18280</link>
   <description>The security issue of large language models (LLMs) has gained wide attention recently, with various defense mechanisms developed to prevent harmful output, among which safeguards based on text embedding models serve as a fundamental defense. Through testing, we discover that the output distribution of text embedding models is severely biased with a large mean. Inspired by this observation, we propose novel, efficient methods to search for **universal magic words** that attack text embedding models. Universal magic words as suffixes can shift the embedding of any text towards the bias direction, thus manipulating the similarity of any text pair and misleading safeguards. Attackers can jailbreak the safeguards by appending magic words to user prompts and requiring LLMs to end answers with magic words. Experiments show that magic word attacks significantly degrade safeguard performance on JailbreakBench, cause real-world chatbots to produce harmful outputs in full-pipeline attacks, and generalize across input/output texts, models, and languages. To eradicate this security risk, we also propose defense methods against such attacks, which can correct the bias of text embeddings and improve downstream performance in a train-free manner.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.18280v3</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.NE</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Haoyu Liang, Youran Sun, Yunfeng Cai, Jun Zhu, Bo Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Redefining non-IID Data in Federated Learning for Computer Vision Tasks: Migrating from Labels to Embeddings for Task-Specific Data Distributions</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14553</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) represents a paradigm shift in distributed machine learning (ML), enabling clients to train models collaboratively while keeping their raw data private. This paradigm shift from traditional centralized ML introduces challenges due to the non-iid (non-independent and identically distributed) nature of data across clients, significantly impacting FL's performance. Existing literature, predominantly model data heterogeneity by imposing label distribution skew across clients. In this paper, we show that label distribution skew fails to fully capture the real-world data heterogeneity among clients in computer vision tasks beyond classification. Subsequently, we demonstrate that current approaches overestimate FL's performance by relying on label/class distribution skew, exposing an overlooked gap in the literature. By utilizing pre-trained deep neural networks to extract task-specific data embeddings, we define task-specific data heterogeneity through the lens of each vision task and introduce a new level of data heterogeneity called embedding-based data heterogeneity. Our methodology involves clustering data points based on embeddings and distributing them among clients using the Dirichlet distribution. Through extensive experiments, we evaluate the performance of different FL methods under our revamped notion of data heterogeneity, introducing new benchmark performance measures to the literature. We further unveil a series of open research directions that can be pursued.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.14553v3</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kasra Borazjani, Payam Abdisarabshali, Naji Khosravan, Seyyedali Hosseinalipour</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>REI-Bench: Can Embodied Agents Understand Vague Human Instructions in Task Planning?</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10872</link>
   <description>Robot task planning decomposes human instructions into executable action sequences that enable robots to complete a series of complex tasks. Although recent large language model (LLM)-based task planners achieve amazing performance, they assume that human instructions are clear and straightforward. However, real-world users are not experts, and their instructions to robots often contain significant vagueness. Linguists suggest that such vagueness frequently arises from referring expressions (REs), whose meanings depend heavily on dialogue context and environment. This vagueness is even more prevalent among the elderly and children, who robots should serve more. This paper studies how such vagueness in REs within human instructions affects LLM-based robot task planning and how to overcome this issue. To this end, we propose the first robot task planning benchmark with vague REs (REI-Bench), where we discover that the vagueness of REs can severely degrade robot planning performance, leading to success rate drops of up to 77.9%. We also observe that most failure cases stem from missing objects in planners. To mitigate the REs issue, we propose a simple yet effective approach: task-oriented context cognition, which generates clear instructions for robots, achieving state-of-the-art performance compared to aware prompt and chains of thought. This work contributes to the research community of human-robot interaction (HRI) by making robot task planning more practical, particularly for non-expert users, e.g., the elderly and children.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.10872v2</guid>
   <category>cs.RO</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chenxi Jiang, Chuhao Zhou, Jianfei Yang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Attribution Projection Calculus: A Novel Framework for Causal Inference in Bayesian Networks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12094</link>
   <description>This paper introduces Attribution Projection Calculus (AP-Calculus), a novel mathematical framework for determining causal relationships in structured Bayesian networks. We investigate a specific network architecture with source nodes connected to destination nodes through intermediate nodes, where each input maps to a single label with maximum marginal probability. We prove that for each label, exactly one intermediate node acts as a deconfounder while others serve as confounders, enabling optimal attribution of features to their corresponding labels. The framework formalizes the dual nature of intermediate nodes as both confounders and deconfounders depending on the context, and establishes separation functions that maximize distinctions between intermediate representations. We demonstrate that the proposed network architecture is optimal for causal inference compared to alternative structures, including those based on Pearl's causal framework. AP-Calculus provides a comprehensive mathematical foundation for analyzing feature-label attributions, managing spurious correlations, quantifying information gain, ensuring fairness, and evaluating uncertainty in prediction models, including large language models. Theoretical verification shows that AP-Calculus not only extends but can also subsume traditional do-calculus for many practical applications, offering a more direct approach to causal inference in supervised learning contexts.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.12094v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.IT</category>
   <category>math.IT</category>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>M Ruhul Amin</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Jailbreaking LLMs' Safeguard with Universal Magic Words for Text Embedding Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18280</link>
   <description>The security issue of large language models (LLMs) has gained wide attention recently, with various defense mechanisms developed to prevent harmful output, among which safeguards based on text embedding models serve as a fundamental defense. Through testing, we discover that the output distribution of text embedding models is severely biased with a large mean. Inspired by this observation, we propose novel, efficient methods to search for **universal magic words** that attack text embedding models. Universal magic words as suffixes can shift the embedding of any text towards the bias direction, thus manipulating the similarity of any text pair and misleading safeguards. Attackers can jailbreak the safeguards by appending magic words to user prompts and requiring LLMs to end answers with magic words. Experiments show that magic word attacks significantly degrade safeguard performance on JailbreakBench, cause real-world chatbots to produce harmful outputs in full-pipeline attacks, and generalize across input/output texts, models, and languages. To eradicate this security risk, we also propose defense methods against such attacks, which can correct the bias of text embeddings and improve downstream performance in a train-free manner.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.18280v3</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.NE</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Haoyu Liang, Youran Sun, Yunfeng Cai, Jun Zhu, Bo Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>How Reliable is Multilingual LLM-as-a-Judge?</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12201</link>
   <description>LLM-as-a-Judge has emerged as a popular evaluation strategy, where advanced large language models assess generation results in alignment with human instructions. While these models serve as a promising alternative to human annotators, their reliability in multilingual evaluation remains uncertain. To bridge this gap, we conduct a comprehensive analysis of multilingual LLM-as-a-Judge. Specifically, we evaluate five models from different model families across five diverse tasks involving 25 languages. Our findings reveal that LLMs struggle to achieve consistent judgment results across languages, with an average Fleiss' Kappa of approximately 0.3, and some models performing even worse. To investigate the cause of inconsistency, we analyze various influencing factors. We observe that consistency varies significantly across languages, with particularly poor performance in low-resource languages. Additionally, we find that neither training on multilingual data nor increasing model scale directly improves judgment consistency. These findings suggest that LLMs are not yet reliable for evaluating multilingual predictions. We finally propose an ensemble strategy which improves the consistency of the multilingual judge in real-world applications.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.12201v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xiyan Fu, Wei Liu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Using Reinforcement Learning to Train Large Language Models to Explain Human Decisions</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11614</link>
   <description>A central goal of cognitive modeling is to develop models that not only predict human behavior but also provide insight into the underlying cognitive mechanisms. While neural network models trained on large-scale behavioral data often achieve strong predictive performance, they typically fall short in offering interpretable explanations of the cognitive processes they capture. In this work, we explore the potential of pretrained large language models (LLMs) to serve as dual-purpose cognitive models--capable of both accurate prediction and interpretable explanation in natural language. Specifically, we employ reinforcement learning with outcome-based rewards to guide LLMs toward generating explicit reasoning traces for explaining human risky choices. Our findings demonstrate that this approach produces high-quality explanations alongside strong quantitative predictions of human decisions.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.11614v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jian-Qiao Zhu, Hanbo Xie, Dilip Arumugam, Robert C. Wilson, Thomas L. Griffiths</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LightRetriever: A LLM-based Hybrid Retrieval Architecture with 1000x Faster Query Inference</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12260</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs)-based hybrid retrieval uses LLMs to encode queries and documents into low-dimensional dense or high-dimensional sparse vectors. It retrieves documents relevant to search queries based on vector similarities. Documents are pre-encoded offline, while queries arrive in real-time, necessitating an efficient online query encoder. Although LLMs significantly enhance retrieval capabilities, serving deeply parameterized LLMs slows down query inference throughput and increases demands for online deployment resources. In this paper, we propose LightRetriever, a novel LLM-based hybrid retriever with extremely lightweight query encoders. Our method retains a full-sized LLM for document encoding, but reduces the workload of query encoding to no more than an embedding lookup. Compared to serving a full-sized LLM on an H800 GPU, our approach achieves over a 1000x speedup for query inference with GPU acceleration, and even a 20x speedup without GPU. Experiments on large-scale retrieval benchmarks demonstrate that our method generalizes well across diverse retrieval tasks, retaining an average of 95% full-sized performance.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.12260v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Guangyuan Ma, Yongliang Ma, Xuanrui Gou, Zhenpeng Su, Ming Zhou, Songlin Hu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>mCLM: A Function-Infused and Synthesis-Friendly Modular Chemical Language Model</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12565</link>
   <description>Despite their ability to understand chemical knowledge and accurately generate sequential representations, large language models (LLMs) remain limited in their capacity to propose novel molecules with drug-like properties. In addition, the molecules that LLMs propose can often be challenging to make in the lab. To more effectively enable the discovery of functional small molecules, LLMs need to learn a molecular language. However, LLMs are currently limited by encoding molecules from atoms. In this paper, we argue that just like tokenizing texts into (sub-)word tokens instead of characters, molecules should be decomposed and reassembled at the level of functional building blocks, i.e., parts of molecules that bring unique functions and serve as effective building blocks for real-world automated laboratory synthesis. This motivates us to propose mCLM, a modular Chemical-Language Model tokenizing molecules into building blocks and learning a bilingual language model of both natural language descriptions of functions and molecule building blocks. By reasoning on such functional building blocks, mCLM guarantees to generate efficiently synthesizable molecules thanks to recent progress in block-based chemistry, while also improving the functions of molecules in a principled manner. In experiments on 430 FDA-approved drugs, we find mCLM capable of significantly improving 5 out of 6 chemical functions critical to determining drug potentials. More importantly, mCLM can reason on multiple functions and improve the FDA-rejected drugs (``fallen angels'') over multiple iterations to greatly improve their shortcomings.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.12565v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>q-bio.QM</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Carl Edwards, Chi Han, Gawon Lee, Thao Nguyen, Bowen Jin, Chetan Kumar Prasad, Sara Szymku\'c, Bartosz A. Grzybowski, Ying Diao, Jiawei Han, Ge Liu, Hao Peng, Martin D. Burke, Heng Ji</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>MMAR: A Challenging Benchmark for Deep Reasoning in Speech, Audio, Music, and Their Mix</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13032</link>
   <description>We introduce MMAR, a new benchmark designed to evaluate the deep reasoning capabilities of Audio-Language Models (ALMs) across massive multi-disciplinary tasks. MMAR comprises 1,000 meticulously curated audio-question-answer triplets, collected from real-world internet videos and refined through iterative error corrections and quality checks to ensure high quality. Unlike existing benchmarks that are limited to specific domains of sound, music, or speech, MMAR extends them to a broad spectrum of real-world audio scenarios, including mixed-modality combinations of sound, music, and speech. Each question in MMAR is hierarchically categorized across four reasoning layers: Signal, Perception, Semantic, and Cultural, with additional sub-categories within each layer to reflect task diversity and complexity. To further foster research in this area, we annotate every question with a Chain-of-Thought (CoT) rationale to promote future advancements in audio reasoning. Each item in the benchmark demands multi-step deep reasoning beyond surface-level understanding. Moreover, a part of the questions requires graduate-level perceptual and domain-specific knowledge, elevating the benchmark's difficulty and depth. We evaluate MMAR using a broad set of models, including Large Audio-Language Models (LALMs), Large Audio Reasoning Models (LARMs), Omni Language Models (OLMs), Large Language Models (LLMs), and Large Reasoning Models (LRMs), with audio caption inputs. The performance of these models on MMAR highlights the benchmark's challenging nature, and our analysis further reveals critical limitations of understanding and reasoning capabilities among current models. We hope MMAR will serve as a catalyst for future advances in this important but little-explored area.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.13032v1</guid>
   <category>cs.SD</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.MM</category>
   <category>eess.AS</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ziyang Ma, Yinghao Ma, Yanqiao Zhu, Chen Yang, Yi-Wen Chao, Ruiyang Xu, Wenxi Chen, Yuanzhe Chen, Zhuo Chen, Jian Cong, Kai Li, Keliang Li, Siyou Li, Xinfeng Li, Xiquan Li, Zheng Lian, Yuzhe Liang, Minghao Liu, Zhikang Niu, Tianrui Wang, Yuping Wang, Yuxuan Wang, Yihao Wu, Guanrou Yang, Jianwei Yu, Ruibin Yuan, Zhisheng Zheng, Ziya Zhou, Haina Zhu, Wei Xue, Emmanouil Benetos, Kai Yu, Eng-Siong Chng, Xie Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FormulaReasoning: A Dataset for Formula-Based Numerical Reasoning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.12692</link>
   <description>The application of formulas (e.g., physics formulas) is a fundamental ability of humans when solving numerical reasoning problems. Existing numerical reasoning datasets seldom explicitly indicate the formulas employed in reasoning, as their questions rely on implicit commonsense mathematical knowledge. In contrast, in this paper, we introduce FormulaReasoning, a new dataset specifically designed for formula-based numerical reasoning. Each of the 4,751 questions in our dataset requires numerical calculation with external physics formulas, making it a more challenging benchmark for evaluating large language models (LLMs). We offer normalized fine-grained annotations for the questions, available in English and Chinese, including formula structures, parameter names, symbols, numerical values, and units, derived from extensive manual effort with LLM assistance for guaranteed quality. We also provide a consolidated formula database to serve as an external knowledge base accompanying the dataset. We employ FormulaReasoning to evaluate LLMs with 7B to over 100B parameters, and explore retrieval-augmented generation with the formula database. Our evaluation also covers supervised methods that break down the reasoning process into formula generation, parameter extraction, and numerical calculation, as well as direct preference optimization methods based on derived preference data.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2402.12692v5</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xiao Li, Bolin Zhu, Kaiwen Shi, Sichen Liu, Yin Zhu, Yiwei Liu, Gong Cheng</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>ClinicRealm: Re-evaluating Large Language Models with Conventional Machine Learning for Non-Generative Clinical Prediction Tasks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18525</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) are increasingly deployed in medicine. However, their utility in non-generative clinical prediction, often presumed inferior to specialized models, remains under-evaluated, leading to ongoing debate within the field and potential for misuse, misunderstanding, or over-reliance due to a lack of systematic benchmarking. Our ClinicRealm study addresses this by benchmarking 9 GPT-based LLMs, 5 BERT-based models, and 7 traditional methods on unstructured clinical notes and structured Electronic Health Records (EHR). Key findings reveal a significant shift: for clinical note predictions, leading LLMs (e.g., DeepSeek R1/V3, GPT o3-mini-high) in zero-shot settings now decisively outperform finetuned BERT models. On structured EHRs, while specialized models excel with ample data, advanced LLMs (e.g., GPT-4o, DeepSeek R1/V3) show potent zero-shot capabilities, often surpassing conventional models in data-scarce settings. Notably, leading open-source LLMs can match or exceed proprietary counterparts. These results establish modern LLMs as powerful non-generative clinical prediction tools, particularly with unstructured text and offering data-efficient structured data options, thus necessitating a re-evaluation of model selection strategies. This research should serve as an important insight for medical informaticists, AI developers, and clinical researchers, potentially prompting a reassessment of current assumptions and inspiring new approaches to LLM application in predictive healthcare.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2407.18525v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yinghao Zhu, Junyi Gao, Zixiang Wang, Weibin Liao, Xiaochen Zheng, Lifang Liang, Miguel O. Bernabeu, Yasha Wang, Lequan Yu, Chengwei Pan, Ewen M. Harrison, Liantao Ma</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>AdaServe: Accelerating Multi-SLO LLM Serving with SLO-Customized Speculative Decoding</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12162</link>
   <description>Modern large language model (LLM) applications exhibit diverse service-level objectives (SLOs), from low-latency requirements in interactive coding assistants to more relaxed constraints in data wrangling tasks. Existing LLM serving systems, which rely on uniform batching and scheduling strategies, often fail to meet these heterogeneous SLOs concurrently. We present AdaServe, the first LLM serving system designed to support efficient multi-SLO serving through SLO-customized speculative decoding. AdaServe formulates multi-SLO serving as a constrained optimization problem and introduces a hardware-aware algorithm that constructs a speculation tree tailored to each request's latency target. It features a speculate-select-verify pipeline that enables fine-grained control over decoding speed while maximizing system throughput. AdaServe further adapts to workload variation by dynamically adjusting speculation parameters. Evaluations across diverse workloads show that AdaServe reduces SLO violations by up to 4.3$\times$ and improves goodput by up to 1.9$\times$ compared to the best performing baselines, highlighting its effectiveness in multi-SLO serving.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12162v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zikun Li, Zhuofu Chen, Remi Delacourt, Gabriele Oliaro, Zeyu Wang, Qinghan Chen, Shuhuai Lin, April Yang, Zhihao Zhang, Zhuoming Chen, Sean Lai, Xinhao Cheng, Xupeng Miao, Zhihao Jia</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Jailbreaking LLMs' Safeguard with Universal Magic Words for Text Embedding Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18280</link>
   <description>The security issue of large language models (LLMs) has gained wide attention recently, with various defense mechanisms developed to prevent harmful output, among which safeguards based on text embedding models serve as a fundamental defense. Through testing, we discover that the output distribution of text embedding models is severely biased with a large mean. Inspired by this observation, we propose novel, efficient methods to search for **universal magic words** that attack text embedding models. Universal magic words as suffixes can shift the embedding of any text towards the bias direction, thus manipulating the similarity of any text pair and misleading safeguards. Attackers can jailbreak the safeguards by appending magic words to user prompts and requiring LLMs to end answers with magic words. Experiments show that magic word attacks significantly degrade safeguard performance on JailbreakBench, cause real-world chatbots to produce harmful outputs in full-pipeline attacks, and generalize across input/output texts, models, and languages. To eradicate this security risk, we also propose defense methods against such attacks, which can correct the bias of text embeddings and improve downstream performance in a train-free manner.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.18280v3</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.NE</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Haoyu Liang, Youran Sun, Yunfeng Cai, Jun Zhu, Bo Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Self-Generated In-Context Examples Improve LLM Agents for Sequential Decision-Making Tasks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00234</link>
   <description>Improving Large Language Model (LLM) agents for sequential decision-making tasks typically requires extensive task-specific knowledge engineering--custom prompts, curated examples, and specialized observation/action spaces. We investigate a different approach where agents automatically improve by learning from their own successful experiences without human intervention. Our method constructs and refines a database of self-generated trajectories that serve as in-context examples for future tasks. Even naive accumulation of successful trajectories yields substantial performance gains across three diverse benchmarks: ALFWorld (73% to 89%), Wordcraft (55% to 64%), and InterCode-SQL (75% to 79%). These improvements exceed those achieved by upgrading from gpt-4o-mini to gpt-4o and match the performance of allowing multiple attempts per task. We further enhance this approach with two innovations: database-level curation using population-based training to propagate high-performing example collections, and exemplar-level curation that selectively retains trajectories based on their empirical utility as in-context examples. With these enhancements, our method achieves 93% success on ALFWorld--surpassing approaches that use more powerful LLMs and hand-crafted components. Our trajectory bootstrapping technique demonstrates that agents can autonomously improve through experience, offering a scalable alternative to labor-intensive knowledge engineering.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.00234v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Vishnu Sarukkai, Zhiqiang Xie, Kayvon Fatahalian</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>REI-Bench: Can Embodied Agents Understand Vague Human Instructions in Task Planning?</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10872</link>
   <description>Robot task planning decomposes human instructions into executable action sequences that enable robots to complete a series of complex tasks. Although recent large language model (LLM)-based task planners achieve amazing performance, they assume that human instructions are clear and straightforward. However, real-world users are not experts, and their instructions to robots often contain significant vagueness. Linguists suggest that such vagueness frequently arises from referring expressions (REs), whose meanings depend heavily on dialogue context and environment. This vagueness is even more prevalent among the elderly and children, who robots should serve more. This paper studies how such vagueness in REs within human instructions affects LLM-based robot task planning and how to overcome this issue. To this end, we propose the first robot task planning benchmark with vague REs (REI-Bench), where we discover that the vagueness of REs can severely degrade robot planning performance, leading to success rate drops of up to 77.9%. We also observe that most failure cases stem from missing objects in planners. To mitigate the REs issue, we propose a simple yet effective approach: task-oriented context cognition, which generates clear instructions for robots, achieving state-of-the-art performance compared to aware prompt and chains of thought. This work contributes to the research community of human-robot interaction (HRI) by making robot task planning more practical, particularly for non-expert users, e.g., the elderly and children.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.10872v2</guid>
   <category>cs.RO</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chenxi Jiang, Chuhao Zhou, Jianfei Yang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Incentivize Contribution and Learn Parameters Too: Federated Learning with Strategic Data Owners</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12010</link>
   <description>Classical federated learning (FL) assumes that the clients have a limited amount of noisy data with which they voluntarily participate and contribute towards learning a global, more accurate model in a principled manner. The learning happens in a distributed fashion without sharing the data with the center. However, these methods do not consider the incentive of an agent for participating and contributing to the process, given that data collection and running a distributed algorithm is costly for the clients. The question of rationality of contribution has been asked recently in the literature and some results exist that consider this problem. This paper addresses the question of simultaneous parameter learning and incentivizing contribution, which distinguishes it from the extant literature. Our first mechanism incentivizes each client to contribute to the FL process at a Nash equilibrium and simultaneously learn the model parameters. However, this equilibrium outcome can be away from the optimal, where clients contribute with their full data and the algorithm learns the optimal parameters. We propose a second mechanism with monetary transfers that is budget balanced and enables the full data contribution along with optimal parameter learning. Large scale experiments with real (federated) datasets (CIFAR-10, FeMNIST, and Twitter) show that these algorithms converge quite fast in practice, yield good welfare guarantees, and better model performance for all agents.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.12010v1</guid>
   <category>cs.GT</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.MA</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Drashthi Doshi, Aditya Vema Reddy Kesari, Swaprava Nath, Avishek Ghosh, Suhas S Kowshik</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>CodeGRAG: Bridging the Gap between Natural Language and Programming Language via Graphical Retrieval Augmented Generation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02355</link>
   <description>Utilizing large language models to generate codes has shown promising meaning in software development revolution. Despite the intelligence shown by the large language models, their specificity in code generation can still be improved due to the syntactic gap and mismatched vocabulary existing between natural language and programming languages. In this paper, we propose CodeGRAG, a Graphical Retrieval Augmented Code Generation framework that bridges the gap between NL and PL to enhance the performance of LLMs. CodeGRAG builds the graphical view of code blocks based on the control flow and data flow of them to better interpret the programming domain knowledge, which can facilitate natural language based LLMs for better understanding of code syntax and serve as a bridge among different programming languages. To take the extracted structural knowledge into the foundation models, we propose 1) a hard meta-graph prompt template to transform the challenging syntax graph into informative graphical view for tuning-free models and 2) a soft prompting technique that injects the domain knowledge of programming languages into model parameters via finetuning the models with the soft signals encoded by GNN expert model. Specifically, two constraints are designed to improve the alignment and structure expressiveness, contributing to the informativeness of the single-token-sized external &lt;GraphEmb&gt; for enhanced code generation. CodeGRAG significantly improves the code generation ability of LLMs and can even offer performance gain for cross-lingual code generation. Implementation is available at https://anonymous.4open.science/r/Code-5970/ .</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2405.02355v4</guid>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kounianhua Du, Jizheng Chen, Renting Rui, Huacan Chai, Lingyue Fu, Wei Xia, Yasheng Wang, Ruiming Tang, Yong Yu, Weinan Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>MigrationBench: Repository-Level Code Migration Benchmark from Java 8</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09569</link>
   <description>With the rapid advancement of powerful large language models (LLMs) in recent years, a wide range of software engineering tasks can now be addressed using LLMs, significantly enhancing productivity and scalability. Numerous benchmark datasets have been developed to evaluate the coding capabilities of these models, while they primarily focus on code generation and issue-resolution tasks. In contrast, we introduce a new coding benchmark MigrationBench with a distinct focus: code migration. MigrationBench aims to serve as a comprehensive benchmark for migration from Java $8$ to the latest long-term support (LTS) versions (Java $17$, $21$), including a full dataset and its subset selected with $5,102$ and $300$ repositories respectively. Selected is a representative subset curated for complexity and difficulty, offering a versatile resource to support research in the field of code migration. Additionally, we provide a comprehensive evaluation framework to facilitate rigorous and standardized assessment of LLMs on this challenging task. We further propose SD-Feedback and demonstrate that LLMs can effectively tackle repository-level code migration to Java $17$. For the selected subset with Claude-3.5-Sonnet-v2, SD-Feedback achieves $62.33\%$ and $27.33\%$ success rate (pass@1) for minimal and maximal migration respectively. The benchmark dataset and source code are available at: https://huggingface.co/collections/AmazonScience/migrationbench-68125452fc21a4564b92b6c3 and https://github.com/amazon-science/MigrationBench respectively.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.09569v2</guid>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Linbo Liu, Xinle Liu, Qiang Zhou, Lin Chen, Yihan Liu, Hoan Nguyen, Behrooz Omidvar-Tehrani, Xi Shen, Jun Huan, Omer Tripp, Anoop Deoras</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>UB-Mesh: a Hierarchically Localized nD-FullMesh Datacenter Network Architecture</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20377</link>
   <description>As the Large-scale Language Models (LLMs) continue to scale, the requisite computational power and bandwidth escalate. To address this, we introduce UB-Mesh, a novel AI datacenter network architecture designed to enhance scalability, performance, cost-efficiency and availability. Unlike traditional datacenters that provide symmetrical node-to-node bandwidth, UB-Mesh employs a hierarchically localized nD-FullMesh network topology. This design fully leverages the data locality of LLM training, prioritizing short-range, direct interconnects to minimize data movement distance and reduce switch usage.
  Although UB-Mesh's nD-FullMesh topology offers several theoretical advantages, its concrete architecture design, physical implementation and networking system optimization present new challenges. For the actual construction of UB-Mesh, we first design the UB-Mesh-Pod architecture, which is based on a 4D-FullMesh topology. UB-Mesh-Pod is implemented via a suite of hardware components that serve as the foundational building blocks, including specifically-designed NPU, CPU, Low-Radix-Switch (LRS), High-Radix-Switch (HRS), NICs and others. These components are interconnected via a novel Unified Bus (UB) technique, which enables flexible IO bandwidth allocation and hardware resource pooling. For networking system optimization, we propose advanced routing mechanism named All-Path-Routing (APR) to efficiently manage data traffic. These optimizations, combined with topology-aware performance enhancements and robust reliability measures like 64+1 backup design, result in 2.04x higher cost-efficiency, 7.2% higher network availability compared to traditional Clos architecture and 95%+ linearity in various LLM training tasks.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.20377v3</guid>
   <category>cs.AR</category>
   <category>cs.NI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Heng Liao, Bingyang Liu, Xianping Chen, Zhigang Guo, Chuanning Cheng, Jianbing Wang, Xiangyu Chen, Peng Dong, Rui Meng, Wenjie Liu, Zhe Zhou, Ziyang Zhang, Yuhang Gai, Cunle Qian, Yi Xiong, Zhongwu Cheng, Jing Xia, Yuli Ma, Xi Chen, Wenhua Du, Shizhong Xiao, Chungang Li, Yong Qin, Liudong Xiong, Zhou Yu, Lv Chen, Lei Chen, Buyun Wang, Pei Wu, Junen Gao, Xiaochu Li, Jian He, Shizhuan Yan, Bill McColl</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Redefining non-IID Data in Federated Learning for Computer Vision Tasks: Migrating from Labels to Embeddings for Task-Specific Data Distributions</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14553</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) represents a paradigm shift in distributed machine learning (ML), enabling clients to train models collaboratively while keeping their raw data private. This paradigm shift from traditional centralized ML introduces challenges due to the non-iid (non-independent and identically distributed) nature of data across clients, significantly impacting FL's performance. Existing literature, predominantly model data heterogeneity by imposing label distribution skew across clients. In this paper, we show that label distribution skew fails to fully capture the real-world data heterogeneity among clients in computer vision tasks beyond classification. Subsequently, we demonstrate that current approaches overestimate FL's performance by relying on label/class distribution skew, exposing an overlooked gap in the literature. By utilizing pre-trained deep neural networks to extract task-specific data embeddings, we define task-specific data heterogeneity through the lens of each vision task and introduce a new level of data heterogeneity called embedding-based data heterogeneity. Our methodology involves clustering data points based on embeddings and distributing them among clients using the Dirichlet distribution. Through extensive experiments, we evaluate the performance of different FL methods under our revamped notion of data heterogeneity, introducing new benchmark performance measures to the literature. We further unveil a series of open research directions that can be pursued.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.14553v3</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kasra Borazjani, Payam Abdisarabshali, Naji Khosravan, Seyyedali Hosseinalipour</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Low-hallucination Synthetic Captions for Large-Scale Vision-Language Model Pre-training</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13123</link>
   <description>In recent years, the field of vision-language model pre-training has experienced rapid advancements, driven primarily by the continuous enhancement of textual capabilities in large language models. However, existing training paradigms for multimodal large language models heavily rely on high-quality image-text pairs. As models and data scales grow exponentially, the availability of such meticulously curated data has become increasingly scarce and saturated, thereby severely limiting further advancements in this domain. This study investigates scalable caption generation techniques for vision-language model pre-training and demonstrates that large-scale low-hallucination synthetic captions can serve dual purposes: 1) acting as a viable alternative to real-world data for pre-training paradigms and 2) achieving superior performance enhancement when integrated into vision-language models through empirical validation. This paper presents following key contributions: 1) a novel pipeline for generating high-quality, low-hallucination, and knowledge-rich synthetic captions. Our continuous DPO methodology yields remarkable results in reducing hallucinations. Specifically, the non-hallucination caption rate on a held-out test set increases from 48.3% to 77.9% for a 7B-size model. 2) Comprehensive empirical validation reveals that our synthetic captions confer superior pre-training advantages over their counterparts. Across 15 vision language tasks, the model trained with our data achieves a significant performance gain of at least 6.2% compared to identical images with alt-text. In 20 common cognitive domains, the model trained with our data outperforms the alt-text data by at least 7.5%. Meanwhile, it also offers considerable support in the text-to-image domain. With our dataset, the FID score is reduced by 17.1 on a real-world validation benchmark and 13.3 on the MSCOCO validation benchmark.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.13123v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xinsong Zhang, Yarong Zeng, Xinting Huang, Hu Hu, Runquan Xie, Han Hu, Zhanhui Kang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>MMAR: A Challenging Benchmark for Deep Reasoning in Speech, Audio, Music, and Their Mix</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13032</link>
   <description>We introduce MMAR, a new benchmark designed to evaluate the deep reasoning capabilities of Audio-Language Models (ALMs) across massive multi-disciplinary tasks. MMAR comprises 1,000 meticulously curated audio-question-answer triplets, collected from real-world internet videos and refined through iterative error corrections and quality checks to ensure high quality. Unlike existing benchmarks that are limited to specific domains of sound, music, or speech, MMAR extends them to a broad spectrum of real-world audio scenarios, including mixed-modality combinations of sound, music, and speech. Each question in MMAR is hierarchically categorized across four reasoning layers: Signal, Perception, Semantic, and Cultural, with additional sub-categories within each layer to reflect task diversity and complexity. To further foster research in this area, we annotate every question with a Chain-of-Thought (CoT) rationale to promote future advancements in audio reasoning. Each item in the benchmark demands multi-step deep reasoning beyond surface-level understanding. Moreover, a part of the questions requires graduate-level perceptual and domain-specific knowledge, elevating the benchmark's difficulty and depth. We evaluate MMAR using a broad set of models, including Large Audio-Language Models (LALMs), Large Audio Reasoning Models (LARMs), Omni Language Models (OLMs), Large Language Models (LLMs), and Large Reasoning Models (LRMs), with audio caption inputs. The performance of these models on MMAR highlights the benchmark's challenging nature, and our analysis further reveals critical limitations of understanding and reasoning capabilities among current models. We hope MMAR will serve as a catalyst for future advances in this important but little-explored area.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.13032v1</guid>
   <category>cs.SD</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.MM</category>
   <category>eess.AS</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ziyang Ma, Yinghao Ma, Yanqiao Zhu, Chen Yang, Yi-Wen Chao, Ruiyang Xu, Wenxi Chen, Yuanzhe Chen, Zhuo Chen, Jian Cong, Kai Li, Keliang Li, Siyou Li, Xinfeng Li, Xiquan Li, Zheng Lian, Yuzhe Liang, Minghao Liu, Zhikang Niu, Tianrui Wang, Yuping Wang, Yuxuan Wang, Yihao Wu, Guanrou Yang, Jianwei Yu, Ruibin Yuan, Zhisheng Zheng, Ziya Zhou, Haina Zhu, Wei Xue, Emmanouil Benetos, Kai Yu, Eng-Siong Chng, Xie Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>UB-Mesh: a Hierarchically Localized nD-FullMesh Datacenter Network Architecture</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20377</link>
   <description>As the Large-scale Language Models (LLMs) continue to scale, the requisite computational power and bandwidth escalate. To address this, we introduce UB-Mesh, a novel AI datacenter network architecture designed to enhance scalability, performance, cost-efficiency and availability. Unlike traditional datacenters that provide symmetrical node-to-node bandwidth, UB-Mesh employs a hierarchically localized nD-FullMesh network topology. This design fully leverages the data locality of LLM training, prioritizing short-range, direct interconnects to minimize data movement distance and reduce switch usage.
  Although UB-Mesh's nD-FullMesh topology offers several theoretical advantages, its concrete architecture design, physical implementation and networking system optimization present new challenges. For the actual construction of UB-Mesh, we first design the UB-Mesh-Pod architecture, which is based on a 4D-FullMesh topology. UB-Mesh-Pod is implemented via a suite of hardware components that serve as the foundational building blocks, including specifically-designed NPU, CPU, Low-Radix-Switch (LRS), High-Radix-Switch (HRS), NICs and others. These components are interconnected via a novel Unified Bus (UB) technique, which enables flexible IO bandwidth allocation and hardware resource pooling. For networking system optimization, we propose advanced routing mechanism named All-Path-Routing (APR) to efficiently manage data traffic. These optimizations, combined with topology-aware performance enhancements and robust reliability measures like 64+1 backup design, result in 2.04x higher cost-efficiency, 7.2% higher network availability compared to traditional Clos architecture and 95%+ linearity in various LLM training tasks.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.20377v3</guid>
   <category>cs.AR</category>
   <category>cs.NI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Heng Liao, Bingyang Liu, Xianping Chen, Zhigang Guo, Chuanning Cheng, Jianbing Wang, Xiangyu Chen, Peng Dong, Rui Meng, Wenjie Liu, Zhe Zhou, Ziyang Zhang, Yuhang Gai, Cunle Qian, Yi Xiong, Zhongwu Cheng, Jing Xia, Yuli Ma, Xi Chen, Wenhua Du, Shizhong Xiao, Chungang Li, Yong Qin, Liudong Xiong, Zhou Yu, Lv Chen, Lei Chen, Buyun Wang, Pei Wu, Junen Gao, Xiaochu Li, Jian He, Shizhuan Yan, Bill McColl</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Conspiracy theories and where to find them on TikTok</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.12545</link>
   <description>TikTok has skyrocketed in popularity over recent years, especially among younger audiences. However, there are public concerns about the potential of this platform to promote and amplify harmful content. This study presents the first systematic analysis of conspiracy theories on TikTok. By leveraging the official TikTok Research API we collect a longitudinal dataset of 1.5M videos shared in the U.S. over three years. We estimate a lower bound on the prevalence of conspiratorial videos (up to 1000 new videos per month) and evaluate the effects of TikTok's Creativity Program for monetization, observing an overall increase in video duration regardless of content. Lastly, we evaluate the capabilities of state-of-the-art open-weight Large Language Models to identify conspiracy theories from audio transcriptions of videos. While these models achieve high precision in detecting harmful content (up to 96%), their overall performance remains comparable to fine-tuned traditional models such as RoBERTa. Our findings suggest that Large Language Models can serve as an effective tool for supporting content moderation strategies aimed at reducing the spread of harmful content on TikTok.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2407.12545v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <category>cs.SI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Francesco Corso, Francesco Pierri, Gianmarco De Francisci Morales</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Arrow: Adaptive Scheduling Mechanisms for Disaggregated LLM Inference Architecture</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11916</link>
   <description>Existing large language models (LLMs) serving systems typically employ Prefill-Decode disaggregated architecture to prevent computational interference between the prefill and decode phases. However, real-world LLM serving scenarios often exhibit significant fluctuations in request input/output lengths, causing traditional static prefill/decode node configuration ratio to result in imbalanced computational loads between these two nodes, consequently preventing efficient utilization of computing resources to improve the system's goodput. To address this challenge, we design and implement Arrow, an adaptive scheduler that leverages stateless instances and elastic instance pools to achieve efficient adaptive request and instance scheduling. Arrow dynamically adjusts the number of instances handling prefill and decode tasks based on real-time cluster performance metrics, significantly enhancing the system's capability to handle traffic spikes and load variations. Our evaluation under diverse real-world workloads shows that Arrow achieves up to $5.62 \times$ and $7.78 \times$ higher request serving rates compared to state-of-the-art PD-colocated and PD-disaggregated serving systems respectively.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.11916v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yu Wu, Tongxuan Liu, Yuting Zeng, Siyu Wu, Jun Xiong, Xianzhe Dong, Hailong Yang, Ke Zhang, Jing Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>SVAFD: A Secure and Verifiable Co-Aggregation Protocol for Federated Distillation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13319</link>
   <description>Secure Aggregation (SA) is an indispensable component of Federated Learning (FL) that concentrates on privacy preservation while allowing for robust aggregation. However, most SA designs rely heavily on the unrealistic assumption of homogeneous model architectures. Federated Distillation (FD), which aggregates locally computed logits instead of model parameters, introduces a promising alternative for cooperative training in heterogeneous model settings. Nevertheless, we recognize two major challenges in implementing SA for FD. (i) Prior SA designs encourage a dominant server, who is solely responsible for collecting, aggregating and distributing. Such central authority facilitates server to forge aggregation proofs or collude to bypass the claimed security guarantees; (ii) Existing SA, tailored for FL models, overlook the intrinsic properties of logits, making them unsuitable for FD.
  To address these challenges, we propose SVAFD, the first SA protocol that is specifically designed for FD. At a high level, SVAFD incorporates two innovations: (i) a multilateral co-aggregation method tha redefines the responsibilities of clients and server. Clients autonomously evaluate and aggregate logits shares locally with a lightweight coding scheme, while the server handles ciphertext decoding and performs the task of generating verification proofs; (ii) a quality-aware knowledge filtration method that facilitates biased logits exclusion against poisoning attacks. Moreover, SVAFD is resilient to stragglers and colluding clients, making it well-suited for dynamic networks in real-world applications. We have implemented the SVAFD prototype over four emerging FD architectures and evaluated it against poisoning and inference attacks. Results demonstrate that SVAFD improves model accuracy, making it a significant step forward in secure and verifiable aggregation for heterogeneous FL systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.13319v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Tian Wen, Sheng Sun, Yuwei Wang, Peiyan Chen, Zhiyuan Wu, Min Liu, Bo Gao</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>KunServe: Efficient Parameter-centric Memory Management for LLM Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18169</link>
   <description>Serving LLMs with a cluster of GPUs is common nowadays, where the serving system must meet strict latency SLOs required by applications. However, the stateful nature of LLM serving requires maintaining huge states (i.e., KVCache) in limited GPU memory. Under spikes in real-world workloads, GPU memory can be easily throttled, leading to orders of magnitude higher response latency due to queuing introduced by waiting for KVCache to be reclaimed. Prior KVCache-centric approaches handle load throttling by dropping, migrating, or swapping KVCache. These methods fail to release sufficient memory quickly with requests still queued.
  This paper proposes the first parameter-centric approach to handling throttling by selectively dropping replicated parameters to instantly free memory for requests, based on an unnoticed observation that model parameters are commonly replicated across GPUs for serving LLMs. With additional memory, all requests can be served with a larger batch without queuing. To make the parameter-centric approach correct and efficient, we cooperatively execute requests on GPUs with a complete copy of parameters using pipeline parallelism, and derive an appropriate drop plan without unnecessary cooperation. We also design techniques to minimize the performance overhead due to pipeline parallelism with the execution patterns of requests under drop. Evaluations show that {\sys} reduces the tail TTFT of requests under throttling by up to 72.2 times compared to the state-of-the-art systems including Llumnix, vLLM and InferCept.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.18169v4</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Rongxin Cheng, Yuxin Lai, Xingda Wei, Rong Chen, Haibo Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>EcoLearn: Optimizing the Carbon Footprint of Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.17972</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) distributes machine learning (ML) training across edge devices to reduce data transfer overhead and protect data privacy. Since FL model training may span hundreds of devices and is thus resource- and energy-intensive, it has a significant carbon footprint. Importantly, since energy's carbon-intensity differs substantially (by up to 60$\times$) across locations, training on the same device using the same amount of energy, but at different locations, can incur widely different carbon emissions. While prior work has focused on improving FL's resource- and energy-efficiency by optimizing time-to-accuracy, it implicitly assumes all energy has the same carbon intensity and thus does not optimize carbon efficiency, i.e., work done per unit of carbon emitted.
  To address the problem, we design EcoLearn, which minimizes FL's carbon footprint without significantly affecting model accuracy or training time. EcoLearn achieves a favorable tradeoff by integrating carbon awareness into multiple aspects of FL training, including i) selecting clients with high data utility and low carbon, ii) provisioning more clients during the initial training rounds, and iii) mitigating stragglers by dynamically adjusting client over-provisioning based on carbon. We implement EcoLearn and its carbon-aware FL training policies in the Flower framework and show that it reduces the carbon footprint of training (by up to $10.8$$\times$) while maintaining model accuracy and training time (within $\sim$$1$\%) compared to state-of-the-art approaches.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2310.17972v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Talha Mehboob, Noman Bashir, Jesus Omana Iglesias, Michael Zink, David Irwin</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>AdaServe: Accelerating Multi-SLO LLM Serving with SLO-Customized Speculative Decoding</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12162</link>
   <description>Modern large language model (LLM) applications exhibit diverse service-level objectives (SLOs), from low-latency requirements in interactive coding assistants to more relaxed constraints in data wrangling tasks. Existing LLM serving systems, which rely on uniform batching and scheduling strategies, often fail to meet these heterogeneous SLOs concurrently. We present AdaServe, the first LLM serving system designed to support efficient multi-SLO serving through SLO-customized speculative decoding. AdaServe formulates multi-SLO serving as a constrained optimization problem and introduces a hardware-aware algorithm that constructs a speculation tree tailored to each request's latency target. It features a speculate-select-verify pipeline that enables fine-grained control over decoding speed while maximizing system throughput. AdaServe further adapts to workload variation by dynamically adjusting speculation parameters. Evaluations across diverse workloads show that AdaServe reduces SLO violations by up to 4.3$\times$ and improves goodput by up to 1.9$\times$ compared to the best performing baselines, highlighting its effectiveness in multi-SLO serving.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.12162v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zikun Li, Zhuofu Chen, Remi Delacourt, Gabriele Oliaro, Zeyu Wang, Qinghan Chen, Shuhuai Lin, April Yang, Zhihao Zhang, Zhuoming Chen, Sean Lai, Xinhao Cheng, Xupeng Miao, Zhihao Jia</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Gradient Correction in Federated Learning with Adaptive Optimization</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02727</link>
   <description>In federated learning (FL), model training performance is strongly impacted by data heterogeneity across clients. Client-drift compensation methods have recently emerged as a solution to this issue, introducing correction terms into local model updates. To date, these methods have only been considered under stochastic gradient descent (SGD)-based model training, while modern FL frameworks also employ adaptive optimizers (e.g., Adam) for improved convergence. However, due to the complex interplay between first and second moments found in most adaptive optimization methods, naively injecting correction terms can lead to performance degradation in heterogeneous settings. In this work, we propose {\tt FAdamGC}, the first algorithm to integrate drift compensation into adaptive federated optimization. The key idea of {\tt FAdamGC} is injecting a pre-estimation correction term that aligns with the moment structure of adaptive methods. We provide a rigorous convergence analysis of our algorithm under non-convex settings, showing that {\tt FAdamGC} results in better rate and milder assumptions than naively porting SGD-based correction algorithms into adaptive optimizers. Our experimental results demonstrate that {\tt FAdamGC} consistently outperform existing methods in total communication and computation cost across varying levels of data heterogeneity, showing the efficacy of correcting gradient information in federated adaptive optimization.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.02727v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Evan Chen, Shiqiang Wang, Jianing Zhang, Dong-Jun Han, Chaoyue Liu, Christopher Brinton</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>DPZV: Elevating the Tradeoff between Privacy and Utility in Zeroth-Order Vertical Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20565</link>
   <description>Vertical Federated Learning (VFL) enables collaborative training with feature-partitioned data, yet remains vulnerable to privacy leakage through gradient transmissions. Standard differential privacy (DP) techniques such as DP-SGD are difficult to apply in this setting due to VFL's distributed nature and the high variance incurred by vector-valued noise. On the other hand, zeroth-order (ZO) optimization techniques can avoid explicit gradient exposure but lack formal privacy guarantees. In this work, we propose DPZV, the first ZO optimization framework for VFL that achieves tunable DP with performance guarantees. DPZV overcomes these limitations by injecting low-variance scalar noise at the server, enabling controllable privacy with reduced memory overhead. We conduct a comprehensive theoretical analysis showing that DPZV matches the convergence rate of first-order optimization methods while satisfying formal ($\epsilon, \delta$)-DP guarantees. Experiments on image and language benchmarks demonstrate that DPZV outperforms several baselines in terms of accuracy under a wide range of privacy constraints ($\epsilon \le 10$), thereby elevating the privacy-utility tradeoff in VFL.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.20565v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jianing Zhang, Evan Chen, Chaoyue Liu, Christopher G. Brinton</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>MMAR: A Challenging Benchmark for Deep Reasoning in Speech, Audio, Music, and Their Mix</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13032</link>
   <description>We introduce MMAR, a new benchmark designed to evaluate the deep reasoning capabilities of Audio-Language Models (ALMs) across massive multi-disciplinary tasks. MMAR comprises 1,000 meticulously curated audio-question-answer triplets, collected from real-world internet videos and refined through iterative error corrections and quality checks to ensure high quality. Unlike existing benchmarks that are limited to specific domains of sound, music, or speech, MMAR extends them to a broad spectrum of real-world audio scenarios, including mixed-modality combinations of sound, music, and speech. Each question in MMAR is hierarchically categorized across four reasoning layers: Signal, Perception, Semantic, and Cultural, with additional sub-categories within each layer to reflect task diversity and complexity. To further foster research in this area, we annotate every question with a Chain-of-Thought (CoT) rationale to promote future advancements in audio reasoning. Each item in the benchmark demands multi-step deep reasoning beyond surface-level understanding. Moreover, a part of the questions requires graduate-level perceptual and domain-specific knowledge, elevating the benchmark's difficulty and depth. We evaluate MMAR using a broad set of models, including Large Audio-Language Models (LALMs), Large Audio Reasoning Models (LARMs), Omni Language Models (OLMs), Large Language Models (LLMs), and Large Reasoning Models (LRMs), with audio caption inputs. The performance of these models on MMAR highlights the benchmark's challenging nature, and our analysis further reveals critical limitations of understanding and reasoning capabilities among current models. We hope MMAR will serve as a catalyst for future advances in this important but little-explored area.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.13032v1</guid>
   <category>cs.SD</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.MM</category>
   <category>eess.AS</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ziyang Ma, Yinghao Ma, Yanqiao Zhu, Chen Yang, Yi-Wen Chao, Ruiyang Xu, Wenxi Chen, Yuanzhe Chen, Zhuo Chen, Jian Cong, Kai Li, Keliang Li, Siyou Li, Xinfeng Li, Xiquan Li, Zheng Lian, Yuzhe Liang, Minghao Liu, Zhikang Niu, Tianrui Wang, Yuping Wang, Yuxuan Wang, Yihao Wu, Guanrou Yang, Jianwei Yu, Ruibin Yuan, Zhisheng Zheng, Ziya Zhou, Haina Zhu, Wei Xue, Emmanouil Benetos, Kai Yu, Eng-Siong Chng, Xie Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Incentivize Contribution and Learn Parameters Too: Federated Learning with Strategic Data Owners</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12010</link>
   <description>Classical federated learning (FL) assumes that the clients have a limited amount of noisy data with which they voluntarily participate and contribute towards learning a global, more accurate model in a principled manner. The learning happens in a distributed fashion without sharing the data with the center. However, these methods do not consider the incentive of an agent for participating and contributing to the process, given that data collection and running a distributed algorithm is costly for the clients. The question of rationality of contribution has been asked recently in the literature and some results exist that consider this problem. This paper addresses the question of simultaneous parameter learning and incentivizing contribution, which distinguishes it from the extant literature. Our first mechanism incentivizes each client to contribute to the FL process at a Nash equilibrium and simultaneously learn the model parameters. However, this equilibrium outcome can be away from the optimal, where clients contribute with their full data and the algorithm learns the optimal parameters. We propose a second mechanism with monetary transfers that is budget balanced and enables the full data contribution along with optimal parameter learning. Large scale experiments with real (federated) datasets (CIFAR-10, FeMNIST, and Twitter) show that these algorithms converge quite fast in practice, yield good welfare guarantees, and better model performance for all agents.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.12010v1</guid>
   <category>cs.GT</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.MA</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Drashthi Doshi, Aditya Vema Reddy Kesari, Swaprava Nath, Avishek Ghosh, Suhas S Kowshik</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Conspiracy theories and where to find them on TikTok</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.12545</link>
   <description>TikTok has skyrocketed in popularity over recent years, especially among younger audiences. However, there are public concerns about the potential of this platform to promote and amplify harmful content. This study presents the first systematic analysis of conspiracy theories on TikTok. By leveraging the official TikTok Research API we collect a longitudinal dataset of 1.5M videos shared in the U.S. over three years. We estimate a lower bound on the prevalence of conspiratorial videos (up to 1000 new videos per month) and evaluate the effects of TikTok's Creativity Program for monetization, observing an overall increase in video duration regardless of content. Lastly, we evaluate the capabilities of state-of-the-art open-weight Large Language Models to identify conspiracy theories from audio transcriptions of videos. While these models achieve high precision in detecting harmful content (up to 96%), their overall performance remains comparable to fine-tuned traditional models such as RoBERTa. Our findings suggest that Large Language Models can serve as an effective tool for supporting content moderation strategies aimed at reducing the spread of harmful content on TikTok.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2407.12545v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <category>cs.SI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Francesco Corso, Francesco Pierri, Gianmarco De Francisci Morales</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LightRetriever: A LLM-based Hybrid Retrieval Architecture with 1000x Faster Query Inference</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12260</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs)-based hybrid retrieval uses LLMs to encode queries and documents into low-dimensional dense or high-dimensional sparse vectors. It retrieves documents relevant to search queries based on vector similarities. Documents are pre-encoded offline, while queries arrive in real-time, necessitating an efficient online query encoder. Although LLMs significantly enhance retrieval capabilities, serving deeply parameterized LLMs slows down query inference throughput and increases demands for online deployment resources. In this paper, we propose LightRetriever, a novel LLM-based hybrid retriever with extremely lightweight query encoders. Our method retains a full-sized LLM for document encoding, but reduces the workload of query encoding to no more than an embedding lookup. Compared to serving a full-sized LLM on an H800 GPU, our approach achieves over a 1000x speedup for query inference with GPU acceleration, and even a 20x speedup without GPU. Experiments on large-scale retrieval benchmarks demonstrate that our method generalizes well across diverse retrieval tasks, retaining an average of 95% full-sized performance.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.12260v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Guangyuan Ma, Yongliang Ma, Xuanrui Gou, Zhenpeng Su, Ming Zhou, Songlin Hu</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
