<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 04:20:34 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 04:20:34 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>FlexSelect: Flexible Token Selection for Efficient Long Video Understanding</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00993</link>
   <description>Long-form video understanding poses a significant challenge for video large language models (VideoLLMs) due to prohibitively high computational and memory demands. In this paper, we propose FlexSelect, a flexible and efficient token selection strategy for processing long videos. FlexSelect identifies and retains the most semantically relevant content by leveraging cross-modal attention patterns from a reference transformer layer. It comprises two key components: (1) a training-free token ranking pipeline that leverages faithful cross-modal attention weights to estimate each video token's importance, and (2) a rank-supervised lightweight selector that is trained to replicate these rankings and filter redundant tokens. This generic approach can be seamlessly integrated into various VideoLLM architectures, such as LLaVA-Video, InternVL and Qwen-VL, serving as a plug-and-play module to extend their temporal context length. Empirically, FlexSelect delivers strong gains across multiple long-video benchmarks including VideoMME, MLVU, LongVB, and LVBench. Moreover, it achieves significant speed-ups (for example, up to 9 times on a LLaVA-Video-7B model), highlighting FlexSelect's promise for efficient long-form video understanding. Project page available at: https://yunzhuzhang0918.github.io/flex_select</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00993v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yunzhu Zhang, Yu Lu, Tianyi Wang, Fengyun Rao, Yi Yang, Linchao Zhu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Flashbacks to Harmonize Stability and Plasticity in Continual Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00477</link>
   <description>We introduce Flashback Learning (FL), a novel method designed to harmonize the stability and plasticity of models in Continual Learning (CL). Unlike prior approaches that primarily focus on regularizing model updates to preserve old information while learning new concepts, FL explicitly balances this trade-off through a bidirectional form of regularization. This approach effectively guides the model to swiftly incorporate new knowledge while actively retaining its old knowledge. FL operates through a two-phase training process and can be seamlessly integrated into various CL methods, including replay, parameter regularization, distillation, and dynamic architecture techniques. In designing FL, we use two distinct knowledge bases: one to enhance plasticity and another to improve stability. FL ensures a more balanced model by utilizing both knowledge bases to regularize model updates. Theoretically, we analyze how the FL mechanism enhances the stability-plasticity balance. Empirically, FL demonstrates tangible improvements over baseline methods within the same training budget. By integrating FL into at least one representative baseline from each CL category, we observed an average accuracy improvement of up to 4.91% in Class-Incremental and 3.51% in Task-Incremental settings on standard image classification benchmarks. Additionally, measurements of the stability-to-plasticity ratio confirm that FL effectively enhances this balance. FL also outperforms state-of-the-art CL methods on more challenging datasets like ImageNet.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00477v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Leila Mahmoodi, Peyman Moghadam, Munawar Hayat, Christian Simon, Mehrtash Harandi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Exploring Model Kinship for Merging Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12613</link>
   <description>Model merging has become one of the key technologies for enhancing the capabilities and efficiency of Large Language Models (LLMs). However, our understanding of the expected performance gains and principles when merging any two models remains limited. In this work, we introduce model kinship, the degree of similarity or relatedness between LLMs, analogous to biological evolution. With comprehensive empirical analysis, we find that there is a certain relationship between model kinship and the performance gains after model merging, which can help guide our selection of candidate models. Inspired by this, we propose a new model merging strategy: Top-k Greedy Merging with Model Kinship, which can yield better performance on benchmark datasets. Specifically, we discover that using model kinship as a criterion can assist us in continuously performing model merging, alleviating the degradation (local optima) in model evolution, whereas model kinship can serve as a guide to escape these traps. Code is available at https://github.com/zjunlp/ModelKinship.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.12613v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.MA</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yedi Hu, Yunzhi Yao, Shumin Deng, Huajun Chen, Ningyu Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Safety at Scale: A Comprehensive Survey of Large Model Safety</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05206</link>
   <description>The rapid advancement of large models, driven by their exceptional abilities in learning and generalization through large-scale pre-training, has reshaped the landscape of Artificial Intelligence (AI). These models are now foundational to a wide range of applications, including conversational AI, recommendation systems, autonomous driving, content generation, medical diagnostics, and scientific discovery. However, their widespread deployment also exposes them to significant safety risks, raising concerns about robustness, reliability, and ethical implications. This survey provides a systematic review of current safety research on large models, covering Vision Foundation Models (VFMs), Large Language Models (LLMs), Vision-Language Pre-training (VLP) models, Vision-Language Models (VLMs), Diffusion Models (DMs), and large-model-based Agents. Our contributions are summarized as follows: (1) We present a comprehensive taxonomy of safety threats to these models, including adversarial attacks, data poisoning, backdoor attacks, jailbreak and prompt injection attacks, energy-latency attacks, data and model extraction attacks, and emerging agent-specific threats. (2) We review defense strategies proposed for each type of attacks if available and summarize the commonly used datasets and benchmarks for safety research. (3) Building on this, we identify and discuss the open challenges in large model safety, emphasizing the need for comprehensive safety evaluations, scalable and effective defense mechanisms, and sustainable data practices. More importantly, we highlight the necessity of collective efforts from the research community and international collaboration. Our work can serve as a useful reference for researchers and practitioners, fostering the ongoing development of comprehensive defense systems and platforms to safeguard AI models.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.05206v4</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xingjun Ma, Yifeng Gao, Yixu Wang, Ruofan Wang, Xin Wang, Ye Sun, Yifan Ding, Hengyuan Xu, Yunhao Chen, Yunhan Zhao, Hanxun Huang, Yige Li, Jiaming Zhang, Xiang Zheng, Yang Bai, Zuxuan Wu, Xipeng Qiu, Jingfeng Zhang, Yiming Li, Xudong Han, Haonan Li, Jun Sun, Cong Wang, Jindong Gu, Baoyuan Wu, Siheng Chen, Tianwei Zhang, Yang Liu, Mingming Gong, Tongliang Liu, Shirui Pan, Cihang Xie, Tianyu Pang, Yinpeng Dong, Ruoxi Jia, Yang Zhang, Shiqing Ma, Xiangyu Zhang, Neil Gong, Chaowei Xiao, Sarah Erfani, Tim Baldwin, Bo Li, Masashi Sugiyama, Dacheng Tao, James Bailey, Yu-Gang Jiang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Compiler Optimization via LLM Reasoning for Efficient Model Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01374</link>
   <description>While model serving has unlocked unprecedented capabilities, the high cost of serving large-scale models continues to be a significant barrier to widespread accessibility and rapid innovation. Compiler optimizations have long driven substantial performance improvements, but existing compilers struggle with neural workloads due to the exponentially large and highly interdependent space of possible transformations. Although existing stochastic search techniques can be effective, they are often sample-inefficient and fail to leverage the structural context underlying compilation decisions. We set out to investigate the research question of whether reasoning with large language models (LLMs), without any retraining, can leverage the context-aware decision space of compiler optimization to significantly improve sample efficiency. To that end, we introduce a novel compilation framework (dubbed REASONING COMPILER) that formulates optimization as a sequential, context-aware decision process, guided by a large language model and structured Monte Carlo tree search (MCTS). The LLM acts as a proposal mechanism, suggesting hardware-aware transformations that reflect the current program state and accumulated performance feedback. Monte Carlo tree search (MCTS) incorporates the LLM-generated proposals to balance exploration and exploitation, facilitating structured, context-sensitive traversal of the expansive compiler optimization space. By achieving substantial speedups with markedly fewer samples than leading neural compilers, our approach demonstrates the potential of LLM-guided reasoning to transform the landscape of compiler optimization.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.01374v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.PL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sujun Tang, Christopher Priebe, Rohan Mahapatra, Lianhui Qin, Hadi Esmaeilzadeh</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>SysLLMatic: Large Language Models are Software System Optimizers</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01249</link>
   <description>Automatic software system optimization can improve software speed, reduce operating costs, and save energy. Traditional approaches to optimization rely on manual tuning and compiler heuristics, limiting their ability to generalize across diverse codebases and system contexts. Recent methods using Large Language Models (LLMs) offer automation to address these limitations, but often fail to scale to the complexity of real-world software systems and applications. We present SysLLMatic, a system that integrates LLMs with profiling-guided feedback and system performance insights to automatically optimize software code. We evaluate it on three benchmark suites: HumanEval_CPP (competitive programming in C++), SciMark2 (scientific kernels in Java), and DaCapoBench (large-scale software systems in Java). Results show that SysLLMatic can improve system performance, including latency, throughput, energy efficiency, memory usage, and CPU utilization. It consistently outperforms state-of-the-art LLM baselines on microbenchmarks. On large-scale application codes, it surpasses traditional compiler optimizations, achieving average relative improvements of 1.85x in latency and 2.24x in throughput. Our findings demonstrate that LLMs, guided by principled systems thinking and appropriate performance diagnostics, can serve as viable software system optimizers. We further identify limitations of our approach and the challenges involved in handling complex applications. This work provides a foundation for generating optimized code across various languages, benchmarks, and program sizes in a principled manner.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.01249v1</guid>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <category>cs.PF</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Huiyun Peng, Arjun Gupte, Ryan Hasler, Nicholas John Eliopoulos, Chien-Chou Ho, Rishi Mantri, Leo Deng, Konstantin L\&quot;aufer, George K. Thiruvathukal, James C. Davis</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated learning framework for collaborative remaining useful life prognostics: an aircraft engine case study</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00499</link>
   <description>Complex systems such as aircraft engines are continuously monitored by sensors. In predictive aircraft maintenance, the collected sensor measurements are used to estimate the health condition and the Remaining Useful Life (RUL) of such systems. However, a major challenge when developing prognostics is the limited number of run-to-failure data samples. This challenge could be overcome if multiple airlines would share their run-to-failure data samples such that sufficient learning can be achieved. Due to privacy concerns, however, airlines are reluctant to share their data in a centralized setting. In this paper, a collaborative federated learning framework is therefore developed instead. Here, several airlines cooperate to train a collective RUL prognostic machine learning model, without the need to centrally share their data. For this, a decentralized validation procedure is proposed to validate the prognostics model without sharing any data. Moreover, sensor data is often noisy and of low quality. This paper therefore proposes four novel methods to aggregate the parameters of the global prognostic model. These methods enhance the robustness of the FL framework against noisy data. The proposed framework is illustrated for training a collaborative RUL prognostic model for aircraft engines, using the N-CMAPSS dataset. Here, six airlines are considered, that collaborate in the FL framework to train a collective RUL prognostic model for their aircraft's engines. When comparing the proposed FL framework with the case where each airline independently develops their own prognostic model, the results show that FL leads to more accurate RUL prognostics for five out of the six airlines. Moreover, the novel robust aggregation methods render the FL framework robust to noisy data samples.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00499v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.ET</category>
   <category>cs.SY</category>
   <category>eess.SY</category>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Diogo Landau, Ingeborg de Pater, Mihaela Mitici, Nishant Saurabh</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Assortment of Attention Heads: Accelerating Federated PEFT with Head Pruning and Strategic Client Selection</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00743</link>
   <description>Parameter Efficient Fine-Tuning (PEFT) has become the de-facto approach in adapting Large Language Models (LLMs) for downstream tasks in Natural Language Processing. However, its adoption in privacy-preserving distributed learning frameworks, such as Federated Learning (FL), remains relatively limited. This is mainly due to challenges specific to FL, such as resource-constrained devices and diverse data distributions among clients. In this paper, we propose an efficient method to perform PEFT within the FL framework for Multi-Head Attention (MHA) based language models. We address the challenges through head pruning, a novel head-specific weighted aggregation mechanism, and a client selection strategy. Head pruning minimizes training complexity within the clients, guided by the importance score computed based on the confidence of the attention head. Weighted aggregation of heads ensures the global model captures crucial updates from diverse clients complementing our client selection strategy. We show results on the MultiNLI benchmark along with 20 Newsgroups, XL-Sum, and E2E NLG datasets. We use the MultiNLI dataset and T5-small model with LoRA as our PEFT method, attaining sparsity levels of up to 90%, resulting in a communication advantage of up to 1.8x and a reduction in training OPs of 3.9x while maintaining the accuracy drop under 2%.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00743v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yeshwanth Venkatesha, Souvik Kundu, Priyadarshini Panda</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedRPCA: Enhancing Federated LoRA Aggregation Using Robust PCA</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01194</link>
   <description>LoRA has emerged as one of the most promising fine-tuning techniques, especially for federated learning (FL), since it significantly reduces communication and computation costs at resource-constrained clients. However, data heterogeneity remains a significant challenge for LoRA-based FL, and the conventional aggregation strategy based on FedAvg suffers from slow convergence and suboptimal accuracy. Motivated by recent advances in model merging, particularly Task Arithmetic, we explore the idea of aggregating client LoRA parameters using scaled averaging. We first observe that a naive application of Task Arithmetic is ineffective due to the high cosine similarity between client updates, indicating significant common knowledge in the updates across clients. To address this issue, we propose decomposing client LoRA updates via Robust Principal Component Analysis (Robust-PCA) into a common low-rank component and client-specific sparse components. Our proposed algorithm FedRPCA aggregates the low-rank components through averaging, consolidating common knowledge, and applies scaled averaging to the sparse components to amplify client-specific knowledge. We evaluate our approach across a variety of vision and language tasks and demonstrate that it achieves higher final accuracy and faster convergence compared to competing baselines.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.01194v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Divyansh Jhunjhunwala, Arian Raje, Madan Ravi Ganesh, Chaithanya Kumar Mummadi, Chaoqun Dong, Jiawei Zhou, Wan-Yi Lin, Gauri Joshi, Zhenzhen Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Unified Solution to Diverse Heterogeneities in One-shot Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21119</link>
   <description>One-Shot Federated Learning (OSFL) restricts communication between the server and clients to a single round, significantly reducing communication costs and minimizing privacy leakage risks compared to traditional Federated Learning (FL), which requires multiple rounds of communication. However, existing OSFL frameworks remain vulnerable to distributional heterogeneity, as they primarily focus on model heterogeneity while neglecting data heterogeneity. To bridge this gap, we propose FedHydra, a unified, data-free, OSFL framework designed to effectively address both model and data heterogeneity. Unlike existing OSFL approaches, FedHydra introduces a novel two-stage learning mechanism. Specifically, it incorporates model stratification and heterogeneity-aware stratified aggregation to mitigate the challenges posed by both model and data heterogeneity. By this design, the data and model heterogeneity issues are simultaneously monitored from different aspects during learning. Consequently, FedHydra can effectively mitigate both issues by minimizing their inherent conflicts. We compared FedHydra with five SOTA baselines on four benchmark datasets. Experimental results show that our method outperforms the previous OSFL methods in both homogeneous and heterogeneous settings. The code is available at https://github.com/Jun-B0518/FedHydra.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.21119v3</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jun Bai, Yiliao Song, Di Wu, Atul Sajjanhar, Yong Xiang, Wei Zhou, Xiaohui Tao, Yan Li, Yue Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Understanding the Statistical Accuracy-Communication Trade-off in Personalized Federated Learning with Minimax Guarantees</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08934</link>
   <description>Personalized federated learning (PFL) offers a flexible framework for aggregating information across distributed clients with heterogeneous data. This work considers a personalized federated learning setting that simultaneously learns global and local models. While purely local training has no communication cost, collaborative learning among the clients can leverage shared knowledge to improve statistical accuracy, presenting an accuracy-communication trade-off in personalized federated learning. However, the theoretical analysis of how personalization quantitatively influences sample and algorithmic efficiency and their inherent trade-off is largely unexplored. This paper makes a contribution towards filling this gap, by providing a quantitative characterization of the personalization degree on the tradeoff. The results further offers theoretical insights for choosing the personalization degree. As a side contribution, we establish the minimax optimality in terms of statistical accuracy for a widely studied PFL formulation. The theoretical result is validated on both synthetic and real-world datasets and its generalizability is verified in a non-convex setting.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.08934v4</guid>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>math.ST</category>
   <category>stat.CO</category>
   <category>stat.TH</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xin Yu, Zelin He, Ying Sun, Lingzhou Xue, Runze Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Retrieval-Augmented Generation: A Comprehensive Survey of Architectures, Enhancements, and Robustness Frontiers</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00054</link>
   <description>Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) has emerged as a powerful paradigm to enhance large language models (LLMs) by conditioning generation on external evidence retrieved at inference time. While RAG addresses critical limitations of parametric knowledge storage-such as factual inconsistency and domain inflexibility-it introduces new challenges in retrieval quality, grounding fidelity, pipeline efficiency, and robustness against noisy or adversarial inputs. This survey provides a comprehensive synthesis of recent advances in RAG systems, offering a taxonomy that categorizes architectures into retriever-centric, generator-centric, hybrid, and robustness-oriented designs. We systematically analyze enhancements across retrieval optimization, context filtering, decoding control, and efficiency improvements, supported by comparative performance analyses on short-form and multi-hop question answering tasks. Furthermore, we review state-of-the-art evaluation frameworks and benchmarks, highlighting trends in retrieval-aware evaluation, robustness testing, and federated retrieval settings. Our analysis reveals recurring trade-offs between retrieval precision and generation flexibility, efficiency and faithfulness, and modularity and coordination. We conclude by identifying open challenges and future research directions, including adaptive retrieval architectures, real-time retrieval integration, structured reasoning over multi-hop evidence, and privacy-preserving retrieval mechanisms. This survey aims to consolidate current knowledge in RAG research and serve as a foundation for the next generation of retrieval-augmented language modeling systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00054v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chaitanya Sharma</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Survey of LLM $\times$ DATA</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18458</link>
   <description>The integration of large language model (LLM) and data management (DATA) is rapidly redefining both domains. In this survey, we comprehensively review the bidirectional relationships. On the one hand, DATA4LLM, spanning large-scale data processing, storage, and serving, feeds LLMs with high quality, diversity, and timeliness of data required for stages like pre-training, post-training, retrieval-augmented generation, and agentic workflows: (i) Data processing for LLMs includes scalable acquisition, deduplication, filtering, selection, domain mixing, and synthetic augmentation; (ii) Data Storage for LLMs focuses on efficient data and model formats, distributed and heterogeneous storage hierarchies, KV-cache management, and fault-tolerant checkpointing; (iii) Data serving for LLMs tackles challenges in RAG (e.g., knowledge post-processing), LLM inference (e.g., prompt compression, data provenance), and training strategies (e.g., data packing and shuffling). On the other hand, in LLM4DATA, LLMs are emerging as general-purpose engines for data management. We review recent advances in (i) data manipulation, including automatic data cleaning, integration, discovery; (ii) data analysis, covering reasoning over structured, semi-structured, and unstructured data, and (iii) system optimization (e.g., configuration tuning, query rewriting, anomaly diagnosis), powered by LLM techniques like retrieval-augmented prompting, task-specialized fine-tuning, and multi-agent collaboration.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.18458v3</guid>
   <category>cs.DB</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xuanhe Zhou, Junxuan He, Wei Zhou, Haodong Chen, Zirui Tang, Haoyu Zhao, Xin Tong, Guoliang Li, Youmin Chen, Jun Zhou, Zhaojun Sun, Binyuan Hui, Shuo Wang, Conghui He, Zhiyuan Liu, Jingren Zhou, Fan Wu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Blockchain-Enabled Privacy-Preserving Second-Order Federated Edge Learning in Personalized Healthcare</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00416</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) has attracted increasing attention to mitigate security and privacy challenges in traditional cloud-centric machine learning models specifically in healthcare ecosystems. FL methodologies enable the training of global models through localized policies, allowing independent operations at the edge clients' level. Conventional first-order FL approaches face several challenges in personalized model training due to heterogeneous non-independent and identically distributed (non-iid) data of each edge client. Recently, second-order FL approaches maintain the stability and consistency of non-iid datasets while improving personalized model training. This study proposes and develops a verifiable and auditable optimized second-order FL framework BFEL (blockchain-enhanced federated edge learning) based on optimized FedCurv for personalized healthcare systems. FedCurv incorporates information about the importance of each parameter to each client's task (through Fisher Information Matrix) which helps to preserve client-specific knowledge and reduce model drift during aggregation. Moreover, it minimizes communication rounds required to achieve a target precision convergence for each edge client while effectively managing personalized training on non-iid and heterogeneous data. The incorporation of Ethereum-based model aggregation ensures trust, verifiability, and auditability while public key encryption enhances privacy and security. Experimental results of federated CNNs and MLPs utilizing Mnist, Cifar-10, and PathMnist demonstrate the high efficiency and scalability of the proposed framework.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00416v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Anum Nawaz, Muhammad Irfan, Xianjia Yu, Zhuo Zou, Tomi Westerlund</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>PSI-PFL: Population Stability Index for Client Selection in non-IID Personalized Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00440</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) enables decentralized machine learning (ML) model training while preserving data privacy by keeping data localized across clients. However, non-independent and identically distributed (non-IID) data across clients poses a significant challenge, leading to skewed model updates and performance degradation. Addressing this, we propose PSI-PFL, a novel client selection framework for Personalized Federated Learning (PFL) that leverages the Population Stability Index (PSI) to quantify and mitigate data heterogeneity (so-called non-IIDness). Our approach selects more homogeneous clients based on PSI, reducing the impact of label skew, one of the most detrimental factors in FL performance. Experimental results over multiple data modalities (tabular, image, text) demonstrate that PSI-PFL significantly improves global model accuracy, outperforming state-of-the-art baselines by up to 10\% under non-IID scenarios while ensuring fairer local performance. PSI-PFL enhances FL performance and offers practical benefits in applications where data privacy and heterogeneity are critical.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00440v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Daniel-M. Jimenez-Gutierrez, David Solans, Mohammed Elbamby, Nicolas Kourtellis</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Towards Graph-Based Privacy-Preserving Federated Learning: ModelNet - A ResNet-based Model Classification Dataset</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00476</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) has emerged as a powerful paradigm for training machine learning models across distributed data sources while preserving data locality. However, the privacy of local data is always a pivotal concern and has received a lot of attention in recent research on the FL regime. Moreover, the lack of domain heterogeneity and client-specific segregation in the benchmarks remains a critical bottleneck for rigorous evaluation. In this paper, we introduce ModelNet, a novel image classification dataset constructed from the embeddings extracted from a pre-trained ResNet50 model. First, we modify the CIFAR100 dataset into three client-specific variants, considering three domain heterogeneities (homogeneous, heterogeneous, and random). Subsequently, we train each client-specific subset of all three variants on the pre-trained ResNet50 model to save model parameters. In addition to multi-domain image data, we propose a new hypothesis to define the FL algorithm that can access the anonymized model parameters to preserve the local privacy in a more effective manner compared to existing ones. ModelNet is designed to simulate realistic FL settings by incorporating non-IID data distributions and client diversity design principles in the mainframe for both conventional and futuristic graph-driven FL algorithms. The three variants are ModelNet-S, ModelNet-D, and ModelNet-R, which are based on homogeneous, heterogeneous, and random data settings, respectively. To the best of our knowledge, we are the first to propose a cross-environment client-specific FL dataset along with the graph-based variant. Extensive experiments based on domain shifts and aggregation strategies show the effectiveness of the above variants, making it a practical benchmark for classical and graph-based FL research. The dataset and related code are available online.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00476v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Abhisek Ray, Lukas Esterle</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Flashbacks to Harmonize Stability and Plasticity in Continual Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00477</link>
   <description>We introduce Flashback Learning (FL), a novel method designed to harmonize the stability and plasticity of models in Continual Learning (CL). Unlike prior approaches that primarily focus on regularizing model updates to preserve old information while learning new concepts, FL explicitly balances this trade-off through a bidirectional form of regularization. This approach effectively guides the model to swiftly incorporate new knowledge while actively retaining its old knowledge. FL operates through a two-phase training process and can be seamlessly integrated into various CL methods, including replay, parameter regularization, distillation, and dynamic architecture techniques. In designing FL, we use two distinct knowledge bases: one to enhance plasticity and another to improve stability. FL ensures a more balanced model by utilizing both knowledge bases to regularize model updates. Theoretically, we analyze how the FL mechanism enhances the stability-plasticity balance. Empirically, FL demonstrates tangible improvements over baseline methods within the same training budget. By integrating FL into at least one representative baseline from each CL category, we observed an average accuracy improvement of up to 4.91% in Class-Incremental and 3.51% in Task-Incremental settings on standard image classification benchmarks. Additionally, measurements of the stability-to-plasticity ratio confirm that FL effectively enhances this balance. FL also outperforms state-of-the-art CL methods on more challenging datasets like ImageNet.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00477v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Leila Mahmoodi, Peyman Moghadam, Munawar Hayat, Christian Simon, Mehrtash Harandi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated learning framework for collaborative remaining useful life prognostics: an aircraft engine case study</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00499</link>
   <description>Complex systems such as aircraft engines are continuously monitored by sensors. In predictive aircraft maintenance, the collected sensor measurements are used to estimate the health condition and the Remaining Useful Life (RUL) of such systems. However, a major challenge when developing prognostics is the limited number of run-to-failure data samples. This challenge could be overcome if multiple airlines would share their run-to-failure data samples such that sufficient learning can be achieved. Due to privacy concerns, however, airlines are reluctant to share their data in a centralized setting. In this paper, a collaborative federated learning framework is therefore developed instead. Here, several airlines cooperate to train a collective RUL prognostic machine learning model, without the need to centrally share their data. For this, a decentralized validation procedure is proposed to validate the prognostics model without sharing any data. Moreover, sensor data is often noisy and of low quality. This paper therefore proposes four novel methods to aggregate the parameters of the global prognostic model. These methods enhance the robustness of the FL framework against noisy data. The proposed framework is illustrated for training a collaborative RUL prognostic model for aircraft engines, using the N-CMAPSS dataset. Here, six airlines are considered, that collaborate in the FL framework to train a collective RUL prognostic model for their aircraft's engines. When comparing the proposed FL framework with the case where each airline independently develops their own prognostic model, the results show that FL leads to more accurate RUL prognostics for five out of the six airlines. Moreover, the novel robust aggregation methods render the FL framework robust to noisy data samples.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00499v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.ET</category>
   <category>cs.SY</category>
   <category>eess.SY</category>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Diogo Landau, Ingeborg de Pater, Mihaela Mitici, Nishant Saurabh</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Addressing the Collaboration Dilemma in Low-Data Federated Learning via Transient Sparsity</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00932</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) enables collaborative model training across decentralized clients while preserving data privacy, leveraging aggregated updates to build robust global models. However, this training paradigm faces significant challenges due to data heterogeneity and limited local datasets, which often impede effective collaboration. In such scenarios, we identify the Layer-wise Inertia Phenomenon in FL, wherein the middle layers of global model undergo minimal updates after early communication rounds, ultimately limiting the effectiveness of global aggregation. We demonstrate the presence of this phenomenon across a wide range of federated settings, spanning diverse datasets and architectures. To address this issue, we propose LIPS (Layer-wise Inertia Phenomenon with Sparsity), a simple yet effective method that periodically introduces transient sparsity to stimulate meaningful updates and empower global aggregation. Experiments demonstrate that LIPS effectively mitigates layer-wise inertia, enhances aggregation effectiveness, and improves overall performance in various FL scenarios. This work not only deepens the understanding of layer-wise learning dynamics in FL but also paves the way for more effective collaboration strategies in resource-constrained environments. Our code is publicly available at: https://github.com/QiaoXiao7282/LIPS.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00932v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Qiao Xiao, Boqian Wu, Andrey Poddubnyy, Elena Mocanu, Phuong H. Nguyen, Mykola Pechenizkiy, Decebal Constantin Mocanu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedRPCA: Enhancing Federated LoRA Aggregation Using Robust PCA</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01194</link>
   <description>LoRA has emerged as one of the most promising fine-tuning techniques, especially for federated learning (FL), since it significantly reduces communication and computation costs at resource-constrained clients. However, data heterogeneity remains a significant challenge for LoRA-based FL, and the conventional aggregation strategy based on FedAvg suffers from slow convergence and suboptimal accuracy. Motivated by recent advances in model merging, particularly Task Arithmetic, we explore the idea of aggregating client LoRA parameters using scaled averaging. We first observe that a naive application of Task Arithmetic is ineffective due to the high cosine similarity between client updates, indicating significant common knowledge in the updates across clients. To address this issue, we propose decomposing client LoRA updates via Robust Principal Component Analysis (Robust-PCA) into a common low-rank component and client-specific sparse components. Our proposed algorithm FedRPCA aggregates the low-rank components through averaging, consolidating common knowledge, and applies scaled averaging to the sparse components to amplify client-specific knowledge. We evaluate our approach across a variety of vision and language tasks and demonstrate that it achieves higher final accuracy and faster convergence compared to competing baselines.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.01194v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Divyansh Jhunjhunwala, Arian Raje, Madan Ravi Ganesh, Chaithanya Kumar Mummadi, Chaoqun Dong, Jiawei Zhou, Wan-Yi Lin, Gauri Joshi, Zhenzhen Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Compiler Optimization via LLM Reasoning for Efficient Model Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01374</link>
   <description>While model serving has unlocked unprecedented capabilities, the high cost of serving large-scale models continues to be a significant barrier to widespread accessibility and rapid innovation. Compiler optimizations have long driven substantial performance improvements, but existing compilers struggle with neural workloads due to the exponentially large and highly interdependent space of possible transformations. Although existing stochastic search techniques can be effective, they are often sample-inefficient and fail to leverage the structural context underlying compilation decisions. We set out to investigate the research question of whether reasoning with large language models (LLMs), without any retraining, can leverage the context-aware decision space of compiler optimization to significantly improve sample efficiency. To that end, we introduce a novel compilation framework (dubbed REASONING COMPILER) that formulates optimization as a sequential, context-aware decision process, guided by a large language model and structured Monte Carlo tree search (MCTS). The LLM acts as a proposal mechanism, suggesting hardware-aware transformations that reflect the current program state and accumulated performance feedback. Monte Carlo tree search (MCTS) incorporates the LLM-generated proposals to balance exploration and exploitation, facilitating structured, context-sensitive traversal of the expansive compiler optimization space. By achieving substantial speedups with markedly fewer samples than leading neural compilers, our approach demonstrates the potential of LLM-guided reasoning to transform the landscape of compiler optimization.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.01374v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.PL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sujun Tang, Christopher Priebe, Rohan Mahapatra, Lianhui Qin, Hadi Esmaeilzadeh</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Gaussian Mixture Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01780</link>
   <description>This paper introduces FedGenGMM, a novel one-shot federated learning approach for Gaussian Mixture Models (GMM) tailored for unsupervised learning scenarios. In federated learning (FL), where multiple decentralized clients collaboratively train models without sharing raw data, significant challenges include statistical heterogeneity, high communication costs, and privacy concerns. FedGenGMM addresses these issues by allowing local GMM models, trained independently on client devices, to be aggregated through a single communication round. This approach leverages the generative property of GMMs, enabling the creation of a synthetic dataset on the server side to train a global model efficiently. Evaluation across diverse datasets covering image, tabular, and time series data demonstrates that FedGenGMM consistently achieves performance comparable to non-federated and iterative federated methods, even under significant data heterogeneity. Additionally, FedGenGMM significantly reduces communication overhead, maintains robust performance in anomaly detection tasks, and offers flexibility in local model complexities, making it particularly suitable for edge computing environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.01780v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sophia Zhang Pettersson, Kuo-Yun Liang, Juan Carlos Andresen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Label-shift robust federated feature screening for high-dimensional classification</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00379</link>
   <description>Distributed and federated learning are important tools for high-dimensional classification of large datasets. To reduce computational costs and overcome the curse of dimensionality, feature screening plays a pivotal role in eliminating irrelevant features during data preprocessing. However, data heterogeneity, particularly label shifting across different clients, presents significant challenges for feature screening. This paper introduces a general framework that unifies existing screening methods and proposes a novel utility, label-shift robust federated feature screening (LR-FFS), along with its federated estimation procedure. The framework facilitates a uniform analysis of methods and systematically characterizes their behaviors under label shift conditions. Building upon this framework, LR-FFS leverages conditional distribution functions and expectations to address label shift without adding computational burdens and remains robust against model misspecification and outliers. Additionally, the federated procedure ensures computational efficiency and privacy protection while maintaining screening effectiveness comparable to centralized processing. We also provide a false discovery rate (FDR) control method for federated feature screening. Experimental results and theoretical analyses demonstrate LR-FFS's superior performance across diverse client environments, including those with varying class distributions, sample sizes, and missing categorical data.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00379v1</guid>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>stat.ME</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Qi Qin, Erbo Li, Xingxiang Li, Yifan Sun, Wu Wang, Chen Xu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>L3Cube-MahaEmotions: A Marathi Emotion Recognition Dataset with Synthetic Annotations using CoTR prompting and Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00863</link>
   <description>Emotion recognition in low-resource languages like Marathi remains challenging due to limited annotated data. We present L3Cube-MahaEmotions, a high-quality Marathi emotion recognition dataset with 11 fine-grained emotion labels. The training data is synthetically annotated using large language models (LLMs), while the validation and test sets are manually labeled to serve as a reliable gold-standard benchmark. Building on the MahaSent dataset, we apply the Chain-of-Translation (CoTR) prompting technique, where Marathi sentences are translated into English and emotion labeled via a single prompt. GPT-4 and Llama3-405B were evaluated, with GPT-4 selected for training data annotation due to superior label quality. We evaluate model performance using standard metrics and explore label aggregation strategies (e.g., Union, Intersection). While GPT-4 predictions outperform fine-tuned BERT models, BERT-based models trained on synthetic labels fail to surpass GPT-4. This highlights both the importance of high-quality human-labeled data and the inherent complexity of emotion recognition. An important finding of this work is that generic LLMs like GPT-4 and Llama3-405B generalize better than fine-tuned BERT for complex low-resource emotion recognition tasks. The dataset and model are shared publicly at https://github.com/l3cube-pune/MarathiNLP</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00863v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Nidhi Kowtal, Raviraj Joshi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Pre-Training and Personalized Fine-Tuning via Over-the-Air Federated Meta-Learning: Convergence-Generalization Trade-Offs</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11569</link>
   <description>For modern artificial intelligence (AI) applications such as large language models (LLMs), the training paradigm has recently shifted to pre-training followed by fine-tuning. Furthermore, owing to dwindling open repositories of data and thanks to efforts to democratize access to AI models, pre-training is expected to increasingly migrate from the current centralized deployments to federated learning (FL) implementations. Meta-learning provides a general framework in which pre-training and fine-tuning can be formalized. Meta-learning-based personalized FL (meta-pFL) moves beyond basic personalization by targeting generalization to new agents and tasks. This paper studies the generalization performance of meta-pFL for a wireless setting in which the agents participating in the pre-training phase, i.e., meta-learning, are connected via a shared wireless channel to the server. Adopting over-the-air computing, we study the trade-off between generalization to new agents and tasks, on the one hand, and convergence, on the other hand. The trade-off arises from the fact that channel impairments may enhance generalization, while degrading convergence. Extensive numerical results validate the theory.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2406.11569v4</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.IT</category>
   <category>eess.SP</category>
   <category>math.IT</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Haifeng Wen, Hong Xing, Osvaldo Simeone</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Learning with Dynamic Client Arrival and Departure: Convergence and Rapid Adaptation via Initial Model Construction</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05662</link>
   <description>Most federated learning (FL) approaches assume a fixed client set. However, real-world scenarios often involve clients dynamically joining or leaving the system based on their needs or interest in specific tasks. This dynamic setting introduces unique challenges: (1) the optimization objective evolves with the active client set, unlike traditional FL with a static objective; and (2) the current global model may no longer serve as an effective initialization for subsequent rounds, potentially hindering adaptation. To address these challenges, we first provide a convergence analysis under a non-convex loss with a dynamic client set, accounting for factors such as gradient noise, local training iterations, and data heterogeneity. Building on this analysis, we propose a model initialization algorithm that enables rapid adaptation to new client sets whenever clients join or leave the system. Our key idea is to compute a weighted average of previous global models, guided by gradient similarity, to prioritize models trained on data distributions that closely align with the current client set, thereby accelerating recovery from distribution shifts. This plug-and-play algorithm is designed to integrate seamlessly with existing FL methods, offering broad applicability in practice. Experimental results on diverse datasets including both image and text domains, varied label distributions, and multiple FL algorithms demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed approach across a range of scenarios.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.05662v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhan-Lun Chang, Dong-Jun Han, Seyyedali Hosseinalipour, Mung Chiang, Christopher G. Brinton</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Communication-Efficient and Tensorized Federated Fine-Tuning of Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13097</link>
   <description>Parameter-efficient fine-tuning (PEFT) methods typically assume that Large Language Models (LLMs) are trained on data from a single device or client. However, real-world scenarios often require fine-tuning these models on private data distributed across multiple devices. Federated Learning (FL) offers an appealing solution by preserving user privacy, as sensitive data remains on local devices during training. Nonetheless, integrating PEFT methods into FL introduces two main challenges: communication overhead and data heterogeneity. In this paper, we introduce FedTT and FedTT+, methods for adapting LLMs by integrating tensorized adapters into client-side models' encoder/decoder blocks. FedTT is versatile and can be applied to both cross-silo FL and large-scale cross-device FL. FedTT+, an extension of FedTT tailored for cross-silo FL, enhances robustness against data heterogeneity by adaptively freezing portions of tensor factors, further reducing the number of trainable parameters. Experiments on BERT and LLaMA models demonstrate that our proposed methods successfully address data heterogeneity challenges and perform on par or even better than existing federated PEFT approaches while achieving up to 10$\times$ reduction in communication cost.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.13097v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sajjad Ghiasvand, Yifan Yang, Zhiyu Xue, Mahnoosh Alizadeh, Zheng Zhang, Ramtin Pedarsani</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Multi-Continental Healthcare Modelling Using Blockchain-Enabled Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17933</link>
   <description>One of the biggest challenges of building artificial intelligence (AI) model in healthcare area is the data sharing. Since healthcare data is private, sensitive, and heterogeneous, collecting sufficient data for modelling is exhausted, costly, and sometimes impossible. In this paper, we propose a framework for global healthcare modelling using datasets from multi-continents (Europe, North America and Asia) while without sharing the local datasets, and choose glucose management as a study model to verify its effectiveness. Technically, blockchain-enabled federated learning is implemented with adaption to make it meet with the privacy and safety requirements of healthcare data, meanwhile rewards honest participation and penalize malicious activities using its on-chain incentive mechanism. Experimental results show that the proposed framework is effective, efficient, and privacy preserved. Its prediction accuracy is much better than the models trained from limited personal data and is similar to, and even slightly better than, the results from a centralized dataset. This work paves the way for international collaborations on healthcare projects, where additional data is crucial for reducing bias and providing benefits to humanity.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.17933v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Rui Sun, Zhipeng Wang, Hengrui Zhang, Ming Jiang, Yizhe Wen, Jiahao Sun, Erwu Liu, Kezhi Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Decentralized Low-Rank Fine-Tuning of Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15361</link>
   <description>While parameter-efficient fine-tuning (PEFT) techniques like Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA) offer computationally efficient adaptations of Large Language Models (LLMs), their practical deployment often assumes centralized data and training environments. However, real-world scenarios frequently involve distributed, privacy-sensitive datasets that require decentralized solutions. Federated learning (FL) addresses data privacy by coordinating model updates across clients, but it is typically based on centralized aggregation through a parameter server, which can introduce bottlenecks and communication constraints. Decentralized learning, in contrast, eliminates this dependency by enabling direct collaboration between clients, improving scalability and efficiency in distributed environments. Despite its advantages, decentralized LLM fine-tuning remains underexplored. In this work, we propose Dec-LoRA, a decentralized fine-tuning algorithm for LLMs based on LoRA. Through extensive experiments on BERT and LLaMA-2 models, we demonstrate that Dec-LoRA achieves performance comparable to centralized LoRA under various conditions, including data heterogeneity and quantization constraints. Additionally, we provide a rigorous theoretical guarantee proving the convergence of our algorithm to a stationary point for non-convex and smooth loss functions. These findings highlight the potential of Dec-LoRA for scalable LLM fine-tuning in decentralized environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.15361v4</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sajjad Ghiasvand, Mahnoosh Alizadeh, Ramtin Pedarsani</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>AtmosSci-Bench: Evaluating the Recent Advance of Large Language Model for Atmospheric Science</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01159</link>
   <description>The rapid advancements in large language models (LLMs), particularly in their reasoning capabilities, hold transformative potential for addressing complex challenges in atmospheric science. However, leveraging LLMs effectively in this domain requires a robust and comprehensive evaluation benchmark. Toward this end, we present AtmosSci-Bench, a novel benchmark designed to systematically assess LLM performance across five core categories of atmospheric science problems: hydrology, atmospheric dynamics, atmospheric physics, geophysics, and physical oceanography. AtmosSci-Bench features a dual-format design comprising both multiple-choice questions (MCQs) and open-ended questions (OEQs), enabling scalable automated evaluation alongside deeper analysis of conceptual understanding. We employ a template-based MCQ generation framework to create diverse, graduate-level problems with symbolic perturbation, while OEQs are used to probe open-ended reasoning. We conduct a comprehensive evaluation of representative LLMs, categorized into four groups: instruction-tuned models, advanced reasoning models, math-augmented models, and domain-specific climate models. Our analysis provides some interesting insights into the reasoning and problem-solving capabilities of LLMs in atmospheric science. We believe AtmosSci-Bench can serve as a critical step toward advancing LLM applications in climate service by offering a standard and rigorous evaluation framework. Our source codes are currently available at Our source codes are currently available at https://github.com/Relaxed-System-Lab/AtmosSci-Bench.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.01159v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chenyue Li, Wen Deng, Mengqian Lu, Binhang Yuan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>From Selection to Generation: A Survey of LLM-based Active Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11767</link>
   <description>Active Learning (AL) has been a powerful paradigm for improving model efficiency and performance by selecting the most informative data points for labeling and training. In recent active learning frameworks, Large Language Models (LLMs) have been employed not only for selection but also for generating entirely new data instances and providing more cost-effective annotations. Motivated by the increasing importance of high-quality data and efficient model training in the era of LLMs, we present a comprehensive survey on LLM-based Active Learning. We introduce an intuitive taxonomy that categorizes these techniques and discuss the transformative roles LLMs can play in the active learning loop. We further examine the impact of AL on LLM learning paradigms and its applications across various domains. Finally, we identify open challenges and propose future research directions. This survey aims to serve as an up-to-date resource for researchers and practitioners seeking to gain an intuitive understanding of LLM-based AL techniques and deploy them to new applications.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.11767v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yu Xia, Subhojyoti Mukherjee, Zhouhang Xie, Junda Wu, Xintong Li, Ryan Aponte, Hanjia Lyu, Joe Barrow, Hongjie Chen, Franck Dernoncourt, Branislav Kveton, Tong Yu, Ruiyi Zhang, Jiuxiang Gu, Nesreen K. Ahmed, Yu Wang, Xiang Chen, Hanieh Deilamsalehy, Sungchul Kim, Zhengmian Hu, Yue Zhao, Nedim Lipka, Seunghyun Yoon, Ting-Hao Kenneth Huang, Zichao Wang, Puneet Mathur, Soumyabrata Pal, Koyel Mukherjee, Zhehao Zhang, Namyong Park, Thien Huu Nguyen, Jiebo Luo, Ryan A. Rossi, Julian McAuley</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Tokens for Learning, Tokens for Unlearning: Mitigating Membership Inference Attacks in Large Language Models via Dual-Purpose Training</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19726</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) have become the backbone of modern natural language processing but pose privacy concerns about leaking sensitive training data. Membership inference attacks (MIAs), which aim to infer whether a sample is included in a model's training dataset, can serve as a foundation for broader privacy threats. Existing defenses designed for traditional classification models do not account for the sequential nature of text data. As a result, they either require significant computational resources or fail to effectively mitigate privacy risks in LLMs. In this work, we propose \methodname, a lightweight yet effective empirical privacy defense for protecting training data of language models by leveraging token-specific characteristics. By analyzing token dynamics during training, we propose a token selection strategy that categorizes tokens into hard tokens for learning and memorized tokens for unlearning. Subsequently, our training-phase defense optimizes a novel dual-purpose token-level loss to achieve a Pareto-optimal balance between utility and privacy. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our approach not only provides strong protection against MIAs but also improves language modeling performance by around 10\% across various LLM architectures and datasets compared to the baselines.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.19726v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Toan Tran, Ruixuan Liu, Li Xiong</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Leveraging Randomness in Model and Data Partitioning for Privacy Amplification</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03043</link>
   <description>We study how inherent randomness in the training process -- where each sample (or client in federated learning) contributes only to a randomly selected portion of training -- can be leveraged for privacy amplification. This includes (1) data partitioning, where a sample participates in only a subset of training iterations, and (2) model partitioning, where a sample updates only a subset of the model parameters. We apply our framework to model parallelism in federated learning, where each client updates a randomly selected subnetwork to reduce memory and computational overhead, and show that existing methods, e.g. model splitting or dropout, provide a significant privacy amplification gain not captured by previous privacy analysis techniques. Additionally, we introduce Balanced Iteration Subsampling, a new data partitioning method where each sample (or client) participates in a fixed number of training iterations. We show that this method yields stronger privacy amplification than Poisson (i.i.d.) sampling of data (or clients). Our results demonstrate that randomness in the training process, which is structured rather than i.i.d. and interacts with data in complex ways, can be systematically leveraged for significant privacy amplification.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.03043v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Andy Dong, Wei-Ning Chen, Ayfer Ozgur</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Understanding the Statistical Accuracy-Communication Trade-off in Personalized Federated Learning with Minimax Guarantees</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08934</link>
   <description>Personalized federated learning (PFL) offers a flexible framework for aggregating information across distributed clients with heterogeneous data. This work considers a personalized federated learning setting that simultaneously learns global and local models. While purely local training has no communication cost, collaborative learning among the clients can leverage shared knowledge to improve statistical accuracy, presenting an accuracy-communication trade-off in personalized federated learning. However, the theoretical analysis of how personalization quantitatively influences sample and algorithmic efficiency and their inherent trade-off is largely unexplored. This paper makes a contribution towards filling this gap, by providing a quantitative characterization of the personalization degree on the tradeoff. The results further offers theoretical insights for choosing the personalization degree. As a side contribution, we establish the minimax optimality in terms of statistical accuracy for a widely studied PFL formulation. The theoretical result is validated on both synthetic and real-world datasets and its generalizability is verified in a non-convex setting.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.08934v4</guid>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>math.ST</category>
   <category>stat.CO</category>
   <category>stat.TH</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xin Yu, Zelin He, Ying Sun, Lingzhou Xue, Runze Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Exploring Model Kinship for Merging Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12613</link>
   <description>Model merging has become one of the key technologies for enhancing the capabilities and efficiency of Large Language Models (LLMs). However, our understanding of the expected performance gains and principles when merging any two models remains limited. In this work, we introduce model kinship, the degree of similarity or relatedness between LLMs, analogous to biological evolution. With comprehensive empirical analysis, we find that there is a certain relationship between model kinship and the performance gains after model merging, which can help guide our selection of candidate models. Inspired by this, we propose a new model merging strategy: Top-k Greedy Merging with Model Kinship, which can yield better performance on benchmark datasets. Specifically, we discover that using model kinship as a criterion can assist us in continuously performing model merging, alleviating the degradation (local optima) in model evolution, whereas model kinship can serve as a guide to escape these traps. Code is available at https://github.com/zjunlp/ModelKinship.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.12613v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.MA</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yedi Hu, Yunzhi Yao, Shumin Deng, Huajun Chen, Ningyu Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Unified Solution to Diverse Heterogeneities in One-shot Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21119</link>
   <description>One-Shot Federated Learning (OSFL) restricts communication between the server and clients to a single round, significantly reducing communication costs and minimizing privacy leakage risks compared to traditional Federated Learning (FL), which requires multiple rounds of communication. However, existing OSFL frameworks remain vulnerable to distributional heterogeneity, as they primarily focus on model heterogeneity while neglecting data heterogeneity. To bridge this gap, we propose FedHydra, a unified, data-free, OSFL framework designed to effectively address both model and data heterogeneity. Unlike existing OSFL approaches, FedHydra introduces a novel two-stage learning mechanism. Specifically, it incorporates model stratification and heterogeneity-aware stratified aggregation to mitigate the challenges posed by both model and data heterogeneity. By this design, the data and model heterogeneity issues are simultaneously monitored from different aspects during learning. Consequently, FedHydra can effectively mitigate both issues by minimizing their inherent conflicts. We compared FedHydra with five SOTA baselines on four benchmark datasets. Experimental results show that our method outperforms the previous OSFL methods in both homogeneous and heterogeneous settings. The code is available at https://github.com/Jun-B0518/FedHydra.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.21119v3</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jun Bai, Yiliao Song, Di Wu, Atul Sajjanhar, Yong Xiang, Wei Zhou, Xiaohui Tao, Yan Li, Yue Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Survey of LLM $\times$ DATA</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18458</link>
   <description>The integration of large language model (LLM) and data management (DATA) is rapidly redefining both domains. In this survey, we comprehensively review the bidirectional relationships. On the one hand, DATA4LLM, spanning large-scale data processing, storage, and serving, feeds LLMs with high quality, diversity, and timeliness of data required for stages like pre-training, post-training, retrieval-augmented generation, and agentic workflows: (i) Data processing for LLMs includes scalable acquisition, deduplication, filtering, selection, domain mixing, and synthetic augmentation; (ii) Data Storage for LLMs focuses on efficient data and model formats, distributed and heterogeneous storage hierarchies, KV-cache management, and fault-tolerant checkpointing; (iii) Data serving for LLMs tackles challenges in RAG (e.g., knowledge post-processing), LLM inference (e.g., prompt compression, data provenance), and training strategies (e.g., data packing and shuffling). On the other hand, in LLM4DATA, LLMs are emerging as general-purpose engines for data management. We review recent advances in (i) data manipulation, including automatic data cleaning, integration, discovery; (ii) data analysis, covering reasoning over structured, semi-structured, and unstructured data, and (iii) system optimization (e.g., configuration tuning, query rewriting, anomaly diagnosis), powered by LLM techniques like retrieval-augmented prompting, task-specialized fine-tuning, and multi-agent collaboration.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.18458v3</guid>
   <category>cs.DB</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xuanhe Zhou, Junxuan He, Wei Zhou, Haodong Chen, Zirui Tang, Haoyu Zhao, Xin Tong, Guoliang Li, Youmin Chen, Jun Zhou, Zhaojun Sun, Binyuan Hui, Shuo Wang, Conghui He, Zhiyuan Liu, Jingren Zhou, Fan Wu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Pre-Training and Personalized Fine-Tuning via Over-the-Air Federated Meta-Learning: Convergence-Generalization Trade-Offs</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11569</link>
   <description>For modern artificial intelligence (AI) applications such as large language models (LLMs), the training paradigm has recently shifted to pre-training followed by fine-tuning. Furthermore, owing to dwindling open repositories of data and thanks to efforts to democratize access to AI models, pre-training is expected to increasingly migrate from the current centralized deployments to federated learning (FL) implementations. Meta-learning provides a general framework in which pre-training and fine-tuning can be formalized. Meta-learning-based personalized FL (meta-pFL) moves beyond basic personalization by targeting generalization to new agents and tasks. This paper studies the generalization performance of meta-pFL for a wireless setting in which the agents participating in the pre-training phase, i.e., meta-learning, are connected via a shared wireless channel to the server. Adopting over-the-air computing, we study the trade-off between generalization to new agents and tasks, on the one hand, and convergence, on the other hand. The trade-off arises from the fact that channel impairments may enhance generalization, while degrading convergence. Extensive numerical results validate the theory.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2406.11569v4</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.IT</category>
   <category>eess.SP</category>
   <category>math.IT</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Haifeng Wen, Hong Xing, Osvaldo Simeone</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Reliable Vertical Federated Learning Framework for Traffic State Estimation with Data Selection and Incentive Mechanisms</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01285</link>
   <description>Vertical Federated Learning (VFL)-based Traffic State Estimation (TSE) offers a promising approach for integrating vertically distributed traffic data from municipal authorities (MA) and mobility providers (MP) while safeguarding privacy. However, given the variations in MPs' data collection capabilities and the potential for MPs to underperform in data provision, we propose a reliable VFL-based TSE framework that ensures model reliability during training and operation. The proposed framework comprises two components: data provider selection and incentive mechanism design. Data provider selection is conducted in three stages to identify the most qualified MPs for VFL model training with the MA. First, the MA partitions the transportation network into road segments. Then, a mutual information (MI) model is trained for each segment to capture the relationship between data and labels. Finally, using a sampling strategy and the MI model, the MA assesses each MP's competence in data provision and selects the most qualified MP for each segment. For the incentive mechanism design, given the MA can leverage the MI mode to inspect the data quality of MP, we formulate the interaction between MA and MP as a supervision game model. Upon this, we devise a penalty-based incentive mechanism to inhibit the lazy probability of MP, thereby guaranteeing the utility of MA. Numerical simulation on real-world datasets showcased that our proposed framework augments the traffic flow and density prediction accuracy by 11.23\% and 23.15\% and elevates the utility of MA by 130$\sim$400\$ compared to the benchmark.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.01285v1</guid>
   <category>cs.GT</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zijun Zhan, Yaxian Dong, Daniel Mawunyo Doe, Yuqing Hu, Shuai Li, Shaohua Cao, Zhu Han</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated learning framework for collaborative remaining useful life prognostics: an aircraft engine case study</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00499</link>
   <description>Complex systems such as aircraft engines are continuously monitored by sensors. In predictive aircraft maintenance, the collected sensor measurements are used to estimate the health condition and the Remaining Useful Life (RUL) of such systems. However, a major challenge when developing prognostics is the limited number of run-to-failure data samples. This challenge could be overcome if multiple airlines would share their run-to-failure data samples such that sufficient learning can be achieved. Due to privacy concerns, however, airlines are reluctant to share their data in a centralized setting. In this paper, a collaborative federated learning framework is therefore developed instead. Here, several airlines cooperate to train a collective RUL prognostic machine learning model, without the need to centrally share their data. For this, a decentralized validation procedure is proposed to validate the prognostics model without sharing any data. Moreover, sensor data is often noisy and of low quality. This paper therefore proposes four novel methods to aggregate the parameters of the global prognostic model. These methods enhance the robustness of the FL framework against noisy data. The proposed framework is illustrated for training a collaborative RUL prognostic model for aircraft engines, using the N-CMAPSS dataset. Here, six airlines are considered, that collaborate in the FL framework to train a collective RUL prognostic model for their aircraft's engines. When comparing the proposed FL framework with the case where each airline independently develops their own prognostic model, the results show that FL leads to more accurate RUL prognostics for five out of the six airlines. Moreover, the novel robust aggregation methods render the FL framework robust to noisy data samples.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00499v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.ET</category>
   <category>cs.SY</category>
   <category>eess.SY</category>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Diogo Landau, Ingeborg de Pater, Mihaela Mitici, Nishant Saurabh</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>MultiHoax: A Dataset of Multi-hop False-Premise Questions</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00264</link>
   <description>As Large Language Models are increasingly deployed in high-stakes domains, their ability to detect false assumptions and reason critically is crucial for ensuring reliable outputs. False-premise questions (FPQs) serve as an important evaluation method by exposing cases where flawed assumptions lead to incorrect responses. While existing benchmarks focus on single-hop FPQs, real-world reasoning often requires multi-hop inference, where models must verify consistency across multiple reasoning steps rather than relying on surface-level cues. To address this gap, we introduce MultiHoax, a benchmark for evaluating LLMs' ability to handle false premises in complex, multi-step reasoning tasks. Our dataset spans seven countries and ten diverse knowledge categories, using Wikipedia as the primary knowledge source to enable factual reasoning across regions. Experiments reveal that state-of-the-art LLMs struggle to detect false premises across different countries, knowledge categories, and multi-hop reasoning types, highlighting the need for improved false premise detection and more robust multi-hop reasoning capabilities in LLMs.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00264v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mohammadamin Shafiei, Hamidreza Saffari, Nafise Sadat Moosavi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Emergent Abilities of Large Language Models under Continued Pretraining for Language Adaptation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00288</link>
   <description>Continued pretraining (CPT) is a popular approach to adapt existing large language models (LLMs) to new languages. When doing so, it is common practice to include a portion of English data in the mixture, but its role has not been carefully studied to date. In this work, we show that including English does not impact validation perplexity, yet it is critical for the emergence of downstream capabilities in the target language. We introduce a language-agnostic benchmark for in-context learning (ICL), which reveals catastrophic forgetting early on CPT when English is not included. This in turn damages the ability of the model to generalize to downstream prompts in the target language as measured by perplexity, even if it does not manifest in terms of accuracy until later in training, and can be tied to a big shift in the model parameters. Based on these insights, we introduce curriculum learning and exponential moving average (EMA) of weights as effective alternatives to mitigate the need for English. All in all, our work sheds light into the dynamics by which emergent abilities arise when doing CPT for language adaptation, and can serve as a foundation to design more effective methods in the future.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00288v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ahmed Elhady, Eneko Agirre, Mikel Artetxe</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Assortment of Attention Heads: Accelerating Federated PEFT with Head Pruning and Strategic Client Selection</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00743</link>
   <description>Parameter Efficient Fine-Tuning (PEFT) has become the de-facto approach in adapting Large Language Models (LLMs) for downstream tasks in Natural Language Processing. However, its adoption in privacy-preserving distributed learning frameworks, such as Federated Learning (FL), remains relatively limited. This is mainly due to challenges specific to FL, such as resource-constrained devices and diverse data distributions among clients. In this paper, we propose an efficient method to perform PEFT within the FL framework for Multi-Head Attention (MHA) based language models. We address the challenges through head pruning, a novel head-specific weighted aggregation mechanism, and a client selection strategy. Head pruning minimizes training complexity within the clients, guided by the importance score computed based on the confidence of the attention head. Weighted aggregation of heads ensures the global model captures crucial updates from diverse clients complementing our client selection strategy. We show results on the MultiNLI benchmark along with 20 Newsgroups, XL-Sum, and E2E NLG datasets. We use the MultiNLI dataset and T5-small model with LoRA as our PEFT method, attaining sparsity levels of up to 90%, resulting in a communication advantage of up to 1.8x and a reduction in training OPs of 3.9x while maintaining the accuracy drop under 2%.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00743v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yeshwanth Venkatesha, Souvik Kundu, Priyadarshini Panda</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>L3Cube-MahaEmotions: A Marathi Emotion Recognition Dataset with Synthetic Annotations using CoTR prompting and Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00863</link>
   <description>Emotion recognition in low-resource languages like Marathi remains challenging due to limited annotated data. We present L3Cube-MahaEmotions, a high-quality Marathi emotion recognition dataset with 11 fine-grained emotion labels. The training data is synthetically annotated using large language models (LLMs), while the validation and test sets are manually labeled to serve as a reliable gold-standard benchmark. Building on the MahaSent dataset, we apply the Chain-of-Translation (CoTR) prompting technique, where Marathi sentences are translated into English and emotion labeled via a single prompt. GPT-4 and Llama3-405B were evaluated, with GPT-4 selected for training data annotation due to superior label quality. We evaluate model performance using standard metrics and explore label aggregation strategies (e.g., Union, Intersection). While GPT-4 predictions outperform fine-tuned BERT models, BERT-based models trained on synthetic labels fail to surpass GPT-4. This highlights both the importance of high-quality human-labeled data and the inherent complexity of emotion recognition. An important finding of this work is that generic LLMs like GPT-4 and Llama3-405B generalize better than fine-tuned BERT for complex low-resource emotion recognition tasks. The dataset and model are shared publicly at https://github.com/l3cube-pune/MarathiNLP</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00863v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Nidhi Kowtal, Raviraj Joshi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FormFactory: An Interactive Benchmarking Suite for Multimodal Form-Filling Agents</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01520</link>
   <description>Online form filling is a common yet labor-intensive task involving extensive keyboard and mouse interactions. Despite the long-standing vision of automating this process with &quot;one click&quot;, existing tools remain largely rule-based and lack generalizable, generative capabilities. Recent advances in Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have enabled promising agents for GUI-related tasks in general-purpose scenarios. However, they struggle with the unique challenges of form filling, such as flexible layouts and the difficulty of aligning textual instructions with on-screen fields. To bridge this gap, we formally define the form-filling task and propose FormFactory, an interactive benchmarking suite comprising a web-based interface, backend evaluation module, and carefully constructed dataset. Our benchmark covers diverse real-world scenarios, incorporates various field formats, and simulates high-fidelity form interactions. We conduct a comprehensive evaluation of state-of-the-art MLLMs and observe that no model surpasses 5% accuracy, underscoring the inherent difficulty of the task. These findings also reveal significant limitations in current models' visual layout reasoning and field-value alignment abilities. We hope our benchmark can serve as a stepping stone for further research into robust, practical form-filling agents.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.01520v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Bobo Li, Yuheng Wang, Hao Fei, Juncheng Li, Wei Ji, Mong-Li Lee, Wynne Hsu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Statement-Tuning Enables Efficient Cross-lingual Generalization in Encoder-only Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01592</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) excel in zero-shot and few-shot tasks, but achieving similar performance with encoder-only models like BERT and RoBERTa has been challenging due to their architecture. However, encoders offer advantages such as lower computational and memory costs. Recent work adapts them for zero-shot generalization using Statement Tuning, which reformulates tasks into finite templates. We extend this approach to multilingual NLP, exploring whether encoders can achieve zero-shot cross-lingual generalization and serve as efficient alternatives to memory-intensive LLMs for low-resource languages. Our results show that state-of-the-art encoder models generalize well across languages, rivaling multilingual LLMs while being more efficient. We also analyze multilingual Statement Tuning dataset design, efficiency gains, and language-specific generalization, contributing to more inclusive and resource-efficient NLP models. We release our code and models.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.01592v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ahmed Elshabrawy, Thanh-Nhi Nguyen, Yeeun Kang, Lihan Feng, Annant Jain, Faadil Abdullah Shaikh, Jonibek Mansurov, Mohamed Fazli Mohamed Imam, Jesus-German Ortiz-Barajas, Rendi Chevi, Alham Fikri Aji</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Retrieval-Augmented Generation: A Comprehensive Survey of Architectures, Enhancements, and Robustness Frontiers</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00054</link>
   <description>Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) has emerged as a powerful paradigm to enhance large language models (LLMs) by conditioning generation on external evidence retrieved at inference time. While RAG addresses critical limitations of parametric knowledge storage-such as factual inconsistency and domain inflexibility-it introduces new challenges in retrieval quality, grounding fidelity, pipeline efficiency, and robustness against noisy or adversarial inputs. This survey provides a comprehensive synthesis of recent advances in RAG systems, offering a taxonomy that categorizes architectures into retriever-centric, generator-centric, hybrid, and robustness-oriented designs. We systematically analyze enhancements across retrieval optimization, context filtering, decoding control, and efficiency improvements, supported by comparative performance analyses on short-form and multi-hop question answering tasks. Furthermore, we review state-of-the-art evaluation frameworks and benchmarks, highlighting trends in retrieval-aware evaluation, robustness testing, and federated retrieval settings. Our analysis reveals recurring trade-offs between retrieval precision and generation flexibility, efficiency and faithfulness, and modularity and coordination. We conclude by identifying open challenges and future research directions, including adaptive retrieval architectures, real-time retrieval integration, structured reasoning over multi-hop evidence, and privacy-preserving retrieval mechanisms. This survey aims to consolidate current knowledge in RAG research and serve as a foundation for the next generation of retrieval-augmented language modeling systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00054v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chaitanya Sharma</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Self-Challenging Language Model Agents</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01716</link>
   <description>Large language models are quickly becoming the foundation for intelligent agents that are capable of using tools. However, training such agents is challenging because it requires human creation and annotation of a diverse set of tasks, tools, and evaluation criteria. In this paper, we propose the Self-Challenging framework for training an agent on high-quality tasks that are generated by itself. The agent first plays the role of challenger and generates a task after interacting with the given tools. The tasks take the form of a novel general class of problems termed Code-as-Task, which are defined by an instruction, a verification function and solution and failure cases which serve as tests, allowing to filter only for high-quality tasks. The agent then takes an executor role and trains on those tasks with reinforcement learning using the evaluation feedback as a reward. Evaluation on two existing multi-turn tool-use agent benchmarks, M3ToolEval and TauBench, shows the Self-Challenging framework achieves over a two-fold improvement in Llama-3.1-8B-Instruct, despite using only self-generated training data.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.01716v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yifei Zhou, Sergey Levine, Jason Weston, Xian Li, Sainbayar Sukhbaatar</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Exploring Model Kinship for Merging Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12613</link>
   <description>Model merging has become one of the key technologies for enhancing the capabilities and efficiency of Large Language Models (LLMs). However, our understanding of the expected performance gains and principles when merging any two models remains limited. In this work, we introduce model kinship, the degree of similarity or relatedness between LLMs, analogous to biological evolution. With comprehensive empirical analysis, we find that there is a certain relationship between model kinship and the performance gains after model merging, which can help guide our selection of candidate models. Inspired by this, we propose a new model merging strategy: Top-k Greedy Merging with Model Kinship, which can yield better performance on benchmark datasets. Specifically, we discover that using model kinship as a criterion can assist us in continuously performing model merging, alleviating the degradation (local optima) in model evolution, whereas model kinship can serve as a guide to escape these traps. Code is available at https://github.com/zjunlp/ModelKinship.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.12613v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.MA</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yedi Hu, Yunzhi Yao, Shumin Deng, Huajun Chen, Ningyu Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Beyond Examples: High-level Automated Reasoning Paradigm in In-Context Learning via MCTS</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18478</link>
   <description>In-context learning (ICL) enables large language models (LLMs) to perform downstream tasks through advanced prompting and high-quality demonstrations. However, traditional ICL paradigms encounter significant limitations in complex reasoning tasks, stemming primarily from their dependence on example quality and absence of explicit reasoning guidance. To address these challenges, we introduce HiAR-ICL, a **Hi**gh-level **A**utomated **R**easoning paradigm in **ICL** that shifts focus from specific examples to abstract reasoning patterns, thereby extending the conventional concept of &quot;context&quot; in ICL. Our approach begins by defining five atomic reasoning actions, upon which we employ Monte Carlo Tree Search to systematically construct high-level reasoning patterns. During inference, HiAR-ICL dynamically selects appropriate reasoning patterns based on problem attributes, providing explicit guidance for the model's reasoning process. Experiments demonstrate HiAR-ICL's effectiveness and efficiency: utilizing only 200 prior samples with Qwen2.5-7B-Instruct, our method achieves 80.6% accuracy on MATH and 62.5% on AMC, exceeding GPT-4o's 77.2% and 57.5%. Our approach enhances performance across models of varying sizes while generalizing effectively across domains. Further analysis reveals that HiAR-ICL can also serve as a plug-and-play inference method compatible with post-training techniques like GRPO. Code and data are available at https://github.com/jinyangwu/HiARICL.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2411.18478v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jinyang Wu, Mingkuan Feng, Shuai Zhang, Feihu Che, Zengqi Wen, Chonghua Liao, Jianhua Tao</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Enhancing LLM-based Hatred and Toxicity Detection with Meta-Toxic Knowledge Graph</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15268</link>
   <description>The rapid growth of social media platforms has raised significant concerns regarding online content toxicity. When Large Language Models (LLMs) are used for toxicity detection, two key challenges emerge: 1) the absence of domain-specific toxic knowledge leads to false negatives; 2) the excessive sensitivity of LLMs to toxic speech results in false positives, limiting freedom of speech. To address these issues, we propose a novel method called MetaTox, leveraging graph search on a meta-toxic knowledge graph to enhance hatred and toxicity detection. First, we construct a comprehensive meta-toxic knowledge graph by utilizing LLMs to extract toxic information through a three-step pipeline, with toxic benchmark datasets serving as corpora. Second, we query the graph via retrieval and ranking processes to supplement accurate, relevant toxic knowledge. Extensive experiments and in-depth case studies across multiple datasets demonstrate that our MetaTox significantly decreases the false positive rate while boosting overall toxicity detection performance. Our code is available at https://github.com/YiboZhao624/MetaTox.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.15268v4</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yibo Zhao, Jiapeng Zhu, Can Xu, Yao Liu, Xiang Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Are LLMs effective psychological assessors? Leveraging adaptive RAG for interpretable mental health screening through psychometric practice</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00982</link>
   <description>In psychological practices, standardized questionnaires serve as essential tools for assessing mental health through structured, clinically-validated questions (i.e., items). While social media platforms offer rich data for mental health screening, computational approaches often bypass these established clinical assessment tools in favor of black-box classification. We propose a novel questionnaire-guided screening framework that bridges psychological practice and computational methods through adaptive Retrieval-Augmented Generation (\textit{aRAG}). Our approach links unstructured social media content and standardized clinical assessments by retrieving relevant posts for each questionnaire item and using Large Language Models (LLMs) to complete validated psychological instruments. Our findings demonstrate two key advantages of questionnaire-guided screening: First, when completing the Beck Depression Inventory-II (BDI-II), our approach matches or outperforms state-of-the-art performance on Reddit-based benchmarks without requiring training data. Second, we show that guiding LLMs through standardized questionnaires can yield superior results compared to directly prompting them for depression screening, while also providing a more interpretable assessment by linking model outputs to clinically validated diagnostic criteria. Additionally, we show, as a proof-of-concept, how our questionnaire-based methodology can be extended to other mental conditions' screening, highlighting the promising role of LLMs as psychological assessors.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.00982v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Federico Ravenda, Seyed Ali Bahrainian, Andrea Raballo, Antonietta Mira, Noriko Kando</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Communication-Efficient and Tensorized Federated Fine-Tuning of Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13097</link>
   <description>Parameter-efficient fine-tuning (PEFT) methods typically assume that Large Language Models (LLMs) are trained on data from a single device or client. However, real-world scenarios often require fine-tuning these models on private data distributed across multiple devices. Federated Learning (FL) offers an appealing solution by preserving user privacy, as sensitive data remains on local devices during training. Nonetheless, integrating PEFT methods into FL introduces two main challenges: communication overhead and data heterogeneity. In this paper, we introduce FedTT and FedTT+, methods for adapting LLMs by integrating tensorized adapters into client-side models' encoder/decoder blocks. FedTT is versatile and can be applied to both cross-silo FL and large-scale cross-device FL. FedTT+, an extension of FedTT tailored for cross-silo FL, enhances robustness against data heterogeneity by adaptively freezing portions of tensor factors, further reducing the number of trainable parameters. Experiments on BERT and LLaMA models demonstrate that our proposed methods successfully address data heterogeneity challenges and perform on par or even better than existing federated PEFT approaches while achieving up to 10$\times$ reduction in communication cost.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.13097v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sajjad Ghiasvand, Yifan Yang, Zhiyu Xue, Mahnoosh Alizadeh, Zheng Zhang, Ramtin Pedarsani</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Safety at Scale: A Comprehensive Survey of Large Model Safety</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05206</link>
   <description>The rapid advancement of large models, driven by their exceptional abilities in learning and generalization through large-scale pre-training, has reshaped the landscape of Artificial Intelligence (AI). These models are now foundational to a wide range of applications, including conversational AI, recommendation systems, autonomous driving, content generation, medical diagnostics, and scientific discovery. However, their widespread deployment also exposes them to significant safety risks, raising concerns about robustness, reliability, and ethical implications. This survey provides a systematic review of current safety research on large models, covering Vision Foundation Models (VFMs), Large Language Models (LLMs), Vision-Language Pre-training (VLP) models, Vision-Language Models (VLMs), Diffusion Models (DMs), and large-model-based Agents. Our contributions are summarized as follows: (1) We present a comprehensive taxonomy of safety threats to these models, including adversarial attacks, data poisoning, backdoor attacks, jailbreak and prompt injection attacks, energy-latency attacks, data and model extraction attacks, and emerging agent-specific threats. (2) We review defense strategies proposed for each type of attacks if available and summarize the commonly used datasets and benchmarks for safety research. (3) Building on this, we identify and discuss the open challenges in large model safety, emphasizing the need for comprehensive safety evaluations, scalable and effective defense mechanisms, and sustainable data practices. More importantly, we highlight the necessity of collective efforts from the research community and international collaboration. Our work can serve as a useful reference for researchers and practitioners, fostering the ongoing development of comprehensive defense systems and platforms to safeguard AI models.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.05206v4</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xingjun Ma, Yifeng Gao, Yixu Wang, Ruofan Wang, Xin Wang, Ye Sun, Yifan Ding, Hengyuan Xu, Yunhao Chen, Yunhan Zhao, Hanxun Huang, Yige Li, Jiaming Zhang, Xiang Zheng, Yang Bai, Zuxuan Wu, Xipeng Qiu, Jingfeng Zhang, Yiming Li, Xudong Han, Haonan Li, Jun Sun, Cong Wang, Jindong Gu, Baoyuan Wu, Siheng Chen, Tianwei Zhang, Yang Liu, Mingming Gong, Tongliang Liu, Shirui Pan, Cihang Xie, Tianyu Pang, Yinpeng Dong, Ruoxi Jia, Yang Zhang, Shiqing Ma, Xiangyu Zhang, Neil Gong, Chaowei Xiao, Sarah Erfani, Tim Baldwin, Bo Li, Masashi Sugiyama, Dacheng Tao, James Bailey, Yu-Gang Jiang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>From Selection to Generation: A Survey of LLM-based Active Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11767</link>
   <description>Active Learning (AL) has been a powerful paradigm for improving model efficiency and performance by selecting the most informative data points for labeling and training. In recent active learning frameworks, Large Language Models (LLMs) have been employed not only for selection but also for generating entirely new data instances and providing more cost-effective annotations. Motivated by the increasing importance of high-quality data and efficient model training in the era of LLMs, we present a comprehensive survey on LLM-based Active Learning. We introduce an intuitive taxonomy that categorizes these techniques and discuss the transformative roles LLMs can play in the active learning loop. We further examine the impact of AL on LLM learning paradigms and its applications across various domains. Finally, we identify open challenges and propose future research directions. This survey aims to serve as an up-to-date resource for researchers and practitioners seeking to gain an intuitive understanding of LLM-based AL techniques and deploy them to new applications.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.11767v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yu Xia, Subhojyoti Mukherjee, Zhouhang Xie, Junda Wu, Xintong Li, Ryan Aponte, Hanjia Lyu, Joe Barrow, Hongjie Chen, Franck Dernoncourt, Branislav Kveton, Tong Yu, Ruiyi Zhang, Jiuxiang Gu, Nesreen K. Ahmed, Yu Wang, Xiang Chen, Hanieh Deilamsalehy, Sungchul Kim, Zhengmian Hu, Yue Zhao, Nedim Lipka, Seunghyun Yoon, Ting-Hao Kenneth Huang, Zichao Wang, Puneet Mathur, Soumyabrata Pal, Koyel Mukherjee, Zhehao Zhang, Namyong Park, Thien Huu Nguyen, Jiebo Luo, Ryan A. Rossi, Julian McAuley</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Tokens for Learning, Tokens for Unlearning: Mitigating Membership Inference Attacks in Large Language Models via Dual-Purpose Training</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19726</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) have become the backbone of modern natural language processing but pose privacy concerns about leaking sensitive training data. Membership inference attacks (MIAs), which aim to infer whether a sample is included in a model's training dataset, can serve as a foundation for broader privacy threats. Existing defenses designed for traditional classification models do not account for the sequential nature of text data. As a result, they either require significant computational resources or fail to effectively mitigate privacy risks in LLMs. In this work, we propose \methodname, a lightweight yet effective empirical privacy defense for protecting training data of language models by leveraging token-specific characteristics. By analyzing token dynamics during training, we propose a token selection strategy that categorizes tokens into hard tokens for learning and memorized tokens for unlearning. Subsequently, our training-phase defense optimizes a novel dual-purpose token-level loss to achieve a Pareto-optimal balance between utility and privacy. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our approach not only provides strong protection against MIAs but also improves language modeling performance by around 10\% across various LLM architectures and datasets compared to the baselines.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.19726v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Toan Tran, Ruixuan Liu, Li Xiong</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Survey of LLM $\times$ DATA</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18458</link>
   <description>The integration of large language model (LLM) and data management (DATA) is rapidly redefining both domains. In this survey, we comprehensively review the bidirectional relationships. On the one hand, DATA4LLM, spanning large-scale data processing, storage, and serving, feeds LLMs with high quality, diversity, and timeliness of data required for stages like pre-training, post-training, retrieval-augmented generation, and agentic workflows: (i) Data processing for LLMs includes scalable acquisition, deduplication, filtering, selection, domain mixing, and synthetic augmentation; (ii) Data Storage for LLMs focuses on efficient data and model formats, distributed and heterogeneous storage hierarchies, KV-cache management, and fault-tolerant checkpointing; (iii) Data serving for LLMs tackles challenges in RAG (e.g., knowledge post-processing), LLM inference (e.g., prompt compression, data provenance), and training strategies (e.g., data packing and shuffling). On the other hand, in LLM4DATA, LLMs are emerging as general-purpose engines for data management. We review recent advances in (i) data manipulation, including automatic data cleaning, integration, discovery; (ii) data analysis, covering reasoning over structured, semi-structured, and unstructured data, and (iii) system optimization (e.g., configuration tuning, query rewriting, anomaly diagnosis), powered by LLM techniques like retrieval-augmented prompting, task-specialized fine-tuning, and multi-agent collaboration.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.18458v3</guid>
   <category>cs.DB</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xuanhe Zhou, Junxuan He, Wei Zhou, Haodong Chen, Zirui Tang, Haoyu Zhao, Xin Tong, Guoliang Li, Youmin Chen, Jun Zhou, Zhaojun Sun, Binyuan Hui, Shuo Wang, Conghui He, Zhiyuan Liu, Jingren Zhou, Fan Wu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Unlocking Personalized Knowledge in Federated Large Language Model: The Power of Mixture of Experts</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00965</link>
   <description>The Mixture of Experts (MoE) architecture has emerged as a prominent strategy for scaling large language models (LLMs), effectively leveraging sparse activation and facilitating task-specific personalization. However, current federated learning (FL) approaches are primarily designed for dense models, making them unable to directly exploit the sparsity inherent in MoE architectures. Treating MoE models as dense networks in federated scenarios results in excessive communication overhead and computational costs, undermining the potential for personalized knowledge sharing. To address these challenges, we propose FLEx (Federated LLMs with Personalized Experts), a novel federated learning framework explicitly tailored for MoE-based LLMs. FLEx efficiently personalizes by pruning the global MoE model to keep only one expert per client, and employs an adaptive gating mechanism to reintegrate these personalized experts into the pre-trained MoE layers, ensuring the original backbone architecture remains unchanged. These personalized experts are trained with local data and stored locally on each client, while the shared modules are aggregated globally. Extensive evaluations on diverse instruction-based datasets under non-IID conditions consistently demonstrate that FLEx outperforms existing federated baselines. Our code is available at https://anonymous.4open.science/r/FLEx-8F12.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00965v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Fan Liu, Bikang Pan, Zhongyi Wang, Xi Yao, Xiaoying Tang, Jingya Wang, Ye Shi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Self-Challenging Language Model Agents</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01716</link>
   <description>Large language models are quickly becoming the foundation for intelligent agents that are capable of using tools. However, training such agents is challenging because it requires human creation and annotation of a diverse set of tasks, tools, and evaluation criteria. In this paper, we propose the Self-Challenging framework for training an agent on high-quality tasks that are generated by itself. The agent first plays the role of challenger and generates a task after interacting with the given tools. The tasks take the form of a novel general class of problems termed Code-as-Task, which are defined by an instruction, a verification function and solution and failure cases which serve as tests, allowing to filter only for high-quality tasks. The agent then takes an executor role and trains on those tasks with reinforcement learning using the evaluation feedback as a reward. Evaluation on two existing multi-turn tool-use agent benchmarks, M3ToolEval and TauBench, shows the Self-Challenging framework achieves over a two-fold improvement in Llama-3.1-8B-Instruct, despite using only self-generated training data.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.01716v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yifei Zhou, Sergey Levine, Jason Weston, Xian Li, Sainbayar Sukhbaatar</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Emergent Abilities of Large Language Models under Continued Pretraining for Language Adaptation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00288</link>
   <description>Continued pretraining (CPT) is a popular approach to adapt existing large language models (LLMs) to new languages. When doing so, it is common practice to include a portion of English data in the mixture, but its role has not been carefully studied to date. In this work, we show that including English does not impact validation perplexity, yet it is critical for the emergence of downstream capabilities in the target language. We introduce a language-agnostic benchmark for in-context learning (ICL), which reveals catastrophic forgetting early on CPT when English is not included. This in turn damages the ability of the model to generalize to downstream prompts in the target language as measured by perplexity, even if it does not manifest in terms of accuracy until later in training, and can be tied to a big shift in the model parameters. Based on these insights, we introduce curriculum learning and exponential moving average (EMA) of weights as effective alternatives to mitigate the need for English. All in all, our work sheds light into the dynamics by which emergent abilities arise when doing CPT for language adaptation, and can serve as a foundation to design more effective methods in the future.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00288v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ahmed Elhady, Eneko Agirre, Mikel Artetxe</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Assortment of Attention Heads: Accelerating Federated PEFT with Head Pruning and Strategic Client Selection</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00743</link>
   <description>Parameter Efficient Fine-Tuning (PEFT) has become the de-facto approach in adapting Large Language Models (LLMs) for downstream tasks in Natural Language Processing. However, its adoption in privacy-preserving distributed learning frameworks, such as Federated Learning (FL), remains relatively limited. This is mainly due to challenges specific to FL, such as resource-constrained devices and diverse data distributions among clients. In this paper, we propose an efficient method to perform PEFT within the FL framework for Multi-Head Attention (MHA) based language models. We address the challenges through head pruning, a novel head-specific weighted aggregation mechanism, and a client selection strategy. Head pruning minimizes training complexity within the clients, guided by the importance score computed based on the confidence of the attention head. Weighted aggregation of heads ensures the global model captures crucial updates from diverse clients complementing our client selection strategy. We show results on the MultiNLI benchmark along with 20 Newsgroups, XL-Sum, and E2E NLG datasets. We use the MultiNLI dataset and T5-small model with LoRA as our PEFT method, attaining sparsity levels of up to 90%, resulting in a communication advantage of up to 1.8x and a reduction in training OPs of 3.9x while maintaining the accuracy drop under 2%.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00743v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yeshwanth Venkatesha, Souvik Kundu, Priyadarshini Panda</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Compiler Optimization via LLM Reasoning for Efficient Model Serving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01374</link>
   <description>While model serving has unlocked unprecedented capabilities, the high cost of serving large-scale models continues to be a significant barrier to widespread accessibility and rapid innovation. Compiler optimizations have long driven substantial performance improvements, but existing compilers struggle with neural workloads due to the exponentially large and highly interdependent space of possible transformations. Although existing stochastic search techniques can be effective, they are often sample-inefficient and fail to leverage the structural context underlying compilation decisions. We set out to investigate the research question of whether reasoning with large language models (LLMs), without any retraining, can leverage the context-aware decision space of compiler optimization to significantly improve sample efficiency. To that end, we introduce a novel compilation framework (dubbed REASONING COMPILER) that formulates optimization as a sequential, context-aware decision process, guided by a large language model and structured Monte Carlo tree search (MCTS). The LLM acts as a proposal mechanism, suggesting hardware-aware transformations that reflect the current program state and accumulated performance feedback. Monte Carlo tree search (MCTS) incorporates the LLM-generated proposals to balance exploration and exploitation, facilitating structured, context-sensitive traversal of the expansive compiler optimization space. By achieving substantial speedups with markedly fewer samples than leading neural compilers, our approach demonstrates the potential of LLM-guided reasoning to transform the landscape of compiler optimization.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.01374v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.PL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sujun Tang, Christopher Priebe, Rohan Mahapatra, Lianhui Qin, Hadi Esmaeilzadeh</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>SeePhys: Does Seeing Help Thinking? -- Benchmarking Vision-Based Physics Reasoning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19099</link>
   <description>We present SeePhys, a large-scale multimodal benchmark for LLM reasoning grounded in physics questions ranging from middle school to PhD qualifying exams. The benchmark covers 7 fundamental domains spanning the physics discipline, incorporating 21 categories of highly heterogeneous diagrams. In contrast to prior works where visual elements mainly serve auxiliary purposes, our benchmark features a substantial proportion of vision-essential problems (75%) that mandate visual information extraction for correct solutions. Through extensive evaluation, we observe that even the most advanced visual reasoning models (e.g., Gemini-2.5-pro and o4-mini) achieve sub-60% accuracy on our benchmark. These results reveal fundamental challenges in current large language models' visual understanding capabilities, particularly in: (i) establishing rigorous coupling between diagram interpretation and physics reasoning, and (ii) overcoming their persistent reliance on textual cues as cognitive shortcuts.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.19099v3</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>physics.ed-ph</category>
   <category>physics.pop-ph</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kun Xiang, Heng Li, Terry Jingchen Zhang, Yinya Huang, Zirong Liu, Peixin Qu, Jixi He, Jiaqi Chen, Yu-Jie Yuan, Jianhua Han, Hang Xu, Hanhui Li, Mrinmaya Sachan, Xiaodan Liang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>OrgAccess: A Benchmark for Role Based Access Control in Organization Scale LLMs</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19165</link>
   <description>Role-based access control (RBAC) and hierarchical structures are foundational to how information flows and decisions are made within virtually all organizations. As the potential of Large Language Models (LLMs) to serve as unified knowledge repositories and intelligent assistants in enterprise settings becomes increasingly apparent, a critical, yet under explored, challenge emerges: \textit{can these models reliably understand and operate within the complex, often nuanced, constraints imposed by organizational hierarchies and associated permissions?} Evaluating this crucial capability is inherently difficult due to the proprietary and sensitive nature of real-world corporate data and access control policies. We introduce a synthetic yet representative \textbf{OrgAccess} benchmark consisting of 40 distinct types of permissions commonly relevant across different organizational roles and levels. We further create three types of permissions: 40,000 easy (1 permission), 10,000 medium (3-permissions tuple), and 20,000 hard (5-permissions tuple) to test LLMs' ability to accurately assess these permissions and generate responses that strictly adhere to the specified hierarchical rules, particularly in scenarios involving users with overlapping or conflicting permissions. Our findings reveal that even state-of-the-art LLMs struggle significantly to maintain compliance with role-based structures, even with explicit instructions, with their performance degrades further when navigating interactions involving two or more conflicting permissions. Specifically, even \textbf{GPT-4.1 only achieves an F1-Score of 0.27 on our hardest benchmark}. This demonstrates a critical limitation in LLMs' complex rule following and compositional reasoning capabilities beyond standard factual or STEM-based benchmarks, opening up a new paradigm for evaluating their fitness for practical, structured environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.19165v2</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Debdeep Sanyal, Umakanta Maharana, Yash Sinha, Hong Ming Tan, Shirish Karande, Mohan Kankanhalli, Murari Mandal</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Exploring Model Kinship for Merging Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12613</link>
   <description>Model merging has become one of the key technologies for enhancing the capabilities and efficiency of Large Language Models (LLMs). However, our understanding of the expected performance gains and principles when merging any two models remains limited. In this work, we introduce model kinship, the degree of similarity or relatedness between LLMs, analogous to biological evolution. With comprehensive empirical analysis, we find that there is a certain relationship between model kinship and the performance gains after model merging, which can help guide our selection of candidate models. Inspired by this, we propose a new model merging strategy: Top-k Greedy Merging with Model Kinship, which can yield better performance on benchmark datasets. Specifically, we discover that using model kinship as a criterion can assist us in continuously performing model merging, alleviating the degradation (local optima) in model evolution, whereas model kinship can serve as a guide to escape these traps. Code is available at https://github.com/zjunlp/ModelKinship.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.12613v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.MA</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yedi Hu, Yunzhi Yao, Shumin Deng, Huajun Chen, Ningyu Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Multi-Continental Healthcare Modelling Using Blockchain-Enabled Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17933</link>
   <description>One of the biggest challenges of building artificial intelligence (AI) model in healthcare area is the data sharing. Since healthcare data is private, sensitive, and heterogeneous, collecting sufficient data for modelling is exhausted, costly, and sometimes impossible. In this paper, we propose a framework for global healthcare modelling using datasets from multi-continents (Europe, North America and Asia) while without sharing the local datasets, and choose glucose management as a study model to verify its effectiveness. Technically, blockchain-enabled federated learning is implemented with adaption to make it meet with the privacy and safety requirements of healthcare data, meanwhile rewards honest participation and penalize malicious activities using its on-chain incentive mechanism. Experimental results show that the proposed framework is effective, efficient, and privacy preserved. Its prediction accuracy is much better than the models trained from limited personal data and is similar to, and even slightly better than, the results from a centralized dataset. This work paves the way for international collaborations on healthcare projects, where additional data is crucial for reducing bias and providing benefits to humanity.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.17933v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Rui Sun, Zhipeng Wang, Hengrui Zhang, Ming Jiang, Yizhe Wen, Jiahao Sun, Erwu Liu, Kezhi Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Enhancing LLM-based Hatred and Toxicity Detection with Meta-Toxic Knowledge Graph</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15268</link>
   <description>The rapid growth of social media platforms has raised significant concerns regarding online content toxicity. When Large Language Models (LLMs) are used for toxicity detection, two key challenges emerge: 1) the absence of domain-specific toxic knowledge leads to false negatives; 2) the excessive sensitivity of LLMs to toxic speech results in false positives, limiting freedom of speech. To address these issues, we propose a novel method called MetaTox, leveraging graph search on a meta-toxic knowledge graph to enhance hatred and toxicity detection. First, we construct a comprehensive meta-toxic knowledge graph by utilizing LLMs to extract toxic information through a three-step pipeline, with toxic benchmark datasets serving as corpora. Second, we query the graph via retrieval and ranking processes to supplement accurate, relevant toxic knowledge. Extensive experiments and in-depth case studies across multiple datasets demonstrate that our MetaTox significantly decreases the false positive rate while boosting overall toxicity detection performance. Our code is available at https://github.com/YiboZhao624/MetaTox.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.15268v4</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yibo Zhao, Jiapeng Zhu, Can Xu, Yao Liu, Xiang Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Are LLMs effective psychological assessors? Leveraging adaptive RAG for interpretable mental health screening through psychometric practice</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00982</link>
   <description>In psychological practices, standardized questionnaires serve as essential tools for assessing mental health through structured, clinically-validated questions (i.e., items). While social media platforms offer rich data for mental health screening, computational approaches often bypass these established clinical assessment tools in favor of black-box classification. We propose a novel questionnaire-guided screening framework that bridges psychological practice and computational methods through adaptive Retrieval-Augmented Generation (\textit{aRAG}). Our approach links unstructured social media content and standardized clinical assessments by retrieving relevant posts for each questionnaire item and using Large Language Models (LLMs) to complete validated psychological instruments. Our findings demonstrate two key advantages of questionnaire-guided screening: First, when completing the Beck Depression Inventory-II (BDI-II), our approach matches or outperforms state-of-the-art performance on Reddit-based benchmarks without requiring training data. Second, we show that guiding LLMs through standardized questionnaires can yield superior results compared to directly prompting them for depression screening, while also providing a more interpretable assessment by linking model outputs to clinically validated diagnostic criteria. Additionally, we show, as a proof-of-concept, how our questionnaire-based methodology can be extended to other mental conditions' screening, highlighting the promising role of LLMs as psychological assessors.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2501.00982v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Federico Ravenda, Seyed Ali Bahrainian, Andrea Raballo, Antonietta Mira, Noriko Kando</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>AtmosSci-Bench: Evaluating the Recent Advance of Large Language Model for Atmospheric Science</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01159</link>
   <description>The rapid advancements in large language models (LLMs), particularly in their reasoning capabilities, hold transformative potential for addressing complex challenges in atmospheric science. However, leveraging LLMs effectively in this domain requires a robust and comprehensive evaluation benchmark. Toward this end, we present AtmosSci-Bench, a novel benchmark designed to systematically assess LLM performance across five core categories of atmospheric science problems: hydrology, atmospheric dynamics, atmospheric physics, geophysics, and physical oceanography. AtmosSci-Bench features a dual-format design comprising both multiple-choice questions (MCQs) and open-ended questions (OEQs), enabling scalable automated evaluation alongside deeper analysis of conceptual understanding. We employ a template-based MCQ generation framework to create diverse, graduate-level problems with symbolic perturbation, while OEQs are used to probe open-ended reasoning. We conduct a comprehensive evaluation of representative LLMs, categorized into four groups: instruction-tuned models, advanced reasoning models, math-augmented models, and domain-specific climate models. Our analysis provides some interesting insights into the reasoning and problem-solving capabilities of LLMs in atmospheric science. We believe AtmosSci-Bench can serve as a critical step toward advancing LLM applications in climate service by offering a standard and rigorous evaluation framework. Our source codes are currently available at Our source codes are currently available at https://github.com/Relaxed-System-Lab/AtmosSci-Bench.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.01159v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chenyue Li, Wen Deng, Mengqian Lu, Binhang Yuan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Safety at Scale: A Comprehensive Survey of Large Model Safety</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05206</link>
   <description>The rapid advancement of large models, driven by their exceptional abilities in learning and generalization through large-scale pre-training, has reshaped the landscape of Artificial Intelligence (AI). These models are now foundational to a wide range of applications, including conversational AI, recommendation systems, autonomous driving, content generation, medical diagnostics, and scientific discovery. However, their widespread deployment also exposes them to significant safety risks, raising concerns about robustness, reliability, and ethical implications. This survey provides a systematic review of current safety research on large models, covering Vision Foundation Models (VFMs), Large Language Models (LLMs), Vision-Language Pre-training (VLP) models, Vision-Language Models (VLMs), Diffusion Models (DMs), and large-model-based Agents. Our contributions are summarized as follows: (1) We present a comprehensive taxonomy of safety threats to these models, including adversarial attacks, data poisoning, backdoor attacks, jailbreak and prompt injection attacks, energy-latency attacks, data and model extraction attacks, and emerging agent-specific threats. (2) We review defense strategies proposed for each type of attacks if available and summarize the commonly used datasets and benchmarks for safety research. (3) Building on this, we identify and discuss the open challenges in large model safety, emphasizing the need for comprehensive safety evaluations, scalable and effective defense mechanisms, and sustainable data practices. More importantly, we highlight the necessity of collective efforts from the research community and international collaboration. Our work can serve as a useful reference for researchers and practitioners, fostering the ongoing development of comprehensive defense systems and platforms to safeguard AI models.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.05206v4</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xingjun Ma, Yifeng Gao, Yixu Wang, Ruofan Wang, Xin Wang, Ye Sun, Yifan Ding, Hengyuan Xu, Yunhao Chen, Yunhan Zhao, Hanxun Huang, Yige Li, Jiaming Zhang, Xiang Zheng, Yang Bai, Zuxuan Wu, Xipeng Qiu, Jingfeng Zhang, Yiming Li, Xudong Han, Haonan Li, Jun Sun, Cong Wang, Jindong Gu, Baoyuan Wu, Siheng Chen, Tianwei Zhang, Yang Liu, Mingming Gong, Tongliang Liu, Shirui Pan, Cihang Xie, Tianyu Pang, Yinpeng Dong, Ruoxi Jia, Yang Zhang, Shiqing Ma, Xiangyu Zhang, Neil Gong, Chaowei Xiao, Sarah Erfani, Tim Baldwin, Bo Li, Masashi Sugiyama, Dacheng Tao, James Bailey, Yu-Gang Jiang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Survey of LLM $\times$ DATA</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18458</link>
   <description>The integration of large language model (LLM) and data management (DATA) is rapidly redefining both domains. In this survey, we comprehensively review the bidirectional relationships. On the one hand, DATA4LLM, spanning large-scale data processing, storage, and serving, feeds LLMs with high quality, diversity, and timeliness of data required for stages like pre-training, post-training, retrieval-augmented generation, and agentic workflows: (i) Data processing for LLMs includes scalable acquisition, deduplication, filtering, selection, domain mixing, and synthetic augmentation; (ii) Data Storage for LLMs focuses on efficient data and model formats, distributed and heterogeneous storage hierarchies, KV-cache management, and fault-tolerant checkpointing; (iii) Data serving for LLMs tackles challenges in RAG (e.g., knowledge post-processing), LLM inference (e.g., prompt compression, data provenance), and training strategies (e.g., data packing and shuffling). On the other hand, in LLM4DATA, LLMs are emerging as general-purpose engines for data management. We review recent advances in (i) data manipulation, including automatic data cleaning, integration, discovery; (ii) data analysis, covering reasoning over structured, semi-structured, and unstructured data, and (iii) system optimization (e.g., configuration tuning, query rewriting, anomaly diagnosis), powered by LLM techniques like retrieval-augmented prompting, task-specialized fine-tuning, and multi-agent collaboration.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.18458v3</guid>
   <category>cs.DB</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xuanhe Zhou, Junxuan He, Wei Zhou, Haodong Chen, Zirui Tang, Haoyu Zhao, Xin Tong, Guoliang Li, Youmin Chen, Jun Zhou, Zhaojun Sun, Binyuan Hui, Shuo Wang, Conghui He, Zhiyuan Liu, Jingren Zhou, Fan Wu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>SysLLMatic: Large Language Models are Software System Optimizers</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01249</link>
   <description>Automatic software system optimization can improve software speed, reduce operating costs, and save energy. Traditional approaches to optimization rely on manual tuning and compiler heuristics, limiting their ability to generalize across diverse codebases and system contexts. Recent methods using Large Language Models (LLMs) offer automation to address these limitations, but often fail to scale to the complexity of real-world software systems and applications. We present SysLLMatic, a system that integrates LLMs with profiling-guided feedback and system performance insights to automatically optimize software code. We evaluate it on three benchmark suites: HumanEval_CPP (competitive programming in C++), SciMark2 (scientific kernels in Java), and DaCapoBench (large-scale software systems in Java). Results show that SysLLMatic can improve system performance, including latency, throughput, energy efficiency, memory usage, and CPU utilization. It consistently outperforms state-of-the-art LLM baselines on microbenchmarks. On large-scale application codes, it surpasses traditional compiler optimizations, achieving average relative improvements of 1.85x in latency and 2.24x in throughput. Our findings demonstrate that LLMs, guided by principled systems thinking and appropriate performance diagnostics, can serve as viable software system optimizers. We further identify limitations of our approach and the challenges involved in handling complex applications. This work provides a foundation for generating optimized code across various languages, benchmarks, and program sizes in a principled manner.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.01249v1</guid>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <category>cs.PF</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Huiyun Peng, Arjun Gupte, Ryan Hasler, Nicholas John Eliopoulos, Chien-Chou Ho, Rishi Mantri, Leo Deng, Konstantin L\&quot;aufer, George K. Thiruvathukal, James C. Davis</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Survey of LLM $\times$ DATA</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18458</link>
   <description>The integration of large language model (LLM) and data management (DATA) is rapidly redefining both domains. In this survey, we comprehensively review the bidirectional relationships. On the one hand, DATA4LLM, spanning large-scale data processing, storage, and serving, feeds LLMs with high quality, diversity, and timeliness of data required for stages like pre-training, post-training, retrieval-augmented generation, and agentic workflows: (i) Data processing for LLMs includes scalable acquisition, deduplication, filtering, selection, domain mixing, and synthetic augmentation; (ii) Data Storage for LLMs focuses on efficient data and model formats, distributed and heterogeneous storage hierarchies, KV-cache management, and fault-tolerant checkpointing; (iii) Data serving for LLMs tackles challenges in RAG (e.g., knowledge post-processing), LLM inference (e.g., prompt compression, data provenance), and training strategies (e.g., data packing and shuffling). On the other hand, in LLM4DATA, LLMs are emerging as general-purpose engines for data management. We review recent advances in (i) data manipulation, including automatic data cleaning, integration, discovery; (ii) data analysis, covering reasoning over structured, semi-structured, and unstructured data, and (iii) system optimization (e.g., configuration tuning, query rewriting, anomaly diagnosis), powered by LLM techniques like retrieval-augmented prompting, task-specialized fine-tuning, and multi-agent collaboration.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.18458v3</guid>
   <category>cs.DB</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xuanhe Zhou, Junxuan He, Wei Zhou, Haodong Chen, Zirui Tang, Haoyu Zhao, Xin Tong, Guoliang Li, Youmin Chen, Jun Zhou, Zhaojun Sun, Binyuan Hui, Shuo Wang, Conghui He, Zhiyuan Liu, Jingren Zhou, Fan Wu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Exploring Model Kinship for Merging Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12613</link>
   <description>Model merging has become one of the key technologies for enhancing the capabilities and efficiency of Large Language Models (LLMs). However, our understanding of the expected performance gains and principles when merging any two models remains limited. In this work, we introduce model kinship, the degree of similarity or relatedness between LLMs, analogous to biological evolution. With comprehensive empirical analysis, we find that there is a certain relationship between model kinship and the performance gains after model merging, which can help guide our selection of candidate models. Inspired by this, we propose a new model merging strategy: Top-k Greedy Merging with Model Kinship, which can yield better performance on benchmark datasets. Specifically, we discover that using model kinship as a criterion can assist us in continuously performing model merging, alleviating the degradation (local optima) in model evolution, whereas model kinship can serve as a guide to escape these traps. Code is available at https://github.com/zjunlp/ModelKinship.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.12613v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.MA</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yedi Hu, Yunzhi Yao, Shumin Deng, Huajun Chen, Ningyu Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated learning framework for collaborative remaining useful life prognostics: an aircraft engine case study</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00499</link>
   <description>Complex systems such as aircraft engines are continuously monitored by sensors. In predictive aircraft maintenance, the collected sensor measurements are used to estimate the health condition and the Remaining Useful Life (RUL) of such systems. However, a major challenge when developing prognostics is the limited number of run-to-failure data samples. This challenge could be overcome if multiple airlines would share their run-to-failure data samples such that sufficient learning can be achieved. Due to privacy concerns, however, airlines are reluctant to share their data in a centralized setting. In this paper, a collaborative federated learning framework is therefore developed instead. Here, several airlines cooperate to train a collective RUL prognostic machine learning model, without the need to centrally share their data. For this, a decentralized validation procedure is proposed to validate the prognostics model without sharing any data. Moreover, sensor data is often noisy and of low quality. This paper therefore proposes four novel methods to aggregate the parameters of the global prognostic model. These methods enhance the robustness of the FL framework against noisy data. The proposed framework is illustrated for training a collaborative RUL prognostic model for aircraft engines, using the N-CMAPSS dataset. Here, six airlines are considered, that collaborate in the FL framework to train a collective RUL prognostic model for their aircraft's engines. When comparing the proposed FL framework with the case where each airline independently develops their own prognostic model, the results show that FL leads to more accurate RUL prognostics for five out of the six airlines. Moreover, the novel robust aggregation methods render the FL framework robust to noisy data samples.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00499v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.ET</category>
   <category>cs.SY</category>
   <category>eess.SY</category>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Diogo Landau, Ingeborg de Pater, Mihaela Mitici, Nishant Saurabh</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
