<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 04:14:47 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 04:14:47 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>FedSlate:A Federated Deep Reinforcement Learning Recommender System</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14872</link>
   <description>Reinforcement learning methods have been used to optimize long-term user engagement in recommendation systems. However, existing reinforcement learning-based recommendation systems do not fully exploit the relevance of individual user behavior across different platforms. One potential solution is to aggregate data from various platforms in a centralized location and use the aggregated data for training. However, this approach raises economic and legal concerns, including increased communication costs and potential threats to user privacy. To address these challenges, we propose \textbf{FedSlate}, a federated reinforcement learning recommendation algorithm that effectively utilizes information that is prohibited from being shared at a legal level. We employ the SlateQ algorithm to assist FedSlate in learning users' long-term behavior and evaluating the value of recommended content. We extend the existing application scope of recommendation systems from single-user single-platform to single-user multi-platform and address cross-platform learning challenges by introducing federated learning. We use RecSim to construct a simulation environment for evaluating FedSlate and compare its performance with state-of-the-art benchmark recommendation models. Experimental results demonstrate the superior effects of FedSlate over baseline methods in various environmental settings, and FedSlate facilitates the learning of recommendation strategies in scenarios where baseline methods are completely inapplicable. Code is available at \textit{https://github.com/TianYaDY/FedSlate}.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2409.14872v2</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yongxin Deng, Xihe Qiu, Xiaoyu Tan, Yaochu Jin</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LLMs for Engineering: Teaching Models to Design High Powered Rockets</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19394</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) have transformed software engineering, but their application to physical engineering domains remains underexplored. This paper evaluates LLMs' capabilities in high-powered rocketry design through RocketBench, a benchmark connecting LLMs to high-fidelity rocket simulations. We test models on two increasingly complex design tasks: target altitude optimization and precision landing challenges. Our findings reveal that while state-of-the-art LLMs demonstrate strong baseline engineering knowledge, they struggle to iterate on their designs when given simulation results and ultimately plateau below human performance levels. However, when enhanced with reinforcement learning (RL), we show that a 7B parameter model outperforms both SoTA foundation models and human experts. This research demonstrates that RL-trained LLMs can serve as effective tools for complex engineering optimization, potentially transforming engineering domains beyond software development.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19394v1</guid>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Toby Simonds</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Calibrating Translation Decoding with Quality Estimation on LLMs</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19044</link>
   <description>Neural machine translation (NMT) systems typically employ maximum a posteriori (MAP) decoding to select the highest-scoring translation from the distribution mass. However, recent evidence highlights the inadequacy of MAP decoding, often resulting in low-quality or even pathological hypotheses -- the decoding objective is not aligned with real-world translation quality. This paper proposes calibrating hypothesis likelihoods with translation quality from a distribution view by directly optimizing their Pearson correlation -- thereby enhancing the effectiveness of translation decoding. With our method, translation on large language models (LLMs) improves substantially after limited training (2K instances per direction). This improvement is orthogonal to those achieved through supervised fine-tuning, leading to substantial gains across a broad range of metrics and human evaluations -- even when applied to top-performing translation-specialized LLMs fine-tuned on high-quality translation data, such as Tower, or when compared to recent preference optimization methods, like CPO. Moreover, the calibrated translation likelihood can directly serve as a strong proxy for translation quality, closely approximating or even surpassing some state-of-the-art translation quality estimation models, like CometKiwi. Lastly, our in-depth analysis demonstrates that calibration enhances the effectiveness of MAP decoding, thereby enabling greater efficiency in real-world deployment. The resulting state-of-the-art translation model, which covers 10 languages, along with the accompanying code and human evaluation data, has been released to the community: https://github.com/moore3930/calibrating-llm-mt.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19044v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Di Wu, Yibin Lei, Christof Monz</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Privacy-Preserving Federated Embedding Learning for Localized Retrieval-Augmented Generation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19101</link>
   <description>Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) has recently emerged as a promising solution for enhancing the accuracy and credibility of Large Language Models (LLMs), particularly in Question &amp; Answer tasks. This is achieved by incorporating proprietary and private data from integrated databases. However, private RAG systems face significant challenges due to the scarcity of private domain data and critical data privacy issues. These obstacles impede the deployment of private RAG systems, as developing privacy-preserving RAG systems requires a delicate balance between data security and data availability. To address these challenges, we regard federated learning (FL) as a highly promising technology for privacy-preserving RAG services. We propose a novel framework called Federated Retrieval-Augmented Generation (FedE4RAG). This framework facilitates collaborative training of client-side RAG retrieval models. The parameters of these models are aggregated and distributed on a central-server, ensuring data privacy without direct sharing of raw data. In FedE4RAG, knowledge distillation is employed for communication between the server and client models. This technique improves the generalization of local RAG retrievers during the federated learning process. Additionally, we apply homomorphic encryption within federated learning to safeguard model parameters and mitigate concerns related to data leakage. Extensive experiments conducted on the real-world dataset have validated the effectiveness of FedE4RAG. The results demonstrate that our proposed framework can markedly enhance the performance of private RAG systems while maintaining robust data privacy protection.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19101v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Qianren Mao, Qili Zhang, Hanwen Hao, Zhentao Han, Runhua Xu, Weifeng Jiang, Qi Hu, Zhijun Chen, Tyler Zhou, Bo Li, Yangqiu Song, Jin Dong, Jianxin Li, Philip S. Yu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>BRIDGE: Benchmarking Large Language Models for Understanding Real-world Clinical Practice Text</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19467</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) hold great promise for medical applications and are evolving rapidly, with new models being released at an accelerated pace. However, current evaluations of LLMs in clinical contexts remain limited. Most existing benchmarks rely on medical exam-style questions or PubMed-derived text, failing to capture the complexity of real-world electronic health record (EHR) data. Others focus narrowly on specific application scenarios, limiting their generalizability across broader clinical use. To address this gap, we present BRIDGE, a comprehensive multilingual benchmark comprising 87 tasks sourced from real-world clinical data sources across nine languages. We systematically evaluated 52 state-of-the-art LLMs (including DeepSeek-R1, GPT-4o, Gemini, and Llama 4) under various inference strategies. With a total of 13,572 experiments, our results reveal substantial performance variation across model sizes, languages, natural language processing tasks, and clinical specialties. Notably, we demonstrate that open-source LLMs can achieve performance comparable to proprietary models, while medically fine-tuned LLMs based on older architectures often underperform versus updated general-purpose models. The BRIDGE and its corresponding leaderboard serve as a foundational resource and a unique reference for the development and evaluation of new LLMs in real-world clinical text understanding.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19467v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jiageng Wu, Bowen Gu, Ren Zhou, Kevin Xie, Doug Snyder, Yixing Jiang, Valentina Carducci, Richard Wyss, Rishi J Desai, Emily Alsentzer, Leo Anthony Celi, Adam Rodman, Sebastian Schneeweiss, Jonathan H. Chen, Santiago Romero-Brufau, Kueiyu Joshua Lin, Jie Yang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>semi-PD: Towards Efficient LLM Serving via Phase-Wise Disaggregated Computation and Unified Storage</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19867</link>
   <description>Existing large language model (LLM) serving systems fall into two categories: 1) a unified system where prefill phase and decode phase are co-located on the same GPU, sharing the unified computational resource and storage, and 2) a disaggregated system where the two phases are disaggregated to different GPUs. The design of the disaggregated system addresses the latency interference and sophisticated scheduling issues in the unified system but leads to storage challenges including 1) replicated weights for both phases that prevent flexible deployment, 2) KV cache transfer overhead between the two phases, 3) storage imbalance that causes substantial wasted space of the GPU capacity, and 4) suboptimal resource adjustment arising from the difficulties in migrating KV cache. Such storage inefficiency delivers poor serving performance under high request rates.
  In this paper, we identify that the advantage of the disaggregated system lies in the disaggregated computation, i.e., partitioning the computational resource to enable the asynchronous computation of two phases. Thus, we propose a novel LLM serving system, semi-PD, characterized by disaggregated computation and unified storage. In semi-PD, we introduce a computation resource controller to achieve disaggregated computation at the streaming multi-processor (SM) level, and a unified memory manager to manage the asynchronous memory access from both phases. semi-PD has a low-overhead resource adjustment mechanism between the two phases, and a service-level objective (SLO) aware dynamic partitioning algorithm to optimize the SLO attainment. Compared to state-of-the-art systems, semi-PD maintains lower latency at higher request rates, reducing the average end-to-end latency per request by 1.27-2.58x on DeepSeek series models, and serves 1.55-1.72x more requests adhering to latency constraints on Llama series models.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19867v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ke Hong, Lufang Chen, Zhong Wang, Xiuhong Li, Qiuli Mao, Jianping Ma, Chao Xiong, Guanyu Wu, Buhe Han, Guohao Dai, Yun Liang, Yu Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Exploring the Role of Knowledge Graph-Based RAG in Japanese Medical Question Answering with Small-Scale LLMs</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10982</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) perform well in medical QA, but their effectiveness in Japanese contexts is limited due to privacy constraints that prevent the use of commercial models like GPT-4 in clinical settings. As a result, recent efforts focus on instruction-tuning open-source LLMs, though the potential of combining them with retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) remains underexplored. To bridge this gap, we are the first to explore a knowledge graph-based (KG) RAG framework for Japanese medical QA small-scale open-source LLMs. Experimental results show that KG-based RAG has only a limited impact on Japanese medical QA using small-scale open-source LLMs. Further case studies reveal that the effectiveness of the RAG is sensitive to the quality and relevance of the external retrieved content. These findings offer valuable insights into the challenges and potential of applying RAG in Japanese medical QA, while also serving as a reference for other low-resource languages.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.10982v5</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yingjian Chen, Feiyang Li, Xingyu Song, Tianxiao Li, Zixin Xu, Xiujie Chen, Issey Sukeda, Irene Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>ShadowKV: KV Cache in Shadows for High-Throughput Long-Context LLM Inference</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21465</link>
   <description>With the widespread deployment of long-context large language models (LLMs), there has been a growing demand for efficient support of high-throughput inference. However, as the key-value (KV) cache expands with the sequence length, the increasing memory footprint and the need to access it for each token generation both result in low throughput when serving long-context LLMs. While various dynamic sparse attention methods have been proposed to speed up inference while maintaining generation quality, they either fail to sufficiently reduce GPU memory consumption or introduce significant decoding latency by offloading the KV cache to the CPU. We present ShadowKV, a high-throughput long-context LLM inference system that stores the low-rank key cache and offloads the value cache to reduce the memory footprint for larger batch sizes and longer sequences. To minimize decoding latency, ShadowKV employs an accurate KV selection strategy that reconstructs minimal sparse KV pairs on-the-fly. By evaluating ShadowKV on a broad range of benchmarks, including RULER, LongBench, and Needle In A Haystack, and models like Llama-3.1-8B, Llama-3-8B-1M, GLM-4-9B-1M, Yi-9B-200K, Phi-3-Mini-128K, and Qwen2-7B-128K, we demonstrate that it can support up to 6$\times$ larger batch sizes and boost throughput by up to 3.04$\times$ on an A100 GPU without sacrificing accuracy, even surpassing the performance achievable with infinite batch size under the assumption of infinite GPU memory. The code is available at https://github.com/bytedance/ShadowKV.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.21465v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hanshi Sun, Li-Wen Chang, Wenlei Bao, Size Zheng, Ningxin Zheng, Xin Liu, Harry Dong, Yuejie Chi, Beidi Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Intelligent4DSE: Optimizing High-Level Synthesis Design Space Exploration with Graph Neural Networks and Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19649</link>
   <description>High-level synthesis (HLS) design space exploration (DSE) is an optimization process in electronic design automation (EDA) that systematically explores high-level design configurations to achieve Pareto-optimal hardware implementations balancing performance, area, and power (PPA). To optimize this process, HLS prediction tasks often employ message-passing neural networks (MPNNs), leveraging complex architectures to achieve high accuracy. These predictors serve as evaluators in the DSE process, effectively bypassing the time-consuming estimations traditionally required by HLS tools. However, existing models often prioritize structural complexity and minimization of training loss, overlooking task-specific characteristics. Additionally, while evolutionary algorithms are widely used in DSE, they typically require extensive domain-specific knowledge to design effective crossover and mutation operators. To address these limitations, we propose CoGNNs-LLMEA, a framework that integrates a graph neural network with task-adaptive message passing and a large language model-enhanced evolutionary algorithm. As a predictive model, CoGNNs directly leverages intermediate representations generated from source code after compiler front-end processing, enabling prediction of quality of results (QoR) without invoking HLS tools. Due to its strong adaptability to tasks, CoGNNs can be tuned to predict post-HLS and post-implementation outcomes, effectively bridging the gap between high-level abstractions and physical implementation characteristics. CoGNNs achieves state-of-the-art prediction accuracy in post-HLS QoR prediction, reducing mean prediction errors by 2.8$\times$ for latency and 3.4$\times$ for resource utilization compared to baseline models.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19649v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AR</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Lei Xu, Shanshan Wang, Emmanuel Casseau, Chenglong Xiao</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Robust Federated Personalised Mean Estimation for the Gaussian Mixture Model</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19955</link>
   <description>Federated learning with heterogeneous data and personalization has received significant recent attention. Separately, robustness to corrupted data in the context of federated learning has also been studied. In this paper we explore combining personalization for heterogeneous data with robustness, where a constant fraction of the clients are corrupted. Motivated by this broad problem, we formulate a simple instantiation which captures some of its difficulty. We focus on the specific problem of personalized mean estimation where the data is drawn from a Gaussian mixture model. We give an algorithm whose error depends almost linearly on the ratio of corrupted to uncorrupted samples, and show a lower bound with the same behavior, albeit with a gap of a constant factor.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19955v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.IT</category>
   <category>math.IT</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Malhar A. Managoli, Vinod M. Prabhakaran, Suhas Diggavi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Out-of-Distribution Generalization: A Causal Augmentation View</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19882</link>
   <description>Federated learning aims to collaboratively model by integrating multi-source information to obtain a model that can generalize across all client data. Existing methods often leverage knowledge distillation or data augmentation to mitigate the negative impact of data bias across clients. However, the limited performance of teacher models on out-of-distribution samples and the inherent quality gap between augmented and original data hinder their effectiveness and they typically fail to leverage the advantages of incorporating rich contextual information. To address these limitations, this paper proposes a Federated Causal Augmentation method, termed FedCAug, which employs causality-inspired data augmentation to break the spurious correlation between attributes and categories. Specifically, it designs a causal region localization module to accurately identify and decouple the background and objects in the image, providing rich contextual information for causal data augmentation. Additionally, it designs a causality-inspired data augmentation module that integrates causal features and within-client context to generate counterfactual samples. This significantly enhances data diversity, and the entire process does not require any information sharing between clients, thereby contributing to the protection of data privacy. Extensive experiments conducted on three datasets reveal that FedCAug markedly reduces the model's reliance on background to predict sample labels, achieving superior performance compared to state-of-the-art methods.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19882v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Runhui Zhang, Sijin Zhou, Zhuang Qi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Token-Shuffle: Towards High-Resolution Image Generation with Autoregressive Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17789</link>
   <description>Autoregressive (AR) models, long dominant in language generation, are increasingly applied to image synthesis but are often considered less competitive than Diffusion-based models. A primary limitation is the substantial number of image tokens required for AR models, which constrains both training and inference efficiency, as well as image resolution. To address this, we present Token-Shuffle, a novel yet simple method that reduces the number of image tokens in Transformer. Our key insight is the dimensional redundancy of visual vocabularies in Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs), where low-dimensional visual codes from visual encoder are directly mapped to high-dimensional language vocabularies. Leveraging this, we consider two key operations: token-shuffle, which merges spatially local tokens along channel dimension to decrease the input token number, and token-unshuffle, which untangles the inferred tokens after Transformer blocks to restore the spatial arrangement for output. Jointly training with textual prompts, our strategy requires no additional pretrained text-encoder and enables MLLMs to support extremely high-resolution image synthesis in a unified next-token prediction way while maintaining efficient training and inference. For the first time, we push the boundary of AR text-to-image generation to a resolution of 2048x2048 with gratifying generation performance. In GenAI-benchmark, our 2.7B model achieves 0.77 overall score on hard prompts, outperforming AR models LlamaGen by 0.18 and diffusion models LDM by 0.15. Exhaustive large-scale human evaluations also demonstrate our prominent image generation ability in terms of text-alignment, visual flaw, and visual appearance. We hope that Token-Shuffle can serve as a foundational design for efficient high-resolution image generation within MLLMs.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.17789v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xu Ma, Peize Sun, Haoyu Ma, Hao Tang, Chih-Yao Ma, Jialiang Wang, Kunpeng Li, Xiaoliang Dai, Yujun Shi, Xuan Ju, Yushi Hu, Artsiom Sanakoyeu, Felix Juefei-Xu, Ji Hou, Junjiao Tian, Tao Xu, Tingbo Hou, Yen-Cheng Liu, Zecheng He, Zijian He, Matt Feiszli, Peizhao Zhang, Peter Vajda, Sam Tsai, Yun Fu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>GLaMoR: Consistency Checking of OWL Ontologies using Graph Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19023</link>
   <description>Semantic reasoning aims to infer new knowledge from existing knowledge, with OWL ontologies serving as a standardized framework for organizing information. A key challenge in semantic reasoning is verifying ontology consistency. However, state-of-the-art reasoners are computationally expensive, and their efficiency decreases as ontology sizes grow. While classical machine learning models have been explored for consistency checking, they struggle to capture complex relationships within ontologies. Large language models (LLMs) have shown promising results for simple reasoning tasks but perform poorly on structured reasoning. The recently introduced Graph Language Model (GLM) offers a way to simultaneously process graph-structured data and text. This paper proposes GLaMoR (Graph Language Model for Reasoning), a reasoning pipeline that transforms OWL ontologies into graph-structured data and adapts the GLM architecture for consistency checking. We evaluate GLaMoR on ontologies from the NCBO BioPortal repository, converting them into triples suitable for model input. Our results show that the GLM outperforms all baseline models, achieving $95\%$ accuracy while being 20 times faster than classical reasoners.
  The Code is accessible under: https://github.com/JustinMuecke/GLaMoR</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19023v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Justin M\&quot;ucke, Ansgar Scherp</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>BadMoE: Backdooring Mixture-of-Experts LLMs via Optimizing Routing Triggers and Infecting Dormant Experts</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18598</link>
   <description>Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) have emerged as a powerful architecture for
  large language models (LLMs), enabling efficient scaling of model capacity
  while maintaining manageable computational costs. The key advantage lies in
  their ability to route different tokens to different ``expert'' networks
  within the model, enabling specialization and efficient handling of diverse
  input. However, the vulnerabilities of MoE-based LLMs still have barely been
  studied, and the potential for backdoor attacks in this context remains
  largely unexplored. This paper presents the first backdoor attack against
  MoE-based LLMs where the attackers poison ``dormant experts'' (i.e., underutilized
  experts) and activate them by optimizing routing triggers, thereby gaining
  control over the model's output. We first rigorously prove the existence of a few ``dominating
  experts'' in MoE models, whose outputs can determine the overall MoE's
  output. We also show that dormant experts can serve as dominating experts to manipulate model predictions.
  Accordingly, our attack, namely \textsc{BadMoE}, exploits the unique
  architecture of MoE models by 1) identifying dormant experts unrelated to the target task, 2)
  constructing a routing-aware loss to optimize the activation triggers of these experts, and 3) promoting dormant experts to dominating roles via poisoned training data.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.18598v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Qingyue Wang, Qi Pang, Xixun Lin, Shuai Wang, Daoyuan Wu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>MODP: Multi Objective Directional Prompting</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18722</link>
   <description>Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) have led to their popularity across multiple use-cases. However, prompt engineering, the process for optimally utilizing such models, remains approximation-driven and subjective. Most of the current research on prompt engineering focuses on task-specific optimization, while neglecting the behavior of the LLM under consideration during prompt development. This paper introduces MODP -- Multi Objective Directional Prompting, a framework based on two key concepts: 1) multi-objectivity: the importance of considering an LLM's intrinsic behavior as an additional objective in prompt development, and 2) directional prompting: a metrics-driven method for prompt engineering to ensure development of robust and high-precision prompts. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our proposed ideas on a summarization task, using a synthetically created dataset, achieving a 26% performance gain over initial prompts. Finally, we apply MODP to develop prompts for Dell's Next Best Action support tool, which is now in production and is used by more than 10,000 internal support agents and serving millions of customers worldwide.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.18722v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Aashutosh Nema, Samaksh Gulati, Evangelos Giakoumakis, Bipana Thapaliya</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>UnifyFL: Enabling Decentralized Cross-Silo Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18916</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) is a decentralized machine learning (ML) paradigm in which models are trained on private data across several devices called clients and combined at a single node called an aggregator rather than aggregating the data itself. Many organizations employ FL to have better privacy-aware ML-driven decision-making capabilities. However, organizations often operate independently rather than collaborate to enhance their FL capabilities due to the lack of an effective mechanism for collaboration. The challenge lies in balancing trust and resource efficiency. One approach relies on trusting a third-party aggregator to consolidate models from all organizations (multilevel FL), but this requires trusting an entity that may be biased or unreliable. Alternatively, organizations can bypass a third party by sharing their local models directly, which requires significant computational resources for validation. Both approaches reflect a fundamental trade-off between trust and resource constraints, with neither offering an ideal solution. In this work, we develop a trust-based cross-silo FL framework called \proj, which uses decentralized orchestration and distributed storage. \proj provides flexibility to the participating organizations and presents synchronous and asynchronous modes to handle stragglers. Our evaluation on a diverse testbed shows that \proj achieves a performance comparable to the ideal multilevel centralized FL while allowing trust and optimal use of resources.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.18916v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sarang S, Druva Dhakshinamoorthy, Aditya Shiva Sharma, Yuvraj Singh Bhadauria, Siddharth Chaitra Vivek, Arihant Bansal, Arnab K. Paul</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LLMs for Engineering: Teaching Models to Design High Powered Rockets</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19394</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) have transformed software engineering, but their application to physical engineering domains remains underexplored. This paper evaluates LLMs' capabilities in high-powered rocketry design through RocketBench, a benchmark connecting LLMs to high-fidelity rocket simulations. We test models on two increasingly complex design tasks: target altitude optimization and precision landing challenges. Our findings reveal that while state-of-the-art LLMs demonstrate strong baseline engineering knowledge, they struggle to iterate on their designs when given simulation results and ultimately plateau below human performance levels. However, when enhanced with reinforcement learning (RL), we show that a 7B parameter model outperforms both SoTA foundation models and human experts. This research demonstrates that RL-trained LLMs can serve as effective tools for complex engineering optimization, potentially transforming engineering domains beyond software development.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19394v1</guid>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Toby Simonds</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>BRIDGE: Benchmarking Large Language Models for Understanding Real-world Clinical Practice Text</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19467</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) hold great promise for medical applications and are evolving rapidly, with new models being released at an accelerated pace. However, current evaluations of LLMs in clinical contexts remain limited. Most existing benchmarks rely on medical exam-style questions or PubMed-derived text, failing to capture the complexity of real-world electronic health record (EHR) data. Others focus narrowly on specific application scenarios, limiting their generalizability across broader clinical use. To address this gap, we present BRIDGE, a comprehensive multilingual benchmark comprising 87 tasks sourced from real-world clinical data sources across nine languages. We systematically evaluated 52 state-of-the-art LLMs (including DeepSeek-R1, GPT-4o, Gemini, and Llama 4) under various inference strategies. With a total of 13,572 experiments, our results reveal substantial performance variation across model sizes, languages, natural language processing tasks, and clinical specialties. Notably, we demonstrate that open-source LLMs can achieve performance comparable to proprietary models, while medically fine-tuned LLMs based on older architectures often underperform versus updated general-purpose models. The BRIDGE and its corresponding leaderboard serve as a foundational resource and a unique reference for the development and evaluation of new LLMs in real-world clinical text understanding.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19467v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jiageng Wu, Bowen Gu, Ren Zhou, Kevin Xie, Doug Snyder, Yixing Jiang, Valentina Carducci, Richard Wyss, Rishi J Desai, Emily Alsentzer, Leo Anthony Celi, Adam Rodman, Sebastian Schneeweiss, Jonathan H. Chen, Santiago Romero-Brufau, Kueiyu Joshua Lin, Jie Yang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Survey of AI Agent Protocols</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16736</link>
   <description>The rapid development of large language models (LLMs) has led to the widespread deployment of LLM agents across diverse industries, including customer service, content generation, data analysis, and even healthcare. However, as more LLM agents are deployed, a major issue has emerged: there is no standard way for these agents to communicate with external tools or data sources. This lack of standardized protocols makes it difficult for agents to work together or scale effectively, and it limits their ability to tackle complex, real-world tasks. A unified communication protocol for LLM agents could change this. It would allow agents and tools to interact more smoothly, encourage collaboration, and triggering the formation of collective intelligence. In this paper, we provide the first comprehensive analysis of existing agent protocols, proposing a systematic two-dimensional classification that differentiates context-oriented versus inter-agent protocols and general-purpose versus domain-specific protocols. Additionally, we conduct a comparative performance analysis of these protocols across key dimensions such as security, scalability, and latency. Finally, we explore the future landscape of agent protocols by identifying critical research directions and characteristics necessary for next-generation protocols. These characteristics include adaptability, privacy preservation, and group-based interaction, as well as trends toward layered architectures and collective intelligence infrastructures. We expect this work to serve as a practical reference for both researchers and engineers seeking to design, evaluate, or integrate robust communication infrastructures for intelligent agents.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.16736v2</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yingxuan Yang, Huacan Chai, Yuanyi Song, Siyuan Qi, Muning Wen, Ning Li, Junwei Liao, Haoyi Hu, Jianghao Lin, Gaowei Chang, Weiwen Liu, Ying Wen, Yong Yu, Weinan Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FreeRide: Harvesting Bubbles in Pipeline Parallelism</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.06941</link>
   <description>The occurrence of bubbles in pipeline parallelism is an inherent limitation that can account for more than 40% of the large language model (LLM) training time and is one of the main reasons for the underutilization of GPU resources in LLM training. Harvesting these bubbles for GPU side tasks can increase resource utilization and reduce training costs but comes with challenges. First, because bubbles are discontinuous with various shapes, programming side tasks becomes difficult while requiring excessive engineering effort. Second, a side task can compete with pipeline training for GPU resources and incur significant overhead. To address these challenges, we propose FreeRide, a system designed to harvest bubbles in pipeline parallelism for side tasks. FreeRide provides programmers with interfaces to implement side tasks easily, manages bubbles and side tasks during pipeline training, and controls access to GPU resources by side tasks to reduce overhead. We demonstrate that FreeRide achieves 7.8% average cost savings with a negligible overhead of about 1% in training LLMs while serving model training, graph analytics, and image processing side tasks.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2409.06941v2</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jiashu Zhang (Yiming), Zihan Pan (Yiming),  Molly (Yiming),  Xu, Khuzaima Daudjee, Sihang Liu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedSlate:A Federated Deep Reinforcement Learning Recommender System</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14872</link>
   <description>Reinforcement learning methods have been used to optimize long-term user engagement in recommendation systems. However, existing reinforcement learning-based recommendation systems do not fully exploit the relevance of individual user behavior across different platforms. One potential solution is to aggregate data from various platforms in a centralized location and use the aggregated data for training. However, this approach raises economic and legal concerns, including increased communication costs and potential threats to user privacy. To address these challenges, we propose \textbf{FedSlate}, a federated reinforcement learning recommendation algorithm that effectively utilizes information that is prohibited from being shared at a legal level. We employ the SlateQ algorithm to assist FedSlate in learning users' long-term behavior and evaluating the value of recommended content. We extend the existing application scope of recommendation systems from single-user single-platform to single-user multi-platform and address cross-platform learning challenges by introducing federated learning. We use RecSim to construct a simulation environment for evaluating FedSlate and compare its performance with state-of-the-art benchmark recommendation models. Experimental results demonstrate the superior effects of FedSlate over baseline methods in various environmental settings, and FedSlate facilitates the learning of recommendation strategies in scenarios where baseline methods are completely inapplicable. Code is available at \textit{https://github.com/TianYaDY/FedSlate}.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2409.14872v2</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yongxin Deng, Xihe Qiu, Xiaoyu Tan, Yaochu Jin</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Leveraging Large Language Models for Effective Label-free Node Classification in Text-Attributed Graphs</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11983</link>
   <description>Graph neural networks (GNNs) have become the preferred models for node classification in graph data due to their robust capabilities in integrating graph structures and attributes. However, these models heavily depend on a substantial amount of high-quality labeled data for training, which is often costly to obtain. With the rise of large language models (LLMs), a promising approach is to utilize their exceptional zero-shot capabilities and extensive knowledge for node labeling. Despite encouraging results, this approach either requires numerous queries to LLMs or suffers from reduced performance due to noisy labels generated by LLMs. To address these challenges, we introduce Locle, an active self-training framework that does Label-free node Classification with LLMs cost-Effectively. Locle iteratively identifies small sets of &quot;critical&quot; samples using GNNs and extracts informative pseudo-labels for them with both LLMs and GNNs, serving as additional supervision signals to enhance model training. Specifically, Locle comprises three key components: (i) an effective active node selection strategy for initial annotations; (ii) a careful sample selection scheme to identify &quot;critical&quot; nodes based on label disharmonicity and entropy; and (iii) a label refinement module that combines LLMs and GNNs with a rewired topology. Extensive experiments on five benchmark text-attributed graph datasets demonstrate that Locle significantly outperforms state-of-the-art methods under the same query budget to LLMs in terms of label-free node classification. Notably, on the DBLP dataset with 14.3k nodes, Locle achieves an 8.08% improvement in accuracy over the state-of-the-art at a cost of less than one cent. Our code is available at https://github.com/HKBU-LAGAS/Locle.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.11983v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Taiyan Zhang, Renchi Yang, Yurui Lai, Mingyu Yan, Xiaochun Ye, Dongrui Fan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Exploring the Role of Knowledge Graph-Based RAG in Japanese Medical Question Answering with Small-Scale LLMs</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10982</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) perform well in medical QA, but their effectiveness in Japanese contexts is limited due to privacy constraints that prevent the use of commercial models like GPT-4 in clinical settings. As a result, recent efforts focus on instruction-tuning open-source LLMs, though the potential of combining them with retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) remains underexplored. To bridge this gap, we are the first to explore a knowledge graph-based (KG) RAG framework for Japanese medical QA small-scale open-source LLMs. Experimental results show that KG-based RAG has only a limited impact on Japanese medical QA using small-scale open-source LLMs. Further case studies reveal that the effectiveness of the RAG is sensitive to the quality and relevance of the external retrieved content. These findings offer valuable insights into the challenges and potential of applying RAG in Japanese medical QA, while also serving as a reference for other low-resource languages.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.10982v5</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yingjian Chen, Feiyang Li, Xingyu Song, Tianxiao Li, Zixin Xu, Xiujie Chen, Issey Sukeda, Irene Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>UnifyFL: Enabling Decentralized Cross-Silo Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18916</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) is a decentralized machine learning (ML) paradigm in which models are trained on private data across several devices called clients and combined at a single node called an aggregator rather than aggregating the data itself. Many organizations employ FL to have better privacy-aware ML-driven decision-making capabilities. However, organizations often operate independently rather than collaborate to enhance their FL capabilities due to the lack of an effective mechanism for collaboration. The challenge lies in balancing trust and resource efficiency. One approach relies on trusting a third-party aggregator to consolidate models from all organizations (multilevel FL), but this requires trusting an entity that may be biased or unreliable. Alternatively, organizations can bypass a third party by sharing their local models directly, which requires significant computational resources for validation. Both approaches reflect a fundamental trade-off between trust and resource constraints, with neither offering an ideal solution. In this work, we develop a trust-based cross-silo FL framework called \proj, which uses decentralized orchestration and distributed storage. \proj provides flexibility to the participating organizations and presents synchronous and asynchronous modes to handle stragglers. Our evaluation on a diverse testbed shows that \proj achieves a performance comparable to the ideal multilevel centralized FL while allowing trust and optimal use of resources.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.18916v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sarang S, Druva Dhakshinamoorthy, Aditya Shiva Sharma, Yuvraj Singh Bhadauria, Siddharth Chaitra Vivek, Arihant Bansal, Arnab K. Paul</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Bullet: Boosting GPU Utilization for LLM Serving via Dynamic Spatial-Temporal Orchestration</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19516</link>
   <description>Modern LLM serving systems confront inefficient GPU utilization due to the fundamental mismatch between compute-intensive prefill and memory-bound decode phases. While current practices attempt to address this by organizing these phases into hybrid batches, such solutions create an inefficient tradeoff that sacrifices either throughput or latency, leaving substantial GPU resources underutilized. We identify two key root causes: 1) the prefill phase suffers from suboptimal compute utilization due to wave quantization and attention bottlenecks. 2) hybrid batches disproportionately prioritize latency over throughput, resulting in wasted compute and memory bandwidth. To mitigate the issues, we present Bullet, a novel spatial-temporal orchestration system that eliminates these inefficiencies through precise phase coordination. Bullet enables concurrent execution of prefill and decode phases, while dynamically provisioning GPU resources using real-time performance modeling. By integrating SLO-aware scheduling and adaptive resource allocation, Bullet maximizes utilization without compromising latency targets. Experimental evaluations on real-world workloads demonstrate that Bullet delivers 1.26x average throughput gains (up to 1.55x) over state-of-the-arts, while consistently meeting latency constraints.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19516v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zejia Lin, Hongxin Xu, Guanyi Chen, Xianwei Zhang, Yutong Lu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Harmonizing Generalization and Personalization in Ring-topology Decentralized Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19103</link>
   <description>We introduce Ring-topology Decentralized Federated Learning (RDFL) for distributed model training, aiming to avoid the inherent risks of centralized failure in server-based FL. However, RDFL faces the challenge of low information-sharing efficiency due to the point-to-point communication manner when handling inherent data heterogeneity. Existing studies to mitigate data heterogeneity focus on personalized optimization of models, ignoring that the lack of shared information constraints can lead to large differences among models, weakening the benefits of collaborative learning. To tackle these challenges, we propose a Divide-and-conquer RDFL framework (DRDFL) that uses a feature generation model to extract personalized information and invariant shared knowledge from the underlying data distribution, ensuring both effective personalization and strong generalization. Specifically, we design a \textit{PersonaNet} module that encourages class-specific feature representations to follow a Gaussian mixture distribution, facilitating the learning of discriminative latent representations tailored to local data distributions. Meanwhile, the \textit{Learngene} module is introduced to encapsulate shared knowledge through an adversarial classifier to align latent representations and extract globally invariant information. Extensive experiments demonstrate that DRDFL outperforms state-of-the-art methods in various data heterogeneity settings.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19103v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shunxin Guo, Jiaqi Lv, Xin Geng</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>semi-PD: Towards Efficient LLM Serving via Phase-Wise Disaggregated Computation and Unified Storage</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19867</link>
   <description>Existing large language model (LLM) serving systems fall into two categories: 1) a unified system where prefill phase and decode phase are co-located on the same GPU, sharing the unified computational resource and storage, and 2) a disaggregated system where the two phases are disaggregated to different GPUs. The design of the disaggregated system addresses the latency interference and sophisticated scheduling issues in the unified system but leads to storage challenges including 1) replicated weights for both phases that prevent flexible deployment, 2) KV cache transfer overhead between the two phases, 3) storage imbalance that causes substantial wasted space of the GPU capacity, and 4) suboptimal resource adjustment arising from the difficulties in migrating KV cache. Such storage inefficiency delivers poor serving performance under high request rates.
  In this paper, we identify that the advantage of the disaggregated system lies in the disaggregated computation, i.e., partitioning the computational resource to enable the asynchronous computation of two phases. Thus, we propose a novel LLM serving system, semi-PD, characterized by disaggregated computation and unified storage. In semi-PD, we introduce a computation resource controller to achieve disaggregated computation at the streaming multi-processor (SM) level, and a unified memory manager to manage the asynchronous memory access from both phases. semi-PD has a low-overhead resource adjustment mechanism between the two phases, and a service-level objective (SLO) aware dynamic partitioning algorithm to optimize the SLO attainment. Compared to state-of-the-art systems, semi-PD maintains lower latency at higher request rates, reducing the average end-to-end latency per request by 1.27-2.58x on DeepSeek series models, and serves 1.55-1.72x more requests adhering to latency constraints on Llama series models.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19867v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ke Hong, Lufang Chen, Zhong Wang, Xiuhong Li, Qiuli Mao, Jianping Ma, Chao Xiong, Guanyu Wu, Buhe Han, Guohao Dai, Yun Liang, Yu Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FreeRide: Harvesting Bubbles in Pipeline Parallelism</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.06941</link>
   <description>The occurrence of bubbles in pipeline parallelism is an inherent limitation that can account for more than 40% of the large language model (LLM) training time and is one of the main reasons for the underutilization of GPU resources in LLM training. Harvesting these bubbles for GPU side tasks can increase resource utilization and reduce training costs but comes with challenges. First, because bubbles are discontinuous with various shapes, programming side tasks becomes difficult while requiring excessive engineering effort. Second, a side task can compete with pipeline training for GPU resources and incur significant overhead. To address these challenges, we propose FreeRide, a system designed to harvest bubbles in pipeline parallelism for side tasks. FreeRide provides programmers with interfaces to implement side tasks easily, manages bubbles and side tasks during pipeline training, and controls access to GPU resources by side tasks to reduce overhead. We demonstrate that FreeRide achieves 7.8% average cost savings with a negligible overhead of about 1% in training LLMs while serving model training, graph analytics, and image processing side tasks.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2409.06941v2</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jiashu Zhang (Yiming), Zihan Pan (Yiming),  Molly (Yiming),  Xu, Khuzaima Daudjee, Sihang Liu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Unified Solution to Diverse Heterogeneities in One-shot Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21119</link>
   <description>One-Shot Federated Learning (OSFL) restricts communication between the server and clients to a single round, significantly reducing communication costs and minimizing privacy leakage risks compared to traditional Federated Learning (FL), which requires multiple rounds of communication. However, existing OSFL frameworks remain vulnerable to distributional heterogeneity, as they primarily focus on model heterogeneity while neglecting data heterogeneity. To bridge this gap, we propose FedHydra, a unified, data-free, OSFL framework designed to effectively address both model and data heterogeneity. Unlike existing OSFL approaches, FedHydra introduces a novel two-stage learning mechanism. Specifically, it incorporates model stratification and heterogeneity-aware stratified aggregation to mitigate the challenges posed by both model and data heterogeneity. By this design, the data and model heterogeneity issues are simultaneously monitored from different aspects during learning. Consequently, FedHydra can effectively mitigate both issues by minimizing their inherent conflicts. We compared FedHydra with five SOTA baselines on four benchmark datasets. Experimental results show that our method outperforms the previous OSFL methods in both homogeneous and heterogeneous settings. Our code is available at https://anonymous.4open.science/r/Fed-SA-A4D7.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.21119v2</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jun Bai, Yiliao Song, Di Wu, Atul Sajjanhar, Yong Xiang, Wei Zhou, Xiaohui Tao, Yan Li, Yue Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Reactive Orchestration for Hierarchical Federated Learning Under a Communication Cost Budget</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03385</link>
   <description>Deploying a Hierarchical Federated Learning (HFL) pipeline across the computing continuum (CC) requires careful organization of participants into a hierarchical structure with intermediate aggregation nodes between FL clients and the global FL server. This is challenging to achieve due to (i) cost constraints, (ii) varying data distributions, and (iii) the volatile operating environment of the CC. In response to these challenges, we present a framework for the adaptive orchestration of HFL pipelines, designed to be reactive to client churn and infrastructure-level events, while balancing communication cost and ML model accuracy. Our mechanisms identify and react to events that cause HFL reconfiguration actions at runtime, building on multi-level monitoring information (model accuracy, resource availability, resource cost). Moreover, our framework introduces a generic methodology for estimating reconfiguration costs to continuously re-evaluate the quality of adaptation actions, while being extensible to optimize for various HFL performance criteria. By extending the Kubernetes ecosystem, our framework demonstrates the ability to react promptly and effectively to changes in the operating environment, making the best of the available communication cost budget and effectively balancing costs and ML performance at runtime.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.03385v2</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.NI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ivan \v{C}ili\'c, Anna Lackinger, Pantelis Frangoudis, Ivana Podnar \v{Z}arko, Alireza Furutanpey, Ilir Murturi, Schahram Dustdar</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedBaF: Federated Learning Aggregation Biased by a Foundation Model</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18352</link>
   <description>Foundation models are now a major focus of leading technology organizations due to their ability to generalize across diverse tasks. Existing approaches for adapting foundation models to new applications often rely on Federated Learning (FL) and disclose the foundation model weights to clients when using it to initialize the global model. While these methods ensure client data privacy, they compromise model and information security. In this paper, we introduce Federated Learning Aggregation Biased by a Foundation Model (FedBaF), a novel method for dynamically integrating pre-trained foundation model weights during the FL aggregation phase. Unlike conventional methods, FedBaF preserves the confidentiality of the foundation model while still leveraging its power to train more accurate models, especially in non-IID and adversarial scenarios. Our comprehensive experiments use Pre-ResNet and foundation models like Vision Transformer to demonstrate that FedBaF not only matches, but often surpasses the test accuracy of traditional weight initialization methods by up to 11.4% in IID and up to 15.8% in non-IID settings. Additionally, FedBaF applied to a Transformer-based language model significantly reduced perplexity by up to 39.2%.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.18352v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jong-Ik Park, Srinivasa Pranav, Jos\'e M. F. Moura, Carlee Joe-Wong</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>DROP: Poison Dilution via Knowledge Distillation for Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.07011</link>
   <description>Federated Learning is vulnerable to adversarial manipulation, where malicious clients can inject poisoned updates to influence the global model's behavior. While existing defense mechanisms have made notable progress, they fail to protect against adversaries that aim to induce targeted backdoors under different learning and attack configurations. To address this limitation, we introduce DROP (Distillation-based Reduction Of Poisoning), a novel defense mechanism that combines clustering and activity-tracking techniques with extraction of benign behavior from clients via knowledge distillation to tackle stealthy adversaries that manipulate low data poisoning rates and diverse malicious client ratios within the federation. Through extensive experimentation, our approach demonstrates superior robustness compared to existing defenses across a wide range of learning configurations. Finally, we evaluate existing defenses and our method under the challenging setting of non-IID client data distribution and highlight the challenges of designing a resilient FL defense in this setting.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.07011v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Georgios Syros, Anshuman Suri, Farinaz Koushanfar, Cristina Nita-Rotaru, Alina Oprea</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Harmonizing Generalization and Personalization in Ring-topology Decentralized Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19103</link>
   <description>We introduce Ring-topology Decentralized Federated Learning (RDFL) for distributed model training, aiming to avoid the inherent risks of centralized failure in server-based FL. However, RDFL faces the challenge of low information-sharing efficiency due to the point-to-point communication manner when handling inherent data heterogeneity. Existing studies to mitigate data heterogeneity focus on personalized optimization of models, ignoring that the lack of shared information constraints can lead to large differences among models, weakening the benefits of collaborative learning. To tackle these challenges, we propose a Divide-and-conquer RDFL framework (DRDFL) that uses a feature generation model to extract personalized information and invariant shared knowledge from the underlying data distribution, ensuring both effective personalization and strong generalization. Specifically, we design a \textit{PersonaNet} module that encourages class-specific feature representations to follow a Gaussian mixture distribution, facilitating the learning of discriminative latent representations tailored to local data distributions. Meanwhile, the \textit{Learngene} module is introduced to encapsulate shared knowledge through an adversarial classifier to align latent representations and extract globally invariant information. Extensive experiments demonstrate that DRDFL outperforms state-of-the-art methods in various data heterogeneity settings.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19103v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shunxin Guo, Jiaqi Lv, Xin Geng</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Soft-Label Caching and Sharpening for Communication-Efficient Federated Distillation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19602</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) enables collaborative model training across decentralized clients, enhancing privacy by keeping data local. Yet conventional FL, relying on frequent parameter-sharing, suffers from high communication overhead and limited model heterogeneity. Distillation-based FL approaches address these issues by sharing predictions (soft-labels) instead, but they often involve redundant transmissions across communication rounds, reducing efficiency. We propose SCARLET, a novel framework integrating synchronized soft-label caching and an enhanced Entropy Reduction Aggregation (Enhanced ERA) mechanism. SCARLET minimizes redundant communication by reusing cached soft-labels, achieving up to 50% reduction in communication costs compared to existing methods while maintaining accuracy. Enhanced ERA can be tuned to adapt to non-IID data variations, ensuring robust aggregation and performance in diverse client scenarios. Experimental evaluations demonstrate that SCARLET consistently outperforms state-of-the-art distillation-based FL methods in terms of accuracy and communication efficiency. The implementation of SCARLET is publicly available at https://github.com/kitsuyaazuma/SCARLET.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19602v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kitsuya Azuma, Takayuki Nishio, Yuichi Kitagawa, Wakako Nakano, Takahito Tanimura</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Unified Benchmark of Federated Learning with Kolmogorov-Arnold Networks for Medical Imaging</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19639</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) enables model training across decentralized devices without sharing raw data, thereby preserving privacy in sensitive domains like healthcare. In this paper, we evaluate Kolmogorov-Arnold Networks (KAN) architectures against traditional MLP across six state-of-the-art FL algorithms on a blood cell classification dataset. Notably, our experiments demonstrate that KAN can effectively replace MLP in federated environments, achieving superior performance with simpler architectures. Furthermore, we analyze the impact of key hyperparameters-grid size and network architecture-on KAN performance under varying degrees of Non-IID data distribution. Additionally, our ablation studies reveal that optimizing KAN width while maintaining minimal depth yields the best performance in federated settings. As a result, these findings establish KAN as a promising alternative for privacy-preserving medical imaging applications in distributed healthcare. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first comprehensive benchmark of KAN in FL settings for medical imaging task.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19639v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>eess.SP</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Youngjoon Lee, Jinu Gong, Joonhyuk Kang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Intelligent4DSE: Optimizing High-Level Synthesis Design Space Exploration with Graph Neural Networks and Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19649</link>
   <description>High-level synthesis (HLS) design space exploration (DSE) is an optimization process in electronic design automation (EDA) that systematically explores high-level design configurations to achieve Pareto-optimal hardware implementations balancing performance, area, and power (PPA). To optimize this process, HLS prediction tasks often employ message-passing neural networks (MPNNs), leveraging complex architectures to achieve high accuracy. These predictors serve as evaluators in the DSE process, effectively bypassing the time-consuming estimations traditionally required by HLS tools. However, existing models often prioritize structural complexity and minimization of training loss, overlooking task-specific characteristics. Additionally, while evolutionary algorithms are widely used in DSE, they typically require extensive domain-specific knowledge to design effective crossover and mutation operators. To address these limitations, we propose CoGNNs-LLMEA, a framework that integrates a graph neural network with task-adaptive message passing and a large language model-enhanced evolutionary algorithm. As a predictive model, CoGNNs directly leverages intermediate representations generated from source code after compiler front-end processing, enabling prediction of quality of results (QoR) without invoking HLS tools. Due to its strong adaptability to tasks, CoGNNs can be tuned to predict post-HLS and post-implementation outcomes, effectively bridging the gap between high-level abstractions and physical implementation characteristics. CoGNNs achieves state-of-the-art prediction accuracy in post-HLS QoR prediction, reducing mean prediction errors by 2.8$\times$ for latency and 3.4$\times$ for resource utilization compared to baseline models.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19649v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AR</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Lei Xu, Shanshan Wang, Emmanuel Casseau, Chenglong Xiao</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Convergence Analysis of Asynchronous Federated Learning with Gradient Compression for Non-Convex Optimization</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19903</link>
   <description>Gradient compression is an effective technique for reducing communication costs in federated learning (FL), and error feedback (EF) is usually adopted to remedy the compression errors. However, there remains a lack of systematic study on these techniques in asynchronous FL. In this paper, we fill this gap by analyzing the convergence behaviors of FL under different frameworks. We firstly consider a basic asynchronous FL framework AsynFL, and provide an improved convergence analysis that relies on fewer assumptions and yields a superior convergence rate than prior studies. Then, we consider a variant framework with gradient compression, AsynFLC. We show sufficient conditions for its convergence to the optimum, indicating the interaction between asynchronous delay and compression rate. Our analysis also demonstrates that asynchronous delay amplifies the variance caused by compression, thereby hindering convergence, and such an impact is exacerbated by high data heterogeneity. Furthermore, we study the convergence of AsynFLC-EF, the framework that further integrates EF. We prove that EF can effectively reduce the variance of gradient estimation despite asynchronous delay, which enables AsynFLC-EF to match the convergence rate of AsynFL. We also show that the impact of asynchronous delay on EF is limited to slowing down the higher-order convergence term. Experimental results substantiate our analytical findings very well.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19903v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Diying Yang, Yingwei Hou, Danyang Xiao, Weigang Wu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Robust Federated Personalised Mean Estimation for the Gaussian Mixture Model</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19955</link>
   <description>Federated learning with heterogeneous data and personalization has received significant recent attention. Separately, robustness to corrupted data in the context of federated learning has also been studied. In this paper we explore combining personalization for heterogeneous data with robustness, where a constant fraction of the clients are corrupted. Motivated by this broad problem, we formulate a simple instantiation which captures some of its difficulty. We focus on the specific problem of personalized mean estimation where the data is drawn from a Gaussian mixture model. We give an algorithm whose error depends almost linearly on the ratio of corrupted to uncorrupted samples, and show a lower bound with the same behavior, albeit with a gap of a constant factor.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19955v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.IT</category>
   <category>math.IT</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Malhar A. Managoli, Vinod M. Prabhakaran, Suhas Diggavi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>GLaMoR: Consistency Checking of OWL Ontologies using Graph Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19023</link>
   <description>Semantic reasoning aims to infer new knowledge from existing knowledge, with OWL ontologies serving as a standardized framework for organizing information. A key challenge in semantic reasoning is verifying ontology consistency. However, state-of-the-art reasoners are computationally expensive, and their efficiency decreases as ontology sizes grow. While classical machine learning models have been explored for consistency checking, they struggle to capture complex relationships within ontologies. Large language models (LLMs) have shown promising results for simple reasoning tasks but perform poorly on structured reasoning. The recently introduced Graph Language Model (GLM) offers a way to simultaneously process graph-structured data and text. This paper proposes GLaMoR (Graph Language Model for Reasoning), a reasoning pipeline that transforms OWL ontologies into graph-structured data and adapts the GLM architecture for consistency checking. We evaluate GLaMoR on ontologies from the NCBO BioPortal repository, converting them into triples suitable for model input. Our results show that the GLM outperforms all baseline models, achieving $95\%$ accuracy while being 20 times faster than classical reasoners.
  The Code is accessible under: https://github.com/JustinMuecke/GLaMoR</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19023v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Justin M\&quot;ucke, Ansgar Scherp</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>semi-PD: Towards Efficient LLM Serving via Phase-Wise Disaggregated Computation and Unified Storage</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19867</link>
   <description>Existing large language model (LLM) serving systems fall into two categories: 1) a unified system where prefill phase and decode phase are co-located on the same GPU, sharing the unified computational resource and storage, and 2) a disaggregated system where the two phases are disaggregated to different GPUs. The design of the disaggregated system addresses the latency interference and sophisticated scheduling issues in the unified system but leads to storage challenges including 1) replicated weights for both phases that prevent flexible deployment, 2) KV cache transfer overhead between the two phases, 3) storage imbalance that causes substantial wasted space of the GPU capacity, and 4) suboptimal resource adjustment arising from the difficulties in migrating KV cache. Such storage inefficiency delivers poor serving performance under high request rates.
  In this paper, we identify that the advantage of the disaggregated system lies in the disaggregated computation, i.e., partitioning the computational resource to enable the asynchronous computation of two phases. Thus, we propose a novel LLM serving system, semi-PD, characterized by disaggregated computation and unified storage. In semi-PD, we introduce a computation resource controller to achieve disaggregated computation at the streaming multi-processor (SM) level, and a unified memory manager to manage the asynchronous memory access from both phases. semi-PD has a low-overhead resource adjustment mechanism between the two phases, and a service-level objective (SLO) aware dynamic partitioning algorithm to optimize the SLO attainment. Compared to state-of-the-art systems, semi-PD maintains lower latency at higher request rates, reducing the average end-to-end latency per request by 1.27-2.58x on DeepSeek series models, and serves 1.55-1.72x more requests adhering to latency constraints on Llama series models.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19867v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ke Hong, Lufang Chen, Zhong Wang, Xiuhong Li, Qiuli Mao, Jianping Ma, Chao Xiong, Guanyu Wu, Buhe Han, Guohao Dai, Yun Liang, Yu Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Robust Collaborative Inference with Vertically Split Data Over Dynamic Device Environments</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.16638</link>
   <description>When each edge device of a network only perceives a local part of the environment, collaborative inference across multiple devices is often needed to predict global properties of the environment. In safety-critical applications, collaborative inference must be robust to significant network failures caused by environmental disruptions or extreme weather. Existing collaborative learning approaches, such as privacy-focused Vertical Federated Learning (VFL), typically assume a centralized setup or that one device never fails. However, these assumptions make prior approaches susceptible to significant network failures. To address this problem, we first formalize the problem of robust collaborative inference over a dynamic network of devices that could experience significant network faults. Then, we develop a minimalistic yet impactful method called Multiple Aggregation with Gossip Rounds and Simulated Faults (MAGS) that synthesizes simulated faults via dropout, replication, and gossiping to significantly improve robustness over baselines. We also theoretically analyze our proposed approach to explain why each component enhances robustness. Extensive empirical results validate that MAGS is robust across a range of fault rates-including extreme fault rates.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2312.16638v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Surojit Ganguli, Zeyu Zhou, Christopher G. Brinton, David I. Inouye</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedBaF: Federated Learning Aggregation Biased by a Foundation Model</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18352</link>
   <description>Foundation models are now a major focus of leading technology organizations due to their ability to generalize across diverse tasks. Existing approaches for adapting foundation models to new applications often rely on Federated Learning (FL) and disclose the foundation model weights to clients when using it to initialize the global model. While these methods ensure client data privacy, they compromise model and information security. In this paper, we introduce Federated Learning Aggregation Biased by a Foundation Model (FedBaF), a novel method for dynamically integrating pre-trained foundation model weights during the FL aggregation phase. Unlike conventional methods, FedBaF preserves the confidentiality of the foundation model while still leveraging its power to train more accurate models, especially in non-IID and adversarial scenarios. Our comprehensive experiments use Pre-ResNet and foundation models like Vision Transformer to demonstrate that FedBaF not only matches, but often surpasses the test accuracy of traditional weight initialization methods by up to 11.4% in IID and up to 15.8% in non-IID settings. Additionally, FedBaF applied to a Transformer-based language model significantly reduced perplexity by up to 39.2%.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.18352v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jong-Ik Park, Srinivasa Pranav, Jos\'e M. F. Moura, Carlee Joe-Wong</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>MetaTrading: An Immersion-Aware Model Trading Framework for Vehicular Metaverse Services</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19665</link>
   <description>Timely updating of Internet of Things (IoT) data is crucial for immersive vehicular metaverse services. However, challenges such as latency caused by massive data transmissions, privacy risks associated with user data, and computational burdens on metaverse service providers (MSPs) hinder continuous collection of high-quality data. To address these issues, we propose an immersion-aware model trading framework that facilitates data provision for services while ensuring privacy through federated learning (FL). Specifically, we first develop a novel multi-dimensional metric, the immersion of model (IoM), which assesses model value comprehensively by considering freshness and accuracy of learning models, as well as the amount and potential value of raw data used for training. Then, we design an incentive mechanism to incentivize metaverse users (MUs) to contribute high-value models under resource constraints. The trading interactions between MSPs and MUs are modeled as an equilibrium problem with equilibrium constraints (EPEC) to analyze and balance their costs and gains, where MSPs as leaders determine rewards, while MUs as followers optimize resource allocation. Furthermore, considering dynamic network conditions and privacy concerns, we formulate the reward decisions of MSPs as a multi-agent Markov decision process. To solve this, we develop a fully distributed dynamic reward algorithm based on deep reinforcement learning, without accessing any private information about MUs and other MSPs. Experimental results demonstrate that the proposed framework outperforms state-of-the-art benchmarks, achieving improvements in IoM of 38.3% and 37.2%, and reductions in training time to reach the target accuracy of 43.5% and 49.8%, on average, for the MNIST and GTSRB datasets, respectively.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.19665v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.GT</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hongjia Wu, Hui Zeng, Zehui Xiong, Jiawen Kang, Zhiping Cai, Tse-Tin Chan, Dusit Niyato, Zhu Han</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>ShadowKV: KV Cache in Shadows for High-Throughput Long-Context LLM Inference</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21465</link>
   <description>With the widespread deployment of long-context large language models (LLMs), there has been a growing demand for efficient support of high-throughput inference. However, as the key-value (KV) cache expands with the sequence length, the increasing memory footprint and the need to access it for each token generation both result in low throughput when serving long-context LLMs. While various dynamic sparse attention methods have been proposed to speed up inference while maintaining generation quality, they either fail to sufficiently reduce GPU memory consumption or introduce significant decoding latency by offloading the KV cache to the CPU. We present ShadowKV, a high-throughput long-context LLM inference system that stores the low-rank key cache and offloads the value cache to reduce the memory footprint for larger batch sizes and longer sequences. To minimize decoding latency, ShadowKV employs an accurate KV selection strategy that reconstructs minimal sparse KV pairs on-the-fly. By evaluating ShadowKV on a broad range of benchmarks, including RULER, LongBench, and Needle In A Haystack, and models like Llama-3.1-8B, Llama-3-8B-1M, GLM-4-9B-1M, Yi-9B-200K, Phi-3-Mini-128K, and Qwen2-7B-128K, we demonstrate that it can support up to 6$\times$ larger batch sizes and boost throughput by up to 3.04$\times$ on an A100 GPU without sacrificing accuracy, even surpassing the performance achievable with infinite batch size under the assumption of infinite GPU memory. The code is available at https://github.com/bytedance/ShadowKV.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.21465v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hanshi Sun, Li-Wen Chang, Wenlei Bao, Size Zheng, Ningxin Zheng, Xin Liu, Harry Dong, Yuejie Chi, Beidi Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Leveraging Large Language Models for Effective Label-free Node Classification in Text-Attributed Graphs</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11983</link>
   <description>Graph neural networks (GNNs) have become the preferred models for node classification in graph data due to their robust capabilities in integrating graph structures and attributes. However, these models heavily depend on a substantial amount of high-quality labeled data for training, which is often costly to obtain. With the rise of large language models (LLMs), a promising approach is to utilize their exceptional zero-shot capabilities and extensive knowledge for node labeling. Despite encouraging results, this approach either requires numerous queries to LLMs or suffers from reduced performance due to noisy labels generated by LLMs. To address these challenges, we introduce Locle, an active self-training framework that does Label-free node Classification with LLMs cost-Effectively. Locle iteratively identifies small sets of &quot;critical&quot; samples using GNNs and extracts informative pseudo-labels for them with both LLMs and GNNs, serving as additional supervision signals to enhance model training. Specifically, Locle comprises three key components: (i) an effective active node selection strategy for initial annotations; (ii) a careful sample selection scheme to identify &quot;critical&quot; nodes based on label disharmonicity and entropy; and (iii) a label refinement module that combines LLMs and GNNs with a rewired topology. Extensive experiments on five benchmark text-attributed graph datasets demonstrate that Locle significantly outperforms state-of-the-art methods under the same query budget to LLMs in terms of label-free node classification. Notably, on the DBLP dataset with 14.3k nodes, Locle achieves an 8.08% improvement in accuracy over the state-of-the-art at a cost of less than one cent. Our code is available at https://github.com/HKBU-LAGAS/Locle.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.11983v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Taiyan Zhang, Renchi Yang, Yurui Lai, Mingyu Yan, Xiaochun Ye, Dongrui Fan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>DROP: Poison Dilution via Knowledge Distillation for Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.07011</link>
   <description>Federated Learning is vulnerable to adversarial manipulation, where malicious clients can inject poisoned updates to influence the global model's behavior. While existing defense mechanisms have made notable progress, they fail to protect against adversaries that aim to induce targeted backdoors under different learning and attack configurations. To address this limitation, we introduce DROP (Distillation-based Reduction Of Poisoning), a novel defense mechanism that combines clustering and activity-tracking techniques with extraction of benign behavior from clients via knowledge distillation to tackle stealthy adversaries that manipulate low data poisoning rates and diverse malicious client ratios within the federation. Through extensive experimentation, our approach demonstrates superior robustness compared to existing defenses across a wide range of learning configurations. Finally, we evaluate existing defenses and our method under the challenging setting of non-IID client data distribution and highlight the challenges of designing a resilient FL defense in this setting.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.07011v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Georgios Syros, Anshuman Suri, Farinaz Koushanfar, Cristina Nita-Rotaru, Alina Oprea</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Differential Privacy Personalized Federated Learning Based on Dynamically Sparsified Client Updates</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09192</link>
   <description>Personalized federated learning is extensively utilized in scenarios characterized by data heterogeneity, facilitating more efficient and automated local training on data-owning terminals. This includes the automated selection of high-performance model parameters for upload, thereby enhancing the overall training process. However, it entails significant risks of privacy leakage. Existing studies have attempted to mitigate these risks by utilizing differential privacy. Nevertheless, these studies present two major limitations: (1) The integration of differential privacy into personalized federated learning lacks sufficient personalization, leading to the introduction of excessive noise into the model. (2) It fails to adequately control the spatial scope of model update information, resulting in a suboptimal balance between data privacy and model effectiveness in differential privacy federated learning. In this paper, we propose a differentially private personalized federated learning approach that employs dynamically sparsified client updates through reparameterization and adaptive norm(DP-pFedDSU). Reparameterization training effectively selects personalized client update information, thereby reducing the quantity of updates. This approach minimizes the introduction of noise to the greatest extent possible. Additionally, dynamic adaptive norm refers to controlling the norm space of model updates during the training process, mitigating the negative impact of clipping on the update information. These strategies substantially enhance the effective integration of differential privacy and personalized federated learning. Experimental results on EMNIST, CIFAR-10, and CIFAR-100 demonstrate that our proposed scheme achieves superior performance and is well-suited for more complex personalized federated learning scenarios.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.09192v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chuanyin Wang, Yifei Zhang, Neng Gao, Qiang Luo</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Unified Solution to Diverse Heterogeneities in One-shot Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21119</link>
   <description>One-Shot Federated Learning (OSFL) restricts communication between the server and clients to a single round, significantly reducing communication costs and minimizing privacy leakage risks compared to traditional Federated Learning (FL), which requires multiple rounds of communication. However, existing OSFL frameworks remain vulnerable to distributional heterogeneity, as they primarily focus on model heterogeneity while neglecting data heterogeneity. To bridge this gap, we propose FedHydra, a unified, data-free, OSFL framework designed to effectively address both model and data heterogeneity. Unlike existing OSFL approaches, FedHydra introduces a novel two-stage learning mechanism. Specifically, it incorporates model stratification and heterogeneity-aware stratified aggregation to mitigate the challenges posed by both model and data heterogeneity. By this design, the data and model heterogeneity issues are simultaneously monitored from different aspects during learning. Consequently, FedHydra can effectively mitigate both issues by minimizing their inherent conflicts. We compared FedHydra with five SOTA baselines on four benchmark datasets. Experimental results show that our method outperforms the previous OSFL methods in both homogeneous and heterogeneous settings. Our code is available at https://anonymous.4open.science/r/Fed-SA-A4D7.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.21119v2</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jun Bai, Yiliao Song, Di Wu, Atul Sajjanhar, Yong Xiang, Wei Zhou, Xiaohui Tao, Yan Li, Yue Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Reactive Orchestration for Hierarchical Federated Learning Under a Communication Cost Budget</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03385</link>
   <description>Deploying a Hierarchical Federated Learning (HFL) pipeline across the computing continuum (CC) requires careful organization of participants into a hierarchical structure with intermediate aggregation nodes between FL clients and the global FL server. This is challenging to achieve due to (i) cost constraints, (ii) varying data distributions, and (iii) the volatile operating environment of the CC. In response to these challenges, we present a framework for the adaptive orchestration of HFL pipelines, designed to be reactive to client churn and infrastructure-level events, while balancing communication cost and ML model accuracy. Our mechanisms identify and react to events that cause HFL reconfiguration actions at runtime, building on multi-level monitoring information (model accuracy, resource availability, resource cost). Moreover, our framework introduces a generic methodology for estimating reconfiguration costs to continuously re-evaluate the quality of adaptation actions, while being extensible to optimize for various HFL performance criteria. By extending the Kubernetes ecosystem, our framework demonstrates the ability to react promptly and effectively to changes in the operating environment, making the best of the available communication cost budget and effectively balancing costs and ML performance at runtime.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.03385v2</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.NI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ivan \v{C}ili\'c, Anna Lackinger, Pantelis Frangoudis, Ivana Podnar \v{Z}arko, Alireza Furutanpey, Ilir Murturi, Schahram Dustdar</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>MODP: Multi Objective Directional Prompting</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18722</link>
   <description>Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) have led to their popularity across multiple use-cases. However, prompt engineering, the process for optimally utilizing such models, remains approximation-driven and subjective. Most of the current research on prompt engineering focuses on task-specific optimization, while neglecting the behavior of the LLM under consideration during prompt development. This paper introduces MODP -- Multi Objective Directional Prompting, a framework based on two key concepts: 1) multi-objectivity: the importance of considering an LLM's intrinsic behavior as an additional objective in prompt development, and 2) directional prompting: a metrics-driven method for prompt engineering to ensure development of robust and high-precision prompts. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our proposed ideas on a summarization task, using a synthetically created dataset, achieving a 26% performance gain over initial prompts. Finally, we apply MODP to develop prompts for Dell's Next Best Action support tool, which is now in production and is used by more than 10,000 internal support agents and serving millions of customers worldwide.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.18722v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CC</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Aashutosh Nema, Samaksh Gulati, Evangelos Giakoumakis, Bipana Thapaliya</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>MetaTrading: An Immersion-Aware Model Trading Framework for Vehicular Metaverse Services</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19665</link>
   <description>Timely updating of Internet of Things (IoT) data is crucial for immersive vehicular metaverse services. However, challenges such as latency caused by massive data transmissions, privacy risks associated with user data, and computational burdens on metaverse service providers (MSPs) hinder continuous collection of high-quality data. To address these issues, we propose an immersion-aware model trading framework that facilitates data provision for services while ensuring privacy through federated learning (FL). Specifically, we first develop a novel multi-dimensional metric, the immersion of model (IoM), which assesses model value comprehensively by considering freshness and accuracy of learning models, as well as the amount and potential value of raw data used for training. Then, we design an incentive mechanism to incentivize metaverse users (MUs) to contribute high-value models under resource constraints. The trading interactions between MSPs and MUs are modeled as an equilibrium problem with equilibrium constraints (EPEC) to analyze and balance their costs and gains, where MSPs as leaders determine rewards, while MUs as followers optimize resource allocation. Furthermore, considering dynamic network conditions and privacy concerns, we formulate the reward decisions of MSPs as a multi-agent Markov decision process. To solve this, we develop a fully distributed dynamic reward algorithm based on deep reinforcement learning, without accessing any private information about MUs and other MSPs. Experimental results demonstrate that the proposed framework outperforms state-of-the-art benchmarks, achieving improvements in IoM of 38.3% and 37.2%, and reductions in training time to reach the target accuracy of 43.5% and 49.8%, on average, for the MNIST and GTSRB datasets, respectively.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2410.19665v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.GT</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hongjia Wu, Hui Zeng, Zehui Xiong, Jiawen Kang, Zhiping Cai, Tse-Tin Chan, Dusit Niyato, Zhu Han</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Learning-based Semantic Segmentation for Lane and Object Detection in Autonomous Driving</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18939</link>
   <description>Autonomous Vehicles (AVs) require precise lane and object detection to ensure safe navigation. However, centralized deep learning (DL) approaches for semantic segmentation raise privacy and scalability challenges, particularly when handling sensitive data. This research presents a new federated learning (FL) framework that integrates secure deep Convolutional Neural Networks (CNNs) and Differential Privacy (DP) to address these issues. The core contribution of this work involves: (1) developing a new hybrid UNet-ResNet34 architecture for centralized semantic segmentation to achieve high accuracy and tackle privacy concerns due to centralized training, and (2) implementing the privacy-preserving FL model, distributed across AVs to enhance performance through secure CNNs and DP mechanisms. In the proposed FL framework, the methodology distinguishes itself from the existing approach through the following: (a) ensuring data decentralization through FL to uphold user privacy by eliminating the need for centralized data aggregation, (b) integrating DP mechanisms to secure sensitive model updates against potential adversarial inference attacks, and (c) evaluating the frameworks performance and generalizability using RGB and semantic segmentation datasets derived from the CARLA simulator. Experimental results show significant improvements in accuracy, from 81.5% to 88.7% for the RGB dataset and from 79.3% to 86.9% for the SEG dataset over 20 to 70 Communication Rounds (CRs). Global loss was reduced by over 60%, and minor accuracy trade-offs from DP were observed. This study contributes by offering a scalable, privacy-preserving FL framework tailored for AVs, optimizing communication efficiency while balancing performance and data security.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.18939v1</guid>
   <category>eess.SY</category>
   <category>cs.SY</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Gharbi Khamis Alshammari, Ahmad Abubakar, Nada M. O. Sid Ahmed, Naif Khalaf Alshammari</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Reactive Orchestration for Hierarchical Federated Learning Under a Communication Cost Budget</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03385</link>
   <description>Deploying a Hierarchical Federated Learning (HFL) pipeline across the computing continuum (CC) requires careful organization of participants into a hierarchical structure with intermediate aggregation nodes between FL clients and the global FL server. This is challenging to achieve due to (i) cost constraints, (ii) varying data distributions, and (iii) the volatile operating environment of the CC. In response to these challenges, we present a framework for the adaptive orchestration of HFL pipelines, designed to be reactive to client churn and infrastructure-level events, while balancing communication cost and ML model accuracy. Our mechanisms identify and react to events that cause HFL reconfiguration actions at runtime, building on multi-level monitoring information (model accuracy, resource availability, resource cost). Moreover, our framework introduces a generic methodology for estimating reconfiguration costs to continuously re-evaluate the quality of adaptation actions, while being extensible to optimize for various HFL performance criteria. By extending the Kubernetes ecosystem, our framework demonstrates the ability to react promptly and effectively to changes in the operating environment, making the best of the available communication cost budget and effectively balancing costs and ML performance at runtime.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2412.03385v2</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.NI</category>
   <pubdate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ivan \v{C}ili\'c, Anna Lackinger, Pantelis Frangoudis, Ivana Podnar \v{Z}arko, Alireza Furutanpey, Ilir Murturi, Schahram Dustdar</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
