<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 03:21:24 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 03:21:24 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>From Images to Signals: Are Large Vision Models Useful for Time Series Analysis?</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24030</link>
   <description>Transformer-based models have gained increasing attention in time series research, driving interest in Large Language Models (LLMs) and foundation models for time series analysis. As the field moves toward multi-modality, Large Vision Models (LVMs) are emerging as a promising direction. In the past, the effectiveness of Transformer and LLMs in time series has been debated. When it comes to LVMs, a similar question arises: are LVMs truely useful for time series analysis? To address it, we design and conduct the first principled study involving 4 LVMs, 8 imaging methods, 18 datasets and 26 baselines across both high-level (classification) and low-level (forecasting) tasks, with extensive ablation analysis. Our findings indicate LVMs are indeed useful for time series classification but face challenges in forecasting. Although effective, the contemporary best LVM forecasters are limited to specific types of LVMs and imaging methods, exhibit a bias toward forecasting periods, and have limited ability to utilize long look-back windows. We hope our findings could serve as a cornerstone for future research on LVM- and multimodal-based solutions to different time series tasks.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.24030v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ziming Zhao, ChengAo Shen, Hanghang Tong, Dongjin Song, Zhigang Deng, Qingsong Wen, Jingchao Ni</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>AdeptHEQ-FL: Adaptive Homomorphic Encryption for Federated Learning of Hybrid Classical-Quantum Models with Dynamic Layer Sparing</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07316</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) faces inherent challenges in balancing model performance, privacy preservation, and communication efficiency, especially in non-IID decentralized environments. Recent approaches either sacrifice formal privacy guarantees, incur high overheads, or overlook quantum-enhanced expressivity. We introduce AdeptHEQ-FL, a unified hybrid classical-quantum FL framework that integrates (i) a hybrid CNN-PQC architecture for expressive decentralized learning, (ii) an adaptive accuracy-weighted aggregation scheme leveraging differentially private validation accuracies, (iii) selective homomorphic encryption (HE) for secure aggregation of sensitive model layers, and (iv) dynamic layer-wise adaptive freezing to minimize communication overhead while preserving quantum adaptability. We establish formal privacy guarantees, provide convergence analysis, and conduct extensive experiments on the CIFAR-10, SVHN, and Fashion-MNIST datasets. AdeptHEQ-FL achieves a $\approx 25.43\%$ and $\approx 14.17\%$ accuracy improvement over Standard-FedQNN and FHE-FedQNN, respectively, on the CIFAR-10 dataset. Additionally, it reduces communication overhead by freezing less important layers, demonstrating the efficiency and practicality of our privacy-preserving, resource-aware design for FL.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.07316v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Md Abrar Jahin, Taufikur Rahman Fuad, M. F. Mridha, Nafiz Fahad, Md. Jakir Hossen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Optimizing Communication and Device Clustering for Clustered Federated Learning with Differential Privacy</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07320</link>
   <description>In this paper, a secure and communication-efficient clustered federated learning (CFL) design is proposed. In our model, several base stations (BSs) with heterogeneous task-handling capabilities and multiple users with non-independent and identically distributed (non-IID) data jointly perform CFL training incorporating differential privacy (DP) techniques. Since each BS can process only a subset of the learning tasks and has limited wireless resource blocks (RBs) to allocate to users for federated learning (FL) model parameter transmission, it is necessary to jointly optimize RB allocation and user scheduling for CFL performance optimization. Meanwhile, our considered CFL method requires devices to use their limited data and FL model information to determine their task identities, which may introduce additional communication overhead. We formulate an optimization problem whose goal is to minimize the training loss of all learning tasks while considering device clustering, RB allocation, DP noise, and FL model transmission delay. To solve the problem, we propose a novel dynamic penalty function assisted value decomposed multi-agent reinforcement learning (DPVD-MARL) algorithm that enables distributed BSs to independently determine their connected users, RBs, and DP noise of the connected users but jointly minimize the training loss of all learning tasks across all BSs. Different from the existing MARL methods that assign a large penalty for invalid actions, we propose a novel penalty assignment scheme that assigns penalty depending on the number of devices that cannot meet communication constraints (e.g., delay), which can guide the MARL scheme to quickly find valid actions, thus improving the convergence speed. Simulation results show that the DPVD-MARL can improve the convergence rate by up to 20% and the ultimate accumulated rewards by 15% compared to independent Q-learning.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.07320v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Dongyu Wei, Xiaoren Xu, Shiwen Mao, Mingzhe Chen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Sparse Self-Federated Learning for Energy Efficient Cooperative Intelligence in Society 5.0</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07613</link>
   <description>Federated Learning offers privacy-preserving collaborative intelligence but struggles to meet the sustainability demands of emerging IoT ecosystems necessary for Society 5.0-a human-centered technological future balancing social advancement with environmental responsibility. The excessive communication bandwidth and computational resources required by traditional FL approaches make them environmentally unsustainable at scale, creating a fundamental conflict with green AI principles as billions of resource-constrained devices attempt to participate. To this end, we introduce Sparse Proximity-based Self-Federated Learning (SParSeFuL), a resource-aware approach that bridges this gap by combining aggregate computing for self-organization with neural network sparsification to reduce energy and bandwidth consumption.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.07613v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Davide Domini, Laura Erhan, Gianluca Aguzzi, Lucia Cavallaro, Amirhossein Douzandeh Zenoozi, Antonio Liotta, Mirko Viroli</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>HLF-FSL. A Decentralized Federated Split Learning Solution for IoT on Hyperledger Fabric</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07637</link>
   <description>Collaborative machine learning in sensitive domains demands scalable, privacy preserving solutions for enterprise deployment. Conventional Federated Learning (FL) relies on a central server, introducing single points of failure and privacy risks, while Split Learning (SL) partitions models for privacy but scales poorly due to sequential training. We present a decentralized architecture that combines Federated Split Learning (FSL) with the permissioned blockchain Hyperledger Fabric (HLF). Our chaincode orchestrates FSL's split model execution and peer-to-peer aggregation without any central coordinator, leveraging HLF's transient fields and Private Data Collections (PDCs) to keep raw data and model activations private. On CIFAR-10 and MNIST benchmarks, HLF-FSL matches centralized FSL accuracy while reducing per epoch training time compared to Ethereum-based works. Performance and scalability tests show minimal blockchain overhead and preserved accuracy, demonstrating enterprise grade viability.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.07637v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Carlos Beis Penedo, Rebeca P. D\'iaz Redondo, Ana Fern\'andez Vilas, Manuel Fern\'andez Veiga, Francisco Troncoso Pastoriza</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Ampere: Communication-Efficient and High-Accuracy Split Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07130</link>
   <description>A Federated Learning (FL) system collaboratively trains neural networks across devices and a server but is limited by significant on-device computation costs. Split Federated Learning (SFL) systems mitigate this by offloading a block of layers of the network from the device to a server. However, in doing so, it introduces large communication overheads due to frequent exchanges of intermediate activations and gradients between devices and the server and reduces model accuracy for non-IID data. We propose Ampere, a novel collaborative training system that simultaneously minimizes on-device computation and device-server communication while improving model accuracy. Unlike SFL, which uses a global loss by iterative end-to-end training, Ampere develops unidirectional inter-block training to sequentially train the device and server block with a local loss, eliminating the transfer of gradients. A lightweight auxiliary network generation method decouples training between the device and server, reducing frequent intermediate exchanges to a single transfer, which significantly reduces the communication overhead. Ampere mitigates the impact of data heterogeneity by consolidating activations generated by the trained device block to train the server block, in contrast to SFL, which trains on device-specific, non-IID activations. Extensive experiments on multiple CNNs and transformers show that, compared to state-of-the-art SFL baseline systems, Ampere (i) improves model accuracy by up to 13.26% while reducing training time by up to 94.6%, (ii) reduces device-server communication overhead by up to 99.1% and on-device computation by up to 93.13%, and (iii) reduces standard deviation of accuracy by 53.39% for various non-IID degrees highlighting superior performance when faced with heterogeneous data.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.07130v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zihan Zhang, Leon Wong, Blesson Varghese</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Robust Federated Personalised Mean Estimation for the Gaussian Mixture Model</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19955</link>
   <description>Federated learning with heterogeneous data and personalization has received significant recent attention. Separately, robustness to corrupted data in the context of federated learning has also been studied. In this paper we explore combining personalization for heterogeneous data with robustness, where a constant fraction of the clients are corrupted. Motivated by this broad problem, we formulate a simple instantiation which captures some of its difficulty. We focus on the specific problem of personalized mean estimation where the data is drawn from a Gaussian mixture model. We give an algorithm whose error depends almost linearly on the ratio of corrupted to uncorrupted samples, and show a lower bound with the same behavior, albeit with a gap of a constant factor.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19955v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.IT</category>
   <category>math.IT</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Malhar A. Managoli, Vinod M. Prabhakaran, Suhas Diggavi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>From Images to Signals: Are Large Vision Models Useful for Time Series Analysis?</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24030</link>
   <description>Transformer-based models have gained increasing attention in time series research, driving interest in Large Language Models (LLMs) and foundation models for time series analysis. As the field moves toward multi-modality, Large Vision Models (LVMs) are emerging as a promising direction. In the past, the effectiveness of Transformer and LLMs in time series has been debated. When it comes to LVMs, a similar question arises: are LVMs truely useful for time series analysis? To address it, we design and conduct the first principled study involving 4 LVMs, 8 imaging methods, 18 datasets and 26 baselines across both high-level (classification) and low-level (forecasting) tasks, with extensive ablation analysis. Our findings indicate LVMs are indeed useful for time series classification but face challenges in forecasting. Although effective, the contemporary best LVM forecasters are limited to specific types of LVMs and imaging methods, exhibit a bias toward forecasting periods, and have limited ability to utilize long look-back windows. We hope our findings could serve as a cornerstone for future research on LVM- and multimodal-based solutions to different time series tasks.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.24030v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ziming Zhao, ChengAo Shen, Hanghang Tong, Dongjin Song, Zhigang Deng, Qingsong Wen, Jingchao Ni</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>S2FGL: Spatial Spectral Federated Graph Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02409</link>
   <description>Federated Graph Learning (FGL) combines the privacy-preserving capabilities of federated learning (FL) with the strong graph modeling capability of Graph Neural Networks (GNNs). Current research addresses subgraph-FL only from the structural perspective, neglecting the propagation of graph signals on spatial and spectral domains of the structure. From a spatial perspective, subgraph-FL introduces edge disconnections between clients, leading to disruptions in label signals and a degradation in the class knowledge of the global GNN. From a spectral perspective, spectral heterogeneity causes inconsistencies in signal frequencies across subgraphs, which makes local GNNs overfit the local signal propagation schemes. As a result, spectral client drifts occur, undermining global generalizability. To tackle the challenges, we propose a global knowledge repository to mitigate label signal disruption and a frequency alignment to address spectral client drifts. The combination of spatial and spectral strategies forms our framework S2FGL. Extensive experiments on multiple datasets demonstrate the superiority of S2FGL. The code is available at https://github.com/Wonder7racer/S2FGL.git.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.02409v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zihan Tan, Suyuan Huang, Guancheng Wan, Wenke Huang, He Li, Mang Ye</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Nexus: Taming Throughput-Latency Tradeoff in LLM Serving via Efficient GPU Sharing</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06608</link>
   <description>Current prefill-decode (PD) disaggregation is typically deployed at the level of entire serving engines, assigning separate GPUs to handle prefill and decode phases. While effective at reducing latency, this approach demands more hardware. To improve GPU utilization, Chunked Prefill mixes prefill and decode requests within the same batch, but introduces phase interference between prefill and decode.
  While existing PD disaggregation solutions separate the phases across GPUs, we ask: can the same decoupling be achieved within a single serving engine? The key challenge lies in managing the conflicting resource requirements of prefill and decode when they share the same hardware. In this paper, we first show that chunked prefill requests cause interference with decode requests due to their distinct requirements for GPU resources. Second, we find that GPU resources exhibit diminishing returns. Beyond a saturation point, increasing GPU allocation yields negligible latency improvements. This insight enables us to split a single GPU's resources and dynamically allocate them to prefill and decode on the fly, effectively disaggregating the two phases within the same GPU.
  Across a range of models and workloads, our system Nexus achieves up to 2.2x higher throughput, 20x lower TTFT, and 2.5x lower TBT than vLLM. It also outperforms SGLang with up to 2x higher throughput, 2x lower TTFT, and 1.7x lower TBT, and achieves 1.4x higher throughput than vLLM-disaggregation using only half the number of GPUs.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.06608v2</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xiaoxiang Shi, Colin Cai, Junjia Du, Zhanda Zhu, Zhihao Jia</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Ampere: Communication-Efficient and High-Accuracy Split Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07130</link>
   <description>A Federated Learning (FL) system collaboratively trains neural networks across devices and a server but is limited by significant on-device computation costs. Split Federated Learning (SFL) systems mitigate this by offloading a block of layers of the network from the device to a server. However, in doing so, it introduces large communication overheads due to frequent exchanges of intermediate activations and gradients between devices and the server and reduces model accuracy for non-IID data. We propose Ampere, a novel collaborative training system that simultaneously minimizes on-device computation and device-server communication while improving model accuracy. Unlike SFL, which uses a global loss by iterative end-to-end training, Ampere develops unidirectional inter-block training to sequentially train the device and server block with a local loss, eliminating the transfer of gradients. A lightweight auxiliary network generation method decouples training between the device and server, reducing frequent intermediate exchanges to a single transfer, which significantly reduces the communication overhead. Ampere mitigates the impact of data heterogeneity by consolidating activations generated by the trained device block to train the server block, in contrast to SFL, which trains on device-specific, non-IID activations. Extensive experiments on multiple CNNs and transformers show that, compared to state-of-the-art SFL baseline systems, Ampere (i) improves model accuracy by up to 13.26% while reducing training time by up to 94.6%, (ii) reduces device-server communication overhead by up to 99.1% and on-device computation by up to 93.13%, and (iii) reduces standard deviation of accuracy by 53.39% for various non-IID degrees highlighting superior performance when faced with heterogeneous data.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.07130v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zihan Zhang, Leon Wong, Blesson Varghese</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>KVFlow: Efficient Prefix Caching for Accelerating LLM-Based Multi-Agent Workflows</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07400</link>
   <description>Large language model (LLM) based agentic workflows have become a popular paradigm for coordinating multiple specialized agents to solve complex tasks. To improve serving efficiency, existing LLM systems employ prefix caching to reuse key-value (KV) tensors corresponding to agents' fixed prompts, thereby avoiding redundant computation across repeated invocations. However, current systems typically evict KV caches using a Least Recently Used (LRU) policy, which fails to anticipate future agent usage and often discards KV caches shortly before their reuse. This leads to frequent cache misses and substantial recomputation or swapping overhead. We present KVFlow, a workflow-aware KV cache management framework tailored for agentic workloads. KVFlow abstracts the agent execution schedule as an Agent Step Graph and assigns each agent a steps-to-execution value that estimates its temporal proximity to future activation. These values guide a fine-grained eviction policy at the KV node level, allowing KVFlow to preserve entries likely to be reused and efficiently manage shared prefixes in tree-structured caches. Moreover, KVFlow introduces a fully overlapped KV prefetching mechanism, which proactively loads required tensors from CPU to GPU in background threads for agents scheduled in the next step, thereby avoiding cache miss stalls during generation. Compared to SGLang with hierarchical radix cache, KVFlow achieves up to 1.83$\times$ speedup for single workflows with large prompts, and up to 2.19$\times$ speedup for scenarios with many concurrent workflows.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.07400v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.MA</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zaifeng Pan, Ajjkumar Patel, Zhengding Hu, Yipeng Shen, Yue Guan, Wan-Lu Li, Lianhui Qin, Yida Wang, Yufei Ding</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Nexus: Taming Throughput-Latency Tradeoff in LLM Serving via Efficient GPU Sharing</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06608</link>
   <description>Current prefill-decode (PD) disaggregation is typically deployed at the level of entire serving engines, assigning separate GPUs to handle prefill and decode phases. While effective at reducing latency, this approach demands more hardware. To improve GPU utilization, Chunked Prefill mixes prefill and decode requests within the same batch, but introduces phase interference between prefill and decode.
  While existing PD disaggregation solutions separate the phases across GPUs, we ask: can the same decoupling be achieved within a single serving engine? The key challenge lies in managing the conflicting resource requirements of prefill and decode when they share the same hardware. In this paper, we first show that chunked prefill requests cause interference with decode requests due to their distinct requirements for GPU resources. Second, we find that GPU resources exhibit diminishing returns. Beyond a saturation point, increasing GPU allocation yields negligible latency improvements. This insight enables us to split a single GPU's resources and dynamically allocate them to prefill and decode on the fly, effectively disaggregating the two phases within the same GPU.
  Across a range of models and workloads, our system Nexus achieves up to 2.2x higher throughput, 20x lower TTFT, and 2.5x lower TBT than vLLM. It also outperforms SGLang with up to 2x higher throughput, 2x lower TTFT, and 1.7x lower TBT, and achieves 1.4x higher throughput than vLLM-disaggregation using only half the number of GPUs.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.06608v2</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xiaoxiang Shi, Colin Cai, Junjia Du, Zhanda Zhu, Zhihao Jia</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Tiny-Align: Bridging Automatic Speech Recognition and Large Language Model on the Edge</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13766</link>
   <description>The combination of Large Language Models (LLM) and Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR), when deployed on edge devices (called edge ASR-LLM), can serve as a powerful personalized assistant to enable audio-based interaction for users. Compared to text-based interaction, edge ASR-LLM allows accessible and natural audio interactions. Unfortunately, existing ASR-LLM models are mainly trained in high-performance computing environments and produce substantial model weights, making them difficult to deploy on edge devices. More importantly, to better serve users' personalized needs, the ASR-LLM must be able to learn from each distinct user, given that audio input often contains highly personalized characteristics that necessitate personalized on-device training. Since individually fine-tuning the ASR or LLM often leads to suboptimal results due to modality-specific limitations, end-to-end training ensures seamless integration of audio features and language understanding (cross-modal alignment), ultimately enabling a more personalized and efficient adaptation on edge devices. However, due to the complex training requirements and substantial computational demands of existing approaches, cross-modal alignment between ASR audio and LLM can be challenging on edge devices. In this work, we propose a resource-efficient cross-modal alignment framework that bridges ASR and LLMs on edge devices to handle personalized audio input. Our framework enables efficient ASR-LLM alignment on resource-constrained devices like NVIDIA Jetson Orin (8GB RAM), achieving 50x training time speedup while improving the alignment quality by more than 50\%. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first work to study efficient ASR-LLM alignment on resource-constrained edge devices.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2411.13766v3</guid>
   <category>cs.SD</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>eess.AS</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ruiyang Qin, Dancheng Liu, Gelei Xu, Zheyu Yan, Chenhui Xu, Yuting Hu, X. Sharon Hu, Jinjun Xiong, Yiyu Shi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>KVFlow: Efficient Prefix Caching for Accelerating LLM-Based Multi-Agent Workflows</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07400</link>
   <description>Large language model (LLM) based agentic workflows have become a popular paradigm for coordinating multiple specialized agents to solve complex tasks. To improve serving efficiency, existing LLM systems employ prefix caching to reuse key-value (KV) tensors corresponding to agents' fixed prompts, thereby avoiding redundant computation across repeated invocations. However, current systems typically evict KV caches using a Least Recently Used (LRU) policy, which fails to anticipate future agent usage and often discards KV caches shortly before their reuse. This leads to frequent cache misses and substantial recomputation or swapping overhead. We present KVFlow, a workflow-aware KV cache management framework tailored for agentic workloads. KVFlow abstracts the agent execution schedule as an Agent Step Graph and assigns each agent a steps-to-execution value that estimates its temporal proximity to future activation. These values guide a fine-grained eviction policy at the KV node level, allowing KVFlow to preserve entries likely to be reused and efficiently manage shared prefixes in tree-structured caches. Moreover, KVFlow introduces a fully overlapped KV prefetching mechanism, which proactively loads required tensors from CPU to GPU in background threads for agents scheduled in the next step, thereby avoiding cache miss stalls during generation. Compared to SGLang with hierarchical radix cache, KVFlow achieves up to 1.83$\times$ speedup for single workflows with large prompts, and up to 2.19$\times$ speedup for scenarios with many concurrent workflows.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.07400v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.MA</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zaifeng Pan, Ajjkumar Patel, Zhengding Hu, Yipeng Shen, Yue Guan, Wan-Lu Li, Lianhui Qin, Yida Wang, Yufei Ding</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedP3E: Privacy-Preserving Prototype Exchange for Non-IID IoT Malware Detection in Cross-Silo Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07258</link>
   <description>As IoT ecosystems continue to expand across critical sectors, they have become prominent targets for increasingly sophisticated and large-scale malware attacks. The evolving threat landscape, combined with the sensitive nature of IoT-generated data, demands detection frameworks that are both privacy-preserving and resilient to data heterogeneity. Federated Learning (FL) offers a promising solution by enabling decentralized model training without exposing raw data. However, standard FL algorithms such as FedAvg and FedProx often fall short in real-world deployments characterized by class imbalance and non-IID data distributions -- particularly in the presence of rare or disjoint malware classes. To address these challenges, we propose FedP3E (Privacy-Preserving Prototype Exchange), a novel FL framework that supports indirect cross-client representation sharing while maintaining data privacy. Each client constructs class-wise prototypes using Gaussian Mixture Models (GMMs), perturbs them with Gaussian noise, and transmits only these compact summaries to the server. The aggregated prototypes are then distributed back to clients and integrated into local training, supported by SMOTE-based augmentation to enhance representation of minority malware classes. Rather than relying solely on parameter averaging, our prototype-driven mechanism enables clients to enrich their local models with complementary structural patterns observed across the federation -- without exchanging raw data or gradients. This targeted strategy reduces the adverse impact of statistical heterogeneity with minimal communication overhead. We evaluate FedP3E on the N-BaIoT dataset under realistic cross-silo scenarios with varying degrees of data imbalance.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.07258v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Rami Darwish, Mahmoud Abdelsalam, Sajad Khorsandroo, Kaushik Roy</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Tiny-Align: Bridging Automatic Speech Recognition and Large Language Model on the Edge</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13766</link>
   <description>The combination of Large Language Models (LLM) and Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR), when deployed on edge devices (called edge ASR-LLM), can serve as a powerful personalized assistant to enable audio-based interaction for users. Compared to text-based interaction, edge ASR-LLM allows accessible and natural audio interactions. Unfortunately, existing ASR-LLM models are mainly trained in high-performance computing environments and produce substantial model weights, making them difficult to deploy on edge devices. More importantly, to better serve users' personalized needs, the ASR-LLM must be able to learn from each distinct user, given that audio input often contains highly personalized characteristics that necessitate personalized on-device training. Since individually fine-tuning the ASR or LLM often leads to suboptimal results due to modality-specific limitations, end-to-end training ensures seamless integration of audio features and language understanding (cross-modal alignment), ultimately enabling a more personalized and efficient adaptation on edge devices. However, due to the complex training requirements and substantial computational demands of existing approaches, cross-modal alignment between ASR audio and LLM can be challenging on edge devices. In this work, we propose a resource-efficient cross-modal alignment framework that bridges ASR and LLMs on edge devices to handle personalized audio input. Our framework enables efficient ASR-LLM alignment on resource-constrained devices like NVIDIA Jetson Orin (8GB RAM), achieving 50x training time speedup while improving the alignment quality by more than 50\%. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first work to study efficient ASR-LLM alignment on resource-constrained edge devices.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2411.13766v3</guid>
   <category>cs.SD</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>eess.AS</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ruiyang Qin, Dancheng Liu, Gelei Xu, Zheyu Yan, Chenhui Xu, Yuting Hu, X. Sharon Hu, Jinjun Xiong, Yiyu Shi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>From Images to Signals: Are Large Vision Models Useful for Time Series Analysis?</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24030</link>
   <description>Transformer-based models have gained increasing attention in time series research, driving interest in Large Language Models (LLMs) and foundation models for time series analysis. As the field moves toward multi-modality, Large Vision Models (LVMs) are emerging as a promising direction. In the past, the effectiveness of Transformer and LLMs in time series has been debated. When it comes to LVMs, a similar question arises: are LVMs truely useful for time series analysis? To address it, we design and conduct the first principled study involving 4 LVMs, 8 imaging methods, 18 datasets and 26 baselines across both high-level (classification) and low-level (forecasting) tasks, with extensive ablation analysis. Our findings indicate LVMs are indeed useful for time series classification but face challenges in forecasting. Although effective, the contemporary best LVM forecasters are limited to specific types of LVMs and imaging methods, exhibit a bias toward forecasting periods, and have limited ability to utilize long look-back windows. We hope our findings could serve as a cornerstone for future research on LVM- and multimodal-based solutions to different time series tasks.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.24030v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ziming Zhao, ChengAo Shen, Hanghang Tong, Dongjin Song, Zhigang Deng, Qingsong Wen, Jingchao Ni</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>S2FGL: Spatial Spectral Federated Graph Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02409</link>
   <description>Federated Graph Learning (FGL) combines the privacy-preserving capabilities of federated learning (FL) with the strong graph modeling capability of Graph Neural Networks (GNNs). Current research addresses subgraph-FL only from the structural perspective, neglecting the propagation of graph signals on spatial and spectral domains of the structure. From a spatial perspective, subgraph-FL introduces edge disconnections between clients, leading to disruptions in label signals and a degradation in the class knowledge of the global GNN. From a spectral perspective, spectral heterogeneity causes inconsistencies in signal frequencies across subgraphs, which makes local GNNs overfit the local signal propagation schemes. As a result, spectral client drifts occur, undermining global generalizability. To tackle the challenges, we propose a global knowledge repository to mitigate label signal disruption and a frequency alignment to address spectral client drifts. The combination of spatial and spectral strategies forms our framework S2FGL. Extensive experiments on multiple datasets demonstrate the superiority of S2FGL. The code is available at https://github.com/Wonder7racer/S2FGL.git.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.02409v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zihan Tan, Suyuan Huang, Guancheng Wan, Wenke Huang, He Li, Mang Ye</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Secure Cooperative Gradient Coding: Optimality, Reliability, and Global Privacy</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07565</link>
   <description>This paper studies privacy-sensitive federated learning (FL) with unreliable communication, focusing on secure aggregation and straggler mitigation. While secure aggregation cryptographically reconstructs the global model without exposing client updates, random link failures disrupt its key coordination, degrading model accuracy. Moreover, unreliable communication can lead to objective inconsistency, causing the global model to converge to arbitrary, sub-optimal points far from the intended optimum. This paper proposes Secure Cooperative Gradient Coding (SecCoGC), a practical solution that achieves secure aggregation with arbitrarily strong privacy guarantees and robust straggler mitigation under unreliable communication. SecCoGC operates natively in the real field, making it directly applicable to practical deployments. To ensure equitable privacy protection across clients, we further introduce Fair-SecCoGC, an extension that enforces fairness in the level of privacy offered to all users. To conclude, this paper formally formulates the problem of secure aggregation in the real field and presents both general and computationally efficient key construction methods. Moreover, it provides a comprehensive privacy analysis under Local Mutual Information Privacy (LMIP) and Local Differential Privacy (LDP) across all protocol layers. Robustness and convergence properties are also rigorously analyzed. Finally, extensive simulations are performed across diverse network conditions and benchmark datasets to validate the effectiveness of the proposed methods. The results show that SecCoGC achieves strong robustness to unreliable communication under arbitrarily strong privacy guarantees. It outperforms existing privacy-preserving methods with performance gains of up to 20\%-70\%.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.07565v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IT</category>
   <category>math.IT</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shudi Weng</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Robust Federated Personalised Mean Estimation for the Gaussian Mixture Model</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19955</link>
   <description>Federated learning with heterogeneous data and personalization has received significant recent attention. Separately, robustness to corrupted data in the context of federated learning has also been studied. In this paper we explore combining personalization for heterogeneous data with robustness, where a constant fraction of the clients are corrupted. Motivated by this broad problem, we formulate a simple instantiation which captures some of its difficulty. We focus on the specific problem of personalized mean estimation where the data is drawn from a Gaussian mixture model. We give an algorithm whose error depends almost linearly on the ratio of corrupted to uncorrupted samples, and show a lower bound with the same behavior, albeit with a gap of a constant factor.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.19955v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.IT</category>
   <category>math.IT</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Malhar A. Managoli, Vinod M. Prabhakaran, Suhas Diggavi</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
