<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 03:11:24 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 03:11:24 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>Optimal Transport-based Domain Alignment as a Preprocessing Step for Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04071</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) is a subfield of machine learning that avoids sharing local data with a central server, which can enhance privacy and scalability. The inability to consolidate data leads to a unique problem called dataset imbalance, where agents in a network do not have equal representation of the labels one is trying to learn to predict. In FL, fusing locally-trained models with unbalanced datasets may deteriorate the performance of global model aggregation, and reduce the quality of updated local models and the accuracy of the distributed agents' decisions. In this work, we introduce an Optimal Transport-based preprocessing algorithm that aligns the datasets by minimizing the distributional discrepancy of data along the edge devices. We accomplish this by leveraging Wasserstein barycenters when computing channel-wise averages. These barycenters are collected in a trusted central server where they collectively generate a target RGB space. By projecting our dataset towards this target space, we minimize the distributional discrepancy on a global level, which facilitates the learning process due to a minimization of variance across the samples. We demonstrate the capabilities of the proposed approach over the CIFAR-10 dataset, where we show its capability of reaching higher degrees of generalization in fewer communication rounds.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.04071v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Luiz Manella Pereira, M. Hadi Amini</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Language-Codec: Bridging Discrete Codec Representations and Speech Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.12208</link>
   <description>In recent years, large language models have achieved significant success in generative tasks related to speech, audio, music, and other signal domains. A crucial element of these models is the discrete acoustic codecs, which serve as an intermediate representation replacing the mel-spectrogram. However, there exist several gaps between discrete codecs and downstream speech language models. Specifically, 1) Due to the reconstruction paradigm of the Codec model and the structure of residual vector quantization, the initial channel of the codebooks contains excessive information, making it challenging to directly generate acoustic tokens from weakly supervised signals such as text in downstream tasks. 2) numerous codebooks increases the burden on downstream speech language models. Consequently, leveraging the characteristics of speech language models, we propose Language-Codec. In the Language-Codec, we introduce a Masked Channel Residual Vector Quantization (MCRVQ) mechanism along with improved fourier transform structures and attention blocks, refined discriminator design to address the aforementioned gaps. We compare our method with competing audio compression algorithms and observe significant outperformance across extensive evaluations. Furthermore, we also validate the efficiency of the Language-Codec on downstream speech language models. The source code and pre-trained models can be accessed at https://github.com/jishengpeng/languagecodec .</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2402.12208v4</guid>
   <category>eess.AS</category>
   <category>cs.SD</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shengpeng Ji, Minghui Fang, Jialong Zuo, Ziyue Jiang, Dingdong Wang, Hanting Wang, Hai Huang, Zhou Zhao</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Fault Localisation and Repair for DL Systems: An Empirical Study with LLMs</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03396</link>
   <description>Numerous Fault Localisation (FL) and repair techniques have been proposed to address faults in Deep Learning (DL) models. However, their effectiveness in practical applications remains uncertain due to the reliance on pre-defined rules. This paper presents a comprehensive evaluation of state-of-the-art FL and repair techniques, examining their advantages and limitations. Moreover, we introduce a novel approach that harnesses the power of Large Language Models (LLMs) in localising and repairing DL faults. Our evaluation, conducted on a carefully designed benchmark, reveals the strengths and weaknesses of current FL and repair techniques. We emphasise the importance of enhanced accuracy and the need for more rigorous assessment methods that employ multiple ground truth patches. Notably, LLMs exhibit remarkable performance in both FL and repair tasks. For instance, the GPT-4 model achieves 44% and 82% improvements in FL and repair tasks respectively, compared to the second-best tool, demonstrating the potential of LLMs in this domain. Our study sheds light on the current state of FL and repair techniques and suggests that LLMs could be a promising avenue for future advancements.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.03396v1</guid>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jinhan Kim, Nargiz Humbatova, Gunel Jahangirova, Shin Yoo, Paolo Tonella</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Cascadia: A Cascade Serving System for Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04203</link>
   <description>Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) have intensified the need to deliver both rapid responses and high-quality answers. More powerful models yield better results but incur higher inference latency, whereas smaller models are faster yet less capable. Recent work proposes balancing this latency-quality trade-off using model cascades, which route simpler queries to smaller models and more complex ones to larger models. However, enabling efficient cascade serving remains challenging. Current frameworks lack effective mechanisms for handling (i) the huge and varying resource demands of different LLMs, (ii) the inherent heterogeneity of LLM workloads, and (iii) the co-optimization of system deployment and routing strategy. Motivated by these observations, we introduce Cascadia, a novel cascade serving framework designed explicitly to schedule request routing and deploy model cascades for fast, quality-preserving LLM serving. Cascadia employs a bi-level optimization method: at the inner level, it uses a mixed-integer linear program to select resource allocations and parallelism strategies based on LLM information and workload characteristics; at the outer level, it applies a weighted Tchebycheff algorithm to iteratively co-optimize the routing strategy and the system deployment produced by the inner level. Our extensive evaluation on diverse workload traces and different model cascades (DeepSeek and the Llama series) demonstrates that Cascadia significantly outperforms both single-model deployments and the state-of-the-art cascade serving baseline, achieving up to 4x (2.3x on average) tighter latency SLOs and up to 5x (2.4x on average) higher throughput while maintaining target answer quality.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.04203v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Youhe Jiang, Fangcheng Fu, Wanru Zhao, Stephan Rabanser, Nicholas D. Lane, Binhang Yuan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>HtFLlib: A Comprehensive Heterogeneous Federated Learning Library and Benchmark</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03954</link>
   <description>As AI evolves, collaboration among heterogeneous models helps overcome data scarcity by enabling knowledge transfer across institutions and devices. Traditional Federated Learning (FL) only supports homogeneous models, limiting collaboration among clients with heterogeneous model architectures. To address this, Heterogeneous Federated Learning (HtFL) methods are developed to enable collaboration across diverse heterogeneous models while tackling the data heterogeneity issue at the same time. However, a comprehensive benchmark for standardized evaluation and analysis of the rapidly growing HtFL methods is lacking. Firstly, the highly varied datasets, model heterogeneity scenarios, and different method implementations become hurdles to making easy and fair comparisons among HtFL methods. Secondly, the effectiveness and robustness of HtFL methods are under-explored in various scenarios, such as the medical domain and sensor signal modality. To fill this gap, we introduce the first Heterogeneous Federated Learning Library (HtFLlib), an easy-to-use and extensible framework that integrates multiple datasets and model heterogeneity scenarios, offering a robust benchmark for research and practical applications. Specifically, HtFLlib integrates (1) 12 datasets spanning various domains, modalities, and data heterogeneity scenarios; (2) 40 model architectures, ranging from small to large, across three modalities; (3) a modularized and easy-to-extend HtFL codebase with implementations of 10 representative HtFL methods; and (4) systematic evaluations in terms of accuracy, convergence, computation costs, and communication costs. We emphasize the advantages and potential of state-of-the-art HtFL methods and hope that HtFLlib will catalyze advancing HtFL research and enable its broader applications. The code is released at https://github.com/TsingZ0/HtFLlib.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.03954v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jianqing Zhang, Xinghao Wu, Yanbing Zhou, Xiaoting Sun, Qiqi Cai, Yang Liu, Yang Hua, Zhenzhe Zheng, Jian Cao, Qiang Yang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>DFPL: Decentralized Federated Prototype Learning Across Heterogeneous Data Distributions</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04947</link>
   <description>Federated learning is a distributed machine learning paradigm through centralized model aggregation. However, standard federated learning relies on a centralized server, making it vulnerable to server failures. While existing solutions utilize blockchain technology to implement Decentralized Federated Learning (DFL), the statistical heterogeneity of data distributions among clients severely degrades the performance of DFL. Driven by this issue, this paper proposes a decentralized federated prototype learning framework, named DFPL, which significantly improves the performance of DFL across heterogeneous data distributions. Specifically, DFPL introduces prototype learning into DFL to mitigate the impact of statistical heterogeneity and reduces the amount of parameters exchanged between clients. Additionally, blockchain is embedded into our framework, enabling the training and mining processes to be implemented locally on each client. From a theoretical perspective, we provide convergence guarantee of DFPL by modeling the resource allocation between training and mining. The experiments highlight the superiority of our DFPL framework in model performance and communication efficiency across four benchmark datasets with heterogeneous data distributions.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.04947v2</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hongliang Zhang, Fenghua Xu, Zhongyuan Yu, Chunqiang Hu, Shanchen Pang, Xiaofen Wang, Jiguo Yu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>AdaptSFL: Adaptive Split Federated Learning in Resource-constrained Edge Networks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13101</link>
   <description>The increasing complexity of deep neural networks poses significant barriers to democratizing them to resource-limited edge devices. To address this challenge, split federated learning (SFL) has emerged as a promising solution by of floading the primary training workload to a server via model partitioning while enabling parallel training among edge devices. However, although system optimization substantially influences the performance of SFL under resource-constrained systems, the problem remains largely uncharted. In this paper, we provide a convergence analysis of SFL which quantifies the impact of model splitting (MS) and client-side model aggregation (MA) on the learning performance, serving as a theoretical foundation. Then, we propose AdaptSFL, a novel resource-adaptive SFL framework, to expedite SFL under resource-constrained edge computing systems. Specifically, AdaptSFL adaptively controls client-side MA and MS to balance communication-computing latency and training convergence. Extensive simulations across various datasets validate that our proposed AdaptSFL framework takes considerably less time to achieve a target accuracy than benchmarks, demonstrating the effectiveness of the proposed strategies.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2403.13101v4</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zheng Lin, Guanqiao Qu, Wei Wei, Xianhao Chen, Kin K. Leung</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>The Built-In Robustness of Decentralized Federated Averaging to Bad Data</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18097</link>
   <description>Decentralized federated learning (DFL) enables devices to collaboratively train models over complex network topologies without relying on a central controller. In this setting, local data remains private, but its quality and quantity can vary significantly across nodes. The extent to which a fully decentralized system is vulnerable to poor-quality or corrupted data remains unclear, but several factors could contribute to potential risks. Without a central authority, there can be no unified mechanism to detect or correct errors, and each node operates with a localized view of the data distribution, making it difficult for the node to assess whether its perspective aligns with the true distribution. Moreover, models trained on low-quality data can propagate through the network, amplifying errors. To explore the impact of low-quality data on DFL, we simulate two scenarios with degraded data quality -- one where the corrupted data is evenly distributed in a subset of nodes and one where it is concentrated on a single node -- using a decentralized implementation of FedAvg. Our results reveal that averaging-based decentralized learning is remarkably robust to localized bad data, even when the corrupted data resides in the most influential nodes of the network. Counterintuitively, this robustness is further enhanced when the corrupted data is concentrated on a single node, regardless of its centrality in the communication network topology. This phenomenon is explained by the averaging process, which ensures that no single node -- however central -- can disproportionately influence the overall learning process.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.18097v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Samuele Sabella, Chiara Boldrini, Lorenzo Valerio, Andrea Passarella, Marco Conti</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Exact and Linear Convergence for Federated Learning under Arbitrary Client Participation is Attainable</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20117</link>
   <description>This work tackles the fundamental challenges in Federated Learning (FL) posed by arbitrary client participation and data heterogeneity, prevalent characteristics in practical FL settings. It is well-established that popular FedAvg-style algorithms struggle with exact convergence and can suffer from slow convergence rates since a decaying learning rate is required to mitigate these scenarios. To address these issues, we introduce the concept of stochastic matrix and the corresponding time-varying graphs as a novel modeling tool to accurately capture the dynamics of arbitrary client participation and the local update procedure. Leveraging this approach, we offer a fresh perspective on designing FL algorithms, provide a rigorous quantitative analysis of the limitations inherent in the FedAvg algorithm, and present FOCUS, Federated Optimization with Exact Convergence via Push-pull Strategy, a provably convergent algorithm designed to effectively overcome the previously mentioned two challenges. More specifically, we provide a rigorous proof demonstrating that FOCUS achieves exact convergence with a linear rate regardless of the arbitrary client participation, establishing it as the first work to demonstrate this significant result.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.20117v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Bicheng Ying, Zhe Li, Haibo Yang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Towards Trustworthy Federated Learning with Untrusted Participants</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01874</link>
   <description>Resilience against malicious participants and data privacy are essential for trustworthy federated learning, yet achieving both with good utility typically requires the strong assumption of a trusted central server. This paper shows that a significantly weaker assumption suffices: each pair of participants shares a randomness seed unknown to others. In a setting where malicious participants may collude with an untrusted server, we propose CafCor, an algorithm that integrates robust gradient aggregation with correlated noise injection, using shared randomness between participants. We prove that CafCor achieves strong privacy-utility trade-offs, significantly outperforming local differential privacy (DP) methods, which do not make any trust assumption, while approaching central DP utility, where the server is fully trusted. Empirical results on standard benchmarks validate CafCor's practicality, showing that privacy and robustness can coexist in distributed systems without sacrificing utility or trusting the server.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.01874v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Youssef Allouah, Rachid Guerraoui, John Stephan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Fingerprinting Deep Learning Models via Network Traffic Patterns in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03207</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) is increasingly adopted as a decentralized machine learning paradigm due to its capability to preserve data privacy by training models without centralizing user data. However, FL is susceptible to indirect privacy breaches via network traffic analysis-an area not explored in existing research. The primary objective of this research is to study the feasibility of fingerprinting deep learning models deployed within FL environments by analyzing their network-layer traffic information. In this paper, we conduct an experimental evaluation using various deep learning architectures (i.e., CNN, RNN) within a federated learning testbed. We utilize machine learning algorithms, including Support Vector Machines (SVM), Random Forest, and Gradient-Boosting, to fingerprint unique patterns within the traffic data. Our experiments show high fingerprinting accuracy, achieving 100% accuracy using Random Forest and around 95.7% accuracy using SVM and Gradient Boosting classifiers. This analysis suggests that we can identify specific architectures running within the subsection of the network traffic. Hence, if an adversary knows about the underlying DL architecture, they can exploit that information and conduct targeted attacks. These findings suggest a notable security vulnerability in FL systems and the necessity of strengthening it at the network level.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.03207v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Md Nahid Hasan Shuvo, Moinul Hossain</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Mitigating Non-IID Drift in Zeroth-Order Federated LLM Fine-Tuning with Transferable Sparsity</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03337</link>
   <description>Federated Learning enables collaborative fine-tuning of Large Language Models (LLMs) across decentralized Non-Independent and Identically Distributed (Non-IID) clients, but such models' massive parameter sizes lead to significant memory and communication challenges. This work introduces Meerkat, a sparse zeroth-order optimization (ZO) method designed for federated LLM fine-tuning. By limiting fine-tuning to a transferable, static, extremely sparse subset of parameters, Meerkat achieves remarkable communication efficiency, enabling cost-effective high-frequency synchronization. With theoretical analysis and experiments, we show that this high-frequency communication effectively mitigates Non-IID data challenges and leads to superior performance compared to full-parameter ZO. Furthermore, experiment results show that Meerkat outperforms existing sparsity baselines with better performance at the same communication frequency. To further handle Non-IID drift, Meerkat leverages traceable local updates and forms a virtual path for each client. This virtual path mechanism reveals the GradIP phenomenon: the inner products between LLM pre-training gradients maintained by server and client gradients estimated via ZO converges for extreme Non-IID clients but oscillates for IID ones. This distinct behavior provides a signal for identifying clients with extreme data heterogeneity. Using this signal, Meerkat-vp is proposed to analyze GradIP trajectories to identify extreme Non-IID clients and applies early stopping to enhance aggregated model quality. Experiments confirm that Meerkat and Meerkat-vp significantly improve the efficiency and effectiveness of ZO federated LLM fine-tuning.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.03337v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yide Ran, Wentao Guo, Jingwei Sun, Yanzhou Pan, Xiaodong Yu, Hao Wang, Jianwen Xie, Yiran Chen, Denghui Zhang, Zhaozhuo Xu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Exploiting LLMs for Automatic Hypothesis Assessment via a Logit-Based Calibrated Prior</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03444</link>
   <description>As hypothesis generation becomes increasingly automated, a new bottleneck has emerged: hypothesis assessment. Modern systems can surface thousands of statistical relationships-correlations, trends, causal links-but offer little guidance on which ones are novel, non-trivial, or worthy of expert attention. In this work, we study the complementary problem to hypothesis generation: automatic hypothesis assessment. Specifically, we ask: given a large set of statistical relationships, can we automatically assess which ones are novel and worth further exploration? We focus on correlations as they are a common entry point in exploratory data analysis that often serve as the basis for forming deeper scientific or causal hypotheses.
  To support automatic assessment, we propose to leverage the vast knowledge encoded in LLMs' weights to derive a prior distribution over the correlation value of a variable pair. If an LLM's prior expects the correlation value observed, then such correlation is not surprising, and vice versa. We propose the Logit-based Calibrated Prior, an LLM-elicited correlation prior that transforms the model's raw output logits into a calibrated, continuous predictive distribution over correlation values. We evaluate the prior on a benchmark of 2,096 real-world variable pairs and it achieves a sign accuracy of 78.8%, a mean absolute error of 0.26, and 95% credible interval coverage of 89.2% in predicting Pearson correlation coefficient. It also outperforms a fine-tuned RoBERTa classifier in binary correlation prediction and achieves higher precision@K in hypothesis ranking. We further show that the prior generalizes to correlations not seen during LLM pretraining, reflecting context-sensitive reasoning rather than memorization.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.03444v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yue Gong, Raul Castro Fernandez</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>GCFL: A Gradient Correction-based Federated Learning Framework for Privacy-preserving CPSS</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03618</link>
   <description>Federated learning, as a distributed architecture, shows great promise for applications in Cyber-Physical-Social Systems (CPSS). In order to mitigate the privacy risks inherent in CPSS, the integration of differential privacy with federated learning has attracted considerable attention. Existing research mainly focuses on dynamically adjusting the noise added or discarding certain gradients to mitigate the noise introduced by differential privacy. However, these approaches fail to remove the noise that hinders convergence and correct the gradients affected by the noise, which significantly reduces the accuracy of model classification. To overcome these challenges, this paper proposes a novel framework for differentially private federated learning that balances rigorous privacy guarantees with accuracy by introducing a server-side gradient correction mechanism. Specifically, after clients perform gradient clipping and noise perturbation, our framework detects deviations in the noisy local gradients and employs a projection mechanism to correct them, mitigating the negative impact of noise. Simultaneously, gradient projection promotes the alignment of gradients from different clients and guides the model towards convergence to a global optimum. We evaluate our framework on several benchmark datasets, and the experimental results demonstrate that it achieves state-of-the-art performance under the same privacy budget.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.03618v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jiayi Wan, Xiang Zhu, Fanzhen Liu, Wei Fan, Xiaolong Xu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedFACT: A Provable Framework for Controllable Group-Fairness Calibration in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03777</link>
   <description>With emerging application of Federated Learning (FL) in decision-making scenarios, it is imperative to regulate model fairness to prevent disparities across sensitive groups (e.g., female, male). Current research predominantly focuses on two concepts of group fairness within FL: Global Fairness (overall model disparity across all clients) and Local Fairness (the disparity within each client). However, the non-decomposable, non-differentiable nature of fairness criteria pose two fundamental, unresolved challenges for fair FL: (i) Harmonizing global and local fairness in multi-class classification; (ii) Enabling a controllable, optimal accuracy-fairness trade-off. To tackle the aforementioned challenges, we propose a novel controllable federated group-fairness calibration framework, named FedFACT. FedFACT identifies the Bayes-optimal classifiers under both global and local fairness constraints in multi-class case, yielding models with minimal performance decline while guaranteeing fairness. To effectively realize an adjustable, optimal accuracy-fairness balance, we derive specific characterizations of the Bayes-optimal fair classifiers for reformulating fair FL as personalized cost-sensitive learning problem for in-processing, and bi-level optimization for post-processing. Theoretically, we provide convergence and generalization guarantees for FedFACT to approach the near-optimal accuracy under given fairness levels. Extensive experiments on multiple datasets across various data heterogeneity demonstrate that FedFACT consistently outperforms baselines in balancing accuracy and global-local fairness.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.03777v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Li Zhang, Zhongxuan Han, Chaochao chen, Xiaohua Feng, Jiaming Zhang, Yuyuan Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>HtFLlib: A Comprehensive Heterogeneous Federated Learning Library and Benchmark</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03954</link>
   <description>As AI evolves, collaboration among heterogeneous models helps overcome data scarcity by enabling knowledge transfer across institutions and devices. Traditional Federated Learning (FL) only supports homogeneous models, limiting collaboration among clients with heterogeneous model architectures. To address this, Heterogeneous Federated Learning (HtFL) methods are developed to enable collaboration across diverse heterogeneous models while tackling the data heterogeneity issue at the same time. However, a comprehensive benchmark for standardized evaluation and analysis of the rapidly growing HtFL methods is lacking. Firstly, the highly varied datasets, model heterogeneity scenarios, and different method implementations become hurdles to making easy and fair comparisons among HtFL methods. Secondly, the effectiveness and robustness of HtFL methods are under-explored in various scenarios, such as the medical domain and sensor signal modality. To fill this gap, we introduce the first Heterogeneous Federated Learning Library (HtFLlib), an easy-to-use and extensible framework that integrates multiple datasets and model heterogeneity scenarios, offering a robust benchmark for research and practical applications. Specifically, HtFLlib integrates (1) 12 datasets spanning various domains, modalities, and data heterogeneity scenarios; (2) 40 model architectures, ranging from small to large, across three modalities; (3) a modularized and easy-to-extend HtFL codebase with implementations of 10 representative HtFL methods; and (4) systematic evaluations in terms of accuracy, convergence, computation costs, and communication costs. We emphasize the advantages and potential of state-of-the-art HtFL methods and hope that HtFLlib will catalyze advancing HtFL research and enable its broader applications. The code is released at https://github.com/TsingZ0/HtFLlib.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.03954v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jianqing Zhang, Xinghao Wu, Yanbing Zhou, Xiaoting Sun, Qiqi Cai, Yang Liu, Yang Hua, Zhenzhe Zheng, Jian Cao, Qiang Yang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Optimal Transport-based Domain Alignment as a Preprocessing Step for Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04071</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) is a subfield of machine learning that avoids sharing local data with a central server, which can enhance privacy and scalability. The inability to consolidate data leads to a unique problem called dataset imbalance, where agents in a network do not have equal representation of the labels one is trying to learn to predict. In FL, fusing locally-trained models with unbalanced datasets may deteriorate the performance of global model aggregation, and reduce the quality of updated local models and the accuracy of the distributed agents' decisions. In this work, we introduce an Optimal Transport-based preprocessing algorithm that aligns the datasets by minimizing the distributional discrepancy of data along the edge devices. We accomplish this by leveraging Wasserstein barycenters when computing channel-wise averages. These barycenters are collected in a trusted central server where they collectively generate a target RGB space. By projecting our dataset towards this target space, we minimize the distributional discrepancy on a global level, which facilitates the learning process due to a minimization of variance across the samples. We demonstrate the capabilities of the proposed approach over the CIFAR-10 dataset, where we show its capability of reaching higher degrees of generalization in fewer communication rounds.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.04071v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Luiz Manella Pereira, M. Hadi Amini</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>AdaptSFL: Adaptive Split Federated Learning in Resource-constrained Edge Networks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13101</link>
   <description>The increasing complexity of deep neural networks poses significant barriers to democratizing them to resource-limited edge devices. To address this challenge, split federated learning (SFL) has emerged as a promising solution by of floading the primary training workload to a server via model partitioning while enabling parallel training among edge devices. However, although system optimization substantially influences the performance of SFL under resource-constrained systems, the problem remains largely uncharted. In this paper, we provide a convergence analysis of SFL which quantifies the impact of model splitting (MS) and client-side model aggregation (MA) on the learning performance, serving as a theoretical foundation. Then, we propose AdaptSFL, a novel resource-adaptive SFL framework, to expedite SFL under resource-constrained edge computing systems. Specifically, AdaptSFL adaptively controls client-side MA and MS to balance communication-computing latency and training convergence. Extensive simulations across various datasets validate that our proposed AdaptSFL framework takes considerably less time to achieve a target accuracy than benchmarks, demonstrating the effectiveness of the proposed strategies.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2403.13101v4</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zheng Lin, Guanqiao Qu, Wei Wei, Xianhao Chen, Kin K. Leung</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>The Built-In Robustness of Decentralized Federated Averaging to Bad Data</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18097</link>
   <description>Decentralized federated learning (DFL) enables devices to collaboratively train models over complex network topologies without relying on a central controller. In this setting, local data remains private, but its quality and quantity can vary significantly across nodes. The extent to which a fully decentralized system is vulnerable to poor-quality or corrupted data remains unclear, but several factors could contribute to potential risks. Without a central authority, there can be no unified mechanism to detect or correct errors, and each node operates with a localized view of the data distribution, making it difficult for the node to assess whether its perspective aligns with the true distribution. Moreover, models trained on low-quality data can propagate through the network, amplifying errors. To explore the impact of low-quality data on DFL, we simulate two scenarios with degraded data quality -- one where the corrupted data is evenly distributed in a subset of nodes and one where it is concentrated on a single node -- using a decentralized implementation of FedAvg. Our results reveal that averaging-based decentralized learning is remarkably robust to localized bad data, even when the corrupted data resides in the most influential nodes of the network. Counterintuitively, this robustness is further enhanced when the corrupted data is concentrated on a single node, regardless of its centrality in the communication network topology. This phenomenon is explained by the averaging process, which ensures that no single node -- however central -- can disproportionately influence the overall learning process.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.18097v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Samuele Sabella, Chiara Boldrini, Lorenzo Valerio, Andrea Passarella, Marco Conti</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Exact and Linear Convergence for Federated Learning under Arbitrary Client Participation is Attainable</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20117</link>
   <description>This work tackles the fundamental challenges in Federated Learning (FL) posed by arbitrary client participation and data heterogeneity, prevalent characteristics in practical FL settings. It is well-established that popular FedAvg-style algorithms struggle with exact convergence and can suffer from slow convergence rates since a decaying learning rate is required to mitigate these scenarios. To address these issues, we introduce the concept of stochastic matrix and the corresponding time-varying graphs as a novel modeling tool to accurately capture the dynamics of arbitrary client participation and the local update procedure. Leveraging this approach, we offer a fresh perspective on designing FL algorithms, provide a rigorous quantitative analysis of the limitations inherent in the FedAvg algorithm, and present FOCUS, Federated Optimization with Exact Convergence via Push-pull Strategy, a provably convergent algorithm designed to effectively overcome the previously mentioned two challenges. More specifically, we provide a rigorous proof demonstrating that FOCUS achieves exact convergence with a linear rate regardless of the arbitrary client participation, establishing it as the first work to demonstrate this significant result.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.20117v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Bicheng Ying, Zhe Li, Haibo Yang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Towards Trustworthy Federated Learning with Untrusted Participants</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01874</link>
   <description>Resilience against malicious participants and data privacy are essential for trustworthy federated learning, yet achieving both with good utility typically requires the strong assumption of a trusted central server. This paper shows that a significantly weaker assumption suffices: each pair of participants shares a randomness seed unknown to others. In a setting where malicious participants may collude with an untrusted server, we propose CafCor, an algorithm that integrates robust gradient aggregation with correlated noise injection, using shared randomness between participants. We prove that CafCor achieves strong privacy-utility trade-offs, significantly outperforming local differential privacy (DP) methods, which do not make any trust assumption, while approaching central DP utility, where the server is fully trusted. Empirical results on standard benchmarks validate CafCor's practicality, showing that privacy and robustness can coexist in distributed systems without sacrificing utility or trusting the server.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.01874v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Youssef Allouah, Rachid Guerraoui, John Stephan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Secure and Private Federated Learning: Achieving Adversarial Resilience through Robust Aggregation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17226</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) enables collaborative machine learning across decentralized data sources without sharing raw data. It offers a promising approach to privacy-preserving AI. However, FL remains vulnerable to adversarial threats from malicious participants, referred to as Byzantine clients, who can send misleading updates to corrupt the global model. Traditional aggregation methods, such as simple averaging, are not robust to such attacks. More resilient approaches, like the Krum algorithm, require prior knowledge of the number of malicious clients, which is often unavailable in real-world scenarios. To address these limitations, we propose Average-rKrum (ArKrum), a novel aggregation strategy designed to enhance both the resilience and privacy guarantees of FL systems. Building on our previous work (rKrum), ArKrum introduces two key innovations. First, it includes a median-based filtering mechanism that removes extreme outliers before estimating the number of adversarial clients. Second, it applies a multi-update averaging scheme to improve stability and performance, particularly when client data distributions are not identical. We evaluate ArKrum on benchmark image and text datasets under three widely studied Byzantine attack types. Results show that ArKrum consistently achieves high accuracy and stability. It performs as well as or better than other robust aggregation methods. These findings demonstrate that ArKrum is an effective and practical solution for secure FL systems in adversarial environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.17226v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kun Yang, Neena Imam</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>The Gaussian Mixing Mechanism: Renyi Differential Privacy via Gaussian Sketches</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24603</link>
   <description>Gaussian sketching, which consists of pre-multiplying the data with a random Gaussian matrix, is a widely used technique for multiple problems in data science and machine learning, with applications spanning computationally efficient optimization, coded computing, and federated learning. This operation also provides differential privacy guarantees due to its inherent randomness. In this work, we revisit this operation through the lens of Renyi Differential Privacy (RDP), providing a refined privacy analysis that yields significantly tighter bounds than prior results. We then demonstrate how this improved analysis leads to performance improvement in different linear regression settings, establishing theoretical utility guarantees. Empirically, our methods improve performance across multiple datasets and, in several cases, reduce runtime.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.24603v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Omri Lev, Vishwak Srinivasan, Moshe Shenfeld, Katrina Ligett, Ayush Sekhari, Ashia C. Wilson</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Unveiling Client Privacy Leakage from Public Dataset Usage in Federated Distillation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08001</link>
   <description>Federated Distillation (FD) has emerged as a popular federated training framework, enabling clients to collaboratively train models without sharing private data. Public Dataset-Assisted Federated Distillation (PDA-FD), which leverages public datasets for knowledge sharing, has become widely adopted. Although PDA-FD enhances privacy compared to traditional Federated Learning, we demonstrate that the use of public datasets still poses significant privacy risks to clients' private training data. This paper presents the first comprehensive privacy analysis of PDA-FD in presence of an honest-but-curious server. We show that the server can exploit clients' inference results on public datasets to extract two critical types of private information: label distributions and membership information of the private training dataset. To quantify these vulnerabilities, we introduce two novel attacks specifically designed for the PDA-FD setting: a label distribution inference attack and innovative membership inference methods based on Likelihood Ratio Attack (LiRA). Through extensive evaluation of three representative PDA-FD frameworks (FedMD, DS-FL, and Cronus), our attacks achieve state-of-the-art performance, with label distribution attacks reaching minimal KL-divergence and membership inference attacks maintaining high True Positive Rates under low False Positive Rate constraints. Our findings reveal significant privacy risks in current PDA-FD frameworks and emphasize the need for more robust privacy protection mechanisms in collaborative learning systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.08001v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Haonan Shi, Tu Ouyang, An Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Generalization in Federated Learning: A Conditional Mutual Information Framework</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04091</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) is a widely adopted privacy-preserving distributed learning framework, yet its generalization performance remains less explored compared to centralized learning. In FL, the generalization error consists of two components: the out-of-sample gap, which measures the gap between the empirical and true risk for participating clients, and the participation gap, which quantifies the risk difference between participating and non-participating clients. In this work, we apply an information-theoretic analysis via the conditional mutual information (CMI) framework to study FL's two-level generalization. Beyond the traditional supersample-based CMI framework, we introduce a superclient construction to accommodate the two-level generalization setting in FL. We derive multiple CMI-based bounds, including hypothesis-based CMI bounds, illustrating how privacy constraints in FL can imply generalization guarantees. Furthermore, we propose fast-rate evaluated CMI bounds that recover the best-known convergence rate for two-level FL generalization in the small empirical risk regime. For specific FL model aggregation strategies and structured loss functions, we refine our bounds to achieve improved convergence rates with respect to the number of participating clients. Empirical evaluations confirm that our evaluated CMI bounds are non-vacuous and accurately capture the generalization behavior of FL algorithms.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.04091v2</guid>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <category>cs.IT</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>math.IT</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ziqiao Wang, Cheng Long, Yongyi Mao</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>S$^3$: Social-network Simulation System with Large Language Model-Empowered Agents</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.14984</link>
   <description>Social network simulation plays a crucial role in addressing various challenges within social science. It offers extensive applications such as state prediction, phenomena explanation, and policy-making support, among others. In this work, we harness the formidable human-like capabilities exhibited by large language models (LLMs) in sensing, reasoning, and behaving, and utilize these qualities to construct the S$^3$ system (short for $\textbf{S}$ocial network $\textbf{S}$imulation $\textbf{S}$ystem). Adhering to the widely employed agent-based simulation paradigm, we employ prompt engineering and prompt tuning techniques to ensure that the agent's behavior closely emulates that of a genuine human within the social network. Specifically, we simulate three pivotal aspects: emotion, attitude, and interaction behaviors. By endowing the agent in the system with the ability to perceive the informational environment and emulate human actions, we observe the emergence of population-level phenomena, including the propagation of information, attitudes, and emotions. We conduct an evaluation encompassing two levels of simulation, employing real-world social network data. Encouragingly, the results demonstrate promising accuracy. This work represents an initial step in the realm of social network simulation empowered by LLM-based agents. We anticipate that our endeavors will serve as a source of inspiration for the development of simulation systems within, but not limited to, social science.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2307.14984v3</guid>
   <category>cs.SI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Chen Gao, Xiaochong Lan, Zhihong Lu, Jinzhu Mao, Jinghua Piao, Huandong Wang, Depeng Jin, Yong Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Generalization in Federated Learning: A Conditional Mutual Information Framework</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04091</link>
   <description>Federated learning (FL) is a widely adopted privacy-preserving distributed learning framework, yet its generalization performance remains less explored compared to centralized learning. In FL, the generalization error consists of two components: the out-of-sample gap, which measures the gap between the empirical and true risk for participating clients, and the participation gap, which quantifies the risk difference between participating and non-participating clients. In this work, we apply an information-theoretic analysis via the conditional mutual information (CMI) framework to study FL's two-level generalization. Beyond the traditional supersample-based CMI framework, we introduce a superclient construction to accommodate the two-level generalization setting in FL. We derive multiple CMI-based bounds, including hypothesis-based CMI bounds, illustrating how privacy constraints in FL can imply generalization guarantees. Furthermore, we propose fast-rate evaluated CMI bounds that recover the best-known convergence rate for two-level FL generalization in the small empirical risk regime. For specific FL model aggregation strategies and structured loss functions, we refine our bounds to achieve improved convergence rates with respect to the number of participating clients. Empirical evaluations confirm that our evaluated CMI bounds are non-vacuous and accurately capture the generalization behavior of FL algorithms.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.04091v2</guid>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <category>cs.IT</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>math.IT</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ziqiao Wang, Cheng Long, Yongyi Mao</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>ConsistentChat: Building Skeleton-Guided Consistent Dialogues for Large Language Models from Scratch</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03558</link>
   <description>Current instruction data synthesis methods primarily focus on single-turn instructions and often neglect cross-turn coherence, resulting in context drift and reduced task completion rates in extended conversations. To address this limitation, we propose Skeleton-Guided Multi-Turn Dialogue Generation, a framework that constrains multi-turn instruction synthesis by explicitly modeling human conversational intent. It operates in two stages: (1) Intent Modeling, which captures the global structure of human dialogues by assigning each conversation to one of nine well-defined intent trajectories, ensuring a coherent and goal-oriented information flow; and (2) Skeleton Generation, which constructs a structurally grounded sequence of user queries aligned with the modeled intent, thereby serving as a scaffold that constrains and guides the downstream instruction synthesis process. Based on this process, we construct ConsistentChat, a multi-turn instruction dataset with approximately 15,000 multi-turn conversations and 224,392 utterances. Experiments on the Light, Topdial, and MT-Eval benchmarks show that models fine-tuned on ConsistentChat achieve a 20-30% improvement in chat consistency and up to a 15% increase in task success rate, significantly outperforming models trained on existing single-turn and multi-turn instruction datasets.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.03558v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jiawei Chen, Xinyan Guan, Qianhao Yuan, Guozhao Mo, Weixiang Zhou, Yaojie Lu, Hongyu Lin, Ben He, Le Sun, Xianpei Han</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Exploiting LLMs for Automatic Hypothesis Assessment via a Logit-Based Calibrated Prior</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03444</link>
   <description>As hypothesis generation becomes increasingly automated, a new bottleneck has emerged: hypothesis assessment. Modern systems can surface thousands of statistical relationships-correlations, trends, causal links-but offer little guidance on which ones are novel, non-trivial, or worthy of expert attention. In this work, we study the complementary problem to hypothesis generation: automatic hypothesis assessment. Specifically, we ask: given a large set of statistical relationships, can we automatically assess which ones are novel and worth further exploration? We focus on correlations as they are a common entry point in exploratory data analysis that often serve as the basis for forming deeper scientific or causal hypotheses.
  To support automatic assessment, we propose to leverage the vast knowledge encoded in LLMs' weights to derive a prior distribution over the correlation value of a variable pair. If an LLM's prior expects the correlation value observed, then such correlation is not surprising, and vice versa. We propose the Logit-based Calibrated Prior, an LLM-elicited correlation prior that transforms the model's raw output logits into a calibrated, continuous predictive distribution over correlation values. We evaluate the prior on a benchmark of 2,096 real-world variable pairs and it achieves a sign accuracy of 78.8%, a mean absolute error of 0.26, and 95% credible interval coverage of 89.2% in predicting Pearson correlation coefficient. It also outperforms a fine-tuned RoBERTa classifier in binary correlation prediction and achieves higher precision@K in hypothesis ranking. We further show that the prior generalizes to correlations not seen during LLM pretraining, reflecting context-sensitive reasoning rather than memorization.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.03444v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yue Gong, Raul Castro Fernandez</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Enhancing LLM-Based Short Answer Grading with Retrieval-Augmented Generation</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05276</link>
   <description>Short answer assessment is a vital component of science education, allowing evaluation of students' complex three-dimensional understanding. Large language models (LLMs) that possess human-like ability in linguistic tasks are increasingly popular in assisting human graders to reduce their workload. However, LLMs' limitations in domain knowledge restrict their understanding in task-specific requirements and hinder their ability to achieve satisfactory performance. Retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) emerges as a promising solution by enabling LLMs to access relevant domain-specific knowledge during assessment. In this work, we propose an adaptive RAG framework for automated grading that dynamically retrieves and incorporates domain-specific knowledge based on the question and student answer context. Our approach combines semantic search and curated educational sources to retrieve valuable reference materials. Experimental results in a science education dataset demonstrate that our system achieves an improvement in grading accuracy compared to baseline LLM approaches. The findings suggest that RAG-enhanced grading systems can serve as reliable support with efficient performance gains.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2504.05276v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yucheng Chu, Peng He, Hang Li, Haoyu Han, Kaiqi Yang, Yu Xue, Tingting Li, Joseph Krajcik, Jiliang Tang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>MultiHoax: A Dataset of Multi-hop False-Premise Questions</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00264</link>
   <description>As Large Language Models are increasingly deployed in high-stakes domains, their ability to detect false assumptions and reason critically is crucial for ensuring reliable outputs. False-premise questions (FPQs) serve as an important evaluation method by exposing cases where flawed assumptions lead to incorrect responses. While existing benchmarks focus on single-hop FPQs, real-world reasoning often requires multi-hop inference, where models must verify consistency across multiple reasoning steps rather than relying on surface-level cues. To address this gap, we introduce MultiHoax, a benchmark for evaluating LLMs' ability to handle false premises in complex, multi-step reasoning tasks. Our dataset spans seven countries and ten diverse knowledge categories, using Wikipedia as the primary knowledge source to enable factual reasoning across regions. Experiments reveal that state-of-the-art LLMs struggle to detect false premises across different countries, knowledge categories, and multi-hop reasoning types, highlighting the need for improved false premise detection and more robust multi-hop reasoning capabilities in LLMs.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.00264v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mohammadamin Shafiei, Hamidreza Saffari, Nafise Sadat Moosavi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Let's Reason Formally: Natural-Formal Hybrid Reasoning Enhances LLM's Math Capability</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23703</link>
   <description>Enhancing the mathematical reasoning capabilities of LLMs has garnered significant attention in both the mathematical and computer science communities. Recent works have made substantial progress in both Natural Language (NL) reasoning and Formal Language (FL) reasoning by leveraging the potential of pure Reinforcement Learning (RL) methods on base models. However, RL approaches struggle to impart new capabilities not presented in the base model, highlighting the need to integrate more knowledge like FL into NL math reasoning effectively. Yet, this integration is challenging due to inherent disparities in problem structure and reasoning format between NL and FL. To address these challenges, we introduce **NL-FL HybridReasoning**, an end-to-end framework designed to incorporate the FL expert into NL math problem-solving. To bridge the NL and FL input format gap, we propose the *NL-FL Problem Alignment* method, which reformulates the Question-Answering (QA) problems in NL as existence theorems in FL. Subsequently, the *Mixed Problem Input* technique we provide enables the FL reasoner to handle both QA and existence problems concurrently. Lastly, we mitigate the NL and FL output format gap in reasoning through an LLM-based *Answer Extraction* mechanism. Comprehensive experiments demonstrate that the **HybridReasoning** framework achieves **89.80%** and **84.34%** accuracy rates on the MATH-500 and the AMC benchmarks, surpassing the NL baseline by 4.60% and 4.82%, respectively. Notably, some problems resolved by our framework remain unsolved by the NL baseline model even under a larger number of trials.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.23703v2</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ruida Wang, Yuxin Li, Yi R. Fung, Tong Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Fingerprinting Deep Learning Models via Network Traffic Patterns in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03207</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) is increasingly adopted as a decentralized machine learning paradigm due to its capability to preserve data privacy by training models without centralizing user data. However, FL is susceptible to indirect privacy breaches via network traffic analysis-an area not explored in existing research. The primary objective of this research is to study the feasibility of fingerprinting deep learning models deployed within FL environments by analyzing their network-layer traffic information. In this paper, we conduct an experimental evaluation using various deep learning architectures (i.e., CNN, RNN) within a federated learning testbed. We utilize machine learning algorithms, including Support Vector Machines (SVM), Random Forest, and Gradient-Boosting, to fingerprint unique patterns within the traffic data. Our experiments show high fingerprinting accuracy, achieving 100% accuracy using Random Forest and around 95.7% accuracy using SVM and Gradient Boosting classifiers. This analysis suggests that we can identify specific architectures running within the subsection of the network traffic. Hence, if an adversary knows about the underlying DL architecture, they can exploit that information and conduct targeted attacks. These findings suggest a notable security vulnerability in FL systems and the necessity of strengthening it at the network level.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.03207v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Md Nahid Hasan Shuvo, Moinul Hossain</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Mitigating Non-IID Drift in Zeroth-Order Federated LLM Fine-Tuning with Transferable Sparsity</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03337</link>
   <description>Federated Learning enables collaborative fine-tuning of Large Language Models (LLMs) across decentralized Non-Independent and Identically Distributed (Non-IID) clients, but such models' massive parameter sizes lead to significant memory and communication challenges. This work introduces Meerkat, a sparse zeroth-order optimization (ZO) method designed for federated LLM fine-tuning. By limiting fine-tuning to a transferable, static, extremely sparse subset of parameters, Meerkat achieves remarkable communication efficiency, enabling cost-effective high-frequency synchronization. With theoretical analysis and experiments, we show that this high-frequency communication effectively mitigates Non-IID data challenges and leads to superior performance compared to full-parameter ZO. Furthermore, experiment results show that Meerkat outperforms existing sparsity baselines with better performance at the same communication frequency. To further handle Non-IID drift, Meerkat leverages traceable local updates and forms a virtual path for each client. This virtual path mechanism reveals the GradIP phenomenon: the inner products between LLM pre-training gradients maintained by server and client gradients estimated via ZO converges for extreme Non-IID clients but oscillates for IID ones. This distinct behavior provides a signal for identifying clients with extreme data heterogeneity. Using this signal, Meerkat-vp is proposed to analyze GradIP trajectories to identify extreme Non-IID clients and applies early stopping to enhance aggregated model quality. Experiments confirm that Meerkat and Meerkat-vp significantly improve the efficiency and effectiveness of ZO federated LLM fine-tuning.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.03337v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yide Ran, Wentao Guo, Jingwei Sun, Yanzhou Pan, Xiaodong Yu, Hao Wang, Jianwen Xie, Yiran Chen, Denghui Zhang, Zhaozhuo Xu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>GCFL: A Gradient Correction-based Federated Learning Framework for Privacy-preserving CPSS</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03618</link>
   <description>Federated learning, as a distributed architecture, shows great promise for applications in Cyber-Physical-Social Systems (CPSS). In order to mitigate the privacy risks inherent in CPSS, the integration of differential privacy with federated learning has attracted considerable attention. Existing research mainly focuses on dynamically adjusting the noise added or discarding certain gradients to mitigate the noise introduced by differential privacy. However, these approaches fail to remove the noise that hinders convergence and correct the gradients affected by the noise, which significantly reduces the accuracy of model classification. To overcome these challenges, this paper proposes a novel framework for differentially private federated learning that balances rigorous privacy guarantees with accuracy by introducing a server-side gradient correction mechanism. Specifically, after clients perform gradient clipping and noise perturbation, our framework detects deviations in the noisy local gradients and employs a projection mechanism to correct them, mitigating the negative impact of noise. Simultaneously, gradient projection promotes the alignment of gradients from different clients and guides the model towards convergence to a global optimum. We evaluate our framework on several benchmark datasets, and the experimental results demonstrate that it achieves state-of-the-art performance under the same privacy budget.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.03618v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jiayi Wan, Xiang Zhu, Fanzhen Liu, Wei Fan, Xiaolong Xu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>HtFLlib: A Comprehensive Heterogeneous Federated Learning Library and Benchmark</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03954</link>
   <description>As AI evolves, collaboration among heterogeneous models helps overcome data scarcity by enabling knowledge transfer across institutions and devices. Traditional Federated Learning (FL) only supports homogeneous models, limiting collaboration among clients with heterogeneous model architectures. To address this, Heterogeneous Federated Learning (HtFL) methods are developed to enable collaboration across diverse heterogeneous models while tackling the data heterogeneity issue at the same time. However, a comprehensive benchmark for standardized evaluation and analysis of the rapidly growing HtFL methods is lacking. Firstly, the highly varied datasets, model heterogeneity scenarios, and different method implementations become hurdles to making easy and fair comparisons among HtFL methods. Secondly, the effectiveness and robustness of HtFL methods are under-explored in various scenarios, such as the medical domain and sensor signal modality. To fill this gap, we introduce the first Heterogeneous Federated Learning Library (HtFLlib), an easy-to-use and extensible framework that integrates multiple datasets and model heterogeneity scenarios, offering a robust benchmark for research and practical applications. Specifically, HtFLlib integrates (1) 12 datasets spanning various domains, modalities, and data heterogeneity scenarios; (2) 40 model architectures, ranging from small to large, across three modalities; (3) a modularized and easy-to-extend HtFL codebase with implementations of 10 representative HtFL methods; and (4) systematic evaluations in terms of accuracy, convergence, computation costs, and communication costs. We emphasize the advantages and potential of state-of-the-art HtFL methods and hope that HtFLlib will catalyze advancing HtFL research and enable its broader applications. The code is released at https://github.com/TsingZ0/HtFLlib.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2506.03954v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Jianqing Zhang, Xinghao Wu, Yanbing Zhou, Xiaoting Sun, Qiqi Cai, Yang Liu, Yang Hua, Zhenzhe Zheng, Jian Cao, Qiang Yang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Let's Reason Formally: Natural-Formal Hybrid Reasoning Enhances LLM's Math Capability</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23703</link>
   <description>Enhancing the mathematical reasoning capabilities of LLMs has garnered significant attention in both the mathematical and computer science communities. Recent works have made substantial progress in both Natural Language (NL) reasoning and Formal Language (FL) reasoning by leveraging the potential of pure Reinforcement Learning (RL) methods on base models. However, RL approaches struggle to impart new capabilities not presented in the base model, highlighting the need to integrate more knowledge like FL into NL math reasoning effectively. Yet, this integration is challenging due to inherent disparities in problem structure and reasoning format between NL and FL. To address these challenges, we introduce **NL-FL HybridReasoning**, an end-to-end framework designed to incorporate the FL expert into NL math problem-solving. To bridge the NL and FL input format gap, we propose the *NL-FL Problem Alignment* method, which reformulates the Question-Answering (QA) problems in NL as existence theorems in FL. Subsequently, the *Mixed Problem Input* technique we provide enables the FL reasoner to handle both QA and existence problems concurrently. Lastly, we mitigate the NL and FL output format gap in reasoning through an LLM-based *Answer Extraction* mechanism. Comprehensive experiments demonstrate that the **HybridReasoning** framework achieves **89.80%** and **84.34%** accuracy rates on the MATH-500 and the AMC benchmarks, surpassing the NL baseline by 4.60% and 4.82%, respectively. Notably, some problems resolved by our framework remain unsolved by the NL baseline model even under a larger number of trials.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2505.23703v2</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ruida Wang, Yuxin Li, Yi R. Fung, Tong Zhang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>AdaptSFL: Adaptive Split Federated Learning in Resource-constrained Edge Networks</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13101</link>
   <description>The increasing complexity of deep neural networks poses significant barriers to democratizing them to resource-limited edge devices. To address this challenge, split federated learning (SFL) has emerged as a promising solution by of floading the primary training workload to a server via model partitioning while enabling parallel training among edge devices. However, although system optimization substantially influences the performance of SFL under resource-constrained systems, the problem remains largely uncharted. In this paper, we provide a convergence analysis of SFL which quantifies the impact of model splitting (MS) and client-side model aggregation (MA) on the learning performance, serving as a theoretical foundation. Then, we propose AdaptSFL, a novel resource-adaptive SFL framework, to expedite SFL under resource-constrained edge computing systems. Specifically, AdaptSFL adaptively controls client-side MA and MS to balance communication-computing latency and training convergence. Extensive simulations across various datasets validate that our proposed AdaptSFL framework takes considerably less time to achieve a target accuracy than benchmarks, demonstrating the effectiveness of the proposed strategies.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2403.13101v4</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zheng Lin, Guanqiao Qu, Wei Wei, Xianhao Chen, Kin K. Leung</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>The Built-In Robustness of Decentralized Federated Averaging to Bad Data</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18097</link>
   <description>Decentralized federated learning (DFL) enables devices to collaboratively train models over complex network topologies without relying on a central controller. In this setting, local data remains private, but its quality and quantity can vary significantly across nodes. The extent to which a fully decentralized system is vulnerable to poor-quality or corrupted data remains unclear, but several factors could contribute to potential risks. Without a central authority, there can be no unified mechanism to detect or correct errors, and each node operates with a localized view of the data distribution, making it difficult for the node to assess whether its perspective aligns with the true distribution. Moreover, models trained on low-quality data can propagate through the network, amplifying errors. To explore the impact of low-quality data on DFL, we simulate two scenarios with degraded data quality -- one where the corrupted data is evenly distributed in a subset of nodes and one where it is concentrated on a single node -- using a decentralized implementation of FedAvg. Our results reveal that averaging-based decentralized learning is remarkably robust to localized bad data, even when the corrupted data resides in the most influential nodes of the network. Counterintuitively, this robustness is further enhanced when the corrupted data is concentrated on a single node, regardless of its centrality in the communication network topology. This phenomenon is explained by the averaging process, which ensures that no single node -- however central -- can disproportionately influence the overall learning process.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.18097v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Samuele Sabella, Chiara Boldrini, Lorenzo Valerio, Andrea Passarella, Marco Conti</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
