<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2025 04:13:45 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2025 04:13:45 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>Vision Foundation Models in Medical Image Analysis: Advances and Challenges</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14584</link>
   <description>The rapid development of Vision Foundation Models (VFMs), particularly Vision Transformers (ViT) and Segment Anything Model (SAM), has sparked significant advances in the field of medical image analysis. These models have demonstrated exceptional capabilities in capturing long-range dependencies and achieving high generalization in segmentation tasks. However, adapting these large models to medical image analysis presents several challenges, including domain differences between medical and natural images, the need for efficient model adaptation strategies, and the limitations of small-scale medical datasets. This paper reviews the state-of-the-art research on the adaptation of VFMs to medical image segmentation, focusing on the challenges of domain adaptation, model compression, and federated learning. We discuss the latest developments in adapter-based improvements, knowledge distillation techniques, and multi-scale contextual feature modeling, and propose future directions to overcome these bottlenecks. Our analysis highlights the potential of VFMs, along with emerging methodologies such as federated learning and model compression, to revolutionize medical image analysis and enhance clinical applications. The goal of this work is to provide a comprehensive overview of current approaches and suggest key areas for future research that can drive the next wave of innovation in medical image segmentation.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.14584v1</guid>
   <category>eess.IV</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Pengchen Liang, Bin Pu, Haishan Huang, Yiwei Li, Hualiang Wang, Weibo Ma, Qing Chang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Where's the Bug? Attention Probing for Scalable Fault Localization</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13966</link>
   <description>Ensuring code correctness remains a challenging problem even as large language models (LLMs) become increasingly capable at code-related tasks. While LLM-based program repair systems can propose bug fixes using only a user's bug report, their effectiveness is fundamentally limited by their ability to perform fault localization (FL), a challenging problem for both humans and LLMs. Existing FL approaches rely on executable test cases, require training on costly and often noisy line-level annotations, or demand resource-intensive LLMs. In this paper, we present Bug Attention Probe (BAP), a method which learns state-of-the-art fault localization without any direct localization labels, outperforming traditional FL baselines and prompting of large-scale LLMs. We evaluate our approach across a variety of code settings, including real-world Java bugs from the standard Defects4J dataset as well as seven other datasets which span a diverse set of bug types and languages. Averaged across all eight datasets, BAP improves by 34.6% top-1 accuracy compared to the strongest baseline and 93.4% over zero-shot prompting GPT-4o. BAP is also significantly more efficient than prompting, outperforming large open-weight models at a small fraction of the computational cost.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.13966v2</guid>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Adam Stein, Arthur Wayne, Aaditya Naik, Mayur Naik, Eric Wong</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Blockchain-based Framework for Scalable and Incentivized Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14170</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) enables collaborative model training without sharing raw data, preserving privacy while harnessing distributed datasets. However, traditional FL systems often rely on centralized aggregating mechanisms, introducing trust issues, single points of failure, and limited mechanisms for incentivizing meaningful client contributions. These challenges are exacerbated as FL scales to train resource-intensive models, such as large language models (LLMs), requiring scalable, decentralized solutions. This paper presents a blockchain-based FL framework that addresses these limitations by integrating smart contracts and a novel hybrid incentive mechanism. The framework automates critical FL tasks, including client registration, update validation, reward distribution, and maintaining a transparent global state. The hybrid incentive mechanism combines on-chain alignment-based rewards, off-chain fairness checks, and consistency multipliers to ensure fairness, transparency, and sustained engagement. We evaluate the framework through gas cost analysis, demonstrating its feasibility for different scales of federated learning scenarios.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.14170v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Bijun Wu, Oshani Seneviratne</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Fine-Tuning of Large Language Models: Kahneman-Tversky vs. Direct Preference Optimization</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14187</link>
   <description>We evaluate Kahneman-Tversky Optimization (KTO) as a fine-tuning method for large language models (LLMs) in federated learning (FL) settings, comparing it against Direct Preference Optimization (DPO). Using Alpaca-7B as the base model, we fine-tune on a realistic dataset under both methods and evaluate performance using MT-Bench-1, Vicuna, and AdvBench benchmarks. Additionally, we introduce a redistributed dataset setup, where only KTO is applicable due to its ability to handle single-response feedback, unlike DPO's reliance on paired responses. Our results demonstrate that KTO, in both its original (KTOO) and redistributed (KTOR) configurations, consistently outperforms DPO across all benchmarks. In the redistributed setup, KTO further validates its flexibility and resilience by maintaining superior performance in scenarios where DPO cannot be applied. These findings establish KTO as a robust and scalable fine-tuning method for FL, motivating its adoption for privacy-preserving, decentralized, and heterogeneous environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.14187v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Fernando Spadea, Oshani Seneviratne</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Accurate Forgetting for Heterogeneous Federated Continual Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14205</link>
   <description>Recent years have witnessed a burgeoning interest in federated learning (FL). However, the contexts in which clients engage in sequential learning remain under-explored. Bridging FL and continual learning (CL) gives rise to a challenging practical problem: federated continual learning (FCL). Existing research in FCL primarily focuses on mitigating the catastrophic forgetting issue of continual learning while collaborating with other clients. We argue that the forgetting phenomena are not invariably detrimental. In this paper, we consider a more practical and challenging FCL setting characterized by potentially unrelated or even antagonistic data/tasks across different clients. In the FL scenario, statistical heterogeneity and data noise among clients may exhibit spurious correlations which result in biased feature learning. While existing CL strategies focus on a complete utilization of previous knowledge, we found that forgetting biased information is beneficial in our study. Therefore, we propose a new concept accurate forgetting (AF) and develop a novel generative-replay method~\method~which selectively utilizes previous knowledge in federated networks. We employ a probabilistic framework based on a normalizing flow model to quantify the credibility of previous knowledge. Comprehensive experiments affirm the superiority of our method over baselines.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.14205v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Abudukelimu Wuerkaixi, Sen Cui, Jingfeng Zhang, Kunda Yan, Bo Han, Gang Niu, Lei Fang, Changshui Zhang, Masashi Sugiyama</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LabTOP: A Unified Model for Lab Test Outcome Prediction on Electronic Health Records</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14259</link>
   <description>Lab tests are fundamental for diagnosing diseases and monitoring patient conditions. However, frequent testing can be burdensome for patients, and test results may not always be immediately available. To address these challenges, we propose LabTOP, a unified model that predicts lab test outcomes by leveraging a language modeling approach on EHR data. Unlike conventional methods that estimate only a subset of lab tests or classify discrete value ranges, LabTOP performs continuous numerical predictions for a diverse range of lab items. We evaluate LabTOP on three publicly available EHR datasets and demonstrate that it outperforms existing methods, including traditional machine learning models and state-of-the-art large language models. We also conduct extensive ablation studies to confirm the effectiveness of our design choices. We believe that LabTOP will serve as an accurate and generalizable framework for lab test outcome prediction, with potential applications in clinical decision support and early detection of critical conditions.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.14259v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sujeong Im, Jungwoo Oh, Edward Choi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>VFL-RPS: Relevant Participant Selection in Vertical Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14375</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) allows collaboration between different parties, while ensuring that the data across these parties is not shared. However, not every collaboration is helpful in terms of the resulting model performance. Therefore, it is an important challenge to select the correct participants in a collaboration. As it currently stands, most of the efforts in participant selection in the literature have focused on Horizontal Federated Learning (HFL), which assumes that all features are the same across all participants, disregarding the possibility of different features across participants which is captured in Vertical Federated Learning (VFL). To close this gap in the literature, we propose a novel method VFL-RPS for participant selection in VFL, as a pre-training step. We have tested our method on several data sets performing both regression and classification tasks, showing that our method leads to comparable results as using all data by only selecting a few participants. In addition, we show that our method outperforms existing methods for participant selection in VFL.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.14375v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Afsana Khan, Marijn ten Thij, Guangzhi Tang, Anna Wilbik</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Efficient AI in Practice: Training and Deployment of Efficient LLMs for Industry Applications</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14305</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable performance across a wide range of industrial applications, from search and recommendations to generative tasks. Although scaling laws indicate that larger models generally yield better generalization and performance, their substantial computational requirements often render them impractical for many real-world scenarios at scale. In this paper, we present methods and insights for training small language models (SLMs) that deliver high performance and efficiency in deployment. We focus on two key techniques: (1) knowledge distillation and (2) model compression via quantization and pruning. These approaches enable SLMs to retain much of the quality of their larger counterparts while significantly reducing training, serving costs, and latency. We detail the impact of these techniques on a variety of use cases at a large professional social network platform and share deployment lessons - including hardware optimization strategies that enhance speed and throughput for both predictive and reasoning-based applications.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.14305v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kayhan Behdin, Yun Dai, Ata Fatahibaarzi, Aman Gupta, Qingquan Song, Shao Tang, Hejian Sang, Gregory Dexter, Sirou Zhu, Siyu Zhu, Tejas Dharamsi, Maziar Sanjabi, Vignesh Kothapalli, Hamed Firooz, Zhoutong Fu, Yihan Cao, Pin-Lun Hsu, Fedor Borisyuk, Zhipeng Wang, Rahul Mazumder, Natesh Pillai, Luke Simon</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LServe: Efficient Long-sequence LLM Serving with Unified Sparse Attention</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14866</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) have shown remarkable potential in processing long sequences, yet efficiently serving these long-context models remains challenging due to the quadratic computational complexity of attention in the prefilling stage and the large memory footprint of the KV cache in the decoding stage. To address these issues, we introduce LServe, an efficient system that accelerates long-sequence LLM serving via hybrid sparse attention. This method unifies different hardware-friendly, structured sparsity patterns for both prefilling and decoding attention into a single framework, where computations on less important tokens are skipped block-wise. LServe demonstrates the compatibility of static and dynamic sparsity in long-context LLM attention. This design enables multiplicative speedups by combining these optimizations. Specifically, we convert half of the attention heads to nearly free streaming heads in both the prefilling and decoding stages. Additionally, we find that only a constant number of KV pages is required to preserve long-context capabilities, irrespective of context length. We then design a hierarchical KV page selection policy that dynamically prunes KV pages based on query-centric similarity. On average, LServe accelerates LLM prefilling by up to 2.9x and decoding by 1.3-2.1x over vLLM, maintaining long-context accuracy. Code is released at https://github.com/mit-han-lab/omniserve.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.14866v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.PF</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shang Yang, Junxian Guo, Haotian Tang, Qinghao Hu, Guangxuan Xiao, Jiaming Tang, Yujun Lin, Zhijian Liu, Yao Lu, Song Han</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Where's the Bug? Attention Probing for Scalable Fault Localization</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13966</link>
   <description>Ensuring code correctness remains a challenging problem even as large language models (LLMs) become increasingly capable at code-related tasks. While LLM-based program repair systems can propose bug fixes using only a user's bug report, their effectiveness is fundamentally limited by their ability to perform fault localization (FL), a challenging problem for both humans and LLMs. Existing FL approaches rely on executable test cases, require training on costly and often noisy line-level annotations, or demand resource-intensive LLMs. In this paper, we present Bug Attention Probe (BAP), a method which learns state-of-the-art fault localization without any direct localization labels, outperforming traditional FL baselines and prompting of large-scale LLMs. We evaluate our approach across a variety of code settings, including real-world Java bugs from the standard Defects4J dataset as well as seven other datasets which span a diverse set of bug types and languages. Averaged across all eight datasets, BAP improves by 34.6% top-1 accuracy compared to the strongest baseline and 93.4% over zero-shot prompting GPT-4o. BAP is also significantly more efficient than prompting, outperforming large open-weight models at a small fraction of the computational cost.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.13966v2</guid>
   <category>cs.SE</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Adam Stein, Arthur Wayne, Aaditya Naik, Mayur Naik, Eric Wong</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Serving Models, Fast and Slow:Optimizing Heterogeneous LLM Inferencing Workloads at Scale</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14617</link>
   <description>Large Language Model (LLM) inference workloads handled by global cloud providers can include both latency-sensitive and insensitive tasks, creating a diverse range of Service Level Agreement (SLA) requirements. Managing these mixed workloads is challenging due to the complexity of the inference stack, which includes multiple LLMs, hardware configurations, and geographic distributions. Current optimization strategies often silo these tasks to ensure that SLAs are met for latency-sensitive tasks, but this leads to significant under-utilization of expensive GPU resources despite the availability of spot and on-demand Virtual Machine (VM) provisioning. We propose SAGESERVE, a comprehensive LLM serving framework that employs adaptive control knobs at varying time scales, ensuring SLA compliance while maximizing the utilization of valuable GPU resources. Short-term optimizations include efficient request routing to data center regions, while long-term strategies involve scaling GPU VMs out/in and redeploying models to existing VMs to align with traffic patterns. These strategies are formulated as an optimization problem for resource allocation and solved using Integer Linear Programming (ILP). We perform empirical and simulation studies based on production workload traces with over 8M requests using four open-source models deployed across three regions. SAGESERVE achieves up to 25% savings in GPU-hours while maintaining tail latency and satisfying all SLOs, and it reduces the scaling overhead compared to baselines by up to 80%, confirming the effectiveness of our proposal. In terms of dollar cost, this can save cloud providers up to $2M over the course of a month.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.14617v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shashwat Jaiswal, Kunal Jain, Yogesh Simmhan, Anjaly Parayil, Ankur Mallick, Rujia Wang, Renee St. Amant, Chetan Bansal, Victor R\&quot;uhle, Anoop Kulkarni, Steve Kofsky, Saravan Rajmohan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Blockchain-based Framework for Scalable and Incentivized Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14170</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) enables collaborative model training without sharing raw data, preserving privacy while harnessing distributed datasets. However, traditional FL systems often rely on centralized aggregating mechanisms, introducing trust issues, single points of failure, and limited mechanisms for incentivizing meaningful client contributions. These challenges are exacerbated as FL scales to train resource-intensive models, such as large language models (LLMs), requiring scalable, decentralized solutions. This paper presents a blockchain-based FL framework that addresses these limitations by integrating smart contracts and a novel hybrid incentive mechanism. The framework automates critical FL tasks, including client registration, update validation, reward distribution, and maintaining a transparent global state. The hybrid incentive mechanism combines on-chain alignment-based rewards, off-chain fairness checks, and consistency multipliers to ensure fairness, transparency, and sustained engagement. We evaluate the framework through gas cost analysis, demonstrating its feasibility for different scales of federated learning scenarios.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.14170v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Bijun Wu, Oshani Seneviratne</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LServe: Efficient Long-sequence LLM Serving with Unified Sparse Attention</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14866</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) have shown remarkable potential in processing long sequences, yet efficiently serving these long-context models remains challenging due to the quadratic computational complexity of attention in the prefilling stage and the large memory footprint of the KV cache in the decoding stage. To address these issues, we introduce LServe, an efficient system that accelerates long-sequence LLM serving via hybrid sparse attention. This method unifies different hardware-friendly, structured sparsity patterns for both prefilling and decoding attention into a single framework, where computations on less important tokens are skipped block-wise. LServe demonstrates the compatibility of static and dynamic sparsity in long-context LLM attention. This design enables multiplicative speedups by combining these optimizations. Specifically, we convert half of the attention heads to nearly free streaming heads in both the prefilling and decoding stages. Additionally, we find that only a constant number of KV pages is required to preserve long-context capabilities, irrespective of context length. We then design a hierarchical KV page selection policy that dynamically prunes KV pages based on query-centric similarity. On average, LServe accelerates LLM prefilling by up to 2.9x and decoding by 1.3-2.1x over vLLM, maintaining long-context accuracy. Code is released at https://github.com/mit-han-lab/omniserve.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.14866v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.PF</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shang Yang, Junxian Guo, Haotian Tang, Qinghao Hu, Guangxuan Xiao, Jiaming Tang, Yujun Lin, Zhijian Liu, Yao Lu, Song Han</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Accurate Forgetting for Heterogeneous Federated Continual Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14205</link>
   <description>Recent years have witnessed a burgeoning interest in federated learning (FL). However, the contexts in which clients engage in sequential learning remain under-explored. Bridging FL and continual learning (CL) gives rise to a challenging practical problem: federated continual learning (FCL). Existing research in FCL primarily focuses on mitigating the catastrophic forgetting issue of continual learning while collaborating with other clients. We argue that the forgetting phenomena are not invariably detrimental. In this paper, we consider a more practical and challenging FCL setting characterized by potentially unrelated or even antagonistic data/tasks across different clients. In the FL scenario, statistical heterogeneity and data noise among clients may exhibit spurious correlations which result in biased feature learning. While existing CL strategies focus on a complete utilization of previous knowledge, we found that forgetting biased information is beneficial in our study. Therefore, we propose a new concept accurate forgetting (AF) and develop a novel generative-replay method~\method~which selectively utilizes previous knowledge in federated networks. We employ a probabilistic framework based on a normalizing flow model to quantify the credibility of previous knowledge. Comprehensive experiments affirm the superiority of our method over baselines.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.14205v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Abudukelimu Wuerkaixi, Sen Cui, Jingfeng Zhang, Kunda Yan, Bo Han, Gang Niu, Lei Fang, Changshui Zhang, Masashi Sugiyama</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Capturing Nuanced Preferences: Preference-Aligned Distillation for Small Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14272</link>
   <description>Aligning small language models (SLMs) with human values typically involves distilling preference knowledge from large language models (LLMs). However, existing distillation methods model preference knowledge in teacher LLMs by comparing pairwise responses, overlooking the extent of difference between responses. This limitation hinders student SLMs from capturing the nuanced preferences for multiple responses. In this paper, we propose a Preference-Aligned Distillation (PAD) framework, which models teacher's preference knowledge as a probability distribution over all potential preferences, thereby providing more nuanced supervisory signals. Our insight in developing PAD is rooted in the demonstration that language models can serve as reward functions, reflecting their intrinsic preferences. Based on this, PAD comprises three key steps: (1) sampling diverse responses using high-temperature; (2) computing rewards for both teacher and student to construct their intrinsic preference; and (3) training the student's intrinsic preference distribution to align with the teacher's. Experiments on four mainstream alignment benchmarks demonstrate that PAD consistently and significantly outperforms existing approaches, achieving over 20\% improvement on AlpacaEval 2 and Arena-Hard, indicating superior alignment with human preferences. Notably, on MT-Bench, using the \textsc{Gemma} model family, the student trained by PAD surpasses its teacher, further validating the effectiveness of our PAD.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.14272v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yanggan Gu, Junzhuo Li, Sirui Huang, Xin Zou, Zhenghua Li, Xuming Hu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FUIA: Model Inversion Attack against Federated Unlearning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14558</link>
   <description>With the introduction of regulations related to the ``right to be forgotten&quot;, federated learning (FL) is facing new privacy compliance challenges. To address these challenges, researchers have proposed federated unlearning (FU). However, existing FU research has primarily focused on improving the efficiency of unlearning, with less attention paid to the potential privacy vulnerabilities inherent in these methods. To address this gap, we draw inspiration from gradient inversion attacks in FL and propose the federated unlearning inversion attack (FUIA). The FUIA is specifically designed for the three types of FU (sample unlearning, client unlearning, and class unlearning), aiming to provide a comprehensive analysis of the privacy leakage risks associated with FU. In FUIA, the server acts as an honest-but-curious attacker, recording and exploiting the model differences before and after unlearning to expose the features and labels of forgotten data. FUIA significantly leaks the privacy of forgotten data and can target all types of FU. This attack contradicts the goal of FU to eliminate specific data influence, instead exploiting its vulnerabilities to recover forgotten data and expose its privacy flaws. Extensive experimental results show that FUIA can effectively reveal the private information of forgotten data. To mitigate this privacy leakage, we also explore two potential defense methods, although these come at the cost of reduced unlearning effectiveness and the usability of the unlearned model.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.14558v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Lei Zhou, Youwen Zhu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LServe: Efficient Long-sequence LLM Serving with Unified Sparse Attention</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14866</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) have shown remarkable potential in processing long sequences, yet efficiently serving these long-context models remains challenging due to the quadratic computational complexity of attention in the prefilling stage and the large memory footprint of the KV cache in the decoding stage. To address these issues, we introduce LServe, an efficient system that accelerates long-sequence LLM serving via hybrid sparse attention. This method unifies different hardware-friendly, structured sparsity patterns for both prefilling and decoding attention into a single framework, where computations on less important tokens are skipped block-wise. LServe demonstrates the compatibility of static and dynamic sparsity in long-context LLM attention. This design enables multiplicative speedups by combining these optimizations. Specifically, we convert half of the attention heads to nearly free streaming heads in both the prefilling and decoding stages. Additionally, we find that only a constant number of KV pages is required to preserve long-context capabilities, irrespective of context length. We then design a hierarchical KV page selection policy that dynamically prunes KV pages based on query-centric similarity. On average, LServe accelerates LLM prefilling by up to 2.9x and decoding by 1.3-2.1x over vLLM, maintaining long-context accuracy. Code is released at https://github.com/mit-han-lab/omniserve.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.14866v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.PF</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shang Yang, Junxian Guo, Haotian Tang, Qinghao Hu, Guangxuan Xiao, Jiaming Tang, Yujun Lin, Zhijian Liu, Yao Lu, Song Han</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Capturing Nuanced Preferences: Preference-Aligned Distillation for Small Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14272</link>
   <description>Aligning small language models (SLMs) with human values typically involves distilling preference knowledge from large language models (LLMs). However, existing distillation methods model preference knowledge in teacher LLMs by comparing pairwise responses, overlooking the extent of difference between responses. This limitation hinders student SLMs from capturing the nuanced preferences for multiple responses. In this paper, we propose a Preference-Aligned Distillation (PAD) framework, which models teacher's preference knowledge as a probability distribution over all potential preferences, thereby providing more nuanced supervisory signals. Our insight in developing PAD is rooted in the demonstration that language models can serve as reward functions, reflecting their intrinsic preferences. Based on this, PAD comprises three key steps: (1) sampling diverse responses using high-temperature; (2) computing rewards for both teacher and student to construct their intrinsic preference; and (3) training the student's intrinsic preference distribution to align with the teacher's. Experiments on four mainstream alignment benchmarks demonstrate that PAD consistently and significantly outperforms existing approaches, achieving over 20\% improvement on AlpacaEval 2 and Arena-Hard, indicating superior alignment with human preferences. Notably, on MT-Bench, using the \textsc{Gemma} model family, the student trained by PAD surpasses its teacher, further validating the effectiveness of our PAD.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.14272v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yanggan Gu, Junzhuo Li, Sirui Huang, Xin Zou, Zhenghua Li, Xuming Hu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>SurveyX: Academic Survey Automation via Large Language Models</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14776</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated exceptional comprehension capabilities and a vast knowledge base, suggesting that LLMs can serve as efficient tools for automated survey generation. However, recent research related to automated survey generation remains constrained by some critical limitations like finite context window, lack of in-depth content discussion, and absence of systematic evaluation frameworks. Inspired by human writing processes, we propose SurveyX, an efficient and organized system for automated survey generation that decomposes the survey composing process into two phases: the Preparation and Generation phases. By innovatively introducing online reference retrieval, a pre-processing method called AttributeTree, and a re-polishing process, SurveyX significantly enhances the efficacy of survey composition. Experimental evaluation results show that SurveyX outperforms existing automated survey generation systems in content quality (0.259 improvement) and citation quality (1.76 enhancement), approaching human expert performance across multiple evaluation dimensions. Examples of surveys generated by SurveyX are available on www.surveyx.cn</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.14776v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xun Liang, Jiawei Yang, Yezhaohui Wang, Chen Tang, Zifan Zheng, Simin Niu, Shichao Song, Hanyu Wang, Bo Tang, Feiyu Xiong, Keming Mao, Zhiyu li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LServe: Efficient Long-sequence LLM Serving with Unified Sparse Attention</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14866</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) have shown remarkable potential in processing long sequences, yet efficiently serving these long-context models remains challenging due to the quadratic computational complexity of attention in the prefilling stage and the large memory footprint of the KV cache in the decoding stage. To address these issues, we introduce LServe, an efficient system that accelerates long-sequence LLM serving via hybrid sparse attention. This method unifies different hardware-friendly, structured sparsity patterns for both prefilling and decoding attention into a single framework, where computations on less important tokens are skipped block-wise. LServe demonstrates the compatibility of static and dynamic sparsity in long-context LLM attention. This design enables multiplicative speedups by combining these optimizations. Specifically, we convert half of the attention heads to nearly free streaming heads in both the prefilling and decoding stages. Additionally, we find that only a constant number of KV pages is required to preserve long-context capabilities, irrespective of context length. We then design a hierarchical KV page selection policy that dynamically prunes KV pages based on query-centric similarity. On average, LServe accelerates LLM prefilling by up to 2.9x and decoding by 1.3-2.1x over vLLM, maintaining long-context accuracy. Code is released at https://github.com/mit-han-lab/omniserve.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.14866v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.PF</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shang Yang, Junxian Guo, Haotian Tang, Qinghao Hu, Guangxuan Xiao, Jiaming Tang, Yujun Lin, Zhijian Liu, Yao Lu, Song Han</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Federated Fine-Tuning of Large Language Models: Kahneman-Tversky vs. Direct Preference Optimization</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14187</link>
   <description>We evaluate Kahneman-Tversky Optimization (KTO) as a fine-tuning method for large language models (LLMs) in federated learning (FL) settings, comparing it against Direct Preference Optimization (DPO). Using Alpaca-7B as the base model, we fine-tune on a realistic dataset under both methods and evaluate performance using MT-Bench-1, Vicuna, and AdvBench benchmarks. Additionally, we introduce a redistributed dataset setup, where only KTO is applicable due to its ability to handle single-response feedback, unlike DPO's reliance on paired responses. Our results demonstrate that KTO, in both its original (KTOO) and redistributed (KTOR) configurations, consistently outperforms DPO across all benchmarks. In the redistributed setup, KTO further validates its flexibility and resilience by maintaining superior performance in scenarios where DPO cannot be applied. These findings establish KTO as a robust and scalable fine-tuning method for FL, motivating its adoption for privacy-preserving, decentralized, and heterogeneous environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.14187v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Fernando Spadea, Oshani Seneviratne</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LServe: Efficient Long-sequence LLM Serving with Unified Sparse Attention</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14866</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) have shown remarkable potential in processing long sequences, yet efficiently serving these long-context models remains challenging due to the quadratic computational complexity of attention in the prefilling stage and the large memory footprint of the KV cache in the decoding stage. To address these issues, we introduce LServe, an efficient system that accelerates long-sequence LLM serving via hybrid sparse attention. This method unifies different hardware-friendly, structured sparsity patterns for both prefilling and decoding attention into a single framework, where computations on less important tokens are skipped block-wise. LServe demonstrates the compatibility of static and dynamic sparsity in long-context LLM attention. This design enables multiplicative speedups by combining these optimizations. Specifically, we convert half of the attention heads to nearly free streaming heads in both the prefilling and decoding stages. Additionally, we find that only a constant number of KV pages is required to preserve long-context capabilities, irrespective of context length. We then design a hierarchical KV page selection policy that dynamically prunes KV pages based on query-centric similarity. On average, LServe accelerates LLM prefilling by up to 2.9x and decoding by 1.3-2.1x over vLLM, maintaining long-context accuracy. Code is released at https://github.com/mit-han-lab/omniserve.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.14866v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.PF</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shang Yang, Junxian Guo, Haotian Tang, Qinghao Hu, Guangxuan Xiao, Jiaming Tang, Yujun Lin, Zhijian Liu, Yao Lu, Song Han</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Efficient AI in Practice: Training and Deployment of Efficient LLMs for Industry Applications</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14305</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable performance across a wide range of industrial applications, from search and recommendations to generative tasks. Although scaling laws indicate that larger models generally yield better generalization and performance, their substantial computational requirements often render them impractical for many real-world scenarios at scale. In this paper, we present methods and insights for training small language models (SLMs) that deliver high performance and efficiency in deployment. We focus on two key techniques: (1) knowledge distillation and (2) model compression via quantization and pruning. These approaches enable SLMs to retain much of the quality of their larger counterparts while significantly reducing training, serving costs, and latency. We detail the impact of these techniques on a variety of use cases at a large professional social network platform and share deployment lessons - including hardware optimization strategies that enhance speed and throughput for both predictive and reasoning-based applications.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.14305v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Kayhan Behdin, Yun Dai, Ata Fatahibaarzi, Aman Gupta, Qingquan Song, Shao Tang, Hejian Sang, Gregory Dexter, Sirou Zhu, Siyu Zhu, Tejas Dharamsi, Maziar Sanjabi, Vignesh Kothapalli, Hamed Firooz, Zhoutong Fu, Yihan Cao, Pin-Lun Hsu, Fedor Borisyuk, Zhipeng Wang, Rahul Mazumder, Natesh Pillai, Luke Simon</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
