<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 02:52:39 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 02:52:39 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>Hyper-Connections</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19606</link>
   <description>We present hyper-connections, a simple yet effective method that can serve as an alternative to residual connections. This approach specifically addresses common drawbacks observed in residual connection variants, such as the seesaw effect between gradient vanishing and representation collapse. Theoretically, hyper-connections allow the network to adjust the strength of connections between features at different depths and dynamically rearrange layers. We conduct experiments focusing on the pre-training of large language models, including dense and sparse models, where hyper-connections show significant performance improvements over residual connections. Additional experiments conducted on vision tasks also demonstrate similar improvements. We anticipate that this method will be broadly applicable and beneficial across a wide range of AI problems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2409.19606v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.NE</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Defa Zhu, Hongzhi Huang, Zihao Huang, Yutao Zeng, Yunyao Mao, Banggu Wu, Qiyang Min, Xun Zhou</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Agent-Enhanced Large Language Models for Researching Political Institutions</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13524</link>
   <description>The applications of Large Language Models (LLMs) in political science are rapidly expanding. This paper demonstrates how LLMs, when augmented with predefined functions and specialized tools, can serve as dynamic agents capable of streamlining tasks such as data collection, preprocessing, and analysis. Central to this approach is agentic retrieval-augmented generation (Agentic RAG), which equips LLMs with action-calling capabilities for interaction with external knowledge bases. Beyond information retrieval, LLM agents may incorporate modular tools for tasks like document summarization, transcript coding, qualitative variable classification, and statistical modeling. To demonstrate the potential of this approach, we introduce CongressRA, an LLM agent designed to support scholars studying the U.S. Congress. Through this example, we highlight how LLM agents can reduce the costs of replicating, testing, and extending empirical research using the domain-specific data that drives the study of political institutions.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.13524v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Joseph R. Loffredo, Suyeol Yun</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LLM-Empowered IoT for 6G Networks: Architecture, Challenges, and Solutions</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13819</link>
   <description>The Internet of Things (IoT) in the sixth generation (6G) era is envisioned to evolve towards intelligence, ubiquity, and self-optimization. Large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable generalization capabilities across diverse domains, including natural language processing (NLP), computer vision (CV), and beyond. In this article, we propose an LLM-empowered IoT architecture for 6G networks to achieve intelligent autonomy while supporting advanced IoT applications. LLMs are pushed to the edge of the 6G network to support the synergy of LLMs and IoT. LLM solutions are tailored to both IoT application requirements and IoT management needs, i.e., LLM for IoT. On the other hand, edge inference and edge fine-tuning are discussed to support the deployment of LLMs, i.e., LLM on IoT. Furthermore, we propose a memory-efficient split federated learning (SFL) framework for LLM fine-tuning on heterogeneous IoT devices that alleviates memory pressures on both IoT devices and the edge server while achieving comparable performance and convergence time. Finally, a case study is presented, followed by a discussion about open issues of LLM-empowered IoT for 6G networks.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.13819v1</guid>
   <category>cs.ET</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xiaopei Chen, Wen Wu, Zuguang Li, Liang Li, Fei Ji</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Enhancing Visual Representation with Textual Semantics: Textual Semantics-Powered Prototypes for Heterogeneous Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13543</link>
   <description>Federated Prototype Learning (FedPL) has emerged as an effective strategy for handling data heterogeneity in Federated Learning (FL). In FedPL, clients collaboratively construct a set of global feature centers (prototypes), and let local features align with these prototypes to mitigate the effects of data heterogeneity. The performance of FedPL highly depends on the quality of prototypes. Existing methods assume that larger inter-class distances among prototypes yield better performance, and thus design different methods to increase these distances. However, we observe that while these methods increase prototype distances to enhance class discrimination, they inevitably disrupt essential semantic relationships among classes, which are crucial for model generalization. This raises an important question: how to construct prototypes that inherently preserve semantic relationships among classes? Directly learning these relationships from limited and heterogeneous client data can be problematic in FL. Recently, the success of pre-trained language models (PLMs) demonstrates their ability to capture semantic relationships from vast textual corpora. Motivated by this, we propose FedTSP, a novel method that leverages PLMs to construct semantically enriched prototypes from the textual modality, enabling more effective collaboration in heterogeneous data settings. We first use a large language model (LLM) to generate fine-grained textual descriptions for each class, which are then processed by a PLM on the server to form textual prototypes. To address the modality gap between client image models and the PLM, we introduce trainable prompts, allowing prototypes to adapt better to client tasks. Extensive experiments demonstrate that FedTSP mitigates data heterogeneity while significantly accelerating convergence.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.13543v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xinghao Wu, Jianwei Niu, Xuefeng Liu, Guogang Zhu, Jiayuan Zhang, Shaojie Tang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Towards Privacy-Preserving Data-Driven Education: The Potential of Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13550</link>
   <description>The increasing adoption of data-driven applications in education such as in learning analytics and AI in education has raised significant privacy and data protection concerns. While these challenges have been widely discussed in previous works, there are still limited practical solutions. Federated learning has recently been discoursed as a promising privacy-preserving technique, yet its application in education remains scarce. This paper presents an experimental evaluation of federated learning for educational data prediction, comparing its performance to traditional non-federated approaches. Our findings indicate that federated learning achieves comparable predictive accuracy. Furthermore, under adversarial attacks, federated learning demonstrates greater resilience compared to non-federated settings. We summarise that our results reinforce the value of federated learning as a potential approach for balancing predictive performance and privacy in educational contexts.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.13550v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mohammad Khalil, Ronas Shakya, Qinyi Liu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Trading-off Accuracy and Communication Cost in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14246</link>
   <description>Leveraging the training-by-pruning paradigm introduced by Zhou et al. and Isik et al. introduced a federated learning protocol that achieves a 34-fold reduction in communication cost. We achieve a compression improvements of orders of orders of magnitude over the state-of-the-art. The central idea of our framework is to encode the network weights $\vec w$ by a the vector of trainable parameters $\vec p$, such that $\vec w = Q\cdot \vec p$ where $Q$ is a carefully-generate sparse random matrix (that remains fixed throughout training). In such framework, the previous work of Zhou et al. [NeurIPS'19] is retrieved when $Q$ is diagonal and $\vec p$ has the same dimension of $\vec w$. We instead show that $\vec p$ can effectively be chosen much smaller than $\vec w$, while retaining the same accuracy at the price of a decrease of the sparsity of $Q$. Since server and clients only need to share $\vec p$, such a trade-off leads to a substantial improvement in communication cost. Moreover, we provide theoretical insight into our framework and establish a novel link between training-by-sampling and random convex geometry.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.14246v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mattia Jacopo Villani, Emanuele Natale, Frederik Mallmann-Trenn</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>PLAY2PROMPT: Zero-shot Tool Instruction Optimization for LLM Agents via Tool Play</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14432</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) are increasingly integrated with specialized external tools, yet many tasks demand zero-shot tool usage with minimal or noisy documentation. Existing solutions rely on manual rewriting or labeled data for validation, making them inapplicable in true zero-shot settings. To address these challenges, we propose PLAY2PROMPT, an automated framework that systematically &quot;plays&quot; with each tool to explore its input-output behaviors. Through this iterative trial-and-error process, PLAY2PROMPT refines tool documentation and generates usage examples without any labeled data. These examples not only guide LLM inference but also serve as validation to further enhance tool utilization. Extensive experiments on real-world tasks demonstrate that PLAY2PROMPT significantly improves zero-shot tool performance across both open and closed models, offering a scalable and effective solution for domain-specific tool integration.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.14432v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Wei Fang, Yang Zhang, Kaizhi Qian, James Glass, Yada Zhu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>VGFL-SA: Vertical Graph Federated Learning Structure Attack Based on Contrastive Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16793</link>
   <description>Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) have gained attention for their ability to learn representations from graph data. Due to privacy concerns and conflicts of interest that prevent clients from directly sharing graph data with one another, Vertical Graph Federated Learning (VGFL) frameworks have been developed. Recent studies have shown that VGFL is vulnerable to adversarial attacks that degrade performance. However, it is a common problem that client nodes are often unlabeled in the realm of VGFL. Consequently, the existing attacks, which rely on the availability of labeling information to obtain gradients, are inherently constrained in their applicability. This limitation precludes their deployment in practical, real-world environments. To address the above problems, we propose a novel graph adversarial attack against VGFL, referred to as VGFL-SA, to degrade the performance of VGFL by modifying the local clients structure without using labels. Specifically, VGFL-SA uses a contrastive learning method to complete the attack before the local clients are trained. VGFL-SA first accesses the graph structure and node feature information of the poisoned clients, and generates the contrastive views by node-degree-based edge augmentation and feature shuffling augmentation. Then, VGFL-SA uses the shared graph encoder to get the embedding of each view, and the gradients of the adjacency matrices are obtained by the contrastive function. Finally, perturbed edges are generated using gradient modification rules. We validated the performance of VGFL-SA by performing a node classification task on real-world datasets, and the results show that VGFL-SA achieves good attack effectiveness and transferability.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.16793v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yang Chen, Bin Zhou</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>SDFLMQ: A Semi-Decentralized Federated Learning Framework over MQTT</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13624</link>
   <description>Federated Learning is widely discussed as a distributed machine learning concept with stress on preserving data privacy. Various structures of Federated Learning were proposed. Centralized Federated learning for instance has been the primary structure that suits cloud computing. Decentralized Federated learning also has been proposed for ecosystems where communication is dominantly peer-to-peer. Semi-Decentralized Federated Learning (SDFL) has emerged recently as a new concept where the interconnected nodes are clustered, and each cluster is managed independently. The potential of SDFL lies in its clustering feature, which distributes the load of the global model update down onto multiple nodes. Since the concept is fairly new, much can be done to render this FL model a reliable, efficient, and real-time service at the edge. In this paper, we propose SDFLMQ, a semi-decentralized Federated learning framework at the Edge that uses MQTT as the communication protocol. We demonstrate how the publish/subscribe communication model is used to facilitate the clustering and load balancing in SDFL. We also demonstrate how SDFLMQ can use some of the core MQTT features to expand its capacity with no significant costs. Based on some primary evaluations, we demonstrate how SDFLMQ can efficiently distribute the load of aggregation, and potentially save unnecessary memory allocation, all with no requirement for a powerful central unit for aggregation and global model update. We also disclose some of the key future expansions of SDFLMQ with a focus on the operation of large deep neural network models at the edge.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.13624v1</guid>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Amir Ali-Pour, Julien Gascon-Samson</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedVSR: Towards Model-Agnostic Federated Learning in Video Super-Resolution</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13745</link>
   <description>Video Super-Resolution (VSR) reconstructs high-resolution videos from low-resolution inputs to restore fine details and improve visual clarity. While deep learning-based VSR methods achieve impressive results, their centralized nature raises serious privacy concerns, particularly in applications with strict privacy requirements. Federated Learning (FL) offers an alternative approach, but existing FL methods struggle with low-level vision tasks, leading to suboptimal reconstructions. To address this, we propose FedVSR1, a novel, architecture-independent, and stateless FL framework for VSR. Our approach introduces a lightweight loss term that improves local optimization and guides global aggregation with minimal computational overhead. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first attempt at federated VSR. Extensive experiments show that FedVSR outperforms general FL methods by an average of 0.85 dB in PSNR, highlighting its effectiveness. The code is available at: https://github.com/alimd94/FedVSR</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.13745v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ali Mollaahmadi Dehaghi, Hossein KhademSohi, Reza Razavi, Steve Drew, Mohammad Moshirpour</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedTilt: Towards Multi-Level Fairness-Preserving and Robust Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13537</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) is an emerging decentralized learning paradigm that can partly address the privacy concern that cannot be handled by traditional centralized and distributed learning. Further, to make FL practical, it is also necessary to consider constraints such as fairness and robustness. However, existing robust FL methods often produce unfair models, and existing fair FL methods only consider one-level (client) fairness and are not robust to persistent outliers (i.e., injected outliers into each training round) that are common in real-world FL settings. We propose \texttt{FedTilt}, a novel FL that can preserve multi-level fairness and be robust to outliers. In particular, we consider two common levels of fairness, i.e., \emph{client fairness} -- uniformity of performance across clients, and \emph{client data fairness} -- uniformity of performance across different classes of data within a client. \texttt{FedTilt} is inspired by the recently proposed tilted empirical risk minimization, which introduces tilt hyperparameters that can be flexibly tuned. Theoretically, we show how tuning tilt values can achieve the two-level fairness and mitigate the persistent outliers, and derive the convergence condition of \texttt{FedTilt} as well. Empirically, our evaluation results on a suite of realistic federated datasets in diverse settings show the effectiveness and flexibility of the \texttt{FedTilt} framework and the superiority to the state-of-the-arts.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.13537v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Binghui Zhang, Luis Mares De La Cruz, Binghui Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Enhancing Visual Representation with Textual Semantics: Textual Semantics-Powered Prototypes for Heterogeneous Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13543</link>
   <description>Federated Prototype Learning (FedPL) has emerged as an effective strategy for handling data heterogeneity in Federated Learning (FL). In FedPL, clients collaboratively construct a set of global feature centers (prototypes), and let local features align with these prototypes to mitigate the effects of data heterogeneity. The performance of FedPL highly depends on the quality of prototypes. Existing methods assume that larger inter-class distances among prototypes yield better performance, and thus design different methods to increase these distances. However, we observe that while these methods increase prototype distances to enhance class discrimination, they inevitably disrupt essential semantic relationships among classes, which are crucial for model generalization. This raises an important question: how to construct prototypes that inherently preserve semantic relationships among classes? Directly learning these relationships from limited and heterogeneous client data can be problematic in FL. Recently, the success of pre-trained language models (PLMs) demonstrates their ability to capture semantic relationships from vast textual corpora. Motivated by this, we propose FedTSP, a novel method that leverages PLMs to construct semantically enriched prototypes from the textual modality, enabling more effective collaboration in heterogeneous data settings. We first use a large language model (LLM) to generate fine-grained textual descriptions for each class, which are then processed by a PLM on the server to form textual prototypes. To address the modality gap between client image models and the PLM, we introduce trainable prompts, allowing prototypes to adapt better to client tasks. Extensive experiments demonstrate that FedTSP mitigates data heterogeneity while significantly accelerating convergence.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.13543v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xinghao Wu, Jianwei Niu, Xuefeng Liu, Guogang Zhu, Jiayuan Zhang, Shaojie Tang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Towards Privacy-Preserving Data-Driven Education: The Potential of Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13550</link>
   <description>The increasing adoption of data-driven applications in education such as in learning analytics and AI in education has raised significant privacy and data protection concerns. While these challenges have been widely discussed in previous works, there are still limited practical solutions. Federated learning has recently been discoursed as a promising privacy-preserving technique, yet its application in education remains scarce. This paper presents an experimental evaluation of federated learning for educational data prediction, comparing its performance to traditional non-federated approaches. Our findings indicate that federated learning achieves comparable predictive accuracy. Furthermore, under adversarial attacks, federated learning demonstrates greater resilience compared to non-federated settings. We summarise that our results reinforce the value of federated learning as a potential approach for balancing predictive performance and privacy in educational contexts.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.13550v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mohammad Khalil, Ronas Shakya, Qinyi Liu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Empowering LLMs in Decision Games through Algorithmic Data Synthesis</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13980</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) have exhibited impressive capabilities across numerous domains, yet they often struggle with complex reasoning and decision-making tasks. Decision-making games, which inherently require multifaceted reasoning logic, serve as ideal sandboxes for evaluating and enhancing the reasoning abilities of LLMs. In this work, we first explore whether LLMs can master complex decision-making games through targeted post-training. To this end, we design data synthesis strategies and curate extensive offline datasets from two classic games, Doudizhu and Go. We further develop a suite of techniques to effectively incorporate this data into LLM training, resulting in two novel agents: Mastermind-Dou and Mastermind-Go. Our experimental results demonstrate that these Mastermind LLMs achieve competitive performance in their respective games. Additionally, we explore whether integrating decision-making data can enhance the general reasoning abilities of LLMs. Our findings suggest that such post-training improves certain aspects of reasoning, providing valuable insights for optimizing LLM data collection and synthesis strategies.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.13980v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Haolin Wang, Xueyan Li, Yazhe Niu, Shuai Hu, Hongsheng Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Trading-off Accuracy and Communication Cost in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14246</link>
   <description>Leveraging the training-by-pruning paradigm introduced by Zhou et al. and Isik et al. introduced a federated learning protocol that achieves a 34-fold reduction in communication cost. We achieve a compression improvements of orders of orders of magnitude over the state-of-the-art. The central idea of our framework is to encode the network weights $\vec w$ by a the vector of trainable parameters $\vec p$, such that $\vec w = Q\cdot \vec p$ where $Q$ is a carefully-generate sparse random matrix (that remains fixed throughout training). In such framework, the previous work of Zhou et al. [NeurIPS'19] is retrieved when $Q$ is diagonal and $\vec p$ has the same dimension of $\vec w$. We instead show that $\vec p$ can effectively be chosen much smaller than $\vec w$, while retaining the same accuracy at the price of a decrease of the sparsity of $Q$. Since server and clients only need to share $\vec p$, such a trade-off leads to a substantial improvement in communication cost. Moreover, we provide theoretical insight into our framework and establish a novel link between training-by-sampling and random convex geometry.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.14246v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Mattia Jacopo Villani, Emanuele Natale, Frederik Mallmann-Trenn</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Technical Report: Aggregation on Learnable Manifolds for Asynchronous Federated Optimization</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14396</link>
   <description>In Federated Learning (FL), a primary challenge to the server-side aggregation of client models is device heterogeneity in both loss landscape geometry and computational capacity. This issue can be particularly pronounced in clinical contexts where variations in data distribution (aggravated by class imbalance), infrastructure requirements, and sample sizes are common. We propose AsyncManifold, a novel asynchronous FL framework to address these issues by taking advantage of underlying solution space geometry at each of the local training, delay-correction, and aggregation stages. Our proposal is accompanied by a convergence proof in a general form and, motivated through exploratory studies of local behaviour, a proof-of-concept algorithm which performs aggregation along non-linear mode connections and hence avoids barriers to convergence that techniques based on linear interpolation will encounter.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.14396v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Archie Licudi</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Semantic Communication in Dynamic Channel Scenarios: Collaborative Optimization of Dual-Pipeline Joint Source-Channel Coding and Personalized Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14084</link>
   <description>Semantic communication is designed to tackle issues like bandwidth constraints and high latency in communication systems. However, in complex network topologies with multiple users, the enormous combinations of client data and channel state information (CSI) pose significant challenges for existing semantic communication architectures. To improve the generalization ability of semantic communication models in complex scenarios while meeting the personalized needs of each user in their local environments, we propose a novel personalized federated learning framework with dual-pipeline joint source-channel coding based on channel awareness model (PFL-DPJSCCA). Within this framework, we present a method that achieves zero optimization gap for non-convex loss functions. Experiments conducted under varying SNR distributions validate the outstanding performance of our framework across diverse datasets.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.14084v1</guid>
   <category>eess.IV</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xingrun Yan, Shiyuan Zuo, Yifeng Lyu, Rongfei Fan, Han Hu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>PLAY2PROMPT: Zero-shot Tool Instruction Optimization for LLM Agents via Tool Play</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14432</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) are increasingly integrated with specialized external tools, yet many tasks demand zero-shot tool usage with minimal or noisy documentation. Existing solutions rely on manual rewriting or labeled data for validation, making them inapplicable in true zero-shot settings. To address these challenges, we propose PLAY2PROMPT, an automated framework that systematically &quot;plays&quot; with each tool to explore its input-output behaviors. Through this iterative trial-and-error process, PLAY2PROMPT refines tool documentation and generates usage examples without any labeled data. These examples not only guide LLM inference but also serve as validation to further enhance tool utilization. Extensive experiments on real-world tasks demonstrate that PLAY2PROMPT significantly improves zero-shot tool performance across both open and closed models, offering a scalable and effective solution for domain-specific tool integration.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.14432v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Wei Fang, Yang Zhang, Kaizhi Qian, James Glass, Yada Zhu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Hyper-Connections</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19606</link>
   <description>We present hyper-connections, a simple yet effective method that can serve as an alternative to residual connections. This approach specifically addresses common drawbacks observed in residual connection variants, such as the seesaw effect between gradient vanishing and representation collapse. Theoretically, hyper-connections allow the network to adjust the strength of connections between features at different depths and dynamically rearrange layers. We conduct experiments focusing on the pre-training of large language models, including dense and sparse models, where hyper-connections show significant performance improvements over residual connections. Additional experiments conducted on vision tasks also demonstrate similar improvements. We anticipate that this method will be broadly applicable and beneficial across a wide range of AI problems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2409.19606v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.NE</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Defa Zhu, Hongzhi Huang, Zihao Huang, Yutao Zeng, Yunyao Mao, Banggu Wu, Qiyang Min, Xun Zhou</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>VGFL-SA: Vertical Graph Federated Learning Structure Attack Based on Contrastive Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16793</link>
   <description>Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) have gained attention for their ability to learn representations from graph data. Due to privacy concerns and conflicts of interest that prevent clients from directly sharing graph data with one another, Vertical Graph Federated Learning (VGFL) frameworks have been developed. Recent studies have shown that VGFL is vulnerable to adversarial attacks that degrade performance. However, it is a common problem that client nodes are often unlabeled in the realm of VGFL. Consequently, the existing attacks, which rely on the availability of labeling information to obtain gradients, are inherently constrained in their applicability. This limitation precludes their deployment in practical, real-world environments. To address the above problems, we propose a novel graph adversarial attack against VGFL, referred to as VGFL-SA, to degrade the performance of VGFL by modifying the local clients structure without using labels. Specifically, VGFL-SA uses a contrastive learning method to complete the attack before the local clients are trained. VGFL-SA first accesses the graph structure and node feature information of the poisoned clients, and generates the contrastive views by node-degree-based edge augmentation and feature shuffling augmentation. Then, VGFL-SA uses the shared graph encoder to get the embedding of each view, and the gradients of the adjacency matrices are obtained by the contrastive function. Finally, perturbed edges are generated using gradient modification rules. We validated the performance of VGFL-SA by performing a node classification task on real-world datasets, and the results show that VGFL-SA achieves good attack effectiveness and transferability.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.16793v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yang Chen, Bin Zhou</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Linearized Alternating Direction Multiplier Method for Federated Matrix Completion Problems</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.12733</link>
   <description>Matrix completion is fundamental for predicting missing data with a wide range of applications in personalized healthcare, e-commerce, recommendation systems, and social network analysis. Traditional matrix completion approaches typically assume centralized data storage, which raises challenges in terms of computational efficiency, scalability, and user privacy. In this paper, we address the problem of federated matrix completion, focusing on scenarios where user-specific data is distributed across multiple clients, and privacy constraints are uncompromising. Federated learning provides a promising framework to address these challenges by enabling collaborative learning across distributed datasets without sharing raw data. We propose \texttt{FedMC-ADMM} for solving federated matrix completion problems, a novel algorithmic framework that combines the Alternating Direction Method of Multipliers with a randomized block-coordinate strategy and alternating proximal gradient steps. Unlike existing federated approaches, \texttt{FedMC-ADMM} effectively handles multi-block nonconvex and nonsmooth optimization problems, allowing efficient computation while preserving user privacy. We analyze the theoretical properties of our algorithm, demonstrating subsequential convergence and establishing a convergence rate of $\mathcal{O}(K^{-1/2})$, leading to a communication complexity of $\mathcal{O}(\epsilon^{-2})$ for reaching an $\epsilon$-stationary point. This work is the first to establish these theoretical guarantees for federated matrix completion in the presence of multi-block variables. To validate our approach, we conduct extensive experiments on real-world datasets, including MovieLens 1M, 10M, and Netflix. The results demonstrate that \texttt{FedMC-ADMM} outperforms existing methods in terms of convergence speed and testing accuracy.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.12733v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Patrick Hytla, Tran T. A. Nghia, Duy Nhat Phan, Andrew Rice</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>On the Convergence of a Federated Expectation-Maximization Algorithm</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.05819</link>
   <description>Data heterogeneity has been a long-standing bottleneck in studying the convergence rates of Federated Learning algorithms. In order to better understand the issue of data heterogeneity, we study the convergence rate of the Expectation-Maximization (EM) algorithm for the Federated Mixture of $K$ Linear Regressions model (FMLR). We completely characterize the convergence rate of the EM algorithm under all regimes of $m/n$ where $m$ is the number of clients and $n$ is the number of data points per client. We show that with a signal-to-noise-ratio (SNR) of order $\Omega(\sqrt{K})$, the well-initialized EM algorithm converges within the minimax distance of the ground truth under all regimes. Interestingly, we identify that when the number of clients grows reasonably with respect to the number of data points per client, the EM algorithm only requires a constant number of iterations to converge. We perform experiments on synthetic data to illustrate our results. In line with our theoretical findings, the simulations show that rather than being a bottleneck, data heterogeneity can accelerate the convergence of iterative federated algorithms.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2408.05819v2</guid>
   <category>stat.ML</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Zhixu Tao, Rajita Chandak, Sanjeev Kulkarni</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Agent-Enhanced Large Language Models for Researching Political Institutions</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13524</link>
   <description>The applications of Large Language Models (LLMs) in political science are rapidly expanding. This paper demonstrates how LLMs, when augmented with predefined functions and specialized tools, can serve as dynamic agents capable of streamlining tasks such as data collection, preprocessing, and analysis. Central to this approach is agentic retrieval-augmented generation (Agentic RAG), which equips LLMs with action-calling capabilities for interaction with external knowledge bases. Beyond information retrieval, LLM agents may incorporate modular tools for tasks like document summarization, transcript coding, qualitative variable classification, and statistical modeling. To demonstrate the potential of this approach, we introduce CongressRA, an LLM agent designed to support scholars studying the U.S. Congress. Through this example, we highlight how LLM agents can reduce the costs of replicating, testing, and extending empirical research using the domain-specific data that drives the study of political institutions.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.13524v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CY</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Joseph R. Loffredo, Suyeol Yun</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>AccelGen: Heterogeneous SLO-Guaranteed High-Throughput LLM Inference Serving for Diverse Applications</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13737</link>
   <description>In this paper, we consider a mixed-prompt scenario for a large language model (LLM) inference serving system that supports diverse applications with both short prompts and long prompts and heterogeneous SLOs for iteration time. To improve throughput when handling long prompts, previous research introduces a chunking method, but has not addressed heterogeneous SLOs. To address the limitation, we propose AccelGen, a high-throughput LLM inference serving system with heterogeneous SLO guarantees for diverse applications. AccelGen introduces four core components: (1) SLO-guaranteed dynamic chunking, which dynamically adjusts chunk sizes to maximize GPU compute utilization while meeting iteration-level SLOs; (2) Iteration-level SLO-based task prioritization, which prioritizes tight-SLO requests and batches requests with similar SLOs; (3) Multi-resource-aware batching, which selects queued requests to maximize the utilizations of both GPU compute resource and key-value cache (KVC). Trace-driven real experiments demonstrate that AccelGen achieves 1.42-11.21X higher throughput, 1.43-13.71X higher goodput, 37-90% higher SLO attainment, and 1.61-12.22X lower response latency compared to the state-of-the-art approaches. It achieves performance near the Oracle, which optimally maximizes goodput.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.13737v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Haiying Shen, Tanmoy Sen</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>PLAY2PROMPT: Zero-shot Tool Instruction Optimization for LLM Agents via Tool Play</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14432</link>
   <description>Large language models (LLMs) are increasingly integrated with specialized external tools, yet many tasks demand zero-shot tool usage with minimal or noisy documentation. Existing solutions rely on manual rewriting or labeled data for validation, making them inapplicable in true zero-shot settings. To address these challenges, we propose PLAY2PROMPT, an automated framework that systematically &quot;plays&quot; with each tool to explore its input-output behaviors. Through this iterative trial-and-error process, PLAY2PROMPT refines tool documentation and generates usage examples without any labeled data. These examples not only guide LLM inference but also serve as validation to further enhance tool utilization. Extensive experiments on real-world tasks demonstrate that PLAY2PROMPT significantly improves zero-shot tool performance across both open and closed models, offering a scalable and effective solution for domain-specific tool integration.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.14432v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Wei Fang, Yang Zhang, Kaizhi Qian, James Glass, Yada Zhu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>SCM: Enhancing Large Language Model with Self-Controlled Memory Framework</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.13343</link>
   <description>Large Language Models (LLMs) are constrained by their inability to process lengthy inputs, resulting in the loss of critical historical information. To address this limitation, in this paper, we propose the Self-Controlled Memory (SCM) framework to enhance the ability of LLMs to maintain long-term memory and recall relevant information. Our SCM framework comprises three key components: an LLM-based agent serving as the backbone of the framework, a memory stream storing agent memories, and a memory controller updating memories and determining when and how to utilize memories from memory stream. Additionally, the proposed SCM is able to process ultra-long texts without any modification or fine-tuning, which can integrate with any instruction following LLMs in a plug-and-play paradigm. Furthermore, we annotate a dataset to evaluate the effectiveness of SCM for handling lengthy inputs. The annotated dataset covers three tasks: long-term dialogues, book summarization, and meeting summarization. Experimental results demonstrate that our method achieves better retrieval recall and generates more informative responses compared to competitive baselines in long-term dialogues. (https://github.com/wbbeyourself/SCM4LLMs)</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2304.13343v4</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Bing Wang, Xinnian Liang, Jian Yang, Hui Huang, Shuangzhi Wu, Peihao Wu, Lu Lu, Zejun Ma, Zhoujun Li</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Hyper-Connections</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19606</link>
   <description>We present hyper-connections, a simple yet effective method that can serve as an alternative to residual connections. This approach specifically addresses common drawbacks observed in residual connection variants, such as the seesaw effect between gradient vanishing and representation collapse. Theoretically, hyper-connections allow the network to adjust the strength of connections between features at different depths and dynamically rearrange layers. We conduct experiments focusing on the pre-training of large language models, including dense and sparse models, where hyper-connections show significant performance improvements over residual connections. Additional experiments conducted on vision tasks also demonstrate similar improvements. We anticipate that this method will be broadly applicable and beneficial across a wide range of AI problems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2409.19606v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.NE</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Defa Zhu, Hongzhi Huang, Zihao Huang, Yutao Zeng, Yunyao Mao, Banggu Wu, Qiyang Min, Xun Zhou</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedVSR: Towards Model-Agnostic Federated Learning in Video Super-Resolution</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13745</link>
   <description>Video Super-Resolution (VSR) reconstructs high-resolution videos from low-resolution inputs to restore fine details and improve visual clarity. While deep learning-based VSR methods achieve impressive results, their centralized nature raises serious privacy concerns, particularly in applications with strict privacy requirements. Federated Learning (FL) offers an alternative approach, but existing FL methods struggle with low-level vision tasks, leading to suboptimal reconstructions. To address this, we propose FedVSR1, a novel, architecture-independent, and stateless FL framework for VSR. Our approach introduces a lightweight loss term that improves local optimization and guides global aggregation with minimal computational overhead. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first attempt at federated VSR. Extensive experiments show that FedVSR outperforms general FL methods by an average of 0.85 dB in PSNR, highlighting its effectiveness. The code is available at: https://github.com/alimd94/FedVSR</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.13745v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Ali Mollaahmadi Dehaghi, Hossein KhademSohi, Reza Razavi, Steve Drew, Mohammad Moshirpour</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Hyper-Connections</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19606</link>
   <description>We present hyper-connections, a simple yet effective method that can serve as an alternative to residual connections. This approach specifically addresses common drawbacks observed in residual connection variants, such as the seesaw effect between gradient vanishing and representation collapse. Theoretically, hyper-connections allow the network to adjust the strength of connections between features at different depths and dynamically rearrange layers. We conduct experiments focusing on the pre-training of large language models, including dense and sparse models, where hyper-connections show significant performance improvements over residual connections. Additional experiments conducted on vision tasks also demonstrate similar improvements. We anticipate that this method will be broadly applicable and beneficial across a wide range of AI problems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2409.19606v3</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <category>cs.NE</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Defa Zhu, Hongzhi Huang, Zihao Huang, Yutao Zeng, Yunyao Mao, Banggu Wu, Qiyang Min, Xun Zhou</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
