<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss>
 <channel>
  <title>arxiv-rss</title>
  <link></link>
  <description></description>
  <docs></docs>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <lastBuildDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 03:28:12 </lastBuildDate>
  <managingEditor></managingEditor>
  <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 03:28:12 </pubDate>
  <item>
   <title>FedFlex: Federated Learning for Diverse Netflix Recommendations</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21115</link>
   <description>Federated learning is a decentralized approach that enables collaborative model training across multiple devices while preserving data privacy. It has shown significant potential in various domains, including healthcare and personalized recommendation systems. However, most existing work on federated recommendation systems has focused primarily on improving accuracy, with limited attention to fairness and diversity. In this paper, we introduce FedFlex, a federated recommender system for Netflix-style TV series recommendations. FedFlex integrates two state-of-the-art matrix factorization algorithms for personalized fine-tuning. FedFlex also applies Maximal Marginal Relevance (MMR) to re-rank items and enhance diversity. We conduct extensive experiments comparing recommendations generated by SVD and BPR algorithms. In a live two-week user study, participants received two recommendation lists: List A, based on SVD or BPR, and List B, a re-ranked version emphasizing diversity. Participants were asked to click on the movies they were interested in watching. Our findings demonstrate that FedFlex effectively introduces diverse content, such as new genres, into recommendations without necessarily compromising user satisfaction.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.21115v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sven Lankester, Manel Slokom, Gustavo de Carvalho Bertoli, Matias Vizcaino, Emmanuelle Beauxis Aussalet, Laura Hollink</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>The Evolution of Video Anomaly Detection: A Unified Framework from DNN to MLLM</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21649</link>
   <description>Video anomaly detection (VAD) aims to identify and ground anomalous behaviors or events in videos, serving as a core technology in the fields of intelligent surveillance and public safety. With the advancement of deep learning, the continuous evolution of deep model architectures has driven innovation in VAD methodologies, significantly enhancing feature representation and scene adaptability, thereby improving algorithm generalization and expanding application boundaries. More importantly, the rapid development of multi-modal large language (MLLMs) and large language models (LLMs) has introduced new opportunities and challenges to the VAD field. Under the support of MLLMs and LLMs, VAD has undergone significant transformations in terms of data annotation, input modalities, model architectures, and task objectives. The surge in publications and the evolution of tasks have created an urgent need for systematic reviews of recent advancements. This paper presents the first comprehensive survey analyzing VAD methods based on MLLMs and LLMs, providing an in-depth discussion of the changes occurring in the VAD field in the era of large models and their underlying causes. Additionally, this paper proposes a unified framework that encompasses both deep neural network (DNN)-based and LLM-based VAD methods, offering a thorough analysis of the new VAD paradigms empowered by LLMs, constructing a classification system, and comparing their strengths and weaknesses. Building on this foundation, this paper focuses on current VAD methods based on MLLMs/LLMs. Finally, based on the trajectory of technological advancements and existing bottlenecks, this paper distills key challenges and outlines future research directions, offering guidance for the VAD community.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.21649v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Shibo Gao, Peipei Yang, Haiyang Guo, Yangyang Liu, Yi Chen, Shuai Li, Han Zhu, Jian Xu, Xu-Yao Zhang, Linlin Huang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Cyst-X: AI-Powered Pancreatic Cancer Risk Prediction from Multicenter MRI in Centralized and Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22017</link>
   <description>Pancreatic cancer is projected to become the second-deadliest malignancy in Western countries by 2030, highlighting the urgent need for better early detection. Intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasms (IPMNs), key precursors to pancreatic cancer, are challenging to assess with current guidelines, often leading to unnecessary surgeries or missed malignancies. We present Cyst-X, an AI framework that predicts IPMN malignancy using multicenter MRI data, leveraging MRI's superior soft tissue contrast over CT. Trained on 723 T1- and 738 T2-weighted scans from 764 patients across seven institutions, our models (AUC=0.82) significantly outperform both Kyoto guidelines (AUC=0.75) and expert radiologists. The AI-derived imaging features align with known clinical markers and offer biologically meaningful insights. We also demonstrate strong performance in a federated learning setting, enabling collaborative training without sharing patient data. To promote privacy-preserving AI development and improve IPMN risk stratification, the Cyst-X dataset is released as the first large-scale, multi-center pancreatic cysts MRI dataset.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.22017v1</guid>
   <category>eess.IV</category>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Hongyi Pan, Gorkem Durak, Elif Keles, Deniz Seyithanoglu, Zheyuan Zhang, Alpay Medetalibeyoglu, Halil Ertugrul Aktas, Andrea Mia Bejar, Ziliang Hong, Yavuz Taktak, Gulbiz Dagoglu Kartal, Mehmet Sukru Erturk, Timurhan Cebeci, Maria Jaramillo Gonzalez, Yury Velichko, Lili Zhao, Emil Agarunov, Federica Proietto Salanitri, Concetto Spampinato, Pallavi Tiwari, Ziyue Xu, Sachin Jambawalikar, Ivo G. Schoots, Marco J. Bruno, Chenchang Huang, Candice Bolan, Tamas Gonda, Frank H. Miller, Rajesh N. Keswani, Michael B. Wallace, Ulas Bagci</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>A Survey on Wi-Fi Sensing Generalizability: Taxonomy, Techniques, Datasets, and Future Research Prospects</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.08008</link>
   <description>Wi-Fi sensing has emerged as a powerful non-intrusive technology for recognizing human activities, monitoring vital signs, and enabling context-aware applications using commercial wireless devices. However, the performance of Wi-Fi sensing often degrades when applied to new users, devices, or environments due to significant domain shifts. To address this challenge, researchers have proposed a wide range of generalization techniques aimed at enhancing the robustness and adaptability of Wi-Fi sensing systems. In this survey, we provide a comprehensive and structured review of over 200 papers published since 2015, categorizing them according to the Wi-Fi sensing pipeline: experimental setup, signal preprocessing, feature learning, and model deployment. We analyze key techniques, including signal preprocessing, domain adaptation, meta-learning, metric learning, data augmentation, cross-modal alignment, federated learning, and continual learning. Furthermore, we summarize publicly available datasets across various tasks,such as activity recognition, user identification, indoor localization, and pose estimation, and provide insights into their domain diversity. We also discuss emerging trends and future directions, including large-scale pretraining, integration with multimodal foundation models, and continual deployment. To foster community collaboration, we introduce the Sensing Dataset Platform (SDP) for sharing datasets and models. This survey aims to serve as a valuable reference and practical guide for researchers and practitioners dedicated to improving the generalizability of Wi-Fi sensing systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2503.08008v2</guid>
   <category>cs.CV</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Fei Wang, Tingting Zhang, Wei Xi, Han Ding, Ge Wang, Di Zhang, Yuanhao Cui, Fan Liu, Jinsong Han, Jie Xu, Tony Xiao Han</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Uncovering Gradient Inversion Risks in Practical Language Model Training</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21198</link>
   <description>The gradient inversion attack has been demonstrated as a significant privacy threat to federated learning (FL), particularly in continuous domains such as vision models. In contrast, it is often considered less effective or highly dependent on impractical training settings when applied to language models, due to the challenges posed by the discrete nature of tokens in text data. As a result, its potential privacy threats remain largely underestimated, despite FL being an emerging training method for language models. In this work, we propose a domain-specific gradient inversion attack named Grab (gradient inversion with hybrid optimization). Grab features two alternating optimization processes to address the challenges caused by practical training settings, including a simultaneous optimization on dropout masks between layers for improved token recovery and a discrete optimization for effective token sequencing. Grab can recover a significant portion (up to 92.9% recovery rate) of the private training data, outperforming the attack strategy of utilizing discrete optimization with an auxiliary model by notable improvements of up to 28.9% recovery rate in benchmark settings and 48.5% recovery rate in practical settings. Grab provides a valuable step forward in understanding this privacy threat in the emerging FL training mode of language models.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.21198v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xinguo Feng, Zhongkui Ma, Zihan Wang, Eu Joe Chegne, Mengyao Ma, Alsharif Abuadbba, Guangdong Bai</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Latte: Collaborative Test-Time Adaptation of Vision-Language Models in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21494</link>
   <description>Test-time adaptation with pre-trained vision-language models has gained increasing attention for addressing distribution shifts during testing. Among these approaches, memory-based algorithms stand out due to their training-free nature and ability to leverage historical test data. However, existing test-time adaptation methods are typically designed for a single domain with abundant data. In decentralized settings such as federated learning, applying these methods individually to each client suffers from limited test data, while directly sharing a single global memory via the server prevents proper personalization to each client's unique distribution. To address this, we propose Latte, a novel framework where each client maintains a local memory to store embeddings from its own historical test data and an external memory to store class prototypes from other relevant clients. During communication, each client retrieves prototypes from similar clients under the server's coordination to expand its memory. For local adaptation, Latte utilizes both embedding similarity and uncertainty to enhance model performance. Our theoretical analysis shows that Latte effectively leverages in-distribution clients while remaining robust to out-of-distribution clients. Extensive experiments on domain adaptation and corruption benchmarks validate that Latte achieves superior performance in decentralized settings, while introducing only negligible communication and computation costs. Our code is available at https://github.com/baowenxuan/Latte .</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.21494v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Wenxuan Bao, Ruxi Deng, Ruizhong Qiu, Tianxin Wei, Hanghang Tong, Jingrui He</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedFlex: Federated Learning for Diverse Netflix Recommendations</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21115</link>
   <description>Federated learning is a decentralized approach that enables collaborative model training across multiple devices while preserving data privacy. It has shown significant potential in various domains, including healthcare and personalized recommendation systems. However, most existing work on federated recommendation systems has focused primarily on improving accuracy, with limited attention to fairness and diversity. In this paper, we introduce FedFlex, a federated recommender system for Netflix-style TV series recommendations. FedFlex integrates two state-of-the-art matrix factorization algorithms for personalized fine-tuning. FedFlex also applies Maximal Marginal Relevance (MMR) to re-rank items and enhance diversity. We conduct extensive experiments comparing recommendations generated by SVD and BPR algorithms. In a live two-week user study, participants received two recommendation lists: List A, based on SVD or BPR, and List B, a re-ranked version emphasizing diversity. Participants were asked to click on the movies they were interested in watching. Our findings demonstrate that FedFlex effectively introduces diverse content, such as new genres, into recommendations without necessarily compromising user satisfaction.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.21115v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sven Lankester, Manel Slokom, Gustavo de Carvalho Bertoli, Matias Vizcaino, Emmanuelle Beauxis Aussalet, Laura Hollink</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedBAP: Backdoor Defense via Benign Adversarial Perturbation in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21177</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) enables collaborative model training while preserving data privacy, but it is highly vulnerable to backdoor attacks. Most existing defense methods in FL have limited effectiveness due to their neglect of the model's over-reliance on backdoor triggers, particularly as the proportion of malicious clients increases. In this paper, we propose FedBAP, a novel defense framework for mitigating backdoor attacks in FL by reducing the model's reliance on backdoor triggers. Specifically, first, we propose a perturbed trigger generation mechanism that creates perturbation triggers precisely matching backdoor triggers in location and size, ensuring strong influence on model outputs. Second, we utilize these perturbation triggers to generate benign adversarial perturbations that disrupt the model's dependence on backdoor triggers while forcing it to learn more robust decision boundaries. Finally, we design an adaptive scaling mechanism to dynamically adjust perturbation intensity, effectively balancing defense strength and model performance. The experimental results demonstrate that FedBAP reduces the attack success rates by 0.22%-5.34%, 0.48%-6.34%, and 97.22%-97.6% under three types of backdoor attacks, respectively. In particular, FedBAP demonstrates outstanding performance against novel backdoor attacks.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.21177v1</guid>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xinhai Yan, Libing Wu, Zhuangzhuang Zhang, Bingyi Liu, Lijuan Huo, Jing Wang</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedStrategist: A Meta-Learning Framework for Adaptive and Robust Aggregation in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14322</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) offers a paradigm for privacy-preserving collaborative AI, but its decentralized nature creates significant vulnerabilities to model poisoning attacks. While numerous static defenses exist, their effectiveness is highly context-dependent, often failing against adaptive adversaries or in heterogeneous data environments. This paper introduces FedStrategist, a novel meta-learning framework that reframes robust aggregation as a real-time, cost-aware control problem. We design a lightweight contextual bandit agent that dynamically selects the optimal aggregation rule from an arsenal of defenses based on real-time diagnostic metrics. Through comprehensive experiments, we demonstrate that no single static rule is universally optimal. We show that our adaptive agent successfully learns superior policies across diverse scenarios, including a ``Krum-favorable&quot; environment and against a sophisticated &quot;stealth&quot; adversary designed to neutralize specific diagnostic signals. Critically, we analyze the paradoxical scenario where a non-robust baseline achieves high but compromised accuracy, and demonstrate that our agent learns a conservative policy to prioritize model integrity. Furthermore, we prove the agent's policy is controllable via a single &quot;risk tolerance&quot; parameter, allowing practitioners to explicitly manage the trade-off between performance and security. Our work provides a new, practical, and analyzable approach to creating resilient and intelligent decentralized AI systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.14322v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Md Rafid Haque, Abu Raihan Mostofa Kamal, Md. Azam Hossain</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedFlex: Federated Learning for Diverse Netflix Recommendations</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21115</link>
   <description>Federated learning is a decentralized approach that enables collaborative model training across multiple devices while preserving data privacy. It has shown significant potential in various domains, including healthcare and personalized recommendation systems. However, most existing work on federated recommendation systems has focused primarily on improving accuracy, with limited attention to fairness and diversity. In this paper, we introduce FedFlex, a federated recommender system for Netflix-style TV series recommendations. FedFlex integrates two state-of-the-art matrix factorization algorithms for personalized fine-tuning. FedFlex also applies Maximal Marginal Relevance (MMR) to re-rank items and enhance diversity. We conduct extensive experiments comparing recommendations generated by SVD and BPR algorithms. In a live two-week user study, participants received two recommendation lists: List A, based on SVD or BPR, and List B, a re-ranked version emphasizing diversity. Participants were asked to click on the movies they were interested in watching. Our findings demonstrate that FedFlex effectively introduces diverse content, such as new genres, into recommendations without necessarily compromising user satisfaction.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.21115v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sven Lankester, Manel Slokom, Gustavo de Carvalho Bertoli, Matias Vizcaino, Emmanuelle Beauxis Aussalet, Laura Hollink</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LeMix: Unified Scheduling for LLM Training and Inference on Multi-GPU Systems</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21276</link>
   <description>Modern deployment of large language models (LLMs) frequently involves both inference serving and continuous retraining to stay aligned with evolving data and user feedback. Common practices separate these workloads onto distinct servers in isolated phases, causing substantial inefficiencies (e.g., GPU idleness) and delayed adaptation to new data in distributed settings. Our empirical analysis reveals that these inefficiencies stem from dynamic request arrivals during serving and workload heterogeneity in pipeline-parallel training. To address these challenges, we propose LeMix, a system for co-locating and managing concurrent LLM serving and training workloads. LeMix integrates offline profiling, execution prediction mechanisms, and runtime scheduling to dynamically adapt resource allocation based on workload characteristics and system conditions. By understanding task-specific behaviors and co-execution interference across shared nodes, LeMix improves utilization and serving quality without compromising serving responsiveness. Our evaluation shows that LeMix improves throughput by up to 3.53x, reduces inference loss by up to 0.61x, and delivers up to 2.12x higher response time SLO attainment over traditional separate setups. To our knowledge, this is the first work to uncover and exploit the opportunities of joint LLM inference and training, paving the way for more resource-efficient deployment of LLMs in production environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.21276v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yufei Li, Zexin Li, Yinglun Zhu, Cong Liu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedStrategist: A Meta-Learning Framework for Adaptive and Robust Aggregation in Federated Learning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14322</link>
   <description>Federated Learning (FL) offers a paradigm for privacy-preserving collaborative AI, but its decentralized nature creates significant vulnerabilities to model poisoning attacks. While numerous static defenses exist, their effectiveness is highly context-dependent, often failing against adaptive adversaries or in heterogeneous data environments. This paper introduces FedStrategist, a novel meta-learning framework that reframes robust aggregation as a real-time, cost-aware control problem. We design a lightweight contextual bandit agent that dynamically selects the optimal aggregation rule from an arsenal of defenses based on real-time diagnostic metrics. Through comprehensive experiments, we demonstrate that no single static rule is universally optimal. We show that our adaptive agent successfully learns superior policies across diverse scenarios, including a ``Krum-favorable&quot; environment and against a sophisticated &quot;stealth&quot; adversary designed to neutralize specific diagnostic signals. Critically, we analyze the paradoxical scenario where a non-robust baseline achieves high but compromised accuracy, and demonstrate that our agent learns a conservative policy to prioritize model integrity. Furthermore, we prove the agent's policy is controllable via a single &quot;risk tolerance&quot; parameter, allowing practitioners to explicitly manage the trade-off between performance and security. Our work provides a new, practical, and analyzable approach to creating resilient and intelligent decentralized AI systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.14322v2</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.CR</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Md Rafid Haque, Abu Raihan Mostofa Kamal, Md. Azam Hossain</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LeMix: Unified Scheduling for LLM Training and Inference on Multi-GPU Systems</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21276</link>
   <description>Modern deployment of large language models (LLMs) frequently involves both inference serving and continuous retraining to stay aligned with evolving data and user feedback. Common practices separate these workloads onto distinct servers in isolated phases, causing substantial inefficiencies (e.g., GPU idleness) and delayed adaptation to new data in distributed settings. Our empirical analysis reveals that these inefficiencies stem from dynamic request arrivals during serving and workload heterogeneity in pipeline-parallel training. To address these challenges, we propose LeMix, a system for co-locating and managing concurrent LLM serving and training workloads. LeMix integrates offline profiling, execution prediction mechanisms, and runtime scheduling to dynamically adapt resource allocation based on workload characteristics and system conditions. By understanding task-specific behaviors and co-execution interference across shared nodes, LeMix improves utilization and serving quality without compromising serving responsiveness. Our evaluation shows that LeMix improves throughput by up to 3.53x, reduces inference loss by up to 0.61x, and delivers up to 2.12x higher response time SLO attainment over traditional separate setups. To our knowledge, this is the first work to uncover and exploit the opportunities of joint LLM inference and training, paving the way for more resource-efficient deployment of LLMs in production environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.21276v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yufei Li, Zexin Li, Yinglun Zhu, Cong Liu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Graph-Augmented Large Language Model Agents: Current Progress and Future Prospects</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21407</link>
   <description>Autonomous agents based on large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated impressive capabilities in a wide range of applications, including web navigation, software development, and embodied control. While most LLMs are limited in several key agentic procedures, such as reliable planning, long-term memory, tool management, and multi-agent coordination, graphs can serve as a powerful auxiliary structure to enhance structure, continuity, and coordination in complex agent workflows. Given the rapid growth and fragmentation of research on Graph-augmented LLM Agents (GLA), this paper offers a timely and comprehensive overview of recent advances and also highlights key directions for future work. Specifically, we categorize existing GLA methods by their primary functions in LLM agent systems, including planning, memory, and tool usage, and then analyze how graphs and graph learning algorithms contribute to each. For multi-agent systems, we further discuss how GLA solutions facilitate the orchestration, efficiency optimization, and trustworthiness of MAS. Finally, we highlight key future directions to advance this field, from improving structural adaptability to enabling unified, scalable, and multimodal GLA systems. We hope this paper can serve as a roadmap for future research on GLA and foster a deeper understanding of the role of graphs in LLM agent systems.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.21407v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>new</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yixin Liu, Guibin Zhang, Kun Wang, Shiyuan Li, Shirui Pan</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>FedFlex: Federated Learning for Diverse Netflix Recommendations</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21115</link>
   <description>Federated learning is a decentralized approach that enables collaborative model training across multiple devices while preserving data privacy. It has shown significant potential in various domains, including healthcare and personalized recommendation systems. However, most existing work on federated recommendation systems has focused primarily on improving accuracy, with limited attention to fairness and diversity. In this paper, we introduce FedFlex, a federated recommender system for Netflix-style TV series recommendations. FedFlex integrates two state-of-the-art matrix factorization algorithms for personalized fine-tuning. FedFlex also applies Maximal Marginal Relevance (MMR) to re-rank items and enhance diversity. We conduct extensive experiments comparing recommendations generated by SVD and BPR algorithms. In a live two-week user study, participants received two recommendation lists: List A, based on SVD or BPR, and List B, a re-ranked version emphasizing diversity. Participants were asked to click on the movies they were interested in watching. Our findings demonstrate that FedFlex effectively introduces diverse content, such as new genres, into recommendations without necessarily compromising user satisfaction.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.21115v1</guid>
   <category>cs.IR</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Sven Lankester, Manel Slokom, Gustavo de Carvalho Bertoli, Matias Vizcaino, Emmanuelle Beauxis Aussalet, Laura Hollink</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Uncovering Gradient Inversion Risks in Practical Language Model Training</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21198</link>
   <description>The gradient inversion attack has been demonstrated as a significant privacy threat to federated learning (FL), particularly in continuous domains such as vision models. In contrast, it is often considered less effective or highly dependent on impractical training settings when applied to language models, due to the challenges posed by the discrete nature of tokens in text data. As a result, its potential privacy threats remain largely underestimated, despite FL being an emerging training method for language models. In this work, we propose a domain-specific gradient inversion attack named Grab (gradient inversion with hybrid optimization). Grab features two alternating optimization processes to address the challenges caused by practical training settings, including a simultaneous optimization on dropout masks between layers for improved token recovery and a discrete optimization for effective token sequencing. Grab can recover a significant portion (up to 92.9% recovery rate) of the private training data, outperforming the attack strategy of utilizing discrete optimization with an auxiliary model by notable improvements of up to 28.9% recovery rate in benchmark settings and 48.5% recovery rate in practical settings. Grab provides a valuable step forward in understanding this privacy threat in the emerging FL training mode of language models.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.21198v1</guid>
   <category>cs.LG</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Xinguo Feng, Zhongkui Ma, Zihan Wang, Eu Joe Chegne, Mengyao Ma, Alsharif Abuadbba, Guangdong Bai</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LIMO: Less is More for Reasoning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03387</link>
   <description>We challenge the prevailing assumption that complex reasoning in large language models (LLMs) necessitates massive training data. We demonstrate that sophisticated mathematical reasoning can emerge with only a few examples. Specifically, through simple supervised fine-tuning, our model, LIMO, achieves 63.3\% accuracy on AIME24 and 95.6\% on MATH500, surpassing previous fine-tuned models (6.5\% on AIME24, 59.2\% on MATH500) while using only 1\% of the training data required by prior approaches. Furthermore, LIMO exhibits strong out-of-distribution generalization, achieving a 45.8\% absolute improvement across diverse benchmarks, outperforming models trained on 100x more data. Synthesizing these findings, we propose the Less-Is-More Reasoning Hypothesis (LIMO Hypothesis): In foundation models where domain knowledge has been comprehensively encoded during pre-training, sophisticated reasoning can emerge through minimal but strategically designed demonstrations of cognitive processes. This hypothesis suggests that the threshold for eliciting complex reasoning is not dictated by task complexity but rather by two key factors: (1) the completeness of the model's pre-trained knowledge base and (2) the effectiveness of post-training examples in serving as &quot;cognitive templates&quot; that guide reasoning.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.03387v3</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace-cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yixin Ye, Zhen Huang, Yang Xiao, Ethan Chern, Shijie Xia, Pengfei Liu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LeMix: Unified Scheduling for LLM Training and Inference on Multi-GPU Systems</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21276</link>
   <description>Modern deployment of large language models (LLMs) frequently involves both inference serving and continuous retraining to stay aligned with evolving data and user feedback. Common practices separate these workloads onto distinct servers in isolated phases, causing substantial inefficiencies (e.g., GPU idleness) and delayed adaptation to new data in distributed settings. Our empirical analysis reveals that these inefficiencies stem from dynamic request arrivals during serving and workload heterogeneity in pipeline-parallel training. To address these challenges, we propose LeMix, a system for co-locating and managing concurrent LLM serving and training workloads. LeMix integrates offline profiling, execution prediction mechanisms, and runtime scheduling to dynamically adapt resource allocation based on workload characteristics and system conditions. By understanding task-specific behaviors and co-execution interference across shared nodes, LeMix improves utilization and serving quality without compromising serving responsiveness. Our evaluation shows that LeMix improves throughput by up to 3.53x, reduces inference loss by up to 0.61x, and delivers up to 2.12x higher response time SLO attainment over traditional separate setups. To our knowledge, this is the first work to uncover and exploit the opportunities of joint LLM inference and training, paving the way for more resource-efficient deployment of LLMs in production environments.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2507.21276v1</guid>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.DC</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>cross</announce_type>
   <rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yufei Li, Zexin Li, Yinglun Zhu, Cong Liu</creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>LIMO: Less is More for Reasoning</title>
   <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03387</link>
   <description>We challenge the prevailing assumption that complex reasoning in large language models (LLMs) necessitates massive training data. We demonstrate that sophisticated mathematical reasoning can emerge with only a few examples. Specifically, through simple supervised fine-tuning, our model, LIMO, achieves 63.3\% accuracy on AIME24 and 95.6\% on MATH500, surpassing previous fine-tuned models (6.5\% on AIME24, 59.2\% on MATH500) while using only 1\% of the training data required by prior approaches. Furthermore, LIMO exhibits strong out-of-distribution generalization, achieving a 45.8\% absolute improvement across diverse benchmarks, outperforming models trained on 100x more data. Synthesizing these findings, we propose the Less-Is-More Reasoning Hypothesis (LIMO Hypothesis): In foundation models where domain knowledge has been comprehensively encoded during pre-training, sophisticated reasoning can emerge through minimal but strategically designed demonstrations of cognitive processes. This hypothesis suggests that the threshold for eliciting complex reasoning is not dictated by task complexity but rather by two key factors: (1) the completeness of the model's pre-trained knowledge base and (2) the effectiveness of post-training examples in serving as &quot;cognitive templates&quot; that guide reasoning.</description>
   <guid>oai:arXiv.org:2502.03387v3</guid>
   <category>cs.CL</category>
   <category>cs.AI</category>
   <pubdate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubdate>
   <announce_type>replace</announce_type>
   <rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</rights>
   <creator>Yixin Ye, Zhen Huang, Yang Xiao, Ethan Chern, Shijie Xia, Pengfei Liu</creator>
  </item>
 </channel>
</rss>
